Okay, we're at Berkeley. time. So, let's
get started.
Quick announcement before we start
class. Um, the weight list should have
processed and everyone should be
enrolled. So, if you expect to be
enrolled in this class, please go and
check your enrollment to see that you
actually are enrolled. If there is a
bug, some if something went wrong, you
know, stuff happens because there's
manual processing that happens to get
people in. So let us know now because
once the ad drop deadline is done this
will be much much much harder to fix. In
fact it might be impossible to fix.
Okay. So if you expect to be enrolled if
you have done homework zero if you've
you know make sure go and actually check
that you are actually enrolled. Don't
trust that you know because we said the
weight list cleared and because but if
you were on the weight list and you did
homework zero whether you were concurren
concurrent enrollment or not you should
be in the class. Okay, everyone good?
Um, just yeah, make sure please please
actually check this.
Um, in other word uh other news,
homework one will be due tomorrow. So,
make sure you're looking at that and are
on top of that
and um keep that in mind. Okay, any
questions before we start.
Okay, good. So today we're going to
basically continue with where we left
off in the last lecture and we're going
to talk about this perspective of trying
to look at or trying to take a linear
perspective on neural networks and then
we will see that this linear perspective
actually gives us a new lens into
looking at our optimization algorithms
and so we'll revisit atom and we'll
revisit gradient descent and then we're
going to go to thinking about well what
are the things that We really need to
make these networks trainable. And one
of the very important things there is
going to be standardization and
initialization and making sure that our
data is actually in ranges and uh and
and the parameters are such that we can
actually uh use the expressive power of
the neural network to get the kind of
function fitting that we want to get and
get use the expressive power that uh
fully. So that's what we're going to be
really talking about in uh in lecture
today. Okay. So last time we talked
about basically this one uh basic
perspective which is that you you let's
say you have a network you have some
input X and maybe you have a bunch of
layers.
you feed into your linear layer at the
end
and then maybe you have an output Y.
And we said, look, one way to think
about this neural network is to say all
of this nonlinear stuff here, this is
doing a feature extraction
and then we're taking all of these
features and feeding them in to a linear
layer and then fitting that linear
layer. Just thinking of that as a
standard linear problem, right? And
except instead of saying, oh, we have
some features that we have come up with
from some side information, we're going
to actually use the data to fit and
understand what the right nonlinear
features would be. Does everyone
remember we talked about that? So this
yellow part we're just thinking of as a
feature extractor.
What I didn't have time to talk about
last time was the second perspective by
which we can think of
excuse me by which we can try to think
of a a second linear perspective that we
can take on our uh deep learning
problem. So for this I want to think
about our network as a function of both
the input data and the parameters.
Right? We're trying to fit the
parameters. So they're also a important
part of what the neural network is able
to express. Right? Of course it's also a
function of what the input comes in. So
let's think of this network as function
f of x comma theta. x is your data and
theta are your parameters. Okay.
And now I want to focus on this as a
function of theta even though x is
there. I'm going to kind of sideline
that just for a minute. Okay.
So let's say we have a network that's
basically doing some kind of that's
giving a scalar output. So we're trying
to say we're trying to do some binary
classification or a linear regression
where we're trying we have a scalar
input and we have a scalar output. Okay.
But let's say we have a bunch of
parameters. So for example like the
example that you did in uh your
discussion you have maybe many many
hidden layers or many many hidden units
in one hidden layer but you have a
scalar input and a scalar output. Okay,
that's the kind of problem that you can
keep in mind.
Then what I can do is I can think of
this
function as a uh linear I can think of
the function of the neural network from
the perspective of linearizing it around
the current parameter values to try and
understand what would happen if the
parameter changed just by a little bit.
And so what is the tool that we have to
think about when we're looking at okay I
have a function and I want to understand
what happens to that function when my
input changes a little bit. what is the
what is the thing that we always have
and use
>> expansion
>> tailor expansion right
so that's exactly what we're going to
try to do and we're going to say look if
I'm at theta and I'm moving a little bit
to delta theta which is exactly in some
sense what something like gradient
descent is trying to do is I'm trying to
train to understand what is the best
value of theta well I could look at the
value at f ofx comma theta and then I
have some correction terms to understand
how f ofx theta plus delta theta is
different from fx x comma theta. And so
what is the first term here? What is the
first term in the tailor expansion? It's
the linear term, right? It's a linear.
It's basically something that's
multiplying this delta theta. And in
fact, what is multiplying this delta
theta? I'm writing this here as an inner
product. This is the gradient
multiplying the delta theta term, right?
And then what's the term out here going
to be?
It's going to be a quadratic term. And
what is the matrix that's going to be in
there?
>> It's going to be a hessa. And then we're
going to have higher order terms, right?
We're not going to think about those at
all right now. I'm completely dropping
them.
I want to focus only on this um you know
first constant uh term and then this
linear term.
And if I think about this I can think of
this as essentially a linear
approximation of this network. Right?
So what is the caveat for me being able
to use this and even
think about this this way
when I'm making an approximation
what is the what do I have to always
check
>> delta
>> I want to check that delta theta in some
sense is small right because if I move
very far away from my initialization
point or wherever my parameters
currently are then this linear
approximation isn't going to hold.
Right? If I have some function,
what the tailor expansion is doing is I
have some function and I'm taking some
um local linear approximation to that.
Right? And so if I move far away, this
local linear approximation is going to
be bad. These terms are going to start
becoming much larger. So this only holds
true in a particular neighborhood. Okay?
And so to be able to use this this uh
this kind of thinking or this kind of
linear approximation,
we have what is called the lazy training
assumption. Okay. And what is the lazy
training assumption? The lazy training
assumption says that your weights of
your neural network are actually moving
by very little bits. They're they're
moving in a lazy fashion. So whatever
training you're doing, your final output
or your final weights and parameters are
actually very close to where they were
initially.
And while this might seem kind of wait,
what's the point, right? If you just
pick some initialization and it works,
then what's the point? What were you
doing with training? Turns out that this
is actually true quite often in
practice. Okay. Um and uh we'll see
actually we're going to explore uh some
aspects of this in terms of the
optimization uh algorithms in just a
little bit.
But this is the this is the assumption
in some sense under which we want to um
we want to be working.
And now the thing that I want to point
out is if I look at this this linear
term here
what is exactly this thing right this is
this is my gradient
which is basically just the transpose of
the derivative. So now we look at this
in our product this is what it looks
like right does everyone see that
so now when I look at the entries of
this I can think of this as essentially
the features of the data right these are
what are multiplying these entries of
delta theta so one other perspective for
this is to think of this as the features
so when I have a when I have x w equal
to y the columns of x are my features
right for Example, if I'm doing polomial
regression, I would have my features be
1 x x^2 x cub x4 so on and so forth. And
those would be so I would have a matrix
with 1 x x^2 x cub x for so on. And
those would be my features, right?
Instead, but I'm not doing polomial
regression here. Here I'm doing my
features are whatever the entries of
this derivative are. Okay? So it's a
It's this I'm using the word feature by
analogy in some sense. this is a feature
because it's
multiplying this uh the the first order
term right and so this is basically what
is changing so when you let's say you
are trying to do fine-tuning of a
network right so I have some I've
already have some parameters I've
already learned them and now I'm
updating them and changing them with
some uh with some fine-tuning one can
think of these are the features that
you're basically uh that you're that
you're tuning. Okay.
Okay. Any questions on this? Basically,
what I want you to see is two important
things. One is that we have this
nonlinear function. Neural network is
fundamentally nonlinear.
But
I can try to think of it in a linear way
by taking this
uh tailor expansion of the network
around the parameters or around a
particular parameter and then thinking
of how how my function changes as my
parameters change little by little.
Make sense? Everyone with me there?
Okay, good.
So now can we revisit our descent
algorithms with taking this perspective?
Okay, one thing I should say, um, I
didn't I'm not really going to talk
about it, but this is very connected to
this idea of the neural tangent kernel,
which you may or may not encounter or
hear about, but this is this idea of
being able to talk about when uh descent
algorithms will converge and give
provable guarantees. And thinking about
the neural tangent kernel basically
comes from
thinking about this exact perspective of
the network as a um uh as a linear
thinking about the linear approximation
of the network in exactly this way. And
basically what you can what you can do
and what you can show is that in the
limit of infinite width networks so it's
a theoretical perspective but as your
networks get wider and wider what ends
up happening is that these features um
can be thought of in a particular sense.
You can you can kind of work the math to
make these into a kernel
and then you can find this kernel that
is what matters for your network in this
infinite width uh in this infinite width
limit. We're not going to talk about it
very much in the class but just an FYI
for you all. If you know this comes up
when people start talking about neural
tangent kernels, what you want to think
about is you want to think about okay,
they're taking this linear perspective
on the network and you're thinking about
the derivatives as the features. Okay,
just putting that out there. Okay.
So
what I want to do now is I want to say
let me revisit
Adam.
Okay. And really I want to revisit Adam
as sin SGD. Right? We talked about this
last time.
Okay. So I have this f ofx
comma theta i
and this is f ofx
comma theta i.
Um,
Okay,
I have this tailor expansion
and what is the fundamental tension when
we are trying to take a gradient descent
or atom or any descent algorithm
perspective.
Well,
what I'm trying to do is, you know,
gradient descent is saying, well, let me
look at the locally linear structure of
this particular function and then let me
try to take a step in the direction that
is indicated as descending from this
local approximation perspective. Right?
So
what I want to do with gradient descent
is I want to converge to the minimum or
wherever I want to converge to very very
fast and converging fast means taking
big steps. Right?
However, my gradient information is
valid in a local neighborhood. Okay? So
if I take these giant big steps, what's
going to happen? I'm going to ruin my
approximation guarantee and so I'm going
to like you know I'll be taking a step
but then my my local linear
approximation is simply not going to
hold true. So that pushes me to take
very small steps right to to make sure
that my approximation is true. So does
everyone see the the tension that is
there between wanting to take larger
steps and wanting to take smaller steps.
This is fundamentally kind of the the
the
issue. So there's a tension here.
want
large steps
to be able
to converge
fast.
And I want small steps
to make sure
uh approximation
still holds.
Okay.
So if I wanted to now put my
optimization hat on,
what's what are ways in which we could
try to actually
resolve such a tension?
So maybe actually yeah take a minute and
like talk and try to think about this.
Take one minute to actually just think
about it. Feel free to talk and engage
engage with the problem. Does is
everyone clear with the issue?
>> Yeah. Good.
>> Yeah.
I guess
you
I think that's
>> Well, I guess
Okay.
>> So, anyone have any particular ideas
they want to share as to how we could
approach this?
>> Yeah.
>> You could just take big steps to start
and then work your way down to smaller
steps.
>> You could just take big steps to start
and work your way down to smaller steps.
That's that's a great idea. And in some
sense, gradient descent, when you think
about it in the traditional convex
perspective, is essentially trying to do
that, right? because you're saying that
as you get closer to your optimum, your
gradient is becoming closer and closer
to zero.
Um, and so even though you have a
constant step size and gradient descent,
it converges because as your gradient is
becoming closer to the optimum, it's
becoming closer to zero. So yes,
absolutely. And so there is this idea of
learning rate schedules where you
basically keep changing your learning
rate um to be able to get to
convergence. So absolutely that's a very
valid idea and that is something that is
very much done in practice. So that's
not what we're going to do today or
that's not the perspective I want to
take today.
>> Yeah.
>> I would see if there's some way that we
could bound or or get some analysis of
the error of our approximation and then
see if we could like we can get some
bounds on that error and maybe determine
the largest step size we can take within
a certain error.
>> Yeah. So we're not going to do exactly
that but we're going to do something in
that basic direction. So the idea was to
say you know try to understand the
trade-offs of the approximation and say
like what's the best you can do given
some constraints essentially. Yeah.
>> Yeah. That's a great idea. So you would
try try to understand the nature or the
curvature of the function and the
geometry that is actually mattering. We
would love to do that but sometimes it
can be very hard to understand what that
local geometry actually is. And so we
want to be able to do things that might
not require us to actually do that but
it's a totally great approach if we
could actually do that.
So what we're going to do today is we're
going to you know take this optimization
perspective
and so we're going to say well I want to
make sure that my step is not too big
and so I'm going to say what if I put a
constraint on the size of the step okay
and I say find the best step but within
some bound okay so the idea
is to bound
the size
of your step.
Okay. So for example, I take my delta
theta and I take some norm on it and I
want to make sure that it is smaller
than some ADA. And so I say look within
this maybe try to find the biggest step
right try to find the best step but
don't go too far otherwise you're going
to lose the properties of the
approximation okay
and now I want to use this to write a
constrained optimization problem for
minimizing my function but I want to
take this local linear perspective on my
neural network. Okay. So the
optimization function I want to write
is the following.
Maybe I want to
this here.
Okay. So what have I written here? I've
just written out
my linear approximation. So let's say
I'm doing some kind of descent
algorithm. So theta I is where I'm
currently at. So maybe I should write
this out here too just to recall.
Call
theta i + 1 is equal to
theta i - aa * whatever your step is
okay
and this step here that we take is
typically
something in the direction of the
gradient right but depending on exactly
whether you're doing gradient descent or
stoastic gradient descent or momentum or
atom or whatever that step is is
different, right? That's the whole
that's that's how these update
algorithms differ. Okay,
so here what I've done is I've said I
just want to take this linear
approximation
and I'm looking at basically the average
over all of my data points. Okay, so
these XL's is what I'm averaging over.
So now when I look at this,
there's something here that I haven't
quite specified yet.
What is the thing that I haven't quite
specified?
Like I've I've handwaved one thing.
>> Yeah.
>> Okay. I'm just using the um standard
uklidian inner product. So good
question, but I'm just using the
standard one.
Yes.
>> Higher order terms for the expansion.
>> Higher order terms. Yes. I'm I'm I'm
ignoring those.
Both of those are are are indeed things
that I am a little bit handwaving.
There's one more thing that I'm
handwaving.
Um, and that is basically I haven't
really told you what norm I'm using
here, right? Uh, there's many different
norms that I could use or I could want
to use. Okay. So, when I say that I
don't want I want to make sure that my
step isn't too big. Well, I can think of
this the standard kind of when you don't
define your norm. The standard thing you
think about is what happens if you take
the two norm and we'll talk about that.
But if you remember, there's actually
many many different norms that you could
think about, right? So if you want to
think about it in a not changing too
much perspective, one natural way to
think about it might be to think about
actually the infinity norm, right? What
does the infinity norm say? The infinity
norm says look at the vector on a
coordinate by coordinate basis and make
sure that no particular coordinate is
larger than this. Right? So the infinity
norm is the maximum of for of all of
your entries. Okay, maximum and absolute
value.
So this is just saying this is the max
over
uh
delta
theta j
should be less than equal to and max
over j. Okay. So I want all of my
entries to be less than that. Yes.
Question.
understanding correctly.
>> Yes.
this linearizing
whatever
is
trying to minimize a loss function.
Um,
so, uh, yes, I'm like,
uh, yes, I am, uh, doing a little bit
of, uh, I didn't I didn't set this up
correctly. So, yes, here I'm I'm doing a
little bit of bad notation. I guess I'm
thinking of f really as the loss
function. Uh so I should not I should
not have used that f in the neural
network sense earlier
but I'm really thinking about how is the
loss function changing given the uh
yeah maybe I should have called this L.
Okay forgive me I should have called
this L but I I used F. Yes
>> in this case we're actually trying to
find the optimal delta vector we just
We're trying to find the optimal vector.
We're trying to actually find the
optimal vector. Um, but we're bounding
only the infinity norm of this.
Okay,
clear. Great question. Thank you for
pointing that out.
Okay. So now when I want to do this, I
want I want to do this optimization.
So I'm looking at this and is there a
term that doesn't matter here?
This term clearly doesn't depend on
delta theta, right? So it's not going to
affect the argument of this. So I can
essentially just completely drop this
from my optimization. It doesn't matter
at all in terms of finding the argument.
It will matter for the minimum value,
but the argument simply doesn't care.
Okay. So I can rewrite this as just
the argument of just this second term.
Okay.
But now when I look at this I have this
summation here
and this inner product over here. Okay.
So summation inner product but the inner
product is basically linear right. So
what I can do is I can take this
summation inside the inner product.
Right? This L is only varying in the
first term. Delta theta is the same for
everything. So I can rewrite this as
argument
delta theta
um
inner product 1 / n sigma l going from
one to n
gradient
I'm just
Okay.
And now when I look at this,
is there something that we can we can
notice when we think about this?
So actually I'll give you a minute to to
think about what what this inner product
is doing. And if there's something you
can notice about what what you can say
about this optimization, take just one
minute to think about it.
or feel free to talk.
Finally,
Okay. So, what I want to think about
here is when I'm looking at this
This is an inner product, right? So
these are two vectors
and here I have a constraint here. This
constraint is a function of is is
basically it's an entry-wise constraint,
right? But this is actually an
entry-wise sum. So I have the first
entry of this times the first entry of
this, the second entry of this, the
second time the second entry of this. So
I can rewrite this whole thing as an
argument.
um over the sum of j
1 / n whatever this whole thing is. So
maybe I can just copy this thing.
And then I want to look at
the J entry of this vector
and times the J entry
of this
right and I'm just writing out the inner
product element by element wise And now
I'm going to write this infinity norm as
saying for every J I want the absolute
value of delta theta to be less than or
equal to ADA. Okay.
So now I have constraints here on every
single entry I should say sorry theta J.
I have constraints here on every entry
and I've pulled out every entry of this
vector here. So this I've basically the
way writing it this way we decouple the
problems
into individual optimization problems on
every single
uh entry of the vector delta theta right
because I want to minimize this thing
but my constraints are my my my my the
different things that I'm optimizing
over the entries of delta theta are no
longer coupled together
right because I have I can rewrite it as
a constraint on every single entry and
now I can just optimize each do each of
these optimizations one by one. Does
that make sense to everyone?
Okay. So I can just rewrite this. So do
each optimization individually.
And then what I can get
is argument.
I'm just going to call this the gradient
with respect to theta of fbatch. So I
just don't have to write this sum out
again. just this whole thing I'm calling
that
>> yes
I'm calling
this thing
fbatch
f
gradient And on that patch.
Okay.
But now this optimization problem
I kind of know how to solve, right? So
I'm saying look I can choose theta to be
anything from minus ADA.
Minus 8 is the smallest it can be
and the largest it can be is plus ADA.
And I have everything of every one of
these is scaled
by this fbatch. Right? this gradient of
fbatch.
So now what ch if I want to now minimize
this thing how do I decide
which to choose
if I have yeah at the back
>> check the sign of the gradient
>> yeah you just check the sign of the
gradient right is that what you were
going to say as well yeah so basically
if
so I can just say that delta theta
Say that delta theta J
is equal to plus ADA if
gradient of Fbatch
is less than zero and is equal to minus
ADA if gradient
is greater than zero. Okay. And so that
gives me that my delta theta star
is just given by minus ADA times the
sign
of the gradient.
But what is this exact algorithm that we
just talked about? Right? This is just
sin SGD. This is exactly the same
algorithm that is kind of the underlying
basis for atom. What we did with Adam
was we did a smoothing of this by adding
an accumulation for the gradient terms.
Okay.
So what this is saying is that
we can think of Adam as
from this linear perspective
as doing a particular descent step under
the constraint that you want to be
constrained in your infinity norm sense.
Okay.
So it's it's it's basically a motivation
a theoretical motivation uh for why sin
SGD makes sense like you can see now how
from the infinity norm perspective the
sign is actually the optimal step that
you can take without while making sure
that your step isn't too big right and
ADA is essentially playing the same role
as the learning rate there's a reason we
chose that bound ADA to get that exactly
same thing out
okay does that make sense for everyone?
Any questions about this?
So, we're going to be building on this
in the coming lectures when we talk
about uh another series of or more in
this family of optimization algorithms.
>> Yes.
>> Um does that mean like function better?
No, it's not about the quality of the
approximation so much, but what there
are several recent papers talking about
and that's what we're trying to distill
and and share to you is the idea that
the particular geometries of the network
seem to matter. And there is there are
recent papers that argue that the
infinity norm is you can think of the
infinity norm as a particular um
particular kind of max norm. I think
that this paper um calls it the max of
max norms and this is particularly
aligned to uh to descent.
So what the thing is is that different
norms might be aligned to different
geometries and maybe the heart of the
problem comes from trying to find the
norm that is aligned. Now in some sense
why the infinity norm is aligned is
still not fully clear but maybe that
that is one perspective that
that is the reason that Adam is
performing well. It's not because these
linear approximations are particularly
good.
Okay. So, in the interest of time, I'm
not going to do this other
uh example. If we have time, I might
come back to it at the end of lecture,
but we will either put it on discussion
or in your homework. But there's now a
natural question that you should be
asking me. I just did this. What is the
natural question that you all have?
We picked the infinity norm somehow but
that was somewhat arbitrary, right? And
there's many many many other norms. So
what's the natural other norm that you
want to take? Right? You want to try the
two norm. So what happens if you do that
exact same optimization problem but you
think about the two norm constraint.
Well, I want to think about delta theta.
Okay, I'm not going to do this right
now. Um, if I have time at the end of
the lecture, I'll come back to it. But
basically, you can follow a very similar
argument. And if you recall from 127
where we talked a lot about, you know,
optimization problems over different
kinds of norm balls, you might see that
there's a very there's a parallel to
exactly what we did, right? We're saying
that let's look at the infinity norm
ball and then let's maximize an inner
product within the infinity norm ball.
That's exactly the calculation that we
did. Similarly, now when you look at the
two norm, you're maximizing an inner
product within the two norm ball.
There's a particular inequality that's
matters here, which what is the
inequality that relates to the two norm?
It's the one that you learned in 16A.
It's like the only one that's the most
basic one.
>> Koshi Schwarz, right? Koshi Schwarz. So
Kashwarge tells you that the inner
product of two vectors is the largest
when they are
aligned. Right? So you can think about
that to think about what this might get
you. I'm not going to do it out, but
maybe we'll put it on the on the
homework or something like that. Okay.
Any questions about this? Because I want
to change gears a little bit with the
last time I have. Yes.
>> So you talked about
The approximation is only valid in
narrow neighborhood. Yes.
>> And I know that the norm is a way of
constraining our model, but I'm just
missing the connection between the two.
>> Okay. So what I'm trying to say is that
this the size of delta theta dictates
the size of the step that I'm taking. So
if I take so I
ADA the ADA that I'm constraining to is
still a hyperparameter. And so I'm still
saying that look, I'm going to choose
some ball where I hope my approximation
is still going to hold true. And by
choosing to search only within that ball
of ADA, I'm saying let's look only at
things where my approximation is going
to be true because if I but I I'm not
I'm not giving you a number ADA that
says here is where your approximation is
true. That's still a hyperparameter.
>> Does that help?
>> Yeah, that helps a lot.
>> Okay.
Okay, so now stepping back, we're trying
to do all this stuff. We're trying to
optimize. We're trying to find the best
optimization algorithms to get to the
minimum as fast as possible. But there's
many, many other things that go into
training our models well. And it's not
just if you choose the right optimizer,
your your stuff is going to work.
There's like 500 other things that you
have to think about. And what we're
going to talk about is some of those
other things because turns out that
these all of these things all interact
to be able to understand how to optimize
over a network well you have to
understand all of the different
components.
So the other important thing or one
other important thing is standardization
and normalization of your data. And
you've all seen this before in your
machine learning class where whenever
you have some data for whatever machine
learning problem, you standardize it.
You normalize it. So what's one standard
way of normalizing things? Well, you
say, let me take my all of my data and
squish it to be within minus one to one
or let me make it zero mean with
variance one. Right? These are standard
things, standard tricks and standard
transformations and scalings that you do
of your data to to get into that range.
Why do we care about doing this? And why
do we standardize the data in this way?
Anyone remember
what is the who cares? Why like why what
happens? What's the bad thing that can
happen if you have some features that
are, you know, on the order of 10 the
minus 2, 10 the minus 3 and other
features that are on the order of, you
know, 10 to the 10 thousands, billions,
whatever. Yeah. The back
>> numerical stability problems.
>> You're going to have numerical stability
problems, right? First, if your dynamic
range is too big, you simply might not
be able to fit it into floatingoint
precision. So, that's that's a clear
that's a uh that's a key issue.
Um but second you might have really bad
conditioning on your matrices right so
you might have problems inverting things
but there's another even in some sense
uh more fundamental issue which is that
like let's say I have different features
I'm trying to predict um I don't know a
person's favorite flavor of ice cream
and I have different features that are
you know the person's height and the
person's birth eight and the person's
um I don't know favorite part of 182 um
whatever these features are these are
all very different types of features
right and so if I have some features
that are really small and other features
that are really large the large features
are going to dominate
in whatever my model ends up predicting
right if I have some some things that
are tiny they're just not they're just
going to be ignored in my error
computation and these big things are
going uh going to matter more even
though they might not actually be the
most uh informative features. So by
normalizing all of the features, what I
can do is I can have all of the features
have an equal chance of having high
predictive power. So one way to think
about is if you think about SVMs, right?
So you think about max margin
separators. Max margin separators are
saying like let let me make sure that
the actual distance is is maximized
right between my two classes right and
now if I have if I have a vector where
um some components maybe the first few
components are always really small and
the last few components are always
really large my distance maximization is
going to matter is going to depend more
on these last few components than on the
first few components does everyone see
that and so I will have a different
perspective than if I had everything
that was approximately in the same order
of magnitude.
So my outcomes will actually be
different if I do and do not normalize
my data.
Everyone understand that? So you're
bought in on the fact that we need to
normalize our data and we need to
standardize things. Okay.
From a neural network perspective,
there's one more important thing is that
neural networks have nonlinearities. The
nonlinearities are the power of the
neural networks. And if you think about
relus for example, well the interesting
stuff in rel is essentially somehow
happening around zero, right? The
nonlinearity of the relu is near zero or
whatever it is. So you want to be able
to make sure that your data is in is set
up in a way that you can actually
harness the power of that nonlinearity.
And if you're kind of way out there in
different places, then you might not be
able to do that very well. Okay.
So to see that, let's consider actually
this like a very simple ReLU case, the
scalar case that you've already all
looked at in your homework.
So here I have some input X and then I
multiply it by a weight. I add a bias
and then I have my ReLU nonlinearity for
this, right?
And my relu nonlinearity looks basically
like this elbow. And where is this
elbow? Well, it's going to be at minus b
over w. Right? So by choosing the weight
and the bias, I get to move where this
elbow actually ends up. So we're going
to train this network. But let's say we
initialize this network at um with you
know normal 01 parameters. So I have B
is normal 01 and my W is also normal 01.
Then it turns out that I can think of um
my uh corner my elbow
as coming from a Kashi distribution
because that's going to be the
distribution that comes from this ratio
of two Gaussian distributions. Okay. So
this Kashi distribution has the
following um density 1 over pi.
Basically it's like 1 /x^2
And this distribution has some
interesting properties, right? A lot of
the mass of this distribution is around
zero. But the mean of it is actually
undefined because this is actually it
ends up being a divergent series.
The variance of this thing is infinite
because these things are heavy tailed.
So you can kind of have mass that the
mass is going out to infinity and you
have a lot of mass going there.
Nonetheless, if I try to look at where
the probability mass of this is, if I
look at the CDFs of these things, well,
I can say that 50% of the probability
mass is actually between minus1 to 1.
And if I keep looking, you know, 90% of
it is between minus 7 to 7, right? 70%
between -2 to 2, 80% between -3 to 3,
and then most of it is actually from
minus 7 to 7. So what does this mean?
This means that these corners, where do
they hang out under this initialization?
Under this initialization, yes, there
some that are way out there, but most of
them are still kind of around zero.
Okay, everyone see that?
Okay, good.
So now what we want to do is we want to
get our data to be in a spot basically
where the nonlinearity is actually
interesting
and here we talked about the relu but
even if I was to take let's say some
other nonlinearity the interesting stuff
is still kind of going to be happening
around zeroish.
So what we want to do is we want to be
able to initialize we want to be able to
standardize our data so that it can be
also around zero and that's why one
thing that you often do is that you will
take your data and you will normalize it
to be zero mean or or standardize it to
be zero mean and variance one or just
uniform between minus1 to one. Okay.
So then what happens basically if we you
know don't do this
let's take an example let's consider and
suppose all of our input data came from
this range of 100 to 200.
Well, you can compute exactly using the
Koshi distribution. The approximate
probability of one of your elbows
landing in this range is about 0.1%.
Right? Really small. So, you're going to
have maybe two, three corners that are
actually going to hit your data. So,
what does that mean? Most of your data
is going to either see just zero or it's
going to see the straight uh aphine
function, right? It's not going to see
anything
interesting. You're going to have a lot
of limitations in kind of the
expressivity that you can uh you can
get. Does everyone see this intuition?
Yeah. And do you see that that could be
bad? So if I want to think about it
mathematically, mathematically why is
this bad?
Okay.
So for this like for example if I take
again a simple example I have some
X um and I'm multiplying it by different
weights W1
and then I add a bias B1
and then it goes into my ReLU
W2 to
Can I have these activations or input
pre-activations that are coming out?
Um, let's say I have a thousand
units here.
So what this is doing is basically
computing this scaler and this is a
thousand dimensional vector of or this
is the features that are coming out
right from doing this.
So what happens if there are no corners?
What do these h1 h2 h thousand actually
look like? These are the features that
I'm trying to get to be interesting.
the red shirt at the back. Yeah,
>> the rail wouldn't do anything in some
sense, right? So, if I have no corners,
what I'm going to have is my hi is going
to be either is going to just be zero.
And this is going to be true for every
input, right?
All of my inputs are in this range. It's
going to be either zero or I will hit
some
I'll hit the linear part, right?
So for some alpha and beta, I'm going to
be
but I don't have an input that like you
know will actually use the elbow part of
this.
Okay.
So what does this mean for if I think
about now if I think about all of my
data and I think about it as a as a I
think about the the the matrix that is
coming from looking at the features of
all of my data
here. Let's say this is going into a
linear layer. Now what does that matrix
looks like? Well, it looks like just
either you have a column of zeros
because you've just hit the zeros or you
have a column that is looking entirely
like this, right?
So this now matrix is this matrix going
to be a full rank matrix?
Well, first you're going to have lots of
columns of zeros in it. So that's
already you're losing a bunch of rank
and even the other columns are all going
to be
related to each other, right? So what
you're going to have is a very low rank
matrix. So for example, just to see that
if you wanted to look at this and say
just hypothetically, let's say all the
beta eyes were zero.
Wrong pen.
And I have some matrix here that is like
alpha 1 x1 + beta 1 alpha 1 x2 + beta 1
alpha 1 x n + beta 1
Let's see. I have all the way to H100.
So, X1 plus beta 1
or beta 1000.
So, let's say I have some matrix like
this.
And if all the betas were zeros,
what are these columns?
Dude, what is the rank of this matrix if
all the betas are zero?
>> Yeah, someone said it. Just say it
louder.
>> One, right? It's just multiples of the
same column.
And similarly, if all the alphas were
zero,
you're still going to have a rank one
matrix because now you just have beta 1,
beta 2, beta 3, beta 4, right? That's
also now just copies of the same row. So
you again end up with a rank one matrix.
So then you can think of this matrix
basically as the sum of the two cases
when alpha is zero and beta is zero. And
you can say that this basically is going
to be a rank two matrix. Okay. But you
definitely rank two is not good enough.
Right?
And maybe you know maybe you got like so
this is this is a case where you got
zero corners between
the in the data range that you have.
Maybe you got like one or two corners,
right? Maybe you got five corners, but
that's still not going to be an
expressive enough matrix for you to be
able to actually use your data. Okay, so
mathematically, like intuitively, you
see why this is bad. But even
mathematically, from you look at if you
look at the conditioning of this matrix,
it's still not a good situation to be in
to have your data be all in a range that
is very different from where your
nonlinearities are hanging out. Okay,
that's basically the main point that I
want to make.
And so one thing that you might want to
think about is like when you're
debugging a neural network or something
isn't working, looking at the
conditioning of your feature matrices is
something that can actually
maybe help, right? Some of these
sometimes these are going to be low rank
and that's maybe fine. But you know when
you're just looking for things to
examine to understand why something
might not be working,
checking your normalization, checking
the scaling, checking whether these
conditionings are okay is is something
that might might help you in making
progress.
Okay, any questions about this?
Okay, so good. So now you're all bought
in that your data kind of needs to be in
a reasonable range to be able to make
progress, right?
But and I can do whatever I want. So
let's say I have some neural network.
I get to control and normalize and
standardize all I want for this part of
the input, right? But there's many many
many many layers.
So for me to be able to have good
training, I kind of want to be able to
say something
about what's happening everywhere in the
network, right? Not just standardizing
the the first layer because maybe I'll
just standardize the first layer and or
the input and things might still blow
up. There's all these kinds of weights
and biases that are doing who knows what
to my data.
So what if we what do we do? Let's say
we assume that our input is
standardized. It's mean zero. It's
variance one. It's very nice. We've
cleaned it up. But there's still now we
want to have a second question that
shows up is where do we start? How do we
initialize our network so that we can
train fast and quickly and not run into
problems where you know things are uh
things are blowing up or things are just
disappearing into zero. How do we try to
uh do this?
Well, we want things to be in the
neighborhood of zero. And so a standard
answer like something that you would
wish would be true and would work would
be to say, well, I really wish I could
just start at zero, right? What's a
better place? I want to be near zero.
So, let me just start all my parameters
at zero. That would be great, right? I
don't if I didn't have to worry about
this.
But what's the problem that comes up if
I try to put all of my weights to zero?
If I initialize all of my weights to
zero, what happens is my input is coming
in and it just get multiplied by 0 0 0
all I do is I pass in a zero and then
there's no gradient. The gradients are
also zero and then nothing moves
anywhere ever.
So
that kind of sucks and that is not
something you want. It wouldn't matter
for the biases because the biases are
only additive. But the weights are
multiplicative and so initializing the
weights to zeros is a problem because
you will basically not get any
gradients. Everything will stagnate.
Nothing will move. You will not train at
all. Okay. So you need to be able to
have something there that you can
actually take gradients on that will
allow you to train.
So you know what do you what do you want
to do? Well, you want to initialize them
so that you can actually
get stuff to work.
And so here we want to make a key
observation is we want to have let's say
we have some nice standardized input. I
kind of want to be able to make sure
that after it goes through this layer my
weights and biases at least initially
are not so crazy that whatever I get at
my output is now a completely totally
different distribution. Right? Because
again then for the next layer I want to
be in the neighborhood of where my
nonlinearities are interesting because
if if if this layer sends everything to
the 100 to 200 range then I'm screwed
again.
Does that make sense to everyone?
Okay.
So our goal is basically to say that can
we somehow have the inputs to every
layer be standardized at least at
initialization because that's what we
control. Whatever happens once we start
training will happen. But at
initialization
can we have that can we have that
basically the statistical properties
at these output activations are the same
same as the statistic properties here
because basically the output activations
from this layer are the input
activations for the are the inputs for
the next layer. Right? Does that make
sense to everyone? Like what that's our
that's our rough rough goal. And does
everyone see why this is like a
reasonable thing to want?
Okay, good. So that brings me to talking
about uh Xavier or Glor uh
initialization and this is
initialization for the weights of the
network. So the weights are basically
the parameters that are multiplying the
data. The biases are the things that are
adding in.
So basically
what this is observing is that look your
neural networks are going to have
different architecture
and the architecture of your neural
network is going to somehow in some
sense determine
or it's going not going to determine but
it's going to influence how big or small
your different quantities
will actually get.
So for example, if I have some inputs,
let's say I have a fan in, I'm going to
call this fan in of D. And so I have
this input, it gets multiplied by W1,
this by W2, this W, whatever W3. I add
them up, I add my bias term, it goes
into a nonlinearity, and it uh it comes
out.
Let's say I want to have that my input
to my nonlinearity which is where I want
which is where my you know I want to
make sure that that is standardized in a
way that it's going to actually be in
the neighborhood of the interesting
stuff. So I want it to be approximately
zero mean. I want it to be approximately
unit variance.
And I'm assuming that say that my inputs
are all approximately zero mean and unit
variance because I've standardized them.
Right?
So now what can I do? What do I need to
do to kind of make sure that the stuff
here
is approximately
has the same statistical properties or
has the zero mean unit variance property
as these inputs here did.
So yeah, we have one minute. Why don't
you think about it before I just walk
through the answer?
Feel
free to talk just yeah
remember your probability linearity of
expectation things like that
Galaxy
Okay.
So here, okay, anyone? So what is the
thought right here? If I have a bunch of
normal 01s coming in,
let's say if I call these
um what should I call them? I can call
them H1, H2,
H
D I guess.
Then I want to look at the variance.
I should add a page.
I want to look at the variance
of
this thing, right?
Because
Let's say B is just zero. Let's just say
I choose to initialize the bias to zero
and kind of don't worry about the bias
in initialization because the bias
initialization is not as big a deal.
It's not going to cause me to blow up or
die out to zero.
But I look at this variance
or I want to look at this variance
because basically this variance is the
variance of what's going to show up
here. Right? Now, if I add a bunch of
zero mean things, let's say all of these
are zero mean. What is going to be the
mean of the thing that shows up here?
They're all going to be zero, right?
Because these um
hi and wi are they're independent.
So, I can just think of their product as
the the product of the expectations is
the expectation of the product. And so
if my WIS are all zero mean, then even
if these are not zero mean, they are,
but I would still get a zero mean thing
here.
And now I want to look at this variance
here. So what is this variance? Well, I
can think of this as the expected value
of
sigma wi hi
squared
minus the expected value of
the expected value of the square minus
the square of the expected value.
Okay,
but I already know that the square of
this expected value
this thing is zero.
And now because
W and H are independent
and are zero mean, I can just write this
further
as the expected value of WI^ 2 times the
expected value of HI 2.
Okay. And so with this now, basically if
I'm adding d of these things together,
what do I need to have each of these be
so that the output is one?
Right? Well, I want to have this guy
all be like one overd so that when I
multiply by one and I add d of them, I'm
going to get one out. Right? So if I
want the variance here
to be one,
not here, here I want the variance here
to be one. I want these things to be
initialized essentially as a normal with
mean zero and variance one overd.
The idea is that if you have more things
adding in that's going to add to your
variance. Make sure you the variance of
the individual things that are adding in
is appropriately small so that when they
add up together their variance is not
too large.
Okay. So this is the key idea behind
Xavier initialization that talks about
this dependence on the architecture of
the neural network and particularly the
fan in at every point. Okay.
Now when you look at actual
implementations in Xavier
um there's sometimes a dependence on the
fan out and you can do different vision
variations but the key idea here is to
realize that what you're trying to do is
you're trying to make sure that things
aren't getting too big or too small
based on the particular architecture of
the network at every different point.
Okay, that's the the key thing that uh
you want to I want to say. The other
thing that I want to say is that it's
worth sometimes looking at the default
parameter settings because the default
parameter settings on the
initializations may or may not do
exactly what you want it to do. But
thinking about what do I want my values
to behave like or look like as they go
through um can is a good way of thinking
about it. Sometimes you care also about
the fan out. So what is happening here?
we just assume that there's only one
thing but you might be going to
different places. So that's something to
to think about. Okay,
the last thing what I want to talk about
and if I have a few minutes I'll come
back to this Xavier initialization but I
want to talk about H initialization
which is a different which is a
different initialization
and what people noticed was that the
Xavier initialization does not work well
when the previous layer is a relu
and why is that the case.
Well, turns out when I look at a relu,
what does a relu look like?
A relu looks like a lot of zero for a
long time and then stuff starts
happening. Okay. And this corner
essentially is around zero. So half of
the time
I'm going to have my ReLU output a zero
and the other half of the time I'm going
to have you know the identity function
come out.
So maybe if I'm coming if I'm looking at
things from a ReLU perspective, my true
fan in is not actually D, but it's only
half of D because half of those have
been zeroed out by the previous ReLU.
Does everyone see that?
And so maybe a better initialization is
to account for the fact that half of my
stuff is going to be zero and put a d
over two here
which looks as like so I'm writing this
this way so that it's clear where that
two is coming from. If you write it this
way it's a little bit harder to see.
Okay but this is the h initialization
and it turns out that this actually
matters in it actually helps improve
performance to use the hood
initialization over the Xavier
initialization. And it was actually
developed because people noticed that
things were not working uh for ReLU
networks. Okay.
And in light of this, I want to point
out something about the about the Xavier
initialization. So there's a little bit
of a
trickery or not fully rigorous thing
that I I've done is that I said that I
wanted to use like an inductive argument
to say that
oh you know if my input is standardized
here well I want to initialize so it's
good here if it's good here it'll be
good here
but here we're actually looking
before the nonlinearity right I gave you
a guarant guarantee on what's happening
before the nonlinearity.
I'm not actually giving you a guarantee
on what's happening after the
nonlinearity.
Whereas if you look at the H
initialization, it's kind of kind of
taking into account the nonlinearity and
it's talking about if you do this well,
you know, half of the time you're going
to be zero, you know, other half of the
time you're identity. So maybe you're
going to be approximately
u approximately good. So there's a
slight difference in in how these two
perspectives are looking at it and if
you in Xavier initialization
you might have to do other things to
sometimes make your data be normalized
or nice and when you talk about
constants I guess you'll be talking
about things like batch uh about
normalizations at every layer so that
you can uh you know make sure that
things are still being kind of be
behaving kind of reasonably.
Okay. Yes. Question. I've seen some
variations of these initialization
algorithms to like utilize the fan out.
So you normalize the backwards. Yes. You
ever need to do that?
>> So um the question is like you know when
you look at when you when you Google
Xavier initialization for example you
will often see something that looks at d
what like instead of one overd fan in
it's one overd fan in plus one overd fan
out. And the
the reason for that is that sometimes if
you're looking at what's happening on
the backward pass, you have uh you you
you also want to take into account
what's happening on the gradient. So the
forward pass is looking at just the
values. What's happening on the backward
pass is the gradient.
The thing the reality is that sometimes
it just doesn't matter too much because
these numbers are all not that uh not
that bad.
The other thing is that if it works, it
works. So there is not as clean an
intuition. Um though one way of thinking
about it is that well on the forward
pass you want one over D fan in. On the
backward pass you want one over D fan
out. You choose the best of both worlds
and you choose one over D fan out plus
fan in as like a midway of making
everyone happy. And if it works
reasonably well, you're happy. So, uh,
sometimes you have to worry about it,
sometimes you don't. It kind of will
depend. That's the answer.
Uh, last question, but we're actually at
time. So, uh, but go ahead.
>> Does the same reasoning apply to the
initialization of the final layer?
initializer of the final layer? That's a
really good question. So the finer layer
can actually be initialized slightly
differently because you don't have the
issue of the zeroing out of the uh of
the gradient. So if I just think about
this, let's say final linear layer
here,
because there's only one, you're only
one hop from the gradient. As long as
your inputs here are not zero, you could
initialize to this to zero and still be
fine.
But that only is true for the last layer
and not true for everything else.
Okay, great. That's it. Thanks.
>> Thank you.
regarding