Okay, let's start.
So,
uh couple of uh reminder, some
announcements. This is the last lecture.
We'll have office hours afterwards. Uh
everyone is presumably extremely busy
working on their final project reports
and you know, still having code running
presumably I I'm guessing for many
people. um trying to get those last few
experiments to run or you know fix bugs.
So, you know, we did extend the deadline
for the final project report to Sunday,
December 7th to give you uh the weekend
also instead of just uh having you do
tomorrow. But remember, you you really
need to finish it because you have to
prepare a poster for Tuesday, December
9th, which will be, you know, in the WS
and then we'll have assigned peer
reviews to everyone for the final
reports uh on Monday and then those are
due on Thursday. So, take advantage of
the posters to do that. Any questions on
the project deadlines and scope? Yeah,
back.
>> Uh,
I think you're on your own. Print the
posters how you want. Um, in the past
some people have used, you know, the
commercial poster printing at things
like the FedEx store. Other people have
used sometimes people have access to
some labs that have some printing, but
it's totally fine and we do not we're
not going to penalize anyone in the
least if you just like print it out on
pieces of paper and like arrange them
together into an array of uh of pieces
of paper. That's totally fine. The point
here is not uh we're not judging you on
fancy looks or styling. That's just not
what we care about. Um, we wish we could
have a departmental printer that people
had access to that printed posters, but
uh they do not. Uh, that request should
be sent uh to the university.
Um, other questions? Yeah.
>> So, we're expecters.
>> Um,
yes. Um, but I think you have access to
an instructional allocation on the inst
machines which will let you print on
regular. You don't have to print in
color. Just print black and white using
the regular instructional printers.
>> Make slides and print on pieces of
paper, right?
>> You could hand dry it too if you wanted.
>> It doesn't have to be you don't have to
spend $200 on like some laminated
fancy thing. Like the point the point is
more for you to explain
to us kind of
what you did and have a
to do that. So, make your poster in a
way that helps you talk. It's not about
like having something shiny. Does that
make sense?
>> So, yeah.
>> So, they're not expecting you to spend a
ton of money on this.
>> Yeah. Um on that note, um we do
encourage everyone bring a printed copy
of your report with you because you
might need to reference it. have a
laptop where you can also bring up plots
and code or anything based on the
conversations we're having. So have it
possible because one of the things about
making a poster is making choices about
how you're going to tell a story to uh
communicate the ideas of what you did in
a clear way. However, in a conversation
at a poster, it can always go deeper and
you want to be prepared to do that, too.
And if you have some cool simulation or
some cool plot that looks really great
in color and you couldn't print it in
color, bring your laptop, right? Show it
on your laptop. That's also
okay. Um any other questions on the sort
of project
um logistics side is really important.
This is the last uh meeting. So, you
know, after you done the peer reviews,
uh those are done. They'll be fed back
to everyone. uh you will then have until
Sunday, December 14th to incorporate all
of the comments that you have gotten
from the peer reviews as well as
anything you you know kind of observed
at the poster in terms of the
conversation. Fold that into your report
and submit the final final version.
Okay, that final final version together
with your reviewing and together with
the uh poster session is what you're
going to be graded on. Right? That's the
key thing.
But you you you definitely want to take
advantage of the peer review to make it
make things better.
>> Question. Yeah.
>> Questioning of the final
group did a huge
happening. So we did our overhaul so
that we didn't have to do a whole bunch
of improvements over during our So, are
we going to be graded on the incremental
improvement between peer reviews?
>> Oh, you're going to be graded. So, uh
sorry, I misspoke. You're going to be
graded on the quality of your final
report. The peer review will we'll also
read we're also reading the peer
reviews, right? So, what we care about
the peer reviews is mostly how you
yourself did peer reviews as an
individuals because that's the
multiplicative factor on your project
grade. So, your report will be graded as
a group. that grade will be multiplied
by your individual grade as at doing a
peer review and that's going to be you
know so that will be your grade but when
I say the report that includes your part
your uh abilities at the poster session
>> okay
>> right so um
>> so to be clear it doesn't matter when
you did your improvements
>> but uh it's
>> but it's better to do
>> yeah do them earlier is you did exactly
the right thing should do as many
improvements as early as possible
because uh it it's harder to do them
later.
>> Okay, thank you.
>> Um, other questions on the project?
Anything?
Okay, great. Um,
I mentioned before final exam always
have to mention it. Wednesday, December
17th at 8 a.m. Again, we don't choose
the times. Uh, the we'll announce the
logistics details of what rooms you have
to go to, who has to go to what room,
and so on. But we are telling you right
now it's no notes, no questions, no
clarifications. You and your pencil and
eraser will be come in. You'll be handed
an exam. There'll be room on there for
scratch scratch work. You turn that in.
That's the way it works. Okay. So,
um as we know you have a lot of stuff to
do next week um just from this class.
Um, however, we did want to point out
that there is a really nice EEK
colloquium on December 10th, Wednesday,
December 10th at uh 4 to 5:00 pm by uh
HAR who's uh from Microsoft research and
she's the person who leads the entire
group that is releasing
Microsoft's models like FI and so on.
Okay, so
it should be quite interesting. Uh on
that note, I wanted to mention briefly
that uh it might be up online uh the
EEKS colloquium yesterday by Bill
Dailyaly from Nvidia was also very
interesting and if you get a chance you
might want to watch that.
Uh it's uh it was very interesting to
see the connections between
all of the improvements that are
happening at the hardware level in the
GPUs and in the racks that hold many
many GPUs and how that impacts how
that's driven by and impacts what's
happening in the architectural side.
That's the part of the course that's the
part of deep learning that we aren't
able to fully engage with for you
because we don't have any way for you to
exercise it um in you know using any
kind of significant compute but it's
quite interesting and I think one of the
things that you'll enjoy uh if you watch
it is to see how different things you've
learned in the class help you understand
what's going on uh in that talk.
So and yeah just you know uh I happened
to be one of the people going out to
dinner with him uh yesterday uh after
his talk and it's very interesting in
the conversations to see how many of the
things that we've talked about how they
work inside Nvidia in terms of shaping
their work and their uh their their own
models as well as their their hardware.
So it's
it's very interesting for you to perhaps
check that talk out. Not required of
course. Um
so uh with that I want to continue on
the material the last set of material
that I want to cover in the we want to
cover in the class. So again pointing
out there's a in the prince textbook
chapter 18 talks about diffusion we are
following in the treatment that we're
doing in lecture uh this particular uh
archive uh paper that came out last year
that really is quite clear and you saw
in discussion uh something that
hopefully helped you understand what was
going on in a much simplified context.
So it's a really the discussion example
was let's just do everything in a purely
discrete world. We just thinking about
coin tosses and you saw in there what
was happening as you took an image and
made it noisier and noisier by flipping
the bits, you know, black and white
image and how you can then think about
what you want to predict. And it was we
really wanted you to see there is that
you can also think about it as not just
predicting the last thing you came from
but as predicting the original image.
You can see the connection between
predicting the original image and
predicting the last thing. We'll come
back to that today in the Gaussian
setting. So you can see the same ideas
here. Um in that you saw the use of KL
divergence as a natural loss that you
want to minimize. If you want to think
about it, it's a useful heristic to
think let me think about Gaussians
first. Always think about Gaussians and
mean squared error like that's you're
anchored there. You've seen that in your
optimization classes. You saw that in
machine learning classes. You've seen we
use that for examples here. And then ask
I want something like squared error for
this other domain for which squared
error is not the right thing. And the
answer is usually KL divergence
as the kind of counterpart.
Um so and you saw that for example in
yeah that's what we you saw in the
discussion. Okay so let's uh begin uh
quickly recap where we were. So the idea
is we want to be able to generate
something like an image and the natural
approaches of trying to do it with a
single shot suffers issues like we
talked about with baes using this
classifier idea and going gradient
descent doesn't really work. So the
problem is that images are very thin in
the set of all images. The images you
care about are very very thin. So you
want to like use make them noisier to
see to learn how to actually move around
this large space because if you just
look at natural images you can't learn
how to navigate in this larger space. So
we said that was the insight from the VA
story and we said well why don't we just
as an idea look at all levels of noisy
images because as we make noise images
increasingly noisy will eventually fill
up the entire space that we want to
build a navigate in. This is a
perspective that one could take.
And the perspective was so somehow
during training we're going to train
this thing with increasingly noisy
images. But what we want to do is to be
able to start at noise and generate an
image somehow. That's our goal and we'll
take many steps. And the whole point was
to figure out how to do this.
So
remember last time we connected this to
the idea of diffusion to the name of if
you thought about the process of
diffusion as there's a tiny amount of
red dye injected into a glass and you
watch it diffuse into the entire glass
and the idea is this is natural images.
The diffusion out is the making them
noisier and noisier. And the reverse
process going to run that movie in
reverse to take a particular piece of
dye that we find out here and then
follow it back in some distributional
sense back to where it was on the
original set of images. That was the
want to run a diffusion in reverse.
So we said okay this is the set the
setting that we have. Any questions on
the setting?
Okay, setting is clear. Now, we
mentioned and today I wanted to hit both
of these that there's two different
approaches to do the backward path. The
one we're going to start with and the
one that you really need to understand
quite well is the natural one of having
randomness on the backward path. We're
then going to talk about how you can
even do it without randomness on the
backward path. But that's a little bit
more intellectually
uh there's a bit of a leaps involved
intellectually to do that.
So we want to do this. We want to
simulate the process going backward. Now
this is important.
We don't expect when we simulate the
process going backward, we will end up
at the same place we did going forward.
This is because we're simulating a
random process going backward and so
there's going to be randomness in it.
So we reminded you of this using a
markup chain to help anchor your
intuition. The example from discussion
is another example like that. So that
was also a kind of markoff chain right
for every pixel where every pixel was
being flipped. A two-state markoff chain
if you want to think of it that way.
Um
okay so next we said okay
we're going to add Gaussian noise in the
way that we go forward. That's how we're
going to make things noisier by adding
straight up adding Gaussian noise
independent every time.
And we want to understand what does the
backward distribution look like. Okay?
Because that's we need to be able to
walk on the backward distribution.
And the question was we really really
wish it were a Gaussian. Why? Because we
like Gaussians. We know how to sample
from them. And the question is is it?
And we asserted. Today I'm going to walk
you through an argument for it and the
homework makes you do it explicitly in a
different setting than the one I'm going
to do. Um
so
it turns out that if the whatever the
underlying distribution is that
generated X0 so there's some P of X0
which is unknown to us we only have
samples from it but if it's sufficiently
smooth if the amount of noise we add is
small enough that it turns out that the
conditional probability going in the
opposite direction is approximately
Gaussian
in that there's a mean term which
depends on where you are in the future.
But the noise term going backwards is
just sigma squ as the one noise going in
the forward direction. And it's
gaussium. Okay. So this I'm going to uh
come back to and show you a kind of a
handwavy argument from I'll copy it from
the paper uh and kind of walk you
through the steps of it that asserts why
this approximation can hold. The paper
itself in the appendix has a more uh
kind of cleaned up rigorous version of
that argument and the homework makes you
do it in a special case which is
interesting of a Gaussian. Okay. To see
what's what's happening there
because the at some level the fact that
it's Gaussian this argument will kind of
convince you of approximately but the
fact that this variance is actually the
same you might think wait does that
really very does that really hold and
the the homework will hopefully help you
understand that better.
Okay. So
I will I don't want I'll talk about this
later, but one thing that's very helpful
whenever you have something that's going
to depend on something being small
enough, you're going to in your mind,
you say maybe I'm going to think about
this as some limit of something going to
zero. And in this setting, it's natural
to take a continuous time perspective
where you're evolving something from
time zero to time one. and you make the
time steps get smaller and smaller as a
way of kind of thinking about this. So
we take a continuous time perspective.
We're just going to think of it instead
of as x of 1 x of 2 x of 3 as x of zero
x of delta t x of 2 delta t x of 3 delta
t all the way up to x of 1. And we're
going to think of the noise we add at
every step as being some new sigma squ
time delta t. So sigma square is is
think of sigma square as being a very
big number and think of delta t as being
a very tiny number such that the product
of this very big number and this very
tiny number is itself tiny.
Okay, that's the way to think of it.
So intuition
big
tiny
very small
very small amounts of noise we're adding
at every step.
Okay, so if we knew that
this distribution has some mean and a
known variance, the mean is a thing we
have to learn from the data. So we'll
talk about how we learn from data in a
moment but just for now think that we've
learned it from the data. So this is the
thing that our neural net is doing. Our
neural net is has some parameters theta
they're being learned and they are
telling us what this mean is.
Okay. Now we've done this in the forward
by looking at the forward diffusion.
Somehow we've learned what this is. We
have to use this to do generation. How
can we use this to do generation? Well,
the idea is
we have a way now because we have a an
explicit expression in terms of a
density for how to go backward one step
namely sample from this Gaussian. So we
just run this process. We just evolve
this process. So what do we do?
How do you evolve this process? Let me
just scroll down a little bit so they
both are visible.
you take you generate your first one. So
I should write that first.
So first
draw
x hat not zero sorry one the last one as
though it is Gaussian
0 sigma squ
remember sigma square is enormous it's
so big that whatever the size of the
original distribution of the images if
you want to think of it is it's
insignificant compared to how big sigma
square is. So we can just draw from
normal zero sigma square to as the
ending point. This is the counterpart of
drawing a uniform uniformly in the glass
a position uniformly in the glass of
water. Okay, that's what this is. And
now we want to go backwards. So we have
it as a Gaussian. So explicitly what you
do is you just say I run my learn
network on this x hat t
and then I add gaussian noise to it.
Right? That's how you get a gaussian
with a known mean. You draw you you take
the mean and you draw a zero mean
gaussian with the variance you want. And
now I've moved back one step.
Now I take the thing that's moved back
one step. I recmp compute a new mean
that tells me a particular direction and
distance to move. I move that much. I go
I go to that position specifically jump
to that position and then I add noise to
it and I keep doing this process over
and over and over again.
Okay. Any questions on how what this
means in terms of generation?
>> Yeah.
>> I want to ask about
that. So
It's just not ta
>> Oh, it's a good question. So the
question is why am I uh why am I doing
uh delta t here and not delta t ^ squ
>> uh so it's important because if you
think about adding a bunch of gaussians
together the variances add
right and I want the total variance at
the end to be such that it's normal zero
with this big sigma squ the paper calls
it sigma squared q but it doesn't matter
right so you'll see some sigma squared
q's uh when I when I copied from the
paper. So to make that work to get there
by adding a bunch of iid things for a
delta for one over delta t of those iid
things you have to use delta t for it to
work otherwise it won't it won't get you
where you want to go.
>> Yeah.
>> So our dnoising process involves
iterative
noise.
>> So it's very important I never said this
is doising
right. We can talk about how we train it
as a kind of denoising, but what we're
talking about here is not denoising.
It's that we have a diffusion process
that takes a little bit of dye at a
particular position and diffuses it
throughout the glass. We want to run
this process in reverse. That's all
we're doing. We can interpret this as a
kind of denoising, but that's not our
goal. Our goal is not denoising. Our
goal is to simulate this process. That's
the stochastic point of view. Yeah, it's
important not to work yourself into a
confusion about oh this is like den
noising as the first step. Hold on.
We're just trying to generate something
from P 0. We're following the strategy.
Okay.
And we we have to add noise because we
know the reverse process when you
reverse the markup chain. Just look at
the markoff chain going backward. It
becomes a time varying markoff chain
that has randomness still in it.
So that's why we're adding noise.
>> Yeah.
>> So I've not talked about how we train
mu. I will talk about training mu in a
moment because right now I'm just saying
that somehow from data we're going to
learn what this uh mu is. Okay we'll in
a moment we'll talk about it but uh
let's just leave it for now. It'll turn
out the loss we'll use is just in this
particular case is just going to be
squared error. Okay. But uh here we're
just putting that aside. We have
so from an intuitive point of view it's
like
learning the mean of a Gaussian
where you have uh some input Z
and then you get to observe versions of
samples from that Gaussian. That's a
regression problem. That's like the
prototypical remember we talked about
the map MLE versions of le squares at
the very beginning one of the first
homeworks it's just that
so we know how to do that that's just
regression but we can come back we'll
come back to it in a moment
so any qu other questions on this
generation process how the generation
works
okay so now this we talked about this
last time this is the way that we're
going to do the generation let's go back
and revisit this claim. Okay, the claim
was that the backward thing is Gaussian.
Let's try to see why that might be true.
So here I'm just quoting the claim from
the paper. And this is a little bit of
the notation here to say let's assume
that we have some density that's
sufficiently smooth because we're going
to hand wave here some things. So enough
smoothness so that tailor expansions and
the like will all work. And let's look
at the joint distribution for one step.
And now
so this is just describing what we just
did. Okay. So here we take the thing we
add noise. That's the way we go forward.
Then as long as delta t is small enough,
there's going to be a mean
and a variance such that the
distribution conditional of xt minus
delta t given that xt is something is
gaussian. That's what this notation
means. Right? I would have written it
without this thing here. Right? This
probability is a gaussian. But
this just saying gaussian what's
gaussian? This is gaussian. What's its
mean? This is its mean. What's it
variance? This is the variance.
That's the claim.
So if you think about it, um how would
you go about trying to argue this or
convince yourself intuitively that
something like this might be true? Well,
there's definitely a conditional
probability here. So you have to use
baze rule. Okay, so there's going to be
a baze rule. Then we're going to have to
drop some terms appropriately.
And one way to think bay rule ends up
with ratios. And when you have ratios,
it's kind of tricky to think about
what's going on. So you take logs to get
rid of the ratio parts.
Okay, now you have to now drop terms
that are going to zero as delta t goes
to zero because those are the terms that
are not going to matter. And make sure
you can keep track of this variance.
Okay, so you want to keep track of this
variance properly.
That's the that's the um style of what
we're going to do. So first baze rule.
Okay, this is just classic baze rule. We
just say conditional probability is the
reverse direction which we know this we
know this is the thing we know it's
grading noise. So this is something we
completely understand
um times this marginal and divided by
this thing.
Okay,
next what are we going to do? We'll take
logs. Okay, so let's see.
Now I have this term here that is this
minus sign. We're going to argue we can
drop it.
What I mean by dropping it is that we're
going to assume it's there, but it's not
going to matter.
Why do we think it's not going to
matter? Because what we're trying to
understand is the distribution for this
quantity here
in BA's rule. What this division is
doing is it's normalizing the
probabilities.
Everyone see that? It's just trying to
make sure the probabilities. It has no
dependence on the actual value of where
you're where you want to evaluate this
density. It's a normalizer.
Everyone see that? So what there's no
dependence on the thing we want to
understand in this term.
So we're just going to say we'll just do
normalization at the end and we'll make
it work. We just want to track what's
happening without the normalizer.
So we're going to drop it because
temporarily it's there in our minds but
we're not going to keep track of how
it's behaving because this is just going
to be taken up by we'll do normalizing
at the end.
Okay.
So now
what do we know? This term we understand
perfectly,
right? Because this is a Gaussian that
we know. So this is not a term we have
to do any work on except to take the log
of its density.
This is the term we need to now get a
handle on. Everyone with me?
Okay. So for this term what we're going
to do is we're going to say well I'm
assuming sufficient smoothness
and I'm assuming delta t is very small.
So what I'm going to do is I'm going to
tailor expand
this guy
around pt.
Okay, I'll expand it around PT
which is the probability, you know, of
what's happening at time t. I'll say
it's basically the same except there's
be a correction term that I have to do
that's coming from the tailor expansion.
So remember from your tailor expansion
course a while back you learned this
that you can actually think of this as
being exact with the right argument in
here. Right? Things are sufficiently
smooth once you take this derivative.
you can actually evaluate it at the
right place and it'll be exact,
right? But you or you can think of it as
a bunch of higher order terms. We're
going to drop a bunch of them anyway.
We're gonna drop it all anyway.
Okay.
So now once we do that
we have this term
this term
and we have this guy which is something
that's order delta t
plus there's normalization. So now you
can say wait what's going to happen?
We're going to be taking the limit of
delta t going to zero.
Okay, so if any of these other terms are
not going to zero as delta t is going to
zero, then this is not going to affect
the normalization.
So we can drop this term.
Okay, this is what we will end up doing.
Okay, so
now let's just evaluate these guys. This
is just here.
This is a Gaussian. So
what's its density? Well, it's X.
There's a constant. A Gaussian density
has a constant in front. That's a part
of the normalizer. So don't worry about
it. Then there's an X minus squared.
Denominator is the uh term the variance,
right? So here is the denominator here
variance. And here's the squared part.
So once you see this, you're like,
"Yeah, I don't really worry about delta
t terms, right? Order delta t terms
because I'm dividing by delta t here,
right? So this is getting big. These
terms are getting big here,
right? And so something that's very
small is not going to affect this is the
intuition.
So I have this and I have this and now I
can now that I know why I can kind of
tentatively handwavy drop it.
So now I'm going to tailor expand this
again
except we did it before around t the
variation in these densities with time
saying there's some small these are
moving smoothly the densities so small
change now we're going to do it around
position xt
okay we're going to tailor expand around
the position xt
so when you do that what do we have
Okay,
when you around expand it around XT, you
get something that's log the constant
term, right? Log P of XT. Everyone good
with this?
So
that term doesn't depend on the thing we
want, which is the thing we're trying to
comput the density of. So it's just
going to be part of the normalizing.
Okay, so this is going to get dropped
because of normalization.
And then we have the first order term
that we care about. What's the first
order term? It's the gradient
with respect to x. Remember these are
all vectors. The gradient with respect
to x of this log term
inner product with how far you moved.
Remember we're centered at xt. We want
to evaluate what's happening here. So
this is the amount we've deviated. And
what's going to change is it's going to
change with the inner product with the
gradient.
This is our tailor expanding of things
perspective
and then there'll be higher order terms
that we're going to not worry about.
Okay. So once we have it in this form we
say okay these are the two terms we're
going to work keep around.
I'm gonna bring this thing inside this
parenthesis basically.
So how do I bring it inside the
parenthesis? I just divide whatever I'm
dividing by I stick over here. So up
here I had a plus inner product.
Now I have a minus this thing inner
product.
And now you can see the end in sight
because you have only a few tricks you
use and you see oh one of my standard
tricks is now going to work. I have
something which looks like a norm
squared
and I have an inner product term which
has as one of the things in the inner
product the thing whose norm I'm
squaring.
So you go oh this is the classic when I
work with Gaussians complete the square
situation.
Okay whenever you're working with a
Gaussian density you think maybe I need
to complete the square.
So one simply does that trick.
You complete the square and you say
I will take this expression
and
there's a thing I'm inner producting
with
this I think of this as the cross term.
This is the square term and there's
another term that's like the the
crossing thing squared but that has no
dependence on this this thing that I
care about.
So it's just another constant as far as
I'm concerned.
Okay.
So now I have something which looks
exactly
like the
log of the density of a Gaussian
except it has a mean now.
And what's that mean? That mean
that mean is something that is XT.
Namely remember you're moving very tiny
bits. So you're going to where do you
expect to be roughly where you are
except a change a small change a delta t
change
right in this direction.
And so this argument
tells you that great I now have a mean
that I want and I also have a variance
and the variance is the same variance I
started with. Nothing around this in
this path of computation changed what
that variance was.
Okay. So this is a little bit handwavy
like all these dropping of terms is not
exactly justified. The appendix argues
in the paper argues why this is okay uh
to drop why all these are actually legal
uh maneuvers to drop. Um but this gives
you a sense of why this is true. So it
says that basically if you're in a part
intuition is if you're in a density
that's pretty flat here that's what
sufficient smooth means sufficiently
flat here and then you convolve with a
Gaussian here it's still going to be
sufficiently flat. Convolving convolving
the Gaussian smooths things. So it was
flat to begin with. That's sufficiently
smooth. Convolve the Gaussian. It's
still pretty much the same. That's how
what led us make this step of moving
from PT to PT minus delta as roughly the
same. Okay. And what do you expect to
have happened? You expect to have
happened is that even looking backwards,
it's you moved in this in this flat
spot. So even looking backwards, it's
like a Gaussian. Same Gaussian smoothing
going in the reverse direction. That's
the kind of the rough intuition behind
this proof of what's happening. You
needed to do the calculations to track
that the mean was actually doing
something, right? This intuition doesn't
tell you what direction the mean's going
to go. And what this tells you is the
mean's deviation has to do with the
gradient of the log probability. This is
called the score.
Okay, this thing is called score.
So if you read papers you talk about
diffusion as score matching and stuff
like this that's fancy way of saying
learning that term
this thing
>> yeah questions
>> conflicting
so I
est
you added noise going backwards and then
you had the logability
then you say
that term is being subtracted
I guess I'm just a bit lost in
clarification.
>> Sure. So let me uh clarify this first
clarification is that in our particular
definition of this mut right we it's a
mean of it's a mean of something that we
learn this the the step going backward
to do the the reverse diffusion that we
do the degeneration is just to use that
mean. There's no subtractions here. It's
just using that mean and then we add
noise. The reason we add noise is to so
because we want to simulate we want to
draw from this density.
We want to pick we want to draw
basically all we want to do is to sample
from this density. We do that in two
steps for any Gaussian. We take the mean
and we sample from a zero mean Gaussian.
That's all we're doing here. There's
nothing particularly fancy and there's
no subtractions happening here.
Um
here this Gaussian density is just we
said that the conditional density of the
next forward step in the diffusion given
where you were before is a Gaussian
centered here with a variance that we
said. So this is just writing that out.
Gaussian centered here this variance.
We'll come back to this thinking about
subtraction in a It'll play a very
important role in a moment, but it's not
not yet.
>> Yeah.
>> Uh, sure. But that's not Yeah, that but
that's not it's true, but that doesn't
matter.
>> Yeah,
>> I have two questions. So, first, can you
explain like why exactly can drop the
normalization again? Ah the reason we
can drop when I said we're dropping the
normalization is just that we're
remembering it's there but we're not
going to write it down. So everything
here is plus normalization plus at the
end whatever we get we'll have to
normalize it.
>> Okay. It doesn't have a dependence on
the thing where that we're trying to
calculate the density of
is a normalizer. So we don't we're not
dropping it. We're just deferring it.
And then at the end what we get is
something that says, "Oh, I got
something that looks
like a Gaussian."
And this is big
in some places
plus stuff that's order delta t.
So there's no way that's going to affect
the normalizer.
It's too small.
Okay,
that's that's why we can then say okay,
it just normalizes to a Gaussian. All
the stuff I dropped that was order delta
t that those were I was actually
dropping those didn't matter in the
thing that I was deferring the
normalizer.
>> Okay. Yeah. Question.
>> I'm not sure I understood when you were
talking about the convolving.
Where does that come in this picture? Uh
so that was an intuition designed to
help people try to connect some of the
mathematical moves to intuitions. Um if
you're comfortable with the mathematical
moves argued under sufficient
smoothness, you don't need that. So all
I was saying is that when we're arguing
for sufficient smoothness like we're
saying all this works with sufficient
smoothness of these probability
distributions
that's then I was saying why is it that
it's reasonable that
This
this particular thing ended up being
replaced with
uh yeah ended up being replaced with
this guy is because these are very
smooth and the only difference between
PT minus delta t and pt is that it was
convolved with a very tiny Gaussian. So
smoothing with a very tiny Gaussian
basically didn't change that density
because it was already very flat here.
>> So the whole thing comes down to all the
regions are super flat so things aren't
changing that much.
>> Yes, all the regions are super flat. So
things aren't changing that much. You
can neglect almost everything. But if
you just did that, you would get the
mean being zero. And that's wrong. So
you have to track it a little bit
carefully to get the mean. And the mean
is almost
just staying here except there is the
score multiplied by delta t term in the
mean. So the delta t that matters is a
small movement in the score direction um
in the mean but not otherwise modulating
the density. That's the whole point of
the argument. So this is like a a kind
of this is this
half handwavy math that you can use to
understand what might be happening but
for math points of view. So this is very
useful for someone in deep learning to
be able to do because it lets you get
some guidance of what might be happening
at that point. There's two choices of
what to do. Choice one says let me try
to make all these arguments rigorous.
Okay, important choice. People do this.
Second choice. I now have enough stuff
to write code. Let me code it up and see
if it works,
right? And then if it works, you're
like, great, now it's worth making it
rigorous or not, right? But if it
doesn't work, you're like, oh, I have to
fix something. So this is like it's it's
a skill to be able to figure out like,
okay, is this even reasonable?
Okay, I'll take a couple more questions.
I want to move on because I want to get
you to see understand how you can work
deterministically too. Yes.
>> Do you mind elaborating one more time on
this
very
>> this one? Okay. Yeah. I'll talk about
this one. This guy, this is the one I
was just describing in words. So, this
is saying that I have a term here that I
don't really like. Okay. Um, I would
much prefer this to just be uh PT and
not PT minus delta t. You could kind of
follow the argument through just keeping
it pt minus delta t like it's it's okay.
What would happen? This this has let me
change this into this. So first
understand the import of it and then we
talk about why it's a valid move. So if
you think about this, if I kept a pt
minus delta t here, what would happen? I
would keep a pt minus delta t here
and then I would have to tailor expand
pt minus delta t in this way and I would
get uh log pt minus delta t still of xt
here and I'd get a gradient of the log
of pt minus delta t here
still of xt
And this would still be the same. Do you
see that? So if I didn't do that step, I
could still drop this term because
although it has a delta t dependence, it
doesn't have an xt minus delta t
dependence. The thing whose density I'm
calculating. So this is dropping it in
terms of normalization is still valid.
And this tailor expansion having a delta
t kind of terms on top of it is also
still valid.
So from that point of view it would just
change this expression
to be instead of the score at P of PT
the score of PT minus delta T which from
our point of view since this is the
thing we're learning anyway we don't
really care about. So first the import
is it didn't much matter but I wanted to
copy the derivation in the paper in case
you wanted to go back and read it in the
paper. That's the first thing. Second
thing is why was it a valid move and why
did you maybe want to do it is you maybe
wanted to get rid of all the delta t
dependence and make sure none of it's
going to bite you
and that from that move's point of view
it was just saying that okay what is the
difference between pt minus delta t and
pt and the answer is something of order
delta t if pt is sufficiently smooth
sufficiently smooth in what in time why
should it be sufficiently smooth in time
because I'm convolving with a very small
thing I'm doing a very little bit of
smoothing of this density. So, it's
probably smooth. Again, this is hand
wavy, but it's the ar it's the style of
the argument.
>> Did that answer your question?
>> Yeah. I guess like we think about it
almost
like t
or x plus a little tiny x right in this
case it's like we're
instead of adding a little delta x delta
t minus delta t plus delta t exactly
yeah it's exactly this in a way this is
easier because delta t is a scalar I
mean scaler and x is a vector but it's
the same
Okay. Um, last question then I want to
move on. Yeah.
>> Um, just from like a historical
perspective, was this like a known
result and then they made the models
based off this result or did they like
derive this result while they were it?
>> Oh, I will come back to this.
>> Okay,
>> let me let me let me first teach you
more and then I'll come back to this
historical perspective. I have a little
bit of historical perspective later, but
let me let me not dwell on the
historical perspective right now. Let me
keep going. First I just want to make
sure that I can um talk about the
training side to this too. So you can
see the whole DDPM picture and then I
can uh show you how one can do something
very cool.
So now we have this idea that we want to
learn this mean. How do we train it?
So the way we train it and you saw this
in discussion already in the discrete
setting is you say I'm going to be doing
SGD type things. So I'm going to pick a
random image. You always think of it as
a vector, right? Some random vector for
my training set. I'll pick a random time
from 0 to one in continuous time. And
then I'll construct a pair Xt minus
delta t and xt.
Right? Because I want to learn the
conditional mean from here to here.
Right? I know these I think of these two
things as being approximately jointly
Gaussian
uh in their distribution. Right? Going
backward.
So how do I get this? Well, I can
definitely do this. I can just take X0
and add noise to it.
And then having done that, I can add a
little bit more noise to get XT. So I
can generate these these pairs very
easily.
Everyone with me? This is the
counterpart of what you saw in
discussion of saying that if you wanted
to get a pair for your pixels with bit
flipping is you just choose a different
probability of flipping and then do a
tiny flip from there. Right? That's we
saw in discussion. Same thing here.
And now I want to basically predict
this. This is my target
and this is my input
and I want to predict it and I believe
it to be Gaussian. So what's the loss
you use for predicting a Gaussian
squared loss,
right? Because you know I know the
Gaussian I also know its variance is
isotropic sigma square identity.
So great
isotropic Gaussian
is straight up squared loss. So I just
do this with squared loss and that's how
I train. Of course this is not how you
actually train and I'll talk about that
in a moment but this conceptually gives
you a way to train.
So here is all that written out in code
from figure from the paper. This
algorithm is in the code in the in the
paper described this way. It's like the
same thing. sample, pick a time from
uniform, add two G, have two Gaussian
noises, generate U squared loss.
They use for the neural net um f theta
and it takes two arguments. It has to
know what time it is.
Okay, so it knows the time
and this is the generation again what we
described before. Start by drawing
something
random from the big Gaussian and then
walk backwards
um from one to delta t and keep going
backward by using the
learn mean f theta was the mean remember
thing we're learning and add a bunch of
noise add some noise to it tiny bit of
noise going backward
>> that second line
Which three are you talking about?
>> This three or this three?
Oh yeah, that's the bug on my part.
Thank you.
That's just me
using the wrong thing. Yeah, there you
go. Thank you very much for correcting
that bug.
So this is how DDPM works. But now we
can think about this a little bit more.
So let's think about it a little bit
more.
In all of this, the thing we wanted was
the mean,
right? So this mu t that we were
learning is supposed to be this mean.
Everyone good with this?
So now let's think about what this mean
is.
And this is coming to the question about
subtractions. So I want to get I'm going
to talk about this question that was
asked earlier about subtractions. So
I can think about
XT minus delta t as being xt minus delta
t minus xt.
This is condition on xt. So I can write
this as equaling this plus this.
It's like a nonmove. It's just a and now
you can see that the thing I have xt
already. The thing I don't know is the
noise. This is the negative of the
noise.
Okay.
And so this is where you might see the
perspective if you read other works on
diffusion um talking about what you're
trying to learn is how to predict the
noise to d noiseise.
Okay, this is where that comes from. It
says I can think of this as being
mu minus xt is just the expected
negative noise.
But there's a key thing here.
What you want mutus XT to be is the
expected negative noise, not the actual
negative noise.
Okay, there's a little difference.
You can think, well, what difference is
there? I love the actual negative noise.
The only thing I can get ever is the
expectation. So, I'm getting the
expectation. But for the purposes of
doing the generation, it was the
expectation. That's how we had to keep
adding the noise because all we had was
the expectation to run the reverse
process. In the homework, we will have
you run
manually by hand. What happens if you
don't do that? Don't add noise. And you
will see what happens. If you don't add
the noise, you will collapse. It will
not generate something nice. It'll just
pull in to zero.
Okay.
So, that's the first thing you can do.
Yeah.
Does the randomness or is it just
function?
>> Oh, f theta is a neural net is a is is
you can think of it as a deep neural net
with no randomness.
>> Yeah. F if this literally f okay let me
I'll write that out point write on
annotate the note accordingly. This is
just
this is what they call it in the paper.
The paper goes back and forth between
calling mut and calling it f theta. Call
it f theta when you want to remind you
that there's parameters associated with
it.
Okay, that's just all it is. It's
literally just mut.
Okay. So now
now comes the so if you remember in
discussion the last thing in discussion
was telling you so what is it you're
trying to predict and if you read the
solution we post the solutions
discussion I don't know if we posted the
solution discussion yet if we haven't we
should we'll post it soon um what that
kale divergence of what you're trying to
predict can also be interpreted as
actually predicting the original image
right in discussion and so
that interpretation isn't visible here.
I want to get you that interpretation
here because that's useful for actually
training.
So the thing is that we did all of this
and we added a bunch of noise but all
the noise in this picture that we added
was iid. We added a bunch of iid noise.
And you can think of it as okay I'm
asking you to predict the expected
uh expected last term of the ID noise
but all you have is where you ended up
okay does everyone see that like and
you're asked to predict the expected
last noise term that got you here but
the last noise term was the same
distribution as all the other noise
terms. So, this answer has to be the
same answer. If you ask me to predict
the third noise term or the 17th, it
doesn't matter which one you ask me to
predict. They're all identically
distributed and they all just added up
to get me where I am. I have no way of
disentangling them. Does everyone see
that as the intuition? So, how can we
turn that intuition into something
mathematical that we can take advantage
of during training?
And so it says, okay,
let me look at all the noise. Here's all
the noise.
The expectation for the last noise term
is just how many noise terms were there,
right? One over that of the prediction
of the entire noise term because all the
noise terms are identical from my point
of view. I'm only observing XD.
asking me to predict any one of them is
the same. So I might as well predict
their entire sum and divide by the
number of them. It's the same thing in
terms of expectations.
Okay. And that's what this is saying.
Okay. Now what's nice about this? What's
nice about this is you can think about
this as predicting learning. Remember
every time you see an expectation as the
thing you're trying to target from the
point of view of machine learning
this guy is going to be the target this
is going to be the input and because
everything is Gaussian squared loss is
going to be your loss
okay so this says great I can just
predict xn not so here's a little
picture again of this symmetry
um that from from the from the paper
just you You wandered somehow and got
here, but you have no all you know is
that you moved this entire direction.
So this perspective lets you do the
training for mu here as though you're
predicting the original image or
alternatively the net noise from the
original image to where I am now.
So this particular idea
again you can like think of it this way
the this particular idea actually makes
training work much better.
It's mathematically equivalent but makes
training work much better. Why? Because
now your target, if you think about this
thing as being predict xnot, your target
is actually an image.
And you've made conets and units and
stuff like this that are designed to
have the inductive bias of making things
that are like images as opposed to
making noise.
Do you see that? So by having your
prediction target be something that
looks like an image is nice from this
mechanical point of view. you built all
this machinery for working with images
and generating images and things like
that.
So that's one perspective and another
more mathematical perspective is that
there's this this net noise you can
think of as having less variance in it
than one term scaled up because there's
lots of noise added together. So it's a
little bit more stable than
just one noise. That turns out to be
mathematically you can work that out
mathemat as a another way of thinking
about what's happening. Intuitively it's
much easier to think of it is now I can
predict an image as opposed to having to
predict a noise.
Okay. So what that does is this now
connects you. So if you go and read any
of the uh blogs or papers about
diffusion models, this should help you
understand what they're doing. There's
going to be some differences in what
they do. Most of them are going to
follow the original style
which is um this style
which is what you have to do in practice
for implementation because you can't let
things variances get bigger and bigger.
But conceptually
it's easier to understand this as an
approximation to what we just talked
about than to understand this directly
which is what so historically this
development of this way of understanding
came much after the original development
of how they analyzed this thing. This is
a much cleaner crisper getting at the
essence of what's actually happening
picture than the picture in the original
papers.
which is why we're following it.
So,
any questions on DDPM?
You kind of should understand roughly
what's happening here. Now, I want to go
to what seems a bit mysterious. Yeah, go
ahead. So it seems like what the kind of
the flow of the argument that we've had
so far from what I understand is like
we're learning some sort of stocastic
process which when you run it forward
maps from any sample to the manifold of
like natural images right that seems
like the
>> yes that's our goal our goal is to learn
something that we can start you can
start at a random place run it forward
>> right
>> backward right in this picture but run
it run it and then end up on the
manifold of natural images or natural
whatevers. It's like a generic recipe
>> and that's done it's modeled as a
stocastic process where we're learning
the mean vector and we're biasing that
in the direction of the manifold. Right.
>> Yes.
>> And so I had so there's like two things
I feel like I'm confused about. One of
them is you had mentioned that it's
necessary for that to be stocastic like
for it to have some noise because to me
like if I was thinking about this nally
I'd be like why not just learn that
directly? Why learn as a stocastic
process? Yes. And second
I guess kind of like related to that is
um actually let's just start there. I
don't have it.
>> Yeah. So that's actually the exact point
I want to get to.
>> Okay.
>> Is to say that you know the intuition
behind this is that we started somewhere
and we wanted to get ourselves onto the
manifold of natural whatevers. And we
set up the process of filling out the
entire space for training as by as a
diffusion. And then we said, okay, if we
wanted to run that process in reverse,
we would have to be doing a time varying
diffusion.
But we didn't really want to do a
diffusion. We just wanted to get there.
So is there a way to do it
deterministically?
We need some randomness. So we
definitely have to pick the initial
condition randomly somehow. But can we
like do the rest without randomness?
That's what we're going to try to
understand next.
>> Yeah. And it seems like that the final
result that you just talked about is a
very strong hint in that direction,
which is that actually
like predicting the original image is
actually what you want to do, right?
Because when you're predicting the
noise, you're learning the noise and
then that's
>> this is giving you a hint that it might
be possible. It says the thing that we
learned which we thought of as telling
us how to get to the last step is
basically telling us how to get to the
actual manifold of images because it
can't tell the difference between the
last step and all the other steps. So
maybe there's a way to pull this off,
but how? That's the question. Can we
actually do it? Okay, so I want to keep
going and so just think about this
picture.
So this I copied the picture. So we have
a stocastic process we've set up that
starts at X0 which we don't know the
distribution of P 0. we don't know P 0
and sort of walks us to P1 which we know
and then we said look I can sample from
P1 and then I can walk backwards
in this process stochcastically and I'll
end up inside P 0 as a distribution. I
won't end up where I started
necessarily. Even if I took this result
and fed it backward here, I'm not going
to end up back where I started. but I'll
end up in the same distribution.
That's our picture.
And along the way, we had all these PTS
which are marginalss along the way. So
there all these marginals is a giant
joint distribution that's constructed by
our stoastic process.
So what's the idea? DDPM
says I'm going to walk backwards to the
same joint distribution that I walked
forward on
except I'm going to go backwards on that
joint distribution
and that'll give me the right marginal
at the end because I'll have the same
joint distribution.
But you realize that you actually have
some design flexibility here. The design
flexibility we have here is that all we
really care about is the marginal at the
end.
So, one way that we could imagine doing
this, again, it's like a leap. I don't
know how to do this yet, but it's a
leap, is maybe I can just walk through
these marginals
going backward
without walking through the joint
distribution. I'll pick a different
joint distribution that'll have the same
marginalss. Then I could walk through
those marginalss and I'll end up in this
marginal I want. Of course, I don't I
don't even have to do that. All I have
to do is end up here. But one way I
don't know how to think about that. So
I'm trying to find ways of thinking of
my freedom. Yeah.
>> P1. Yes. Marginal at different steps.
So this is the idea. Okay. You only need
P 0 not. So here's the question. Let's
try to walk backwards the same marginals
but a different joint distribution. So
now what I'm going to do is you might
think this is ridiculous. Okay, you can
do this, but is there any example, any
reason to believe this would succeed?
So, I'm going to try to show you a
simple example that will give you why
this might succeed. And then this
example will turn out to contain the
kernel of how to do all of this. So,
what's the example?
Example is okay, I have to simplify this
picture. So, I'm going to simplify it to
two Gaussians,
normal 01 and normal 02.
Okay, everyone good? So I'm going to
think about how are this is the marginal
for X is normal 01. The marginal for Y
is normal 02.
Now I will tell you a joint
distribution. The joint distribution is
X is drawn normal 01. Y is drawn as X
plus normal 01 independent.
That's like the forward diffusion path.
If I do this, I can do B rule to go
backwards given Y. What do I do? I take
I added two Gaussians and I got
something. What's your best prediction
of the one of those Gaussians? Half,
right? What's the standard deviation of
this? A half.
Okay.
So, this is the B rule going backwards.
That's what we were doing before.
Everyone with me?
This is stochastic.
How would I sample X given Y? I take Y
over two and add a Gaussian.
Okay, everyone's good with this. Okay,
now I want everyone to take one minute
with a piece of paper and ask yourself,
do you know any deterministic
way of connecting X and Y such that X
will have a distribution 01? something
has to be random. Okay. And Y will have
a distribution normal 02.
I want a deterministic connection
between X and Y such that the marginalss
are this way. Take one minute to think.
So I hear some questions. By
deterministic I just mean that the
connection between X and Y is
deterministic. They something has to be
random,
>> right? So
>> Okay, that's a minute.
So, anyone want to volunteer a way that
I can connect X and Y such that they
have these distributions?
>> Yeah.
Y2.
>> Sure. So everyone hear that? There's
like I just connect them by square root
of two. So what does that mean? So I can
think of it this way.
Okay, this is the forward direction.
And then
reverse direction is x =
y / two.
Everyone good with this? So I go forward
by multiplying by two. I go backward by
dividing by two. If I want to sample X
given Y, I can sample from Y normal 02
and go backward by dividing by two. So
it's clearly possible to connect two
Gaussians in two different ways to have
the same marginalss. But you might think
this example is too simple, right? And
it kind of is, but only kind of. Okay.
So now I'll comment a little bit on the
history.
How did people discover this idea?
Obviously, they knew this forever. They
didn't know this had any relevance to
the problem. Okay. But then how do they
the complicated way? So what they did
was they said continuous time diffusion
could be understood using a stocastic
differential equation. People have been
studying stocastic differential
equations for a long time in part
because they're very important in
physics and finance. Um then they said
if you want to study stoastic
differential equation you can study how
the probability distributions evolve.
haven't done for a long time. The
probability distributions evolve using
ODEs, actually PDS that go across time
and space.
Smoothly changing probability
distributions can be connected to each
other via something called transport
maps. Transport maps are like something
people study of how do I move
probability from one place to the other
in the smallest amount of movement of
probability that still gets me from one
probability distribution to another
distribution. People have studied this
for a long time.
Then these maps can be move
probabilities to each other
deterministically. And so people said ah
I can use transport mapping on these
ODEs to connect backward and result in a
different way of doing sampling. But
this is a lot of mathematical machinery
that people had built up that allowed
them to discover this connection. But it
took time and they they did it. But we
can do it more simply now after we know
the connection exists. Okay. So we'll
follow a different approach which is
this is possible.
Maybe we can do this. How? We can guess
something and see if it works. Once you
know something is possible, you just
have to figure out how to guess.
So now how do you do this? What should
we guess? Okay,
so you say what do I know? Okay, I'll
say okay X I want to guess the
deterministic connection. So I want to
go backwards.
I'm gonna think of it as I start here at
Xhat T and then I have this estimate for
the noise this expected noise.
Okay.
And I want to put something here in
front of this. I got to put something in
front of this and see if I can make it
work. That would be the easiest thing if
I could do it.
Does everyone see why this would be a
guess?
And looking at the previous thing, you
might think that the answer might end up
having square roots in it, right? Just
because we got square roots up there.
Maybe there'll be square roots, but who
knows?
So then you have to guess what should
this thing be. So you try things. The
first thing you try, the first try is
always let's try one,
right? Let's just try to go back by the
amount of the expectation. You do that,
it won't work. Okay, homework will make
you do it and we'll show you why it
doesn't work. So that's wrong.
So now what's your next choice? Okay,
next choice is I don't know the answer.
Let me try something.
Okay, this is like how does this help?
Okay, why does this help?
This helps because if you have such a
str thing and you want it to work and
you don't know what to guess, you say
let me pick an example
for which I know the answer
and let me figure out how to make the
example what the lambda should be for
the example I chose
and then I'll get a guess.
You see this? It's like a way of moving.
If you you want to guess something and
you don't know what it is, pick
something which you know you can analyze
everything and try to fill in the what
the thing should be.
So you want to pick the easiest example.
Okay, the easiest example of a
distribution for P
for which you can do forward diffusion
and understand backwards process.
So what is the absolutely easiest
probability distribution?
Uniform.
>> Uniform. Tell me something easier than
uniform.
>> Yeah.
>> Concentrate all mass on one point. A
constant. So just pick zero.
Okay.
Try zero. I mean like you're trying you
you you think something might work. Try
the simplest thing. Worst case it
doesn't work but you didn't spend too
much work. So go for it, right? So try
zero.
always zero. Why is this nice? Because
now I know all the marginalss. They're
all Gaussian.
And hey, I know how to connect two
Gaussians. I know that works. So maybe
this will work.
So you try it. So you go, okay, here we
go.
I know XT
XT is going to be a Gaussian with
variance T sigma squ.
I start at zero. I keep moving.
So I know mut is this conditional
expectation
in this case. But this is a Gaussian.
This is a Gaussian. This is connected to
this independently. This is jointly
Gaussian. I know exactly what the answer
is here.
So
I know that what is my prediction to go
back one step? Where am I?
like just go t minus delta t over t.
Okay, good. So now I plug it in. I'm
guessing, right? So
xt minus delta t equals xt plus this
guy.
Plug in my prediction minus xt.
Simplify math a little bit. This is just
xt * 1 minus lambda delta t / t.
Now I want to make it work. What does it
mean to make it work?
I would like to get the distribution of
this correct.
Right? I know what distribution I want
for this. I want it to be normal with a
given variance. I know the distribution
of this
normal with a known variance. I know
this is a constant. I can do this. This
is algebra now. So you solve for lambda.
Okay. Mash the distribution variances.
So I know the the variance I want here.
The variance I want here is sigma square
t minus delta t.
This has to be I know the variance of
this sigma square t. I know I have to
square this guy.
So now I look at this and I go okay
sigma squares cancel. That's good.
But I have
algebra. I can solve this algebra. Does
everyone see? This is now just algebra.
So you can just grind through the
algebra which I will not bore you with.
It's like literally three calculations
of algebra. I'll post the notes so you
can look at it there. I want to keep get
to the point. You can also write this in
a different form.
Okay, using other algebra tricks it
doesn't matter. Important thing is I
have a actual prediction for lambda
from this simple example.
And then I can say okay let's think of
how this behaves
when when t is large this thing is
basically a half because t minus delta t
is basically t and this is just a half.
when
t is something else like delta t this is
one
and then it quickly cuts to half.
Everyone see this?
So
it just says that basically
run backwards
except instead of going the full
direction full amount go half.
Okay. and go half half half and at the
very end, you know, kind of glide in
slightly differently.
It says do this.
Okay. Does it work? It does. So, you
just like write code and it works. It's
like great. Now, of course, you can go
and do and actually there's like a just
description of how you can prove it
prove it more generally. Um, but in
terms of code, you already have code,
right? Because it says what do you do?
sample from the outer distribution.
Take a step by this much
and repeat.
This is DDIM sampling and it works. So I
want to show you a cool picture. It's
like an OD perspective on this. Um it
just tells you like what direction am I
moving? That's all that matters. Okay.
So here here's a cool picture from the
paper.
So the cool picture here is you want to
learn this spiral,
okay? And you have samples. So what
happens? You have too few samples like
this. You can't even see the spiral
here, right? What does it learn? It
learns these like collection of spiders.
Okay? So in that the flows are all
moving in to those data points, those
training points.
And this is like a um an MLP. They train
an MLP for this.
If you add more points, the flows are
moving like this. And with enough
points, you can kind of see how they're
all coming in kind of to this spiral
shape. It's kind of has learned to flow
in this way. And you can see how it's
kind of basically just flowing you in
this direction into into where you want
to go.
So this is how there's a lot more that
can be said about diffusion. Um, but now
you have equipped to fully read this
paper and then to full after you fully
read this paper to go off and read a
bunch more if you wanted to and be able
to understand what's going on and have
it demystified a bit. Okay, I'm
basically out of time. So I'll take a
question because I don't see anyone here
yet for the next thing.
>> Yeah.
>> So does this figure kind of implies that
your training data has to densely cover,
right?
>> Yes. This figure is actually very
thoughtprovoking and provocative because
it tells you that the training data has
to cover the manifold enough which is
you already know that you need to have
enough samples and you see here maybe
you would have hoped that it would
extrapolated the spiral in and it
definitely did not without with the only
the inductive bias of an MLP
right so it does it just yeah that's
true
okay so with that um see everyone at the
poster session have office hours now and
then at the exam. Okay. end.