confusion about is that when you uh when
you compute gradients so this cross
entropy loss is generating a gradient
what happens the gradient comes down for
a full fine tune it comes down hits
everything here but because there's
attention blocks connecting across time
the gradient also flows back this way
okay so the attention is going making
the gradients flow back to everything
so just because there's no loss
on this question part doesn't mean that
the gradients aren't flowing over here.
Okay, that was like a one little point
of confusion. I want to make sure
everyone wasn't confused by that.
Okay, so then we said, okay, we want to
think about fine-tuning or using a
pre-trained model for certain task, we
introduced this idea. So here I've kind
of labeled them with more like shaded
numbers, okay, uh than I did last time.
So we said because we know that these
large language models and other
generative models uh can exhibit this in
context learning behavior. It's possible
to have this pure prompting style of
using for doing a new task. Okay. So in
kind of pure prompting using just plain
ordinary incontext learning pure
prompting is you give a bunch of
examples and then you ask it for
something new uh as the way that you uh
do a new task. But after a model has
been instruction tuned, you can also
give a combination of instructions
and
examples and have it do the new task.
And in fact, optimizing the prompts is
something that can be done. People saw
that they could do this as humans. We
talked last time about there are
packages out there that will do uh
prompt optimization
uh for you automatedly. Of course, you
have to give it a bunch of examples,
right? If you want to have it optimize
the prompt, you want any automated thing
to optimize something for you, it has to
be able to score itself. So it needs to
know you know some way of scoring itself
evaluating itself and then it can do
some kind of keeping the prompts be hard
prompts and do an optimization approach
that keeps things hard as you know
discrete sets of things for prompting
but still climbs a hill. Okay, so these
are packages one can use. And then we
shifted to the idea of saying okay,
we're not going to talk much about that
approach. We talk about soft prompting
which is we're going to assume that we
have access to the model and can run
gradients through it and we're going to
allow ourselves the flexibility of
having a prompt not be hard, meaning not
be a set of tokens. So the way we did
that was that we said, "Okay,
we're gonna So this is a a re a redrawn
version from last time.
We're still going to have the question
and a correct answer that we want it to
match. Okay, that's still going to be
there. We need something to optimize.
So the thing we're going to optimize is
think was the pre-prompt the thing that
goes before the question except instead
of forcing it to be hard we're just
going to allow ourselves to have a
custom embedding that we use. So however
long this is if it was 100 tokens long
it would just be a hundred different
embeddings one after the other and all
of them are learnable parameters. So
instead of going through an embedder you
can do it this way. Last time I talked
about it as if you want to think about
it, you can think about it as having a
hundred custom tokens that are going to
be learned and all the other tokens
embeddings is fixed. Both of these views
are identical.
And as we said before, as I just said,
the gradients when they come back, they
encounter the attention mechanism or in
a state space model, the state space
convolutions or the state uh recurrence
and then they can go back. So that I've
drawn in these highlighted colors of all
these gradients going back. Yes. Is the
transformer itself frozen and you're
just optimizing the prompt or are you
optimizing the whole thing?
>> Excellent question. The gradients are
flowing through everything because
that's how back prop works. However, the
only learnable parameters is this custom
embedding. When I say the only learnable
parameters are this custom embedding, it
means all the other parameters are
frozen. So this is a bit uh subtle. So
back prop if you remember is going to go
back and propagate the gradients
backwards and as it does this it
computes all these intermediate
gradients.
Now what we're going to do is we're not
going to take those gradients all the
way down to par the parameters there but
they might run through the parameters.
You might have to compute this for
backrop and but that's okay. Even if
they're computed for backrop we're not
going to use them. We're not going to
apply them. We're only going to apply
the updates to the parameters we're
learning which are these guys.
Okay, so the reason I bring this up is
that if you think about implementing
this on hardware, we're we're going to
cut the number of learnable parameters
down a lot potentially with these
parameter efficient fine-tuning
approaches. Like we talked last time
about how short the custom embeddings
are relative to the 8 billion parameters
you might have in your uh large model.
But you still have to compute all these
activations and back prop through them.
So we gave you this homework problem. If
you remember, we talked about this great
this idea of um regen recalculating
intermediate activations because you
might run out of memory of storing them.
So that memory consideration of storing
the intermediate activations or
potentially having to regenerate them
that still exists. Having a parameter
efficient fine-tune where you have only
fewer learnable parameters doesn't
change that memory requirement.
The memory requirement it's changing is
the memory requirement for the
parameters that are being updated.
and potentially the momentum terms on
the parameters being updated and for
something like atom w the kind of
keeping track of scale par that you have
to do. So Adam W if you remember or atom
generally tracks 3x
you need 3x you know parameter momentum
and scale. So that's the memory that
does shrink only the only ones you
actually can optimize over. Okay. So
any questions on this? There were some
questions last time. Hopefully I've
addressed the confusions that people had
before um with this short recap.
Everyone's good.
Okay, so going back up here,
I went very fast through the idea of
saying, okay, instead of doing it at the
level of the embedding for a soft
prompt, you can also have this soft
prefix idea where instead of making the
learnable parameters be a fake embedding
for a prompt, you directly act on
everything that's influencing
uh the generation. So remember what's
what's making the gradients pass this
way is actual dependence and that
dependence in a transformer is going
through the key value pairs in a state
space model is going through the state.
So the gradients are flowing through
that thing.
So in soft prefixes what you do is you
simply wherever
the gradient flows back it's flowing
back through for example attention which
means the way it's going back the
queries are being generated attention
here.
So the query path for the gradient just
goes vertically
in attention but the keys and values are
in the past.
Everyone know this right? So the keys
and values that path of the computation
sends gradients back into the past too.
So when those gradients go back into the
past on those keys and values you can
just say okay I'm going to make all
those keys and values learnable
parameters.
Okay that means the keys and values that
exist back here not the keys and values
that exist over here. Keys and values
exist over here are computed based on
the question and then the auto
reggressive generation or whatever. But
back here, this is the part that's the
frozen pre-prompt. So these keys and
values are always the same. So instead
of saying that all these keys and values
have to come from a embedding, they can
just be their own thing.
Everyone get the idea.
Ask me a question if you don't because I
got office hours. I got questions about
this. So I want to make sure.
>> Yeah.
>> So then would you learn the keys and
values for each block independent of
each other or would you still preserve
their
Great question. So the question was, let
me walk over here and say it. So
maybe the picture is a bit misleading.
So let me change the picture.
Oops. Okay. I didn't mean to do that.
Okay, good.
So
the transformer network has residual
connections and stuff moving upward
that's used to do computations
for the past here.
We're not doing any of those
computations,
right? We're just going to have keys and
values sitting up here. So when the
gradient comes back and it hits these
keys and values, it's okay. I will
update those keys and values with the
gradient. those keys and values because
they are learnable parameters, they
don't depend on anything.
Does everyone see that? Like during
execution, they don't depend on
anything. They're just parameters. So
they don't send gradients to anything
else.
So the gradients stop at these keys and
values when they're going back. I've
drawn it for one block, but remember
there's the entire length of this uh you
know prefix could be 100 long. So
there's a hundred different key value
pairs associated back here. for example
that are then rep there's different ones
across the different layers. All of
those are learnable parameters in this
soft prefix approach. Now as you can
imagine from these kind of extremes you
can construct hybrids too where you say
some of these key values are learned
some of them are generated from an
embedding like all this possibility
exists. Okay but you get the idea.
>> Yeah. When this do you have to use the
same question or can you use like
similar sort of questions
like this?
>> Excellent. Excellent. Uh so let me make
that very clear by making an edit to the
slide.
Okay. Yeah. So, we talk about these
pre-prompts. The pre-prompt is for
whatever you consider the thing you're
fine-tuning for. The thing you're
fine-tuning for isn't a specific answer.
You don't need to train a model to give
a specific answer. Just copy and paste
that specific answer. So you want a
model that will respond to a whole bunch
of kinds of questions. Now those
questions might have their own
hierarchical structure. For example,
they might be now I'm going to ask you a
question about this. Now then a question
about this proceeds. All of that I'm
grouping into question during training
meaning fine-tuning training. You will
have a whole collection of these
questions and their corresponding
answers that you want. You will train
for all of that. And when using it,
you'll also use it with this part will
be fixed and then you'll stick in
whatever held out for testing, right?
Held out question and you expect to get
an answer you want out. Okay, so yeah, I
put the I hopefully putting these eyes
will help you just like there's lots
like a training set. There's lots of
them
for for doing fine tuning. Fine tuning
requires a training set. It's a kind of
training.
Does that answer your question? Is
everyone good with this?
Okay. So,
um what happened was this is this is
from last time just you know the number
of parameters we're talking about for a
soft prompt is like for 100 long and
embedding is 4,96 it's like just 40k.
It's much much smaller than the size of
a a substantial model like seven or
eight billion. So it's very short and
even with the soft prefix you get up
with this calculation up to something
like 262,000 which is still way shorter
than
the size of the model or 26 million
times 100 right so 2 26 million is still
way smaller than seven or eight billion
so it's substantially smaller and what I
mentioned last time is that as models
get larger people empirically observed
that this soft prompting and prefix soft
prefix type fine-tuning did very well.
What I mean by doing very well, people
would do experiments where they would
say, I will do a full fine-tune.
I'll see what I can do with a full fine
tune and I'll do a just a soft prompt or
just a soft prefix. And what they were
finding is that
the model would do as well as a full
fine-tune. and in some cases better than
a full fine tune
by just doing this. Okay, so I'll pause
here for a moment and ask you guys a
question based on what you know about
machine learning. Uh why do you think
conceivably it could do better with a
soft prompt or a soft prefix where you
only have 40,000 parameters or 26
million parameters you're uh learning
during the fine-tuning process versus
doing a full fine-tune in which case
you're twe tweaking all seven or eight
billion parameters in this example.
Anyone want to tell me why from your
machine learning knowledge, why might it
do better uh with uh with parameter
efficient fine tune?
Okay, so I'll pause a minute. I noticed
people's facial expressions. So I'm
going to like say how many of you I'm
not going to call on you. How many of
you feel like you know the answer? Raise
your hand. I'm not going to call on you.
Okay. How many of you feel like you
don't know the answer? raise your hand.
Okay. So, a lot of you actually feel
like you don't I wasn't sure. So, it's
good to make sure that stuff comes back
into your mind because we're talking
about everything we're talking about now
for a little bit is going to be about
fine-tuning. So, it's good to remember
stuff about basic learning. Um,
in machine learning problems, let me go
back to examples you've seen there. If I
told you I'm I have a data set and I
want to do regression on it and I fit a
line and the line fit better than
fitting a 500 degree polomial for
generalization.
Everyone remember that kind of story. If
I asked you that question and I asked
you why might this be happening
where a line is a degree two a degree
one but means two parameters and degree
500 is 501 parameters okay now I'm not
going to call on you how many people
feel you could answer that question
very good okay now having said that how
many people feel you could answer this
question which is why is it again as a
hypothesis why a soft prompt with 40,000
parameters or a soft prefix with 26
million parameters might do better than
a full fine tune raise your hand
okay good
now I will ask who wants to say
something raise your hand okay less
people okay
>> uh the standard bias variance tradeoff.
Um the smaller parameter model probably
is better generalizable to a bunch of
problems whereas the massive model is
just overtrained.
>> Okay, so use the different word but um
the classic explanation for this is a
kind of overfitting right which is that
what you have is you have so many
parameters that you have fit to the
details of your training set in such a
way that isn't the right way to
generalize. But with fewer parameters,
you're more inclined to, you know,
generalize properly. So this is should
be your gut reaction. Of course, you
might be bothered, and you probably
should be um because this is 40,000, and
the size of things you might be
fine-tuning on might be much smaller
than 40,000.
Okay? So the amount of things you might
be fine- tuning on might be a thousand
examples.
So it's this is still a little bit
weird. Okay, I don't want to I don't
want to mislead you, but it should give
you an idea that it's not completely
crazy for the idea of a parameter
efficient way to do better for
generalization than that. But there's
still something to be explained here if
you do it with a fall because both are
too big.
Um
okay, good. So now once you saw this
people also saw that depending on the
kind of problem soft prefixes and soft
prompts would do well at generalizing
but at other kinds of problems they
would not do so well at generalizing
as compared to a full fine tune.
So at that point
once you understood that it might be
possible to only adjust a few parameters
and get good generalization on uh some
particular subro some particular problem
that people said okay what could I do
that's more general than just doing a
soft prompt or a soft prefix and that's
what brings us to the idea of luras,
okay, which are
low rank adaptations.
So, some of you have already heard this
term. How many of you have heard of all?
A lot of you. Okay, so but now we can
talk about you know it in more detail.
So the idea in Allora is to say let's
step back and not think about something
that's restricted to this uh prompting
setup. But just generally if I want to
take a model and only adjust a small
number of parameters, what can I do as a
generic recipe?
So very early on people would try things
like saying I'm just going to fine-tune
this these particular layers which is
still reasonable. They would experience
that you know sometimes for certain
kinds of problems tuning certain layers
was important
as compared to others but this is like a
more of a generic kind of recipe.
So the idea of Allora is to say that
when I have a pre-trained model, what I
have is a whole bunch of weight
matrices.
Okay, lots and lots of weight matrices.
I also have bias vectors, but I have lot
whole bunches of weight matrices and
bias vectors. Most of the parameter
count is in these weight matrices.
Okay.
Now,
a quick aside.
I didn't plan on saying this, but I just
thought of it, so I should probably
mention it. So, note
embedded
better
slash
output layer
are different.
Okay, so what do I mean by that? We have
these big models, right? So I'll use the
transformer model as the example.
So
you have this embedder and this debtor
and you also have inside here you have
you know norms attention state space
models
feed forward networks of different types
of stuff. Everything inside here there's
bias type things and there's matrix type
things and you know where those are
right everyone good with that and the
matrices actually are matrices what do I
mean by matrices being matrices I mean
you might say well the matrix is a
matrix well I mean is the matrixes
acting in a matrix- like way it's you
know it takes vectors and it multiplies
them and the entire vector the different
components of the entire vector while
not the same kind of have the same
qualitative character. Uh and you could
imagine key thing is you could imagine
rotating it and changing coordinates.
Okay, you could imagine rotating and
changing coordinates and it' still kind
of be the same. Everyone with me? Okay,
so you have all these matrix matrix type
things here inside here.
the embed and the debeter. Although you
might think of them and represent them
in PyTorch as a big matrix, they're not
quite the same in their matrixiness
because you can't really think about
potentially rotating them and being the
same on the input side because the DMB
the embedtor for example takes one hot
vectors in. It's made for one hot
vectors. The D embedder is generating
scores for different tokens,
right? It's it's really the embedder and
the D embedter are collections of
vectors.
They're not really a matrix. I mean,
they are a matrix, but they're also kind
of not. So, we talk about low rank
updates. This has this is for some
things that are matrix- like in their
nature. One doesn't do Lauras for the
embed or the debtor.
If you're going to have have to have a
custom output layer, you will just make
it custom.
And if you want to adjust the embed, you
can have special tokens you add, but you
don't like do a lower on the embed
typically.
Okay. So aside, so now you have a
matrix. So for example, think about an
MLP matrix, right? In an MLP matrix, a
standard MLP, you have something that
will take uh a 4,000 long vector and
expand it to 16,000, four times larger.
You might then relue it or in a current
modern very modern approach, ReLU square
it. And then you have another MLP on the
top that'll like shrink it back down to
4,000. Everyone remember? So this
example of a weight matrix. So 4,000 by
16,000 has 64 million parameters in here
in this matrix. And there's many of
these in your model. That's how models
get big.
So what you can do in Laura, the key
idea of a Laura is to say that instead
of trying to update every parameter
inside that matrix independently,
you're going to let all the parameters
inside that matrix move, but only in a
low rank way. So your updates are just
going to be
uh delta W's and delta W's are required
to have their rank be small.
And what you want is not that every
individual update is low rank but
together you might change rank a lot.
You might change might change the matrix
a lot in a high rank way. Remember the
argument for m up. So remember in the m
argument we said that by default if you
have batch size one your weight matrix
update is going to be rank one. Remember
that argument. But when you apply it
over and over again, the net update is
not rank one.
Here we're going to say that throughout
the entire adaptation process,
we're only going to make a low rank
update.
Okay?
So this part we're going to freeze. This
is not going to change during training.
And only this delta W will change during
training. And delta W is required to
have a rank that's small.
This is the idea.
So,
so in this case, you know, default rank
of this matrix is like 4,000. Um, this
will be much smaller like 20 or five or
one something much smaller.
This is the idea. So now how do you do
this?
So
the standard approach and there are
emerging approaches that go a little bit
beyond away from this standard approach
but I'm going to talk about the standard
approach says
if I'm going to make an update I have to
have parameters because eventually I'm
going to run gradient descent of some
kind and it's going to have to update
parameters. So I can't just say I want
delta w to be a rank r matrix. I have to
have a representation that makes it be
rank r. So the easiest way to make make
a matrix be rank R is to say that it's a
product of two matrices whose structural
rank cannot exceed R. Like you look at
them and there's no way that things rank
can exceed R.
And so at that once you've made that
decision,
the choices are made for you. Okay, so
if we wanted this matrix to have 4,000
uh different columns and 16,000 rows,
then we can write delta W as B * A
where B is going to have 16,000 rows and
R and A is going to have 4,000 columns
and then the number
R adjust to whatever you want the rank
uh to be.
Everyone with me here?
So
ask a question if you don't understand
what's going on here.
So what does this mean?
It means that
in a graphical way you can think of it
this way that numbers come in and before
these get multiplied a vector came in
and it got multiplied by warst star.
Instead we're adding another path
uh wherever we have this particular war
star a parallel path in which first you
meet a matrix a and then you meet matrix
b and then you add together that's what
this means so this part is frozen and
this part is learned
everyone good okay so now I'm going to
first tell you what the current sort of
best practice is here and then we're
going to like talk through it in more
detail
Current best practice is you should
optimize this using an optimizer
uh like atomw.
You should not be optimizing this using
uh by default using optimizers like uh
muon and the like. There's some emerging
work on when you should do that and not
do that, but I'm going to tell you a
default if you're wanting to do it. By
default, you should be using a u
optimized light atom w
you will initialize B to be zero and you
initialize A to be non zero.
And then you're going to use two
different learning rates for B and A in
the updates in which case you'll learn
use a larger learning rate for B by some
factor lambda and lambda is something
which you have to learn for a family of
problems. People have published what
they think that lambda is like for a
certain family of problems. It's like
four 10. So things like that is what
what it looks like empirically.
then you use for A. But both A and B
will update.
Okay, so we're going to go into why this
might be later, but like put that out
there so you know what the kind of thing
is that one does when you're doing lower
training. So we could stop here and just
say this is the recipe. Do this for and
then this is how you do a fine tune.
Okay, so any question on like what the
kind of recipe here looks like?
>> Yeah.
Yeah, it's a good question. It's a a a
topic of active research of trying to
understand it exactly what's going on.
It's not understood exactly why
different things I can give you one kind
of basic intuition. Um the basic
intuition is that
it's not clear that
the induced norm of A is the right
object given that you know it's going to
be definitely followed by a B
and is acting in the context of this.
It's just not clear that that's the
right way to look at what the
update is because it's not like a
generic I'm just you know in when you
use muon generally you have these
matrices and they're acting and then
they fall some kind of some nonlinear
thing is happening afterwards or soon
thereafter here it's there's a lot of
very linear stuff happening around it
and so it's not clear that the intuition
is still holds. Um that said, people
have tried it and done experiments.
There's a very interesting experiment in
the Kimmy papers where they said that um
they're doing a full fine tune. So I
don't know if they've done the same
experiment for Allora that a full
fine-tune on a model that was trained
with muon using muon works better than a
full fine-tune of a model that was
trained using atom w. But you do the
fine-tune fully using muon
like the same optimizer seems to work a
little bit better. So but it's an
emerging area like we don't know the
answer. I I don't know the answer. Might
be some recent papers that that tell me
the answer but I don't know it. Um
okay.
So that's for full fine tune for Laura.
I'm not not sure. I I can tell you more
a little bit in a little bit about it.
Okay, so now let's talk about this in a
little bit more detail. So you know what
to do in practice, you know, follow this
recipe.
So a comment is important which is after
you've done the Laura fine tune. So
you've done all this Laura fine tuning,
you've now got this A and the B and now
you want to use the model for some new
task.
You don't have to do this calculation
and this calculation.
What you can do is just multiply
A and B together, add them into war and
have a new W and just use that new W for
inference. So Allora fine-tune run at
inference time costs the same as running
the original model. It's not different.
It doesn't cost you more because you had
this. This is just for during training
to keep track of these parameters are
frozen and this is what's learned.
Okay.
Okay. So now I want to talk about
initialization of this. So
I've told you this particular uh
initialization is what when does but
let's talk about if you didn't know that
that was the right answer.
You know your default initialization
would not be that your default
initializations would be let's try a few
initializations. So initialization idea
zero would be
in it
a equals 0
b equals z. Just start with zero.
And why doesn't this work? Anyone know?
Why not?
Yeah.
>> Yeah. Gradient will be zero.
So the gradients are zero because
remember the gradients are all these out
outer products right on matrices. You
did this in the homework. the outer
product of what was the input and the
gradient's coming back. So on B the
gradient is zero because this one if A
is zero this is zero and then it doesn't
matter what you're out outer producting
a zero vector with you're going to get a
zero matrix right so the gradients on B
are zero
for A. If B is zero, whatever gradient
has back propped through B is now zero.
And so it doesn't matter there's
activation here that's zero and the
outer product is going to be zero again.
So the gradients on A are zero. So both
zero doesn't work. The gradients are
always zero and you can't get out of
that.
So now let's try that didn't work. So
now let's try the other idea.
Hit it a
Xavier B Xavier.
Okay, so just initialize A and B the
same way you'd initialize any matrix.
You know, look at the appropriate fan in
choose Xavier initialization, choose a
Gaussian, just fill it up. Everyone
understand what what this idea is? Just
do it the way you would do anything
else. Why not?
I want to pick someone different than
people who've answered already.
So remember this in the context of doing
a fine tune. So you have your model,
it's been trained, do some pre some
pre-training task, it does something,
learned a bunch of stuff. Now you've
chosen a bunch of uh matrices that
you're going to do lauras on. So you're
going to choose to adjust adopt those
matrices in the network. You choose a
particular rank R. You set up these A's
and B's. And now you're going to
initialize them. Then you're going to
run it and do updates. Okay. So now
what's wrong with initializing these
both using Xavier?
>> Yeah.
>> Could it be that Xavier was assuming
that
standard. But then if you multip
interesting objection so the interesting
objection is that if I do Xavier
initialization for A and B maybe the
product is very weird. Okay, that's a
good idea. Okay, it turns out the
product um will be definitely low rank.
So that from a matrix point of view is
definitely weird but it's not um it's
not particularly harmful in any way in
that a random vector in will come out
using with Xavier initialization was
such that a random RMS norm vector in
would have RMS norm out of one that will
still be true because it'll be in RMS
norm one again RMS norm one out so it's
not weird from the logic of Xavier
initialization per
Um
yeah
>> does it have something to do with the R
is a learnable parameter?
>> So R is not a learnable parameter. R is
a parameter that we chose. We say how
many par what is the amount of
parameters I want. So maybe I should go
back a little bit talk about R. Sorry.
So here
note
r
oops
times 16k parameters
this is
r * 4k parameters.
So total
is
r
* 4k
pull the 4k out
times
4 + 1 in this case parameters.
Okay so stop calculate parameters here.
Oh a little bigger. Sorry I made it
small. Okay. So if I think about this,
this is like five R times 4k parameters.
So if R is like three, this is far
smaller than 64 million. So this is why
it's parameter efficient. Okay. So R
adjusts the number of parameters that I
have to tune. Nothing that can have an
impact on the number of parameters can
be a learnable parameter
using uh PyTorch
and standard deep learning gradient
based methods. Okay, because that's just
you can't have the number of parameters
be learnable using gradients because
it's integer.
Okay, so R is definitely not a learnable
parameter. Um let's go back. So, we're
back to this question like why is this
not a good idea?
Okay, so I see most only a few people
are answering. So, I want to like stop
at this point. Pause, talk to your
neighbors and discuss
what else can go wrong
besides zero gradients
in the fine-tuning context. Okay,
remember that's what we're trying to do.
We're saying it's not the right answer,
which means something goes wrong. We're
doing fine-tuning and the problem isn't
zero gradients. So you have a gradient.
So something else has to go wrong. So
talk to your neighbor for a minute and
ask what else could possibly go wrong.
Yeah,
I was thinking
Okay,
>> so I wrote a hint. We ran out of ran out
of our minute fast. So the hint I was uh
going to say was remember how we think
about learning is the reason we're using
gradients at all is we're taking a local
perspective, right? We want to think of
our model as having some local
linearity. We then you know take steps
such that things are good. Remember
that's how we're thinking about learning
at a big level. So now after you guys
have t thought about it what is wrong
with initializing A and B to not zero
meaning just both Xavier
from the perspective of doing
fine-tuning. Is anyone able to talk it
through and get an idea of what might be
going wrong?
So gradients aren't zero. Um yeah
>> I think at the beginning if not
something
>> delta w
would be initialized
to something big.
Okay. And because the delta w is
initialized something big, you start off
not where you wanted to start. So you
want to fine-tune a model, which means
you want to start at the model as it is,
but you're going to initialize it to
something that's not there, but
somewhere else.
and that somewhere else you don't know
is good at anything.
So reviewing a fine-tune or on a
foundation model the implicit idea is
that this model has good embeddings. It
has learned how to do a lot of stuff. We
just don't know how to do exactly this.
I want to keep all the stuff that it
knows and I want to adapt it. But by
starting off with delta W is initialized
to something big, you're taking the
entire model and shaking it far away.
And now it's lost potentially all the
stuff it knew how to do. And so you
might as well have started from
initializing the entire model to
someplace randomish.
And so you're not going to get this
benefit.
Okay. So this doesn't work.
So that leads to
you know two
One should be zero
because if one of them is zero they're
both uh the product is going to be zero
and you'll start at zero.
Okay. So and for a long time people
thought yeah this is good. Okay one of
them is zero. uh this is fine. So a
comment here people were doing
this particular approach that's
described initializing B to zero and A
to non zero from the start
mostly as breaking the symmetry and the
reason for that you might think why
would you make B zero and that's just
because I'm writing everything with this
kind of column perspective on vectors
but a lot of the implementations are
defaulting kind of to a row perspective
on vectors just because they're shapes
and so writing and I write it as B times
A, right? But a lot of people write A
time B.
And so from that point of view, you
know, they were they were often
initializing the so a yeah they were
initializing it so that uh the
the first thing was zero from their
point of view. Okay. in the in that way
of doing it. But so what people did, you
could either do it empirically. They
said I can try both
and see which one works better. People
expected it not to matter. But it turned
out actually this one works a little bit
better. So you can just take it at that
uh as one approach. Now the
the idea that these things
using being trained with atom W might
need a different learning rate than you
would use that you than you used that
you found during pre-training. That
should also be potentially clear to you
because you're treat you're training a
different model,
right? It has it's very different than
what you were doing during pre-training.
So using this pre-training learning
right here might not be the right
answer. Remember if you have to sweep
one hyperparameter the hyperparameter
you sweep is learning rate. So the idea
you'd have to sweep the hyperparameter
here is kind of natural. Okay. So using
a different hyperparameter people knew
from the beginning of Lauras that use a
different one.
What emerged more recently is this idea
that often you you do better by using a
different learning rate for A and B
using atom w. Now
from your point of view, how you've been
taught, this should not be surprising to
you.
Okay? Because when you were taught uh
thinking about MUP, we said, "Hey, for
doing atom, the learning rate you want
to use should depend on the fan in of
the matrix,
right? And B and A have very, very
different fanins.
Do you guys see that
A's fan in is for in this example is
4,96
right and B's fan in is R
which is like five or 10 they're very
different so from a MUP perspective it's
not surprising to expect a different
learning rate
does everyone see that so originally
people were using one learning rate but
Now it's a a different learning rate is
reasonable. Now
the surprising thing is that you can't
just use the MUP scaling to get the
right learning rates here. Part of this
is what I was describing before. Induced
norms are not quite exactly the right
thing of what's going on here. But the
easier way of understanding it is that
you know all of the arguments we make
about what happening with an induced
norm and the size we're implicitly doing
all these expectations.
Remember like we're doing this like
assume that everything is Gaussian how
do variances add that kind of thing.
Okay. And you know expectation type
calculations work when you get
concentration when you're adding enough
stuff together. So in the MUP paper uh
you saw when we asked you to look at it
that you should use a particular size
but it can't be too small to get the
hyperparameter transfer. You have to
make things small but big enough. And
the big enough rule of thumb I think in
the MP paper was like a 100ish.
But the Laura's the size we use is much
smaller often, right? It's like 10 one
four numbers like this are often used
and that's too small.
And so from that point of view you can
think of okay wait
the just using the mup scaling might be
too aggressive for the difference in
learning rate of these two things and
one has to think about it. So the
practical answer is an empirical factor
that uh seems to vary and you have to
figure it out for that kind of problem
what it is.
Okay.
So now you understand um what's
happening here. There is an intuition
that people have which I'm not sure is
um actually correct but you'll hear it
that says well B was initialized to zero
so I need a larger learning rate to move
it somewhere else.
That's kind of fishy. Okay, it's not
because B is initialized to zero which
means what? A's gradients are going to
be very small when it starts off but
you're using atoms so that'll get scaled
out. So it's a little bit iffy. Okay,
but okay. So so far
all we have is that the initialization
of one of them namely uh a should be non
zero. Now the question is but
initialized to what?
Does everyone see that? It's a question.
How do we initialize it?
So there's a few choices.
The default one is just do Xavier.
This works and is the common one done in
practice.
Okay. However, there's papers that
suggest that there's other
initializations that can do better.
So
the next initialization
says that look all of this remember all
of this is a
war plus delta w that's what we're doing
here okay war star plus delta w
you saw the uh derivation of mu p and
thinking about what's happening even in
muon what you're seeing is that the
gradients that are coming are typically
not full rank matrices and even after
and this is a fine-tuning setting so
you're going to be adjusting somewhere
here so one perspective says that the
gradients that are coming are not
uh full rank uh matrices
so why am I setting initializing a to be
or I A to be random,
shouldn't I try to align A with the
directions that I'm actually expecting
to see gradients pushing me in? Does
everyone see this?
So
the second idea is the following.
compute a
batch of large
batch of gradients
for W. Just compute them for the entire
W. Remember back prop is computing them
anyway effectively. Just compute them
for W.
Take the SVD.
This is probably not going to have a
bunch of equal things.
It's going to have some singular values
that are big and some singular values
that are small. This is the direction
that for your fine-tuning data set that
you want to move in a full fine-tune
this W matrix.
What it says is just pick the top
Okay, initialize your matrix to pick the
top R
uh singular directions for a batch of
gradients on W for your matrix. Yeah,
>> it says on W star.
>> Yeah, for Yeah, good good point. For
war, meaning just hold yourself at war.
Don't take any steps. Just compute the
gradients on war. So you just take a
pass through your data, compute the
gradients on bar,
take a pass on for all the matrices that
you want to do. Just compute these
gradients. If you can't hold them all in
memory, then just do them a few at a
time. This is like tied to the number of
matrices you're doing. So you can afford
if you can afford one pass through your
data, you can do this or one pass
through a sub subset of your data.
Compute these gradients, compute the
SVD, pick the top R, and use that for
your initialization.
What that does is it starts you off with
a being such that it's moving in the
direction the gradient would want to
move largely and then w can move can
choose to move in specifically how much
it wants to move out in that direction
but then you're allowing a to be a
learnable parameter so this can adjust
during training but just initialization
to get you motion at the beginning this
is one approach
Alternate approach says well
war star is probably also not something
whose singular values are all balanced.
It might also have an approximately low
rank structure to it. Not fully but
might have you know a lot of its energy
in in some particular direction. So
instead of doing instead of going and
computing a batch of gradients just say
warst star came to be the way it is
because of batches of gradients landing
here.
Whatever the directions are that are
preferred here might be the same
directions to start in here for this
problem.
So this approach says
take SVD
of
war itself
pick top R
and use that to initialize your update.
This says you're going to start off
moving align to the directions that W
star is moving a lot in is is is is
amplifying a lot.
Okay, these are and you can take hybrids
of these.
Okay, so you can take this approach and
say well I won't take R. I'll just take
some of the tops and I'll make the rest
random. And people explore this uh for
kind of how to do the initialization of
a
So you can look in the literature but
this kind of gets you set to the kind of
main components of what people talk
about. Yeah.
>> Certainly this is not random. This is
this is definitely not random, right?
Yeah. You start somewhere. Yes, that's
true. Um so you won't get diversity if
you like do it again with a different
seed on where you start. You still start
there. Um you still have the randomness
in your back shuffling that can happen.
So your actual evolution path is still
random but yeah this is the initial
condition is far less random. Both of
these are less random.
This is definitely fully deterministic
and this is also deterministic if you go
through the entire batch. It only
depends on the batch. So if you
subsample the batch there's a randomness
from subsampling the batch but nothing
else.
Yeah, that's that is true. Um, so does
everyone understand that comment? The
comment was that we're definitely doing
something not random. Does this matter?
And the answer is it definitely matters
if you wanted to sample like different
initializations to see how well you
might be doing. But in deep learning,
the reality is many times unless we're
doing experiments, we're not actually
sampling lots of different
initializations in practice
um for production
because it's too expensive.
So
people don't mind that you're losing
this if you can get a better
initialization that goes the right
place.
Now again there's not a there's papers
that show this approaches work better.
There's other papers arguing that
these
don't give you that much of an
improvement uh or and some argue they
might even be harmful because they think
that the actual updates that you need to
move in are not necessarily in the
principal directions
but uh in terms of what's delivering
performance
but this is what's known
as standard different choices for
initialization.
Okay, any questions on Laura's
uh covered
this in the detail I wanted.
So again, if you look in the literature,
there's lots of variations on luras
because they're very practical. I mean
effectively
practically most fine tunes that are
done of models are done using loras.
uh I would say empirically this is this
the way it is. Um so for example I mean
I'm talking about transformer models but
in diffusion models people will do uh
alla that says I'm going to tune my
model to be better at generating you
know cats I have lots of pictures of
cats I want to be better at making cats
so here or this kind of cats and they'll
like just do do Laura fine tuning
so
luras are very practical people have
found that given the same parameter
count a Laura will tend to do better
than a soft prompt or a prefix uh soft
prefix. Lauras however uh for running at
inference time require you to actually
do this merging of into the weights. So
that's different. So there's system
level considerations that can be
different in using LA.
Okay,
good.
Um I will make one comment here before I
move on.
The fact that Laura's worked
made people also think about, wait a
minute, I have a a I have a a model. I
did a Laura on it to make it be better
at this kind of task.
I also the same model. I did a lura on
it to get better at this other task.
It got better at both those tasks from
doing Lauras from this one place. I
trained them separately, but I was
anchored at the same place.
Why don't I add both of them in?
Right? So, the fact that Laura's worked
made people be more willing to explore
the idea of doing model level
arithmetic. Take the entire parameters
and add them together or average them
together. And the amazing thing is that
that also works.
Okay, so we're not going to talk about
it um in the class. We should be aware
this is like a right point to make you
aware of it. There's a whole business of
merging models together of taking models
that have been tuned during Allora from
the same thing, another model tuned use
tune fine-tuned using Allora from the
same place and then like mixing them
together.
Um so then you you can adjust how much
of this one and how much of that one.
What exactly is the right geometry to
add them? A little bit of subtlety here.
Um in connection should I think about as
adding on a sphere? Should I add on
uklidian space? But the important thing
is even if you add a uklidian space and
you just tune how much you want of each
of them you can sometimes get models
that have now acquired both capabilities
and sometimes you know synergistic
capabilities too. So people play around
with this, but Laura's tell you why this
might be reasonable kind of at a high
level. Yeah.
>> Yeah. Um I had a question about So it
seems like kind of at a high level what
we're trying to do is like figure out
the knobs and levers that have been
learned and then kind of turn those
knobs and levers rather than trying to
retrain the entire model. Um and I know
one of the ways or one of the things
I've heard about a lot is people doing
sparse autocoders for interpretability.
Yes. trying to understand and it looks
kind of like Aurora is an auto looks
kind of like an autoenccoder. So I'm
wondering do people do these with sparse
auto encoders where you're projecting
into a higher dimensional space but
enforcing some sort of sparity and then
trying to train on that or I don't know
if that even makes sense but
>> okay so I'm going to budget myself only
a minute to answer your question because
I want to get to something else but um
so at a high level the so people
understand the question the question was
saying look in interpretability when
you're trying to understand what a model
is doing you can train a sparse
autoenccoder where you take it you train
a model a little little autoenccoder for
some part of the model that says I would
like to run this through a vector that's
sparse so I can see what different
things might correspond to. So when you
do sparse autoenccoders what you're
trying to do is you're saying I would
like to decompose what's happening into
a sum of low rank subspaces
that where each subspace is hopefully a
lot is I try where I'm expecting motion
to be only in low rank ways as opposed
to full. So this is usually done on
activations for example. So if you
expect activations have a low rank space
that have corresponds to meaning then
alla also makes sense for the same
reason because it says if this is the
direction which corresponds to being
nice and this is the direction that
corresponds to um being skeptical. If I
would like to my model to be trained for
this problem to be nice and skeptical.
What I would like to do is to have align
to the activation direction of niceness
and arise aligned to the direction of sp
of of skeptical like the right motion.
I'm gonna act in this lower lower
dimensional space. So yes, that is true.
Um
so this is all so we we pointed you to
papers in the project for
interpretability on you know this linear
representation hypothesis and things
like this. So yeah, this is definitely
connected and this is also connected to
the idea that you why you might be able
to do model arithmetic of add different
models together and get things to you
know combine learn both things again an
active area of research uh to understand
how to you know what's going on here why
this works
okay so we've talked about
initialization and we talked about
Laura's I want to change uh gears and
talk about something different
So this is the idea of metalarning.
So we've just told you that foundation
models are models that we expect to be
good at being fine-tuned.
So we train on some task that's broad in
general. It gets good at doing that and
then you say okay this is a good place
to start for doing a fine tune.
And metalarning
is kind of asking the question that says
okay if I want to make a model better
at what? At being fine-tunable.
Okay, I want to make a model that's
better at being fine-tunable for certain
kinds of tasks.
How do I do it?
So you can think of it as kind of one
way think about it is a kind of a
hierarchical perspective. It says I have
a
foundation model which is good at lots
and lots of different things. Now I have
some family subf family of tasks.
I could tune the foundation model for
this every individual task in this subf
family. But what if I wanted to make a
model that was tuned for this entire
subf family such that I could take that
model and then tune it for the
individual tasks. Can I get some kind of
benefit from having all of this task as
a collection?
Okay, that's the metalarning problem.
So, everyone understand what we're
trying to do? Trying to make a model
that's better at being fine-tuned.
So, the question the first question that
you should have is what's a good
baseline approach like what is the right
kind of starting point for doing this?
So there's one baseline which is just
easy which is the zero baseline which is
nothing do nothing
random initialization.
Okay. So this is whatever your task is
just start with random initialization
and train a model for it. Okay, so
that's like one. Um,
another baseline approach is
general foundation model.
So just have very very high level
foundation model that encompasses the
family of tasks you're interested in.
Use that. Don't do anything special.
So these are like very very basic
baselines. So now let's do the next one
is what I want to know. So what comes
next?
So the approach I'm going to talk about
I consider to be a very very interesting
conceptual development. I'll preface
everything by saying that practically
speaking,
this particular approach I'm going to
describe is not done that much anymore,
but it's still very useful conceptually.
Um, so I'm going to talk about it for
that reason. So this approach is we can
call it has a name. It's called mammal.
And mammal is useful conceptually
because
before mammal came out people were
already trying to solve this metalarning
problem. Okay. Um maml came out before
uh foundation models were available for
non-image tasks.
Okay. So there was imageet but for other
kinds of problems like robotics and so
on there was nothing even remotely
approaching a foundation model. nor was
there anything approaching a foundation
model for language tasks when mammal was
developed. Um the main author of mammals
is Chelsea Finn who was a graduate
student here a professor now at
Stanford. So
what people are already trying to solve
this problem and the problem was viewed
as I have a collection of tasks and for
every everything in this ta in this
collection of tasks I would like to be
able to fine-tune it for this
collection. Can I do it?
And the mammal approach you can think of
as being a systematic way of reasoning
about what you might do in this setting
and just translating that into something
operational. And so it's useful for that
um that purpose for that reason.
So before you even think about what an
approach might be that is different than
doing nothing,
you have to ask yourself the question,
if I'm trying to do something, I'm
trying to make a model better at being
fine-tuned for tasks, what do I have to
work with? First question, right, before
you want it, like I want to make a tasty
meal. Okay, great. What ingredients do I
have? Right? It's first question.
So what do you need?
So if I want to make a model better at
being fine-tuned for tasks from a
certain family, I should have some
examples of tasks from a certain family,
right? Does everyone see that? I'm doing
machine learning. I want to be good at
something. I have to have examples of
it. Everyone with me is like a very
important highle point surprisingly not
fully appreciated before um this work.
basic ingredient.
So now the question is what does it mean
to have a collection of tasks in a
machine learning setting? A collection
of tasks means data.
Okay.
So this means i.e.
training data
these different tasks.
So for a machine learning problem what
do you need? Is training data enough?
What else do you need? What's the
minimum requirement for a machine
learning problem? Here's some training
data.
>> Test data.
>> Test data. I can always make test data
from my training data. Like I can split
it off.
But you need something more than data.
>> A model.
A model is what I want to make. So I I
have a model architecture. Fine. But
that's what I want to make. My goal is
to have making a model that's better at
being fine-tuned. That's my objective.
What else do I need?
An optimizer is how I train it. But my
optimizer requires something to be able
to work.
>> I need labels. Yes. But I don't just
need labels. I need a loss that goes
with those labels. Right?
Plus loss
some loss function.
So my loss function can be different for
different tasks.
My training data can be different for
different tasks. But I need it to
understand what the task is.
Okay. So oftentimes the loss might be
I'll use cross entropy loss or I'll use
like squared loss or I might have some
waiting on losses. Whatever it is for
your task, it is what it is. You have to
have it though.
Okay. So I need to have a collection of
tasks from the family which includes um
a loss function. So
if I want to make a model that's good at
doing something,
I also need to know what that something
is.
Okay.
So the other thing
is I need to have an approach
to fine-tuning.
So I if I want to make a model better at
being fine-tuned for tasks, I need to
say, well, how am I going to fine-tune
it? Make a model that's better at blah.
Well, how am I going to do blah?
So this could we could just put in the
standard approach. It's totally fine to
put in the standard approach. We have to
have it. So example
use Allora
and
the SGD
optimizer
on training data.
Okay. So if you want to solve a problem
with machine learning
to even begin I have to have a
collection of tasks. I need to have an
approach. I want to be better at X.
Okay. How am I going to do X? I'm going
to do this. This is the counterpart of
what a model architecture is. Okay. And
an optimizer.
I also need to know a have a way of
knowing if I'm any good at it,
right? Because I would like to train a
model so it's good at blah. I have to be
able to say am I any good at blah or
not? I need to have a way of doing that.
So I need an approach
to evaluation
and again there's this there's a default
but you have to make it explicit. What's
the default? This default is
eval performance
unheld outset.
using a loss.
Okay,
some some loss might be a different
loss. Okay, but it is what we have.
Okay, mamml said this is the basic thing
I need to even begin to do this problem.
If I want to make it be good at
fine-tuning for a certain task, I have
to say what do I mean by fine-tuning?
Okay, I'm going to use the std optimizer
and a Laura on a certain model as an
example. It could be anything. I just
have a models from scratch full fine
tune. Doesn't matter. It doesn't have to
be a can be full fine tune. Has to be
something that involves gradient steps.
Then I have an approach to evaluation on
held outset. Wonderful.
The key insight
I'll use a different color for this
key insight.
is that in machine learning the default
the default approach to doing a problem
is to train like you're tested
with the constraint about making
everything differentiable.
Okay, that's the default. If you want to
make a good classifier, standard
classifier, what do you do? You take
your classifier, you run it on data, you
see what the loss is, you make sure it's
differentiable, and then you get better
at the thing that you want to do at
inference time.
Okay.
So what mammal did was just say how do I
translate this key insight that we have
for standard ML to this setting and so
what's the approach I'll talk about it
more next time but what's the approach
it says take the tasks that I have in my
training set of tasks
proceed to view the initialization of
them as a learnable parameter the model
I start with that's the learnable
parameter
fine-tune it using the SG optimizer for
a while,
evaluate it using a held out set,
compute the loss,
and then run gradients all the way back
through this entire process.
run the gradients back through the
entire learning process itself and
update the initial condition and keep
doing this.
Okay. So
second thing is re insight was second
insight
learning process
of SGD
is like an RNN.
So you can train it like that. Okay. So
we'll talk more about this next time. We
have a homework problem that walks you
through this. But uh it's good to think
about because this sheds insight onto
how in context learning works. Okay,
I'll talk about that next time.
Okay, so now I have office hours.