So this is the
uh welcome everyone back from
Thanksgiving. Uh you
a few announcements uh basic things. So
this week we're going to be talking
about uh finishing up the RL post
training stuff and talk about diffusion
models. Be the last topic um for the for
the course. We'll release another
homework uh tomorrow. So you'll have
homework that you can do on diffusion
models stuff. So everything that's in
scope for uh class will be hit in
discussion homework lecture everything
like that.
Um
so uh a few announcements that I want to
make. First uh one from before we talked
about having this survey we get handed
out to we told everyone to fill out. We
said if you reached 80% as a class or
75% we'd give uh everybody 3% uh extra
credit. The class did not reach that
only reached 40%. So, but we decided to
be a little nice and instead of people
that actually did the work, uh instead
of giving people three, we just kind of
prorrated it and give we'll give one and
a half percent um to people for thank
you for filling them up. They're uh were
useful for us.
So, uh other very important deadlines.
So as you can as we announced at the
very beginning, this class has a lot of
effort and work um at the end uh for you
because the project and the final are
the dominant terms of what you're graded
on and they are happening now. So the
final project report we said was due
Friday, December 5th. We're gonna extend
that deadline for you
to Sunday
December 6th 7th 7th. Okay. So, um why
are we doing that? there's a limit on
how much we can extend it because
we need to make sure that you have
yourself time to prepare your posters
which are required um for Tuesday
December 9th remember same time as class
uh in R week you will have your poster
session it'll be up in the was
and uh also because we want to make sure
>> two hours we have two hours uh this
class time plus another um half hour so
two hours in the pause. Uh we understand
if some subset of your team cannot make
the last half hour because if another
class is doing something similar, but
this is the class time. So um we expect
everyone else to be there for the first
one and a half hours for sure. Um and we
are
going to have all of you do your
posters. So we encourage you all to
enjoy. Some of you should stand next to
your poster. Some of you should be
enjoying the other posters, interacting
with the students, um, learning. We as
staff will be walking around and, you
know, using
>> the whole team, like we will be walking
around and when one of us shows up to
talk to you about your poster, your
whole team should show up there.
>> Yeah.
>> Right. So, everyone should be like, look
at other posters, but as soon as a
faculty member or staff member comes to
your poster, show up.
>> Yeah. So, you can maybe, you know, rig
your phones with some summon but button
or something. Um so the important thing
is that as you uh
as during this time of your poster we'll
also have assigned everyone reviews on
the final project reports. So you can
use that interaction during the poster
to help you if you want um when you're
writing your reviews but you need to
submit your reviews by Thursday. The
timeline is pretty tight. It has to
happen um by Thursday. The reason is
that the final final report that you
will submit
we cannot make due later than Sunday
December 14th because the next day is
final exam week. That's like the limit
for when we can make stuff due. So we
want to make sure that everyone gets all
the feedback you can to make your final
report as good as it can be. So it's
very important for you to do the um peer
reviews.
The remember the final exam is Wednesday
December 17th uh 8 in the morning. We'll
announce the room details and which room
you particularly should go to um closer
to that that date. Uh
important thing is this exam will be no
questions, no clarifications, no notes.
You walk in with the stuff in your head,
your pencil, and we will give you on a
piece of paper what we think you need to
know based on what you should have
already internalized from the class.
Okay?
So, it's very important you walk in
prepared. You might want to make notes
for yourself as a part of your study
process, but you're not going to be able
to use them during the exam.
So, the it'll be three hours long.
You've seen plenty of exam problems
already. We'll also post the final exam
from last semester, but you'll have seen
pretty much every problem already
because we're putting on the homework
for you. So, our expectation in how to
succeed in the class is for students to
have done the homework through the
class. This last time we know is very
busy with projects and you can just
review homework and discussion and walk
in and you should be fine. If you've
internalized everything, it's probably
not humanly possible to learn everything
in the remaining uh two weeks uh of the
class before that exam.
Okay. So, uh another uh announcement, we
will we will very soon post the
participation grading self-grading form
for you. Basically, it's very very easy,
very short. take a picture of yourself,
drop it in, mark which TA, and upload to
the appropriate TA uh who's can
basically tell that you were going to
discussion. Um, if you want to get a
basic participation credit from ED posts
and attach screenshots of your ED posts
into that form, submit to great scope.
It's very straightforward. We're not
asking for long things. And just mark
what special participations you did. Um
reminder people if you haven't done your
special participation um yet also make
sure you upload it to grade scope. We
have great scope entries for you to
upload your special participation
reports too. So that way you can just
have all your grades be um done. Um
questions on the logistics. Yeah.
>> Um so when is the participation due?
There's one piece that I'm trying to
make that requires me to have lecture
notes from the day after tomorrow.
>> Yeah. So uh the participation uh form
we'll basically have submit to you we'll
give put it up for you like tomorrow um
after the last discussion basically um
and then for the special ones uh they
have to be done by the end of the uh RR
week
>> sounds
>> right so you you should be fine there's
like no no problem with that any other
questions on sort of logistic stuff yeah
>> in terms of like A and B like the kind
of posts should we like screenshot post
and attach it to grades as well or is it
just enough to have it on the edge like
shared with everyone?
>> Um I guess you could screenshot and
attach it. It's up to you. You submit a
report. We don't care about the main
report. Um yeah, it's you don't have to
screenshot the ED post. We just want the
PDF mostly for that. You should have
posted it on ED though. That was
>> the way I did it is like in the post I
described stuff and then gave the
appropriate like section of the chat.
Yeah.
PDF.
>> Yeah. Then if you have additional
content in the ED post that you consider
as part of the thing then for sure
include that.
>> Okay.
>> Okay. Just submit whatever you think is
the representative of what you did. Um
again we're not we're not grading these
in incredible detail. We just want to
see that you participated and tried to
help your fellow students in this way um
by sharing these reports. Um okay so
those are the announcements I want to
make. Just I guess I one more comment is
just uh people were asking about
readings. We I was pointing them out
very earlier. Um but you know there is
good treatment in the prince textbook of
VAEEs. There is uh decent treatment of
diffusion although we have will treat
diffusion in a slightly different way.
Um, and there's a little bit of RL, uh,
the type we're talking about in chapter
19.5. There's other parts of RL we're
not talking about in the class. So,
don't worry about other RL things in
chapter 19. Um, but there's a lot of
stuff how we're talking about it. It's
not in the textbook. But this is these
are references that you can also use.
Um, I want to turn it over for
>> one quick comment which is about this. I
can just use this. Okay. A so for the
extra credit about the participation um
probably all of you have read the post.
We got way more responses than we ever
thought. We thought I thought like five
people would be interested in doing this
but so we're going to change the
structure of the assignment a little bit
in light of the fact that there are so
many people interested in doing it. I
know some of you said like oh I didn't
see this. Can we like do something? So
we're going to change it to have two
approaches. So there's going to be
essentially a blue team and a red team
baseline team where the red team is
going to be tasked with doing the making
these websites using only vibe coding.
You must all all code should be AI
generated and that is a baseline. The
blue teams must beat the red team to be
able to receive any kind of extra
credit.
Right? So basically this is to make sure
that there's some level of high quality
submissions that uh that come through as
well as to give people an opportunity to
have a loweffort way of putting in uh
something. So for example, the red
teaming will be uh slightly less points.
Um but blue teams that do not do better
than the red teams will receive no
points. Does that make sense? Um, and I
will explain all of this in an ED post,
but yes, there's a question. No. No.
Okay. Does that Yes.
>> So, teams get credit no matter what as
long as their website makes sense.
>> Red teams get credit no matter what as
long as their website makes sense. But
it'll be less credit than the blue
teams. and the blue teams if you want to
really get a lot of credit then it has
to actually be a substantially nice
website that is not purely vibe coded
and you know a beats like looks better
and I guess we'll the staff will be
looking at this and making some kind of
uh objective judgments
uh on this does that roughly make sense
yes
>> how will you know if it's not purely
voded just like
>> has to has to beat the
>> you could have you could have purely
vibe coded it the blue teams are not
prohibited from using vibe coding. I
expect all of you to be vibe coding most
of this.
But it has to be better functionality
uh and more impressive than the
uh than what's generated purely by the
red teams. Does that make sense?
>> So the idea of the red teams is it's
it's AI generation completely. You can
do meta cognition but anything that
involves like doing the work you know we
expect that to be done uh delegated to
agents uh to do that. So just to get
establish a baseline so you could human
judgment and so on is all intended to be
in blue team. you can be smart about it
and I mean maybe we can we can see if we
want to structure it so that for every
blue team that a red team beats we can
give more points so that like there's
incentive to see how bad good you can
get but yeah we'll see
>> so I think on the original post it said
that you get like five points for the
assignment so I was just wondering like
as a point of reference like how much
exactly point
>> so there's 100 points in the course
>> okay
>> and so if you get one point so for
example you instead of starting at zero
you will now all start at 1.5.
>> Yes.
>> Okay. So,
>> yeah, logistics have to be taken care
of. So, hopefully we've addressed them.
I want us to quickly hopefully
>> yeah, quickly finish up the um oral post
training. So remember basic story of
post training is pre-train a model you
SFT it for doing some kind of
instruction following which is basically
trying to maximize the probability of
responses right that's what cross
entropy loss is trying to do um then you
want to make it better at solving
problems so you have to be willing to
spend something spend more compute while
answering and then you want to train it
to be better we introduce the idea of
RLVR
which is u if you have an autograder for
your problem so you can tell if a
particular solution is good or not um
and can score it how can you use that
and we talked about this scaling law
perspective which I don't want to recap
um and then we kind of used one
particular recipe to kind of help you
understand the basic ideas that are
needed so this is the scalar RL u recipe
which is useful because it connects to
stuff that we've taught in class and
helps you understand the different
components of doing this kind of RL post
training so the the key thing in RL post
training and there was confusion about
this so I want to make sure everyone get
understands it for for verifiable
rewards is you you take a problem that
you know how to autograde and you
proceed to ask the model to do many many
different generations many many
different attempts to solve that problem
okay that's what G is these generations
G
and then what you want to do your basic
idea is you want to reward the
generations that are good and penalize
the ones that are bad to make the model
more likely to generate good generations
in the future. And so as you saw in
homework three, there's this trick that
you don't have gradients on the reward.
Uh so you instead you do this log
probability uh trick and now you have to
basically put a score in front,
right? So this that's just this thing,
right? So the role of this thing is done
by uh this expression and what this
expression is doing is it's saying that
we would like to compute how much better
this generation is or how much worse
this is in a normalized way relative to
other generations for the problem. So
you remove the mean that way you can
tell better or worse than the average
and you normalize by the standard
deviation so that there's on a common
scale. Okay, that's what this uh a hat
is. And what you do here is the other
thing that was described in this
perspective and you can there's
different approaches to doing RL VR and
many different recipes and they kind of
vary on different axes. We'll kind of
show you some of those axes just by
example. There's an entire class um 185
285 uh which we taught about uh RL per
se and deep learning. So this is just a
taste
that what we're doing here is we're
taking this uh although generation is an
entire sequence we're going to treat it
as a bag of tokens
and every token will inherit the
advantage from its generation. So if the
generation succeed that token is a good
token if the generation failed that
token is a bad token. You think of it
that way and we use the probability kind
of at the individual token level here
and then we have to do some adjustments.
Okay, the adjustments are required
because to make this stuff work in
practice,
you're going to be so problem homework
three problem that you saw it very much
relied on the fact that this probability
and this probability are the same
probability. I got questions about this
in office hours. So I want to make sure
everyone everyone's clear on it.
And you do this trick so that you can
get what you want, which is a gradient
on this expectation.
Now the problem is that when you're
doing this in practice, if you wanted to
make this distribution and this
distribution be the same distribution,
you would have to do these things
sequentially.
You would have to use the distribution
you have to do to make the generations.
So you make a bunch of generations using
this distribution. Then you have to
autograde these distributions. These
these generations. Now you've computed
all this stuff
and now you can go ahead and compute
this loss and then do the update.
Everyone with me? Do you see this
connection, the ordering? But you don't
want to do that. You don't want to have
the machines that you have available for
doing
uh the back prop to have to sit and wait
for the generations to happen.
Okay, that's not a good idea to waste
your resources that way. And it turns
out good code for doing the generation
is different than good code for doing
back prop because when you're doing the
generation you don't have to store
everything around to be do back prop.
You just have to have the generation
happen. So there's actually different
code bases that are used to do the
generation and to do the back prop. As a
result, there's going to be a difference
between the actual probabilities used to
do the generation and the probabilities
that are used to do the training. Does
everyone see this? So, you're not going
to be able to have this probability and
this probability be the same
probability. So, you have to patch this
problem. And a standard way of patching
this problem is to say whenever you're
generating using a different probability
adjust with the ratio of the
probabilities. Okay, this is called
important sampling where you say oops I
generated with this probability so let
me divide by it and let me this is the
probability I wanted to generate with
but I didn't. So I compute this ratio
and I stick it in here but I don't want
a gradient on this. So that's why
there's a stop gradient here like don't
take gradients on. This is an adjustment
I'm doing.
Okay. Now, I misspoke last time, so I
want to make sure this has been very
clear. Um, I fixed it in the notes so
that if people read the notes, it was
wasn't there. But what does this minimum
mean?
The minimum means that if this ratio
is too big, which means that
there was a helpful question that I uh
fumbled last time. If this training
policy that you're actually training and
the generation policies have become
significantly out of sync with each
other and have the training policy is
assigning a very large probability to
this relative to the generation pro uh
probability. Now think about it that
these are ratios of numbers between zero
and one. The only way that's getting big
is if the denominator is getting small.
Everyone see that? like you're not you
see there's not like a you can't really
go that high. So the only way to get big
is the denominator gets small. And so
from a practical perspective this is
important when you're doing like long uh
training runs because the probability
that something was generated with very
low probability is also low.
Okay, but it can happen. So if that were
to happen, cap it at epsilon.
Don't let it get beyond a certain point.
Um otherwise go ahead and use it to
adjust the probabilities as you need to.
Okay.
So what's going on is you do this for
doing the generations and of course as
soon as you have done uh
an update. So you apply updates as soon
as you can apply an update you can send
that updated set of parameters back to
whatever servers are doing the
generations.
Everyone with me? So you have to send
that update over.
And so this generation basically tracks
the training with a lag of some kind.
And now there's all if you read the
paper, there's all kinds of interesting
tricks that are referenced in that paper
to kind of get this to go faster. And
one of them is even what's called
in-flight updates. So inflight update
means while the generator is generating
okay so it's generating a generation
it'll be like okay now a new model and
it'll keep generating
but think about it when you do a
everyone see what hear what I'm talking
about like you're you're generating and
this response isn't coming from one
model it's coming from model switched
different model so if you're going to do
this correctly you would go back and
recomputee all the keys and values under
the new model, but that involves work.
So you say whatever and you just keep
going. So people do tricks like this to
use scale key values from a different
model to generate under a new model and
just for the speed and it's worth it.
Okay, so that's what the scale RL paper
talks about. Lots of tricks involved in
making this stuff work um in practice,
but you now have all of the sort of
ingredients understood for understanding
what's happening here. And that was the
point of last lecture.
>> Yes.
>> Pa just the relative training generation
probabilities.
>> So P theta is just the generation
probabilities here. So remember in in
the homework three what you had was you
had a model that would generate outputs
with some probability and you could
score them in a non-ifferiable way.
So you want to still get a gradient that
you need to be update those
probabilities by updating the model
that's updating with parameters theta
right the model has parameters theta
it's generating something with
probabilities so this is a way to do it
so p theta is just the model in this
picture the engineering issue is that
there isn't one model the engineering
issue is you have a generating model and
a training model
in practice so you have to deal with the
fact that there's is a discrepancy and
this discrepancy is important to deal
with. If you don't do these kinds of
tricks, uh the training goes bad.
The imbalances uh effect affects the
actual quality of the training.
Okay.
So this we talked about before last
time. So now continuing
there's one thing I want to talk about
which is this particular paper. or the
SCARL RL paper says that they find for
the LM context that they're talking
about that this is the recipe that they
think works the best and they're basing
this on uh findings at scale from this
team out of China who made the Minimax
model which proposed something pretty
much similar. They just did some
engineering updates on Minimax. Not
really that any conceptual updates. Uh
but there's many many many uh such um
RLVR recipes out there. I'm sure you
know before the year is out there will
probably be an updated version that
someone who says, "Oh, here's a tweak
that does a little bit better than
this." Lots of tweaks keep happening and
many people believe many of them are not
public. So public ones keep coming up
also.
So
there's another thing that is al also
done in these problems and that is just
as we saw in VAE where we added an
auxiliary loss involving KL in these
kinds of RL problems they often use KL
regularization with respect to some
reference policy pyreff
so there's a very basic kind of approach
to thinking about this so RL people so
in machine learning learning generally
we think about minimizing losses okay so
we think about some loss when I minimize
it RL people often think about
maximizing a reward
it's just negative signs um difference
about them but so following the RL
perspective they think about as arg max
I want to find the best policy that
maximizes
the expectation if I generate
uh the responses. So X is the prompt.
Think of X as prompts and Y is the uh
response. So I generate the Y response
under this policy. I want to maximize
the expected reward.
Suppose I had a reward. Now in an RLVR
con uh context, this would be something
that you could just directly evaluate.
Okay. But in a other con in other
context, this might be you have a model
for the reward that you have to train to
also learn separately. However it is,
you have a reward. So if you just do
this, you get something. But if you add
a regularizer, so in
in classic ML, we add regularizers with
positive signs. They're added things to
the loss. But when you're maximizing a
reward, the regularizer term shows up
with a negative sign.
Okay? You think of like a cost function,
right? The kale divergence. So this says
you put some weight on the regularizing
term and you penalize the KL divergence
between the thing that you're maximizing
and some reference policy.
What is this saying? This is saying that
you want to tell the the training
approach to not move too far from this
reference policy. try to stay close to
the reference policy to the extent you
can. That's what a regularizer like this
is doing. So many RL training recipes
involve this kind of regularizer, which
is why I wanted to make sure I talked
about it.
So it turns out when you do this kind of
thing,
you get a solution
that says
basically
your policy should be kind of
proportional to the reference policy
except with an adjustment.
If the reward was high,
you should upweight that kind of
response.
And if the reward is low, you should
downweight that kind of response. Does
everyone see what this is doing?
And of course, if you do this upweing
down of uh of sequences, then you're no
longer going to have a probability that
adds to one. So divide by whatever you
need to do to make this thing be a
probability that adds to one. It sums up
to one.
Okay. So this is a this is what doing
kale regularization
does. Okay. It says
anchor to the reference policy and just
up and down weight probabilities to the
extent you can. And the purpose of doing
this is in part to avoid this
catastrophic forgetting type of
phenomena. Okay. So not have
capabilities go away. Okay. Yeah.
Question.
>> What is Z of X?
>> Oh, this is just whatever I need to do
to make this be a probability.
>> Oh,
>> right. So I normalize I Z of X is the
sum over all possible Y's of this thing.
So that this whole thing will be an
appropriate probability overwise.
>> Yeah. Question. Yes.
>> So it mitigates catastrophic forgetting
when you set py to be your original
model. Is that the idea?
>> It m it minimize it. It it mitigates
catastrophic forgetting. If you make pyf
be a model that you think of as being
original or having having attributes you
like. This is then used in different
ways. The basic thing it's doing is it's
keeping you close.
But uh if you if you set pyrf to be a
model that you don't want to forget too
much from then it does have that uh
property.
>> Yes.
>> Is this related to like energy?
Yeah, this is all very closely related
to energy and this is coming out of so
these kind of kale divergence
regularizers have a long history in uh
information theory and statistical
physics where statistical physics they
originate in the context of thinking
about things with energy and finding
states that are appropriately high
probability. Uh so it's it's all it has
a long tradition which is why people um
use it but from a practical perspective
and deep learning point of view it is
completely reasonable to think of it as
I just have a few go-to defaults for
things and my go-to default
distributions are uniform and Gaussian
and my go-to default uh
distance measure on probabilities is
kale divergence and so I just use
Okay. So if you want to understand for
example um GRPO which at this point you
have all the tools you need to to read
the paper and understand like our goal
remember is to teach you enough so you
can learn on your own. So GRPO is
in spirit like this some variations but
it also has a k regularization
regularizing term in it
and it clips in both direction. This is
this min is clipping only high values.
It's also clipping low values in gpo
and it doesn't gpo doesn't take a bag of
tokens perspective. It takes a sequence
perspective
in terms of how it thinks about you know
this uh this part here
and uh this part here.
Okay. So there's a whole family of such
um algorithms that people have and the
key insight for verifiable rewards was
hey we can make lots of generations for
the same u prompt and that's useful for
us to see what's the variation what we
get remember all this is in the context
of earlier approaches to uh that I just
earlier even more basic approaches for
using test time compute which is
generate lots of samples and pick the
best one. Okay. So
now it turns out that if you have u a
reward model
and
you actually trust it, you can use that
to make any generative model better.
How? Generate 1,000
responses from your generative model and
pick the one that has the highest
reward.
Okay? like there's tricks like this that
uh exist and that's actually a very
strong baseline when you can actually
learn a reward model.
Okay, so good. I wanted to make sure
people understood this and now I want to
switch uh to talk about what happens if
you don't have verifiable rewards. What
do people do? So what's RHF? Remember I
told you historically RLHF came first
in the development of these things but
uh it's easier to understand it kind of
in the reverse direction now.
So
uh
when you have human feedback the idea is
you don't have a autograder that can
grade responses. You have to count on
people to grade the responses.
So here's some of the problems. Okay,
humans are expensive.
If you ask a human to grade something
and you say, "What's your batch size?"
My batch size is um 100.
Um what's your total size of your
training data? You want um 10,000.
Okay, you're going to have a human go
score 10,000 things. I mean, it's And
but this is like one shot. Then I do
this again over millions of examples.
This gets expensive fast.
So the key key insight was to say
instead of using human responses
directly
in RLHF the idea was I will use human
responses
to train an AI reward model.
Okay. Okay, so I will try to train a
model that will be my reward model from
the human responses and then I'll use
that reward model to grade the
generations that my model is doing
during RL training.
Everyone with me? So the human the human
model would basically act this this
model would do the job of um you know
this function
here.
So you still have to do RL type stuff
because the sampling operations in the
generation are non-ifferiable.
Okay. So there's still there's still the
issue of non-ifferiability even if you
have a differentiable reward model.
Okay. So
second problem is
humans aren't good at giving real valued
scores.
Just very terrible.
Okay. Uh,
so what are humans good at? Humans good
are good at telling if something's
better than something else at
comparisons. Now, you've probably all
experienced this. You've experienced
this. If you're using some of the
commercial models, it'll every now and
then ask you, which do you like better,
this or this? This is why it's doing
that. It's trying to get human feedback
on what's better.
So now you have a conundrum which is
your reward model is supposed to be
giving you something which is a real
number
and
humans are good at giving binary
feedback. So you have to learn a real
valued reward model from binary feedback
is the traditional approach. So what
people do is follow the following kind
of course pipeline.
You pre-train a model, you SFT it on
good examples to get it to be sort of
good enough to generate reasonable
responses. Then you generate a bunch of
uh things that you want to be able to
score.
You get humans to score them on
comparisons.
Okay. that costs a lot of money in human
time. Then you use that data to train or
update your reward model.
Okay. Now having done this, you then
proceed to do RL as though you're doing
like RLVR. Okay. Except you have this
reward model directly. So you can follow
some RL recipe to keep training this.
Now as you do this training what'll
happen is the model will start changing
and be different and now there will be a
discrepancy a significant discrepancy at
some point between this model's
probability of doing generations and
this thing that you use to train the re
reward model. So now the problem is your
generations that this thing is making
might become out of distribution from
the perspective what the reward model
was trained at. Everyone see the issue?
So you do update you say okay let's do
some more generations and get some more
human feedback
and this is the gold standard for doing
um RLHF
and you you can hopefully understand
this in light of everything we've talked
about
again lots of algorithmic details and
variations that people have in how you
do uh this and then
but then the question is how do you do
this
how do you train a reward model based on
uh binary comparisons.
But that you realize, oh, okay, that you
know how to do, right? Because that's
kind of like a classifier. Your all ML
classifiers generate scores and you can
train scores based on binary
information.
So this is like a classical ML problem.
You just train a score. And if the score
can then be used to
successfully do these binary
comparisons, great.
You'll have a useful score.
Okay, that's uh that's what's happening
here. Now, the key thing I want to talk
about is something called DPO.
And what DPO did was
it said, this is a figure from the
paper. This is uh the paper is titled
direct preference optimization your L
your language model is secretly a reward
model. Um came out in 2023 very
influential paper.
uh one of the the faculty authors, one
of the faculty authors was Chelsea Finn
who we mentioned before from the mammal
work
and it says instead of having all of
this uh complexity,
can we just take the preference data
that we get from here
and not train a reward model at all?
Just take the preference data itself and
use that to do finetuning on the model.
Okay,
so this is the idea.
So when you have preference outputs, all
you have are pairs that say this is the
winner, this is the better response, and
this is the loser, this is the worst
response. That's all you have. Can I use
this to do fine-tuning?
Okay, everyone good with this? Okay,
so the first thing you might try is to
say great,
let me just try to maximize the
probability of the winners and minimize
the probability of the losers.
Right? So I'll do gradient ascent on
winners and gradient descent on losers,
right? For their probabilities. Um, I
can do that.
And it seems like a good idea. It seems
like actually it's following the spirit
of what we were talking about with the
with this thing, right? Because remember
what is this doing right up here for
verifiable rewards? It's saying make the
responses that are correct more likely
and make the responses that are
incorrect less likely. Right? That's
what's happening here. Everyone remember
this? See this? So like try to do the
same thing. We have winners, we have
losers.
Okay. So
what happens? So here's table three from
the paper. Um
it's trying to do a like a summarization
task. They have some ideas of good
summaries and bad summaries. And they
said, you know, here is this prompt.
It's like some Reddit uh data. it wants
to summarize a post or there's some
prompt goes on
and then what's the response and after
you do this you get just junk
so the model had been sfted to sort of
do something on this task and now it's
just completely lost everything
okay everyone this is bad.
What happened? Why did this happen?
Right? This is like a kind of
forgetting, but it's a kind of
forgetting that has been exacerbated by
saying that perfectly grammatical and
reasonable responses that just happen
not to be preferred are actually like
really bad.
That's what's happening here.
Does everyone see that? When I tell it
don't do this, it doesn't like there's
many different reasons to not do this.
And one could be like, oh, this is
coherent. I shouldn't be coherent.
You see, like it's ambiguous. So this
thing is saying make these good
responses and this is saying be
incoherent. That's not what you meant,
but that could a perfectly reasonable
interpretation from the model's point of
view. So this doesn't work. Okay.
So then you say, "Okay, okay, whatever.
Let me just ignore the losers at all. I
have good examples. Let me just SFT on
the winners. Just treat the winners as
these are good examples."
If you do that, it's not horrible. The
paper doesn't have a table. I wish it
did for how this one behaved. It's a key
part of their algorithm, but not talked
about as a baseline. Um,
so then what they what they do is they
say, "Great. Now this here's the DPO
idea.
The DPO idea is is there a question?
Okay, DPO idea is SFT on the winners
first.
Call this your new reference. We're
going to start here.
then use the following loss
starting at x0 to do uh gradient descent
I will take so this minus sign in front
of this expectation that just comes from
the fact I'm viewing this as a loss
otherwise this if I treat as a reward
this would be this minus sign wouldn't
be there
let me take the log of the sigmoid
of this following difference of ratios
of probabilities. So what I'm going to
do is I'm going to take the probability
that my model that I'm training
generates the winner response divided by
the probability the reference model
generates the winner response.
Subtract that subtract from that the
probability the same ratio for the loser
and
just run gradient uh gradient on this.
Okay. And the sigmoid is just uh here.
Now if you read the paper and I think
we'll give you a homework that walks you
through kind of more of the derivation
of this. I don't want to spend too much
time on it.
What it's doing is it's using a model
for how the human is generating
preferences.
Okay, how it chooses things and it kind
of builds that in.
Okay. So what's happening here is that
it's just doing SGD on preference pairs
except it's using this loss.
Yeah.
>> Yes. Exactly. You're still penalizing
the loser and uplifting the winner,
except you're doing it slightly
differently.
So what this should remind you of is
something you saw uh we saw an example
of in in ML class uh basic ML class
where you say you could do
classification just using squared loss.
Okay. So saying make everything that's a
positive class mapped to plus one
everything that's a negative class
mapped in minus one. And it kind of
works actually. It's not like it's bad.
Um but it can sometimes be not as good.
And so what you do is you use something
like logistic loss which shapes this a
little bit differently and is more
sensitive to what you want that treat
like classification problem and that
tends to work a little bit better. So
this is the same kind of idea. It's
asking the question what is the
counterpart of the right kind of loss
function for preferences and it uses
there's actually variations. This is
DPO. There's others that treat it
differently. There's some that involve
uh kind of human
irrationality models where you prefer
winning more or you you you dislike
losing more than you like winning. So
things like this, lots of variations
that people have, but it's kind of
shaping the loss to be a little
different. But
what's interesting and I think as a
question I want to ask first is just I
make sure people are following me is
if you look at this as a loss function
where are the gradients going this is
just SGD there's nothing here that's
happening I'm not drawing this stuff
according to in in the whole point of
one of the big points of doing this is
you can do this even if you didn't draw
data from a particular distribution it's
just there you have preference data.
So this is just your your training data
set.
Now if you do this, the gradients,
they'll go through the log, they go
through the sigma, but they're not going
to enter the reference policy. The
reference policy is not being trained.
It's just sitting there.
And so at first glance, you look at this
and you say, wait, log of a ratio is
just a difference of logs.
And so inside this thing I just have a
sum of four terms.
Two of which the gradients are not going
into at all.
So the other terms just have only the pi
theta in them.
So how is this any different from as the
question was how is this any diff? Why
is this any different from just
uplifting
the positive examples and down down
pushing down the negative examples? Does
everyone see the question? Like just so
take uh take a minute and think about it
and just I'm asking at first a purely
technical level like are these doing
anything given this given these facts
are are there? What what are they doing
at all even like is it possible for them
to have any effect?
So just take a minute talk to your
neighbors.
Okay. So, I'll stop.
>> So, chance to think about it. So, who
wants to suggest to me why these might
be having any effect at all in what's
going on here?
>> Um, yeah,
>> it seems like the the ps are scaling the
adjustment to pi so that like the
farther away the p the bigger the loss.
So um at first glance when you look at
it because you take this ratio
right it's saying I'm scaling it
appropriately to look relative to pyrev
but that's what this argument is
designed to say maybe not like this
ratio is inside of the log and the log
will just break that scaling off into
separate things. So at a level of
intuition, yeah, it's definitely doing
that, but at a level of intuition for
why that matters, it doesn't answer the
question because it seems like the log
is killing all of that.
Yeah,
>> I think it's just like a baseline. So
now we have like positive rewards,
negative.
If we don't have that baseline, we will
have like all the rewards positive.
>> So it's the when you say all the words
be positive, what do you mean?
like the yusen.
So the the probabilities are positive
that's fine. The ratio of probabilities
is also positive. So it's still
positive.
This taking ratios doesn't make it not
be positive. So that's not that's not
really an explanation. It's true but it
doesn't it doesn't doesn't tell you why
this is having any effect even at like a
at a like basic level.
>> Yeah.
>> Um it's inside the signal. So you're
doing a subtraction
difference.
kind of acting like the divergence was.
So if it moves too far away from the
reference policy, the sigmoid will like
saturate it. So the gradients will be
the flatter.
>> Okay, great. So let me just draw a
sigmoid. That's what you're basically
saying is remember what a sigmoid looks
like.
Okay, sigmoid looks like this. So a
sigmoid has flat sections. So what this
is doing is it's doing something to
adjust what's happening inside the
sigmoid. And the sigmoid allows for the
possibility of saturation
of what's happening. And indeed that's a
good way of thinking about it. So if you
want to think about it, you can just
group these terms a little differently
and say you have something that's
comparing
the winner to the loser
and you have another
where is the right kind of place to look
at. So it turns out this the only point
of doing this is to say yeah it could
make a difference right this can make a
difference because it's going to shift
you around inside the sigmoid. Now the
paper has a nice derivation. I think we
we'll make you do it in the homework. um
says if you look at this guy and
actually take the gradient and take
advantage of the properties of the
gradients of sigmoids and the gradients
of logs and stuff like this you get that
the expression
um over here if you take the gradient of
it it turns into a term which is
increase the probability of the winner
and a term that says decrease the
probability of the loser as we had
before but it has a waiting on it
says
I'm doing the sigmoid
sigmoid of this difference when when
this difference is large and positive
it says do this
but when the difference is
negative
it's saying yeah saturate this out and
basically don't do this I don't need to
adjust these
Okay. And
the final issue in DPO why the paper
gets its title at all is it's saying
that if I think about this as a I can
think of this as a reward estimate and
it says what does a model think is good
and the answer is models think things
are good if they like to generate them.
That's it. you treat the probability of
the model generating something as a
reward model as as a reward model. So
high probability things are deemed good,
low probability things are deemed bad
and that's it and you can just work with
that.
So this thing uh very brief view of uh
of DPO but this had a huge effect um
practically because this was simple
enough to do and you didn't have to do a
bunch of generations and have to train a
reward model at all and
as a result people could take data sets
that they would handcraft or kind of
interrogate other models to generate
data sets and use them to fine-tune
other different models and it created a
whole cottage industry of people doing
all kinds of fine-tunes without having
to do full RL with uh reward models and
people implemented it. There's like
companies and libraries out there that
you can use. You can basically do it on
a collab notebook now finetune a model
using DPL.
So uh to show you this is not uh an area
which is that's the final word things
keep going. So the third I would
consider kind of important idea in this
gener in this kind of sequence of work
was to say
maybe instead of just having the
reference policy start at the reference
policy that said upweight the winners
you every some number of iterations say
I have a new reference policy namely the
policy that I just trained.
Okay, so this is the TRDPO idea. This
came out in I ICLR
this year. Um, and basically every like
512ish
training steps say, okay, I have a new
reference policy. It's the current one.
This seems to work even better
by allowing things to adjust. And
there's like good reasons for it. You
can read the papers. It's very nice to
hear to think about why it's doing this.
Um
but this is uh kind of what's in DPO
land. Uh so between the DPO ideas reward
modeling um with RHF you kind of now
have a full perspective on what's going
on with the post training of models
using RL ideas
as an introduction meaning you can now
start reading the papers and look and
read and understand things as you need
to.
Okay, any questions on this?
Okay, great. So now I'm going to switch
topics. So now I'm going to talk about
diffusion models for generation.
So that was the um RL
uh post-training interlude return back
to generative models.
So
it's interesting because you can think
about diffusion models for generation as
a kind of test time compute relative to
a VAE. Okay, so think about a VAE. You
train a VAE for doing generation. You do
a bunch of training, but then when you
have to do a generation, you draw a
random Gaussian,
shove it into your decoder and say what
comes out.
One shot.
everyone there. Other techniques are
also of that flavor. Um there's things
called GANs which we're not going to
talk about this term um because of time
uh where you also do different ways of
training but then you take a model you
shove in noise and out comes a
generation and that's it.
Diffusion models as well as auto
reggressive models they think some
amount of time before they give a model
up output out. So do things over and
over again. So you've already seen this
in auto reggressive generation. So in
auto reggressive generation instead of
doing the generation one sentence or
sequence at a time, you do it one chunk
or token at a time. Right? In images
it's by patches.
And so what you do is the during
training you learn a conditional
distribution
and then you do the generation with
sampling one step at a time. So as
you're doing the generation you're
introducing randomness and keep moving.
Okay, everyone cool with this kind of
perspective and auto reggressive
generation.
So to do this and it was most natural to
do this in cases where the training data
itself has an inherent sequentiality to
it. So you can train to learn what comes
next.
So now diffusion models one way of
thinking about them is to say I would
like to spend effort while doing the
generation not just have to do it in one
shot
but my pro my domain doesn't necessarily
have inherent sequentiality like images
an image doesn't you can you can make an
image sequential in many different ways
you can raster scan the image you can
space filling curve through an image you
low res space filling curve through the
image followed by medium res space
filling curve through the image followed
by high-res space filling curve through
the image right you can do lots of
things for an image to try to make it be
sequential but it isn't
it's something you're imposing right
image really is all at once
if you recall from lecture 18 we talked
about ideas that didn't work for doing
generation and we already had a kind of
test time compute idea which didn't work
which was to say
remember we said one way you could
imagine doing it is to use a cat
classifier and just pick random noise
and gradient ascent that's the test time
compute
right on the cat score but if you did
this we told you you wouldn't get a
picture of a cat
right and we identified the challenge as
being the fact that there's all possible
images in the sense of pixel arrays. And
then there's the manifold of natural
images, which is a much lower
dimensional object.
And
the cat classifier was only trained on
this stuff.
And if you shove in something over here,
it's like well out of its distribution.
So gradient descent on isn't going to
get you someplace nice.
Everyone remember bring this stuff back
into memory.
So you can think of diffusion models as
trying to make this kind of idea work.
Okay, in spirit.
So
remember in that lecture we started with
we had this classifier idea and then we
had the autoenccoder idea and then we
made the autoenccoder idea work by using
the VAE idea.
So we want to see if we can do that same
kind of move on this idea. So what does
that how does that look?
So the key insight we have from the VA
story was
you can't ask a model to work on
something very far from its
distribution. And so in the VAE we
wanted the decoder to be robust and to
see things that were more noise-like.
And so we had noisy things appear during
training.
So now the question is we need to
somehow have noisy things appear during
training for this idea of taking
something out in very noisy land and
making it move towards this thing. Okay,
that's our goal trying to follow the
idea of start out here move towards
here.
So now this is like the question how
noisy should it be
for the VAE? We said look we're going to
have a kale regularizer term. We will
set up a noise amount and we will kind
of optimize this the tension between
reconstruction loss and how noisy things
are. And we ask it to balance that
through our hyperparameter choice.
This feels different. So what should we
do? So here I want to point out that
there's two extremes are very clear.
Okay, which is
since we're definitely going to start
with stuff that's very noisy,
we we should see very noisy things
during training. Everyone with me? So,
we have to see very noisy things. At
some point, we're taking steps, right?
And we're going to end up here. So, we
have to see things that are basically
clean.
These two extremes are required
for the story of trying to get start
somewhere and then move towards natural
images. So the question becomes what
else? So here is where I thought a meme
would be useful. Okay,
so
total noise
somehow clean desired samples. The
question is what goes here?
So
if you think of it this way, there's
actually a natural bridge,
okay? That goes between
total noise and something clean, which
is everything in between, okay? Right?
You there's there's not like you have
only
out here and this place.
You can add noise to here and get
nearby. You can add more noise to here
and get further out. You can kind of
draw around here
like
increasingly
noisy
blobs
around natural images by adding more
noise. So if you think in training you
want to see everything and you expect
that somehow during the generation
you're going to start far away and then
move towards natural images
you can train on all of that by just
adjusting the amount of noise you add.
That's like an idea. So far we don't
have a technique. We don't have an
approach to do it. We just have
ingredients that we want to use.
So if you look in there's a nice figure
in Prince which kind of describes what
you're trying to do is somehow during
training you're going to have things
that are going to be differently noisy
all the way up to fully noise and then
during actual operations you're going to
somehow start with noise and then move
towards images. This is just the idea I
described except in pictures.
Still no details.
Okay. So now
I want to
contrast the way I'm going to talk about
it with the way in Prince. You can read
the work in prints. It's reasonably well
written. It's good and it follows the
traditional perspective from this paper
um by Soul Dix at all. I know actually
know the last author um from way back
undergrad days. um
which is called deep unsupervised
learning using non-equilibrium
thermodynamics and this appeared in ICML
2015. I'll make the connection to
non-equilibrium thermodynamics in a
moment.
Um
and what
this involves is like how do you
generate stuff that goes from
clean to very noisy? And the approach in
the paper and also practically important
and interesting is
if you want to make an image more noisy,
you add noise to it. But if you add
noise to it using real numbers, what
will happen is you will start with
something that's small and you will get
something that's big. And we already
told you that in deep learning you
cannot have wide variations of dynamic
range. That's not okay. So it says scale
along the way. Scale things down and
then add noise and then keep doing this.
Eventually you will scale the actual
image out to nothing and the noise will
be all that remains. Okay. So this is
very practical, very important. Um,
however,
it turns out that it's easier to
understand this if we say, let me
pretend I don't do the scaling for
conceptual purposes.
And that's the treatment we're going to
follow here. Although we will
acknowledge the other treatment in the
homework um with a extra problem we're
giving you and you'll see a variation of
it in discrete space for in tomorrow's
uh discussion. So I want to point out
this paper that came out uh June of last
year. Uh it's a tutorial paper um by
Pritham Nuran with co-authors who's now
at Apple again a former Berkeley
undergrad knew him then um called
stepby-step diffusion and elementary
tutorial. So I really recommend this.
We're going to follow that perspective.
So let's go back here. Okay. So we want
to understand how to move from
some place you know here onto here onto
the image onto the manifold of natural
images somehow.
So
what we're going to do for simplicity in
this picture is we're not going to worry
about any of the scaling. We're
literally going to do the obvious thing.
We're going to take an image or whatever
vector we're abstract vector and we're
just going to add noise to it. Keep
adding noise to it.
So
idea is start here with something that's
actually on the unknown distribution
that we want to learn. Okay, we don't
know what this distribution is, but we
have samples of it. Add noise, add
noise, add noise, add noise, add noise,
add noise, add noise. And if you want to
think about it, think of it this way.
Suppose this thing was something which
had pixel values between minus1 and one.
Okay? And I keep adding noise. At some
point, I keep adding Gaussian noise.
Gaussian noise. Keep adding Gaussian
noise.
At some point, I have something where
the Gaussian noise is standard deviation
is 10,000 because I keep adding it.
10,000 steps of adding standard
deviation one. For example,
at this point, this is a Gaussian with
standard deviation 10,000 in every
vector. And sure, that original minus1
to one is in there somewhere, but it's
basically gone at this point. This is
you could basically just sample a
Gaussian and get the same thing.
Okay, so this is the the picture of the
forward um part of the diffusion. And
our perspective on this is to say, can
we think about this so that
having trained a network
on these kind of forward paths which we
can simulate, we can generate these
easily, can we train a network that will
allow us to go backward?
Okay, this is a a version of the basic
picture of it's possible
uh
it's possible to go in this direction.
Start there and move out. Can I go in
this direction?
This way.
So we're trying to network to predict
backwards in time.
So to understand this
right
there's many many steps conceptually
that we have to get get uh understand
how to do somehow you train a network
and then you have to somehow use this
network to move backwards.
Okay.
So
there's an interesting design question
which we have to ask and that actually
divides the approaches into two
different approaches and the key design
question is do I need to have randomness
on the backward path. So I drew this
path as shaking is it are paths like
that or are paths like this?
Okay.
So remember in auto reggressive
generation when you do auto reggressive
gener you do use randomness as you move
you keep doing this random sampling as
you're doing the generation token by
token.
Okay. So we're going to start with the
randomness is totally natural
perspective and later not this lecture
but the next lecture I will show how we
can eliminate this randomness um in the
in the backward path.
So
these approaches are divided into two
different categories. When you do
randomness
in the way that you go backward, that's
called stochcastic sampling.
And when you don't have randomness, it's
called deterministic sampling.
And kind of paradmatic approaches are
what are called DDPM and DDIM
for this. And we're going to talk about
the original solixine at all paper was a
DDPM and we're going to start with that
one. And then there's approaches that do
this.
We'll do that next time.
Okay. So first
let's uh
let's explain this. Maybe it's good for
a moment to explain why is this thought
of as um
why is this called diffusion? Okay. Why
is it called diffusion at all?
So, here's a picture of why it's called
diffusion. Okay. Think of a glass of
water.
Okay.
Water.
Okay. Now, we're going to do make
believe is we're going to have a very
very slow motion camera. Okay. or if you
want to not think of as water, think of
it as a more viscous uh liquid. Okay,
we're going to take a pipet,
dip it in the water, and I'm going to
inject a little bit of
red dye
in a little curve here. Okay, so a
little bit of red dye is going to be put
into this water.
Everyone understand the picture? What
happens next?
Okay, what happens next is that red dye
is going to by the random motion,
thermal motion of these water molecules
is going to be pulled out and diffuse
until eventually it fills the entire
glass of water.
Everyone see that? Now when that red dye
has diffused out and has filled the
entire glass of water, this thing is in
equilibrium.
It doesn't mean that every individual
red dye molecule is no longer moving
around randomly. In fact, it is. But at
the macro scale, there's red dye
everywhere.
Okay. So this process is called
diffusion.
We want to do the same thing for images.
So imagine a movie of this red dye
diffusing out.
We want to run that movie in reverse.
Okay? And we want to have something move
from equilibrium out into
non-equilibrium state.
Okay? Now equilibrium you should think
about in your probability language is
like stationary distributions.
So you want to move from a stationary
distribution to a non-stationary
distribution. Everyone with me in terms
of the analogies. This is why it's
called diffusion. So now for intuition
we want to simulate the stoastic case is
we literally want to simulate the
reverse process. We have a process that
was well defined.
Take something add noise. You want to
simulate the reverse process. If you
want to think about stocastic processes,
your go-to intuitive model is markoff
chains because you've all seen them. So
consider the simple three-state markoff
chain for illustrative purposes. I have
states A, B, and C. I have 90%
probability of staying in state and I
have a 5% probability of going to one of
the other states.
Everyone understand this markup chain?
What's a stationary distribution? 1/3
Okay.
Now to understand the counterpart of
diffusion models, think of it this way.
Suppose my desired distribution was not
the equilibrium distribution. My desired
distribution was 1/2 in A and 1/2 in C.
Okay. So suppose I started with examples
that were half the time in A and half
the time in C and never in B.
Okay. So the picture I want to think
about is
I start in this and I take a bunch of
steps. So now the diffusion process is
operation of the markup chain. Okay,
take many many many many steps and
eventually I'll end up in
1/3.
Now suppose I was watching this movie
run in reverse.
Okay. So what does the movie look like
going forward? It looks like hang out
here, go here, go here, go here, go
here, go here. Kind of bounce around,
right? Do this kind of thing. That's the
movie. So this movie after it's moved
around for a long time,
you can't tell going forward and going
backward anymore.
looks the same going forward, going
backward.
Everyone see that stationary
distribution kind of point of view for
this markup chain happens to be
reversible.
But when you run it backwards,
something different happens.
When you run it backwards,
what'll happen is it'll slowly move mass
into A and C.
Do you see that?
So when I run the diffusion markup chain
backwards, what'll happen is at over
here
it'll be randomly bouncing around
but sometime it'll start having a pull
towards A and C. So in particular if the
very next step
after the first step suppose after the
very next step you happen to be in B
what does the markoff chain look like
backwards from that last step that very
first step
well there's a half probability that you
came from A and a half probability you
came from C. There is no probability you
came from B. you're definitely moving
and you're moving here or here.
Do you see that? Whereas if you're in A,
you know, you're mostly in A. There's a
small probability you came from C. You
start say C, there's some probability
you came from A, but mostly in C. You're
never moving to B.
So the markup chain looks different in
the forward and reverse direction
because it started out of a stationary
distribution.
So the markoff chain is time invariant
going forward
but going backwards it's time varying.
It's still markoff but it's time varying
going backwards.
Okay. So with that intuition you can see
that if you want to run this process
backward you're going to be adding it's
going to be moving around. You're going
to be adding noise as you go as you move
backwards.
So
the key thing to think about is we're
interested in
what does one step of moving backward in
the markup chain look like.
So it's time varying for sure. Everyone
there you got that from this intuition.
Same thing's going to be here true here.
So what is the backward path look like?
Is it like a Gaussian?
If it was like a Gaussian, we can think
about it more easily. If it's not like a
Gaussian, it's harder to think about.
At some point, it's definitely not
Gaussian because you started with
something that was definitely not
Gaussian.
But
if we assume the forward path is
conditionally Gaussian like we're doing,
we're adding a little bit of noise.
It turns out, and we'll talk about why
next time, that as long as the density
for X0 is sufficiently smooth,
if this additive noise is small enough
that
the backward path also looks
conditionally Gaussian approximately.
So when you look at the probability
distribution for XT minus one condition
on XT, what you get is something that
has a mean that depends on where you
were
and a noise that's Gaussian. So that
mean depending on where you were is the
difference between A and C. A and C in
that example and B. B will tend to flow
towards A and B. A and C will have a
different flow. That's what this is
capturing in the Gaussian setting.
And
this is the thing we need to learn from
data.
Okay.
So
um I'll pause here and just comment on
this. So what we're going what you'll do
in discussion is you will see let me
just go zip a little bit ahead is you'll
see how this kind of process works for a
very discrete setting where everything
is just zeros and ones. Okay. And what
you're doing is you're sampling paths
going forward by picking a random place
going forward adding noise and seeing
what one step looks like. And you're
trying to learn what's the probability
distribution going in the reverse
direction
from data. And once you have that, you
will just run this process
backwards because you know it's mean,
you know it's variance. You just run
and see where you end up. Okay. So next
time we'll continue. You'll see in
discussion which will help you in a
discrete setting to uh see it slightly
differently and then we'll like put
everything together.
Okay. See you guys on Thursday. I have
office hours now.
>> Yeah.