come to lecture in your study groups and
sit with your study group together. Um
that way when something's confusing you
have someone next to you that you can
actually ask a question and I find that
this really makes a difference to the
students uh as you go forward. So
strongly strongly recommend that whoever
you're working with on homeworks get
them to come to lecture and sit next to
you in the lecture room.
Okay. So, I'm going to try a couple of
different ways of presenting the
material today in terms of how I use the
technology. If you have any feedback on
this, please let me know. Um, and I will
try to adapt to whatever is working with
the best for the most number of people.
So, what we're going to do today uh is
we're going to pick up where we left off
last. Before I start officially,
um let me just remind you all that
homework zero is due. When is homework
zero due?
>> Tomorrow at 10:59 p.m. Friday. And what
happens if you don't submit homework
zero?
>> You're dropped from the class, right?
So, please submit homework zero. Don't
accidentally get dropped from the class.
Don't wait till 10:58 to submit it and
then have grades grow crash on you and
then send us an email because the wait
list is so huge. And as you've probably
seen, we are not able to respond to all
of your emails. So, just, you know,
submit it at 10 p.m. instead of 10:59
p.m. That way, you have all this time to
deal with any kind of buffer, whatever,
late submission, this that. Um, make
sure it goes in. You've had more than a
week to complete it, and it should be
all material that's based on
prerequisites.
Okay. Any administrative questions
before we start?
Okay. So, the expansion is definitely
happening. You should all be getting
emails and like be officially being led
into the class. We are hoping to clear
the wait list. Okay, so all of you on
the wait list, fingers crossed. I cannot
promise anything, but we are absolutely
hoping to clear the weight list. Okay,
so uh
uh that's the good news. Okay, so today
is all about optimization. We started
talking about it last time and we're
going to continue talking about it. The
first thing that I want to talk about is
building on what we started off last
time and talking about the implicit
regularization of gradient descent. So
last time we talked about how gradient
descent converges for linear regression
and we notice that what matters the most
is really this largest value of xrpose x
or the largest singular value of the
matrix x itself. Right? Remember we saw
this that you know we you you have to
have the learning rate smaller than
this. If this is if you need to remember
this go and look at the 127 notes so you
can recall this. And the key takeaway
that I want you to remember from that is
that the geometric properties of your
loss function matter in terms of the
practical parameters and hyperparameters
that you will be using in tuning your
functions. So here is a condition on ADA
your learning rate or your step size
that is a function of the geometry of
your underlying loss function and here
we did this for le squares or so it's a
quadratic loss function but this is not
specific to le squares for example I had
a question right after lecture it's like
I heard this thing about smoothness and
like strong convexity and isn't
convergence supposed to depend on that
so what smoothness and strong convexity
are is they're essentially
generalizations
of what we're looking at in terms of
these quadratic functions to try and
sandwich other functions or approximate
them using other quadratic functions.
And so by looking at you know upper and
lower bounds of our desired function in
terms of quadratic functions we can get
what is known as um strong convexity
bounds. We call we call these mu strong
convexity usually or we can get
smoothness bounds. We call these L is
usually a parameter associated with that
L smoothness. And we can generalize this
intuition that we have for uh gradient
descent on linear regression or
quadratic loss problems to other
problems where what will matter is now
the ratio of the smoothness to the uh
strong convexity parameter. Here what we
found that matters in terms of the
convergence rate was the ratio of the
largest to the smallest singular value.
Right? Everyone remember that discussion
from last time? Okay, great. So now
we're going to kind of build on this
intuition about um singular values and
start talking about ridge and ridge
regularization and think about how this
leads to the implicit regular
regularization of um gradient descent.
So remember that war star
is given by
uh for ridge
xrpose x plus lambda i inverse
xrpose y and we also said that this is
equal to xrpose
xxrpose plus lambda i inverse
time y. Okay, these are the two ridge
solutions. One is the straight form, the
other is the kernel form.
And now we wanted to try and say well
can we look at ridge in the SVD
coordinates. Right? Clearly we see even
just from the straight convergence proof
of gradient descent that the singular
values and the particular directions the
um singular vectors matter in terms of
how gradient descent is going to behave.
So let's look at ridge in those d in
those coordinates as well. So here let's
say this SVD of X is U sigma VRpose
then I can write my W star
as just filling this out. So coming from
here
if I just write this. So vranspose
um sigma transpose
u *
actually there should not be a transpose
here. This should be v sigma uranspose
sigma transpose urpose u sigma vranspose
plus lambda i
inverse XRPOSE again will give me a
U
b sigma transpose uranspose
times y I'm just plugging in my svd here
okay so now I can do some manipulations
of this and in particular what I will
see here is that this u transpose is
just going to cancel right
and then I have this identity here I can
write this identity as VVRpose because
these are orthonormal matrices. Everyone
remember that? And so I can just pull
these out and so I can rewrite this
effectively
equal to
V sigma transpose sigma
plus lambda I whole inverse vranspose V
sigma transpose uranspose Y
again. And now these vranspose
again because V is an orthonormal matrix
VRpose is just its inverse. So that also
cancels. And so I'm left with
V V.
Okay.
So, what does this look like when I try
to write out this matrix? What is this
matrix in the middle?
Well, this is an almost diagonal thing.
This is an almost diagonal thing. So,
when I multiply them together, what am I
going to have? I'm going to have
something with the squares of the
singular values on the diagonal, as many
singular values as I have. And what's
the rest going to be? It's going to be
all zeros, right?
And then I have this lambda time I which
is also diagonal. So the sum of these
things to is going to be diagonal. And
so I'll either have a singular value
squared plus lambda or I'll just have
that lambda. Does everyone see that when
I add those two matrices together? So
what I'm going to have is something of
this form.
And then I'm going to have some lambdas
here based on how these dimensions
actually work out.
And this is all inverse.
So what this means is when I try to
write out my w star,
what do I get? I can write it
as vi coming from this v here. This V
here gives me the VI.
Sigma I divided by sigma I^ 2 + lambda
times
ui transpose time
y and how many terms are going to be in
this sum?
Basically I'm going down the diagonal,
right? So whatever my dimension is.
So what do I see here in this particular
setup?
If I look at this now
this particular quantity is what is
governing the scaling. So I'm thinking
of this this uranspose y this is a
scalar. Does everyone see that
this is a scaler? So now I'm basically
looking at my W star as in the SVD basis
and these are the coefficients
for every single singular vector of my
matrix. Everyone see that? Because these
are just scalers.
So what is going to happen to
sigma i over sigma i^ 2 plus lambda if
um lambda is much much bigger than sigma
like sigma is like one and lambda is a
million for example
what is this quantity going to become
if lambda is really large basically
lambda is going to dominate and this
thing is going to become smaller and
smaller and smaller, right? It's going
to kind of tend to zero
as lambda goes to infinity, right? For a
fixed sigma i.
So what this means is that if I have
some small singular values compared to
my ridge regularization parameter
lambda, what's going to happen is that
are those vectors going to really show
up in my optimal solution? No. There
those components are just decaying away,
right?
Whereas on the other hand, what happens
to this sigma i^ 2 plus lambda when I
have u sigma i is much bigger than
lambda. Well, then this just behaves
like 1 / sigma i,
right? Because I have a sigma i over
sigma i squar approximately this is like
1 over sigma i. So I'm going to get that
component there. And what this means is
that the directions that have low
singular values
don't show up in your optimal solution
with ridge. Right? And by varying
lambda, you can vary how easy it is for
those low singular values to show up.
Now what are those directions? When you
think intuitively about what does it
mean for a particular direction to have
a
low singular value. So take a minute and
like find a person next to you and talk
to them about this. What does it mean
when a direction is a low singular value
or a high singular? I'm going to give
you one minute to actually talk.
[Music]
Yeah.
[Applause]
30 minutes.
And that was
Okay, that's a minute.
That's one minute. So, if you want these
breaks to talk, then you have to stop
when I say stop. Otherwise, we'll never
finish. Okay. So, what is the impact of
having a
um what what does it mean to have a
small singular value? What does that
mean for those directions in terms of
the data?
Yeah,
>> low variance.
>> Low variance, right? So the large
singular values capture directions that
have a lot of variance in the data. The
small singular values are the ones that
don't have that that much variance in
the data. So what that means is that
when you look at your data points,
right, what is X made of? X is made of
basically the rows of X are your data
points. Those directions that are not
represented in the data are the
directions that have small singular
values.
So if you don't have a lot of
information about particular directions,
maybe you shouldn't actually be paying
too much attention to those when you're
trying to fit your function. Remember we
started talking about ridge because
ridge or regularization in general is a
common solution to the problem of
overfitting. Where does overfitting
happen? When you're too married to your
particular training data points because
you're like, "Oh my gosh, I love my
training data. I'm so happy to have it.
let me try to fit it absolutely
perfectly. But you fit in these
directions that miss maybe aren't, you
know, really representative. You're just
fitting some noise and it reduces your
generalization. It reduces your
performance on the test data.
So by ignoring the directions or putting
less weight on the directions that have
low variability, you can actually
improve your performance, right? And
that's why regularization in general is
um can be a very good thing. So
regularization is not just about
incorporating some kind of side
information about your data. For
example, you know that your true vector
might be small or if you use ton of
maybe you know that your true vector is
close to some other vector or you know
something about specific components. But
what it's trying to say is that look you
know maybe you don't want to move in
those directions where there are um low
singular values. Okay
make sense to everyone.
So what I want to remind you now if I
look at for example my gradient descent
update this is what it looks like for
um again the just the le squares problem
here I'm not thinking about rich I'm not
regularizing it but what you'll notice
here is that there's this xrpose that
multiplies this vector here right and so
this vector
this vector is basically your residual
right or your error that you're
when you're currently predicting your
current best guess is wt and so x wt
minus y is how bad are you at predicting
y on your training data
and what is xrpose xrpose is your data
so basically what this says is that my
gradient descent will always take a step
only in the span of the data I can never
leave the span of the data does is that
clear using gradient descent so always
remains
in the span assuming you initialize at
zero
of the data.
The other thing that I'll briefly
mention because it might come up later.
If I look at the gradient descent update
for a ridge,
it has a similar property
and I have wt + 1 is equal to
um
1 - 2 a lambda
- 2 a times
So basically when I look at this um
gradient descent update for ridge, what
I have here is this extra term
on the WT. If I compare it to the
I don't see a siren blaring telling us
to get out of the room. So I think we
can continue.
So if I didn't if my lambda was zero,
I'm just at back at gradient descent,
right?
What is this doing? What is this term
doing? This is coming from the
regularization.
And what it's saying is look every time
maybe just like down weight a little bit
on WT right it's pulling down the weight
it used to in gradient descent this
would be one this is saying do something
slightly less than one okay
and so this term is called sometimes
uh weight decay
and what you'll see is that uh we
haven't what you'll see is that gradient
descent actually has this implicit
regularization property that I'm going
to talk about in just a minute and so
often when you're implementing
uh gradient descent in deep learning we
will not actually have an explicit
regularization
we will not include a ridge parameter or
a lasso parameter or anything like that
and even then there will be a
regularizing effect and there are other
tricks that we can use by which we can
avoid overfitting even though we might
not have an explicit regularization. So
I'm going to talk about that next.
However, sometimes there are other
benefits to not having your weights get
too large. And so sometimes even though
you won't have a ridge term in your
loss, what you will do is you will
include some kind of weight decay
schedule that will you know just kind of
keep pulling your weights down by a
little bit to avoid them from getting
too big. So this is another thing that
this is a piece of terminology that I
wanted to put out there that sometimes
regularization weight decay and now what
I'm going to talk about as implicit
regularization and early stopping of
gradient descent are all talked about
sometimes in the same breath and
sometimes interchangeably and they all
mean the spiritually same idea
implemented in slightly different ways.
So what I want you to understand is that
whatever when someone's talking about
this that's the kind of idea that
they're talking about. Okay, everyone
with me? Questions? Okay, good.
So now let's go back to gradient
descent. And now what I want to get to
is this implicit regularization.
And what do I mean by that?
So, I'm going to take again um my
gradient descent update equation and I'm
going to write it out. But now I'm going
to write it out in my SVD basis.
So to write it out in my SVD basis, I'm
just going to do a change of basis.
Multiply by VRpose.
So I'm multiplying the whole equation by
VRpose. This xrpose I'm going to replace
with the svd. So I get a v sigma
transpose
u uranspose
and then I have this x wt
minus y.
And so when this I change bases into
this new coordinate. Let me call this
new vector w tilda. Let's say
so now I'm this new basis minus 2 ADA.
These vranspose V's cancel.
Um
so then I have this sigma transpose and
then I can pull this urpose into here I
have a U sigma
V transpose WT
minus URPOSE Y.
This is equal to then
W tilda T transpose minus 2 ADA. These
uranspose U's cancel. This thing I'm
going to pull into becoming another W
tilda because now this is just
expressing my old WT in the SVD basis.
Everyone see that?
So then I have a sigma transpose
sigma w
tilda t
minus uranspose y.
So now what has happened by me writing
this in the svd basis? Let me look at
this. Right? This is a vector. But what
has happened to this thing? What kind of
matrix is this?
This is again a diagonal matrix, right?
This is a diagonal matrix. So now when I
look at the different components of WT,
they're no longer coupled, right? By
transforming into the SVD basis, I've
basically diagonalized my problem. And
now I can look at this component by
component. So I can basically look at
the E component.
And that is 2 ADA times I basically have
this sigma i^ 2 w tilda t
minus
sigma i and then whatever is the
component I'm just going to call this y
i twiddle
right I don't really care about this is
just some scalar here
so what do I notice when I look at this
this singular value
is showing up right
and so when I'm taking so this is the
step that I'm taking in the direction of
the i singular vector does everyone see
that now we've projected into that basis
so this is the step that I'm taking
according to that direction everyone
with me there
okay
folks I need you to like give me some
feedback, thumbs up, thumbs down, like
because otherwise I will keep barreling
at you and you will understand nothing.
But if you tell me that you don't
understand, then there's a hope that I
might tell you again. I still might not,
but at least there's a chance, right?
So, you're good. Please nod. Give me
thumbs up, thumbs down.
>> Is there a typo on the third?
>> Oh, yeah.
Yeah, this is all the I component and
this is a uh these are not vectors
anymore actually. This is
>> okay.
So when you look at singular values yes
question
>> yeah I was just curious on the second
line um where you crossed out the
transpose Yes.
>> Where did the go and then the line after
that?
>> I expressed this in the V basis.
>> Oh, it's a different basis. Okay. Thank
you.
>> Because I put a twiddle here.
>> So now we're looking at this in this
basis
and what I see is that the size of the
singular value matters for how big a
step I can take. I pulled this singular
value inside. But maybe actually it's
even clearer to write it as wti
twiddle minus 2 a sigma i times sigma wt
comma i minus
yi
right
so you can think of this as your
residual you know are you already
matching in this direction or not but if
you're not matching how big the step you
take depends yes on your learning rate
but it also depends on the singular
value. So for the big singular values,
you're going to take big steps and for
the small singular values, you're going
to take small steps, right? So you're
going to be moving faster in some
directions than you are in others. And
singular values tend to vary when you
think when you just look at them for a
matrix, they tend to vary across orders
of magnitude. So you know you will have
singular values that are like 10 or 100
10 five and then you'll have some
singular values that are like 10 the
minus2 10 the minus 5 10 the minus there
they're they can be very small so
there's a huge variation in these and so
when you're plotting singular values
it's a good rule of thumb when you're
looking at these things sometimes it can
be useful to plot on log scale you might
not see the kind of variation that you
need to see when you plot on linear
scale so just a trick to keep in mind if
you're ever trying to debug your code in
this uh in this kind of stuff.
And so what's going to happen? Let's say
I have all of these directions to
different directions to move in. Right?
So let's say I have just a two
dimensional setup and I have a really
big singular value uh this way and a
really small singular value that way.
Right? I'm going to take big steps along
this direction and I'm going to converge
pretty quickly along those big singular
values. But I still have not moved as
much in the other direction where the
singular value is small. Okay. So what
does this mean? If I let's say don't run
gradient descent to convergence.
If I somehow do what is called early
stopping of gradient descent.
Gradient descent naturally has this
property that it likes moving along
large singular values more than it likes
moving along small singular values. So
it'll do the large singular values first
and only then later do the small
singular values. So if I stop early
without running to convergence, what's
going to happen is that I'm not going to
move in those directions that have small
singular values that maybe I didn't want
to move in anyways because that's what
my ridge was doing,
right? That's exactly
what this term is doing in ridge. I
haven't actually put any ridge par
regularization on this. There's no ridge
penalty. But if I say I stop early,
I will get the same benefit. So you you
might hear this term early stopping.
Have have people ever heard of this term
early stopping in machine learning?
And so early stopping doesn't literally
mean I mean it can it can mean just you
know stop doing gradients descent at a
random early point before it has
converged. But often what this means is
that you actually run gradient descent
for a long time and then you keep you
have training checkpoints for your model
and then you go back and you pick that
training checkpoint that actually
performs best before you start running
into the overfitting regime. So you
might have some training loss curve is
coming down down down down and then
maybe it starts going up because you're
starting to overfit. So then you find
that checkpoint where you've actually
done the best. And now what this is
saying is this is giving you a reason
for why that's a totally valid thing to
do. It's not some arbitrary let's well
there's a lot of magic and alchemy in
deep learning. But there's an element of
principled alchemy, right? This is
explaining to you why this is just like
doing regularization. Does that make
sense? Questions?
>> Yes. So did you say it converges in the
directions with high singular values
first but then it still converges the
low value
>> it will keep going. So for example right
if I if I now move let's say I have
these two directions I can move it right
I'm moving a two dimensional so I can
either move this way or this way and I'm
taking these giant steps this way but
now I've reached my optimum.
>> If I've reached my optimum what does
that mean for this term?
>> It's zero
>> right? So I'm not going to move like
let's say I have a possibility let's say
I'm working with a problem where I can
actually reach zero loss
then now that I have reached my optimum
my large singular values are no longer
going to move and then now there's
gradient pressure to make steps in the
directions of the small singular values
>> right now to decrease my loss I can't I
can't decrease my loss by moving in this
direction anymore I've already zeroed
out my residual so now I have to start
moving this way and I'll get there but
my singular so small it'll go like this.
>> Okay. But it will still move along.
>> But I will still eventually move there.
>> But maybe this is just maybe I'm just
fitting noise in doing this and I don't
really want to be doing it.
>> Does that make sense?
>> Yeah, absolutely.
>> Yeah.
>> AIS and you move across that ais
So I'm expressing gradient descent here
in the SVD basis. So that's it's a
gradient descent isn't saying well I
will move in direction V1 and then V2
and then V3 and then V4. This is what is
happening kind of in the back it's not
even in the back end it's just happening
but it's it's a perspective it's a lens
through which you're viewing the
standard gradient descent update which
is not done component wise it's done in
whatever braces you're in.
You're decomposing into the SVD basis.
>> Okay. So in the SVD basis your data set
moves only one direction at a time.
>> No no it will move in all directions but
it will do the best thing. So it will
move the step size it will take in each
direction is proportional to the
singular value in that direction. So it
will move in this way and this way but
the step horizontally will be this big
and the step vertically will be this
big.
>> Okay. So you're just going to get to
your optimum in this direction much
slower. So for example, your optimum
might be, you know, you might want need
to move in this direction a little bit,
but you've already converge along this
axis. Yes. Question at the back.
>> Yeah. So kind of along that line, if you
have a smaller singular value which
corresponds to you like in theory need
to go a shorter direction like shorter
distance in that orthogonal direction to
reach your optimum for that smaller
variance sigma. So, so you you don't so
so you're you're there the the the
residual which is the distance to your
optimum is not a function of your
singular value. That's whatever it is.
Just because your singular value is
small doesn't mean your initial is
somehow magically close to your that's a
function of where you've initialized.
Right? The question was like the small
singular values means you're closer to
your optimum in that direction or not.
But no.
Does that make sense?
>> Yeah. Okay, good. Yes, question.
>> Yeah, I just want to make sure that I
get you right. So the right intuition is
that for large singular value
directions, you move a proportionally
larger reser distance as you run
gradient descent early on and then as uh
those will converge first and so when
you keep running then you start
optimizing the smaller.
>> Exactly. Exactly. Because you you know
you have you have some amount of
gradient pressure and if you can just
like you have to choose a direction,
right? There's a trade-off, right? You
know I can I can I I only have a certain
step size. I can take and I can choose
to distribute that component. I can
choose to distribute my vector that I'm
taking a step in. You know, I can have a
component in each orthogonal direction.
The directions of the SVD are
orthogonal. My step size is still fixed.
So, I can't have large components in
every direction, but proportionally the
large singular values will pull a larger
component. And so, there won't be that
much step size left to take in the
smaller direction. Okay? you have to
spread it across whatever dimensions you
have.
>> These are good questions. Okay, last
question.
>> Is the second line second to last? Is
that supposed to be a vector? Is that
>> Yeah, that's probably not a vector.
Okay, awesome. Okay, good. So with this
um basically I hope you've learned that
geometry matters and that it's a good
thing to look at even simple cases
because it turns out that this intuition
generalizes to um you know other larger
other larger problems that you know we
looked at this in the case of um just le
squares with a quadratic loss but early
stopping is something that is commonly
used in training lots of networks.
even though you might not be working
exactly on the le squares problem for
linear regression. So these kinds of
intuitions are helpful and that's kind
of what we're going to be building today
and uh and the next class. Okay, good.
So I haven't written down much about
early stopping but is everyone clear on
that? You can Google early stopping if
you can't find this and you'll find um
you'll find information on it as well.
Okay, last question. Can you explain
what the implicit
>> Okay. What is the implicit
regularization here?
So maybe I'll write this out.
Okay. So what is the implicit
regularization?
So in a ridge
if lambda is large
uh we don't move
in directions
of small
singular values. Actually I shouldn't
say we don't move. So I should say we
don't
have
large
components
of
um
directions
with large singular with small singular
values in the ridge
solution. Okay, is that clear to
everyone? So and ridge is regularizing
right. So it's basically saying one
there's many lenses of looking at
regularization. One's lens by which we
can look at regularization is to say
don't move in directions of small
singular values.
Gradient descent
with early stopping
also does not move
in
directions
of
small singular values.
Does that make sense?
So that's why this is regularizing.
Can we wait for office hours?
>> Are you still moving?
>> What?
>> You're still moving.
>> You're still moving. I mean, ridge is
not saying don't move either. It's just
saying you move quite a bit less. This
is not zero.
>> That's like zero.
>> We don't It moves a little bit. Okay.
Sure.
Does not move.
>> A better terminology would be the
weights at the end are proportionally
less.
>> Yeah. But I mean this is so these are
all like these are all intuitions for
getting you there, right? Yes. You're
moving but you're moving you know does
not move or moves very little
in directions of small singular values.
So yes it's not that you're not moving
at all. It's totally possible to move
small amounts but your
your step size is proportional basically
to the to the to the to the value to the
singular value.
Okay. Good.
Okay, so with that I want to now get to
the next part of optimization which I'm
sure you've all seen before is
stochastic gradient descent, right? So
gradient descent is great. Gradient
descent works wonderfully for convex
functions,
but guess what? Like real life is hard
and real life includes non-convex
functions. If everything we wanted to
optimize was convex, life would really
would be really nice. And in particular,
fitting neural networks and deep neural
networks requires
being able to optimize over long
non-convex landscapes. So what do we do?
Basically, SGD is um is the solution
that leads us to be able to um have
better generalization in these
non-convex landscapes. The other thing
about gradient descent is that when you
have lots and lots and lots of data,
computing the gradient over many many
many many many data points is
computationally expensive. What SGD does
is it gives you a way of being a little
bit lazy and saying I'm going to only
compute the gradient in in certain
spaces and over a certain subset of my
data and move in that direction. Okay,
so everyone here has seen some version
of state SGD before like your machine
learning class has covered this, right?
So you know the basic idea. Okay, good.
So what is SGD doing? SGD is thinking
about basically this setup where you
have a loss function here. And now I'm
calling my loss function f and theta is
my parameter
and I have this loss function that
decomposes as a sum of other loss
functions
and many many common loss functions that
we like to think about actually have
this property. So for example if I just
think about my standard squared loss
function which is our canonical you know
we don't know what anything is doing.
Let us try a loss function and
understand how it behaves. We always try
the same loss function. Well, when I
look at this le squares loss function, I
can think about it as
you know the argument over this is the
same as a normalized version of that. I
can just uh average the over the number
of data points. But this is basically
the same as looking at the loss per data
point. Right?
So I can think of my squared loss as
actually the loss on the first data
point plus the loss on the second data
point plus the loss on the third data
point. So on and so forth. So I
naturally have a way of taking my loss
function and decomposing it into this
sum of component loss functions.
Now if I wanted to take a gradient step
and do proper gradient descent, I had to
take the gradient for the loss with
respect to every single data point. If n
is large, that's a lot of data points.
What if instead I took the lazy approach
and I said let's just take a few of you
and you take what is called a batch or a
mini batch
and say instead of taking the gradient
over all of the data points I will take
the gradient over just some subset of
data points I'll pick B of them
uniformly at random iid
and this is my batch and that's the
gradient step I take everything else is
exactly the same.
So sometimes you will hear people
talking about full batch gradient
descent or full batch SG. Full batch SGD
is just gradient descent because you're
taking all of your data
um into uh and accounting for that in
your gradient. Okay.
So what this is doing is this is saying
ideally I have a certain gradient and I
would like to move in that direction.
Instead I'm going to move in this
direction that is you know um
in expectation the same but slightly
different. So I can think of it as a
noisy version of my gradient um instead
of moving exactly in the direction of
the gradient. And when I think about
what I'm doing in expectation, well, in
expectation, the gradient of each of
these is just the gradient of my true
function, right? Because I'm basically
to taking I'm looking at a uniform iid,
which gives me a one. If I have n
different data points, I have a one
overn probability of picking each of
these and I average over all of them.
That just returns to me my original
gradient. So on average I'm doing
exactly what gradient descent would do
but I'm doing it a little bit more uh
more shakily.
Questions on this? Everyone clear on
what SGD is? You should have seen this
before.
So what are some advantages of this?
Basically, we see that you know the one
nice thing about it is that yes, it is
noisy, but it still always improves the
fit on a subset of the data, not all of
the data. The second advantage of it is
that it is actually computationally
less expensive because you have to
compute fewer gradients. And the third
nice property of it is that because
you're not always going in the direction
of the gradient, sometimes you can
escape local minima and saddle points,
right? So let's say I have like
something like this where I have some
local minima and then a bigger ravine.
Gradient discount can get stuck in that
local minima. But stocastic gradient
descent because it's noisy sometimes it
will do things that are not exactly in
the direction of the optimal gradient
and that will allow it to get out of a
local minima and escape to somewhere
else. Okay, so that's great but
typically when you take some algorithm
and you add a bunch of noise to it, it
doesn't perform better, it performs
worse. Right? We have these nice
convergence guarantees for gradient
descent. What about SGD?
So in general, one of the things that if
you just read about SGD um you know
anywhere in a standard textbook, what
you will hear is that the optimization
perspective says that we need to have a
decreasing step size or a learning rate
schedule that allows for the ADA itself
to get smaller over time which will
allow SGD to converge. If you don't do
that because the gradient is noisy,
you'll get close to the solution. you'll
get close to the optimal, but then
you'll just do this like bouncing
around, dancing around it because your
gradient is never actually hitting zero.
You're just kind of on average zero, but
you're never actually exactly zero. So
you you'll see this kind of bouncing.
And if I have time, I'll try to show you
a demo of this. We'll see if I actually
get to it.
But in practice, what you see is that
sometimes SGD can actually converge with
constant step sizes. And I'm going to
try to show you a proof uh at the end of
class of why this actually happens um
for the least squares case and we'll or
not the least squares case but really
the um underdetermined um case of having
a linear system that you're trying to
fit
questions here. We're good.
So for example, this is a really nice
picture from the prince book. So what
you're seeing here is a lost landscape.
The valleys are the dark colors. The
peaks are kind of these lighter colors.
And what you see is you have three
different initialization points. One,
two, and three.
And when you do gradient descent, well,
you know, you initialize at one and it
kind of finds its way to the right
minimum. When you initialize at three,
it finds its way to the right minimum.
But two kind of takes a different path
and doesn't really get you to the
minimum the the global minimum it takes
you to a different local minimum and it
kind of gets stuck there. Does everyone
see that from this uh picture?
Stoastic gradient descent on the other
hand because it's not taking the optimal
gradient step in every time point
instead of kind of going off in this
direction which is where the optimal
gradient would have pointed you. It
happens to have a batch where the
gradient kind of points this direction
and it allows it to escape falling into
that local minimum over there and
actually converge to um a better
minimum.
>> Yes. Question.
>> Also fall into the wory.
>> It could also do bad things. Yes, it's
entirely possible that it will do bad
things. there's no guarantee um except
that we will actually show that in some
cases you can provably show that
gradient descent uh will converge to the
right optimum
but there's there's no guarantees on
this right especially in these
complicated non-convex spaces it it it
could go to the bad place but the thing
that kind of gives you hope is that you
know on average it's doing the the right
thing um and there's many many different
components to the gradient there's many
different batches you get lots and lots
of tries at this
questions.
Okay, so that's really what I want to
say about SGD. I want to get to one more
thing and then if we have time at the
end, I'm going to try and walk you
through a proof of convergence of uh
stoastic gradient descent which will try
to which will kind of bring out more
properties of SG as we go through it.
But
SGD or gradient descent, both of these
are still, you know, they're they're
great algorithms, but we always want to
be able to do better. And the one thing
that we can do to do better, there's
many things, and we're going to talk
about momentum today. We will talk about
Adam in the next class
as sequential or as as a series of
improvements that have come to get
gradient descent to be better and better
and better as an algorithm.
So let's think about gradient descent.
Again, we can just think about this
scalar case. Um remember if we look at
things in the SVD basis, now we just
talked about this a bunch. Essentially
everything just reduces to this scalar
case. Right? So understanding this
scalar case is equivalent to thinking
about a gradient descent in the vector
case but looking at it in the SVD basis
and we know that basically our step size
had better be smaller than uh sigma max
squ to be able to get to the minimum
uh or to be able to converge at all. So
what does this what does this mean? If I
look at this particular quantity. Okay.
So I have a range of different values
for ADA. ADA could be zero or the
largest thing ADA could be is one over
sigma squ.
So what happens when ADA is zero? What
is the value of this particular what is
this value or what is this like this is
the this is this is
uh determining the convergence rate of
this recurrence relation. Right? So
well when sigma is zero when ada is zero
sorry this is just one and when a is is
at its largest size well this is
negative one right so I can think about
these igen values basically I can think
about them as igen values in the complex
plane but you know we happen to have
uh no imaginary part for any of these
for this particular example
if you had imaginary parts you would get
oscillations But we're not really going
to worry about that right now.
And so when I have values, let's say
that are, you know, over here between 0
and one, I have these positive but
convergent igen values, I'm going to get
this kind of exponential decay, right,
of my error, and it's just going to go
uh exponentially to zero.
On the other hand, kind of as ADA
increases and I'm moving over closer and
closer to here, as I get closer and
closer to zero, what's going to happen
to the shape of this exponential? I'm
going to start decreasing faster and
faster, right? As I get closer to zero,
but then what happens as soon as I kind
of flip to the other side of zero,
I'm going to start seeing some
oscillations now because I'm multiplying
by a minus one every time, right? So I'm
still going to converge, but I'm going
to start doing things like bouncing
around to converge. I'm going to start
my error convergence is going to start
looking like this.
And eventually these oscillations will
kind of get bigger and bigger and bigger
and then I'll stop being able to
converge. That oscillation will force me
to diverge as I cross this minus one
boundary.
Does this does this make sense of what
we're we're doing? Okay.
So what's going to happen is that
basically this max singular value is
going to dictate
the learning rate I can choose right I
have a learning rate and it's always the
same for every direction doesn't I'm not
be able to pick we might we'll we'll
talk about this later but one of the key
challenges here is that we cannot our
algorithm does not allow us to pick a
different ADA for every different
direction.
So I can choose a good ADA that will
allow me to converge reasonably fast in
my largest singular value.
But that could still mean a lot slower
convergence for other directions that
have smaller singular values. Right?
These might these might not be tiny
singular values in which I don't want to
move and I don't care about. They might
be like medium singular values but I
still might converge slowly in them
because my ADA is picked based on my
maximum one.
Okay.
So can we basically do something to to
sm to improve our conversions? Can we
somehow smooth out some of these
oscillations? Right? We might like if we
want to keep making ADA bigger.
Oscillations are bad, but can we smooth
them out? Is there something we can do
to improve our convergence rate while
not oscillating too much? Okay, is
that's the problem that we want to try
and tackle. Okay. And that is the
problem that momentum is trying to
solve. Is everyone with me on what the
problem is?
That we have different singular values
and we want to kind of not just focus on
the largest one. We want to be somewhat
uh equitable.
So when you have oscillations,
what's the way of smoothing out
oscillations? Like what's your
intuition? What have you seen before?
decrease magnitude.
>> Decrease magnitude of what?
>> The mountain you're jumping by.
>> That's dictated by ADA, right? We can't
actually decrease the magnitude on one
singular value without affecting the
other singular values.
So yeah,
>> moving average.
>> Keep a moving average, right? That's a
way of
same idea. Yeah. Okay. So keep a moving
average, right? The idea is to say that
if you're bouncing around a lot, well,
don't bounce so much. And if you keep
averaging yourself, you're going up and
down and up and down. If you average,
you're going to kind of zero out
yourself. And then you might oscillate
less. Okay?
So then the question comes, well, how
much do I average? Right? Do I average
the past two steps, the past three
steps, the past five steps? How do I
think about this average?
The thing about deep learning and just
learning algorithms in general is that
you're not like you want to also be able
to implement these algorithms. And so
when I think about taking an average,
that is my standard intuition for
reducing oscillations. But let's say I
want to do a moving average window of
10. That means I have to remember the
gradient of the past 10 points and then
average it average them. Maybe I want to
do a larger window. You know, I don't
know. This is again one more
hyperparameter that has now been
introduced that I have to tune. What is
the right amount of averaging? Okay,
but what is another way that we know to
do averaging or for those of you who
have heard have you ever has anyone
heard the term low pass filter? Yeah. So
the EES in the room definitely have 16A
have definitely heard uh uh what a low
pass filter is. So a low pass filter is
something that's saying take my high
frequency oscillations and smooth them
out, right? don't have high frequencies
in my signal. Keep only the low low pass
the low frequencies. Right? Big
oscillations are high frequencies.
A low pass filter is basically an
average averaging mechanism. And we have
these in nature everywhere, right? And
these are often coming when we have a a
kind of state in our system.
So one example of this just comes from
circuits straight up circuits. So for
example if I have this is a standard low
RC lowass filter what do I have is I
have just this uh resistance and as VIN
changes my V out is going to change but
what this capacitor is going to do is is
going to dampen my change right so for
example if this um if my VN is pretty
constant right if my VN is pretty
constant what's going to happen is my
capacitor is just going to saturate no
current is going to flow this Okay. And
then VN is just going to be equal to V
out. That's what for a constant input.
But now if my VN is like going up and
down and up and down, what's going to
happen is I'm going to charge discharge
charge discharge charge discharge my
capacitor and it's going to eat up some
of that charge. What's going to come out
at V out is going to be a smooth
version, a much smooth version. It's
going to be an automatic averaging of
what VN is. And the way this is being
done is basically through maintaining
state, right? The charge on the
capacitor is dictating whether the
capacitor is acting like a short or like
an open circuit. And therefore what
we're seeing is
that averaged version. The nice thing
about this is this is essentially doing
averaging. But do I need to now what is
the memory required to implement this?
Do I need to remember the 10 past
values? No. The state is automatically
changing. It's the state space model
now. And so automatically my memory is
being captured by this capacitor. I
don't want to take questions about the
circuits here because I know that people
probably have forgotten their circuits.
Go remind yourself of this. But
basically this is a straight
differential equation that this is this
is modeling, right? For a step input of
V, you have this exponential decay that
you can um you can capture. What I want
you to get is the physics intuition of
this. And you know we talked about in
the first lecture of how essentially
there's we're looking at analog
circuits. That's what neural networks
are in some sense. And these intuitions
help us actually understand a lot of
what's going on.
So if we take this and we actually
discretise
what this is doing,
we can think of this in the following
way.
Where is my pointer?
I can think of maintaining a state. So I
take think of this zk as my state
variable.
And I update my zk plus one at every
iteration as some beta time zk. So
basically where I was previously or what
my previous gradient was plus 1 minus
beta times the new gradient that I have
got in
okay
so what is happening when I when I do
this so let's say z is zero and just
take one minute and try to write out use
this recurrence relation start with z
not is zero and try to write out what
how zen not is evolving so that you will
see what is going on so take a minute
write this out, discuss with your
neighbor. You know, the two of you can
uh do it on one piece of paper to
encourage interaction. So,
>> I'll give you one minute. I have a
timer.
Just sit there.
[Music]
Okay.
>> So,
what's happening here as I run this?
What what does what does Z1 look like?
Right? Everyone got what I got?
Basically, I just have, you know, this
is just zero. So, I just have this one
term here.
Okay. But then what happens the next
time step? This thing goes and populates
here
and I get a new term here. Now it gets
multiplied by this beta. So I have a
beta* 1 minus beta. Then this whole
thing gets now multiplied again by
another um uh beta term. And so now if I
look at my state, my Z's, how are they
evolving? where there's some weight
times my oldest gradient and then the
slightly larger weight times my middle
gradient and then the largest weight is
on my most recent gradient. Right? So I
have this exponentially decaying average
that is saying take my history of
gradients put less weight on the ones
that were really way back when when we
knew nothing. put more weight on the
current data
um
but use this to keep kind of moving in
the direction that you were moving in.
So if you get some like you know crazy
outlier point what this is saying is
that if you were moving in this
direction and this was kind of working
even if you have a huge thing you're
still you're not going to completely
change course and move just in the
direction of the new gradient but the
momentum that you were moving in
previously is going to keep you moving a
little bit in that direction.
Does that does that make sense? That's
why this is called momentum. There's
like a physics analogy that uh people
are thinking about maybe like a a a ball
rolling.
The momentum is just like keep doing
what you were doing. Don't always just
follow the new thing. Okay. It's a good
uh strategy for life too to be grounded.
Whatever new trendy thing comes in, you
don't have to jump on the boat every
time. Especially for those of you who
are interested in deep learning. It's
going to be hard. The times are crazy.
So finding ways to be grounded is just a
good useful life strategy. Little bit of
uh philosophy in there. Okay.
So does everyone see what this kind of
momentum term is is trying to do and how
it's actually helping us.
So if I look now at
so this is now this is now so this we
just talked about momentum in the
context of gradient descent. But I can
also do momentum with stochastic
gradient descent. Right? And typically
that's what we will be we we do do. And
now in stoastic gradient descent, my
gradients are already noisy. So when I
do momentum, I'm just basically getting
more averaging, right? And so in a in a
sense it's it's going to be helpful.
It's going to be better. There is a
downside with stoastic gradient descent
is that I'm averaging, but I'm averaging
noisy things. So the noise from my early
iterates it might have been really high
and it might have been really big
because my gradient was large then is
going to creep in later. So there is
like this downside in the sense uh of
momentum as well when you're doing it in
SGD and there's a trade-off always if
like how big do you make your sliding
window and effectively the choice of the
beta parameter is what is dictating how
big you make your sliding window.
Uh does that make sense? uh but momentum
basically helps with SGD for the very
same reason that it helps with uh
gradient descent.
And now again this is from uh the prince
book. I think this is a really great
figure. So what you have here is you
have these two different initializations
and this is stoastic gradient descent uh
converging to the optimum but it takes
this like really noisy shaky bumpy path.
But what you see when you have SGD with
momentum is that these paths are kind of
much smoother because they're they're
not jumping around as much because
they're low pass filtered, right? The
the spikes have all kind of uh gone down
quite a bit. Okay,
I've talked a lot. I'll pause for
questions.
>> Yes. So this general like smoothing
effect is the end result of it.
Basically you have less iterations to
get to a minimum.
>> Yes. Okay. So what's the bang for the
buck?
>> Um we don't care like you know I could
have an ugly trajectory you're saying
but you know I'm not here for the
visualizations. I'm here for getting to
the minimum. So what's who cares? Who
cares if my trajectory is is is is
smoother or not? So what you can prove
you can provably show that actually um
this will actually this will this will
improve convergence and if you remember
gradient descent kind of has a
convergence rate that depends on the
condition number. What you will find
with momentum is that your convergence
rate will actually depend on the square
root of the condition number. So you
will actually drastically improve your
um
your convergence rate. So you will get
to the
um get to the minimum faster. So you can
you can actually theoretically prove
guarantees like this when you uh when
you choose the right choice of beta. So
again the right choice of the learning
rate and the beta parameter matters. So
the advantage is basically that you can
converge faster. The downside in the
sense is that now you have this beta
parameter that's one more hyperparameter
that you had to figure out and you had
to figure out the right uh right value
for it.
So yes, long story short, you will
converge faster. In practice, uh
sometimes people find that just momentum
with SGD doesn't improve things that
much. And that's what leads to things
like atom and other algorithms that
we're going to talk about uh in the next
class. But theoretically, you have
guarantees that actually improve its
performance and the and it does improve
performance basically.
>> Yes. Would doing something like just
normal moving averages be okay rather
than doing like this exponential decay
of an average?
>> So would doing something like normal
moving averages be okay? It would be
okay. I mean no one's preventing you
from writing your own optimizer and
running it and it would work. But when
you do moving averages, you're being
inefficient and you're you're having
your uh you're using more compute
essentially, right? You're having you're
using more memory. You have a certain
server. It has a certain uh memory and
it has a certain uh power, right? And so
you want to be smart about how you
allocate it. And so you what is the
advantage of converging faster? Well,
that's less money you have to pay
essentially, right? That's why you want
to get to the optimum faster.
So you could do the moving average but
now you've basically doubled the uh uh
you know if you want to have a moving
window average of size 10 then you have
10 numbers that you had to remember
whereas now when I look at the momentum
equations here where did they go right
if I look at the momentum equations here
really I've only doubled my memory
doubling is still a thing but I'm now
just remembering my
uh W's and my Z's and my my Z's are what
is updating. So I replace the gra I'm
replacing the gradient update here. I
forgot to say this but just to be
explicit.
My gradient descent is WK + 1 equal to W
K minus ADA. And here I would have the
gradient with momentum. Instead of the
gradient I have this moving average of
gradients that's represented by the ZK.
Make sense?
>> Yes. Also, if you just did a straight
moving average, would you just keep
going in direction? Like, assuming
there's enough of a run, you have so
much momentum just keep rolling over.
>> Oh, you're saying that if you did a
moving average with no with no decaying
weight. Yeah, you might end up in this
position where you have like a huge
large gradient at the beginning and you
know, you're subsequent gradients are
decreasing, but you're not even taking
that into uh into account because you
have a lot of weight on the on the
beginning. So you wouldn't I mean you
wouldn't be taking advantage of the
currentness of your update if you didn't
decay your weight. So just a moving
average. But what what would be
reasonable is to do a moving average of
a small window size. So you don't want
to ever be averaging all of your
gradients. But something that is
reasonable is just to say like I'm going
to average the past five gradients or
the past 10 gradients and forget the
ones that were 100 time steps ago.
Okay. Good.
Okay, so we have a little bit of time
and I'm going to try and now walk you
through this proof for uh actually how
stoastic gradient descent can uh
converge.
So what are we trying to do here? We are
trying to do what we've been doing so
far is take a simple case of SGD and try
and understand at the guts level of why
this thing can or cannot work so that
when we're trying to develop new
algorithms,
we can rely on our core understanding of
how this should behave in the simple
cases. Right? when you're looking at
some loss plot like this is the common
thing that everyone kind of runs up into
is that you've now implemented your code
it's lines and lines of code maybe some
LLM wrote half of it how do you even
know that what your system is doing like
you know you optimize something you got
some fit is it doing the right thing is
there a bug is there not a bug like
debugging these things is a beast
the point of trying to teach you all of
this math behind things is to give you
the intuition efficient so that you can
look at simple cases and say hey can I
intuitively understand what this is
doing in cases where I can reason about
so that I can see what whether whether
my implementation is correct or not okay
so there's a there's a there's a reason
for kind of understanding this at this
nitty-gritty level even though there's a
automatic library that you can you know
download and just implement you don't
need to understand this to implement SGD
But you do need to understand this to
develop the next algorithm to debug
these things in complicated cases.
That's what we're trying to teach you.
So let's consider a case of SGD where
you actually can get to zero loss. So
I'm thinking of an underdetermined
system and maybe I'm trying to get to
the uh minimum norm solution. So I have
X where um it's a wide matrix.
So D is bigger than N. This is this N
byD matrix that I have here.
And I'm assuming here that I have full
row rank. So
uh I can easily do an xxrpose inversion.
Okay. So let war star be the minimum
norm solution. In this case there's
infinitely many solutions because I have
an underdetermined system. Let's pick
the minimum norm one. We know exactly
what it is. It's given by this
expression.
And now let's say what let's try and
explore what happens when we do SGD just
with batch size one. Okay. So before
doing that what I want to just do is I
want to say let's look at the system but
in a slightly transformed space. So what
I'm going to do is I'm going to say
instead of looking at W which is my
optimal parameter I want to look at the
error of my optimal parameter. So I want
to look at the difference between
W, which is where I currently am, and W
star. Okay. So I'm just going to do a,
you know, transformation of coordinates
and instead of looking at W's, I'm going
to look at Q's where Q is the distance
of where I currently am to W star. Does
that make sense to everyone? So instead
of writing XW is equal to Y, I'm going
to write XQ equal to zero where Q is
just my error. No big deal.
So we know from the SVD now that all
that matters really for us is the
directions with the nonzero singular
values. Obviously I cannot move in
directions where I have no data points
because I can SGD and gradient descent
will only move me in the directions of
the data points. So you know let's go to
the SVD basis. we have evidence that
this is a a useful thing to do.
So I can look at my xq and I write it in
the svd basis. So I have here u sigma
vranspose * q
and now sigma is a wide matrix right
because my x is a wide matrix so it's of
the following form where sigma 1 is this
diagonal matrix here and then I have a
bunch of zeros afterwards right so this
is a square n byn part and this is an n
* d minus n part
okay
and I can just rewrite this therefore as
kind of These zeros aren't going to
matter. So I write this as this X
twiddle time Z where this is now the
part that I care about. X twiddle is
just my U sigma 1. Okay.
So I want to again just try to simplify
my system as much as possible. I'm not
going to walk you through this. But if I
now was to think about what would my um
what would be my uh initial condition
also in the SVD basis, I can do a
similar similar algebra to this and see
that my initial condition
would end up being kind of like this. I
initially started at zero
in my new coordinates. My initial
condition became minus war because I was
looking at my error.
And now don't worry about this, but what
I want you to see is that here the last
d minus n entries are basically zero.
What that tells us is that all I really
need to care about is the evolution of
the system according to this x twiddle
and this z, right? Because my initial
condition doesn't have anything in the
last d minus n coordinates and my state
evolution also doesn't have anything in
the last d minus n coordinates. So I can
basically reduce
my attention to looking at this square
system
x twiddle z equal to zero. Okay. And row
by row actually you can show I'm not
going to do it right now but that the
irow of this system is basically the
irow of your original system. Okay. So
these are exactly the same things but
you're just focusing attention on the
directions that matter and throwing away
all the rest.
So how are we going to try and show that
this thing actually converges? Well, if
I was to take a gradient descent step,
this would be my loss function. And I
would get a gradient descent step that
looks something like this.
What would be the corresponding
stochastic gradient descent step when I
have batch size one?
So now until now we haven't really
started, we haven't really dealt with
randomness.
in the discussions that we have talked
about so far. And now one of the things
I like about showing you this proof is
that we have to wrestle with the
inherent randomness of SGD. When I say
I'm doing SGD with batch size one and
I'm picking iid over my initial data
points, do I know which data point I'm
going to get?
No, I don't know this. Right? So that
means that when I'm doing SGD, what I'm
going to have here
is instead of this deterministic matrix
XRPOSE X, I'm going to have
this matrix that is given by the
specific data point I choose and I index
it by this it is the random index that
happens to be sampled at that time.
Okay, so this is the SGD update that I
get and we're just doing this for batch
size one.
Does that make sense questions? So I'm
not going to calculate out the SGD
gradient, you know, do this um u
actually it'll be on your homework so
you will have to do it but you can do it
on your own time. What I'm trying to
give you is a is the big ideas of the
proof. You can check the algebra on your
own time.
So now what we want to do is we want to
say given this SGD update can we argue
that my quadratic loss is actually going
to go to zero. I want to look at this
loss as it follows the path of evolution
dictated by this dynamical system and
say what is happening to this quadratic
function.
This is very similar to problems that
those of you who have taken classes in
control theory might have already seen,
right? I see a controls person in the
room.
What you're trying to say is that this
is my loss function. How do I show that
is actually going to zero? One standard
technique for doing this is called
leapono functions. You don't need to
know what a leapono function is. But
what is the key idea? If I want to show
that this thing goes to zero, well, if I
can tell you that at every step I take,
I'm always decreasing,
I'm always only going down, and I
furthermore tell you that I'm lower
bounded by zero, that I can never cross
zero,
then where am I going to go? I have to
get to zero. Right? So basically, so you
can you can prove this, you know, you
can analysis classes do this. There's
lots of ways of proving this. We're not
going to do that. Just believe me on
this principle. Intuitively, you can see
that, right? If you're rolling down a
hill, you're always moving downwards and
there's a floor, you can't get below
that, you're eventually going to hit
that floor. So that's the technique that
we're going to use to argue that this
happens. And this is called the idea of
a leap of function.
I have one minute. I will probably talk
a little bit about this in the next
lecture. But what I want to tell you now
is that the key insight that we are
going to get from doing this proof is
we're going to see how this loss
function evolves
as a function of time as you're taking
steps. And we'll see that there's a part
of it that looks kind of like gradient
descent. And that will show that the
loss function is decreasing. And there's
a part of it that we will show cannot
increase too much as long as your data
points are not too large. And that will
give us a intuition again or a condition
for why sometimes normalizing your data
and things like that are important in uh
the deep learning problems that we care
about. So I'm out of time to do this in
detail. I will teach you the rest of
this proof in the next class. Do not
forget to do homework zero. Please
submit it on time. I have office hours
now in 400. Corey,
>> I'm just curious what's the expected
time frame for homework zero. Like what
is the expected amount of time I should
spend on doing the homework?
>> It really depends on your preparation
and how much time you're willing to put
in. If you've taken guys all spend like
10 hours
>> about the same, you know, is it like
this every week
>> or is it more a whole one will be like a
>> It's a hard class.
>> Okay.
>> Okay. Thanks.
>> Hi.
>> Will we be able to know if like the
weather