Okay, let's start. So last time we just
barely started RNN's. We want to kind of
do a bunch of RNN stuff and then get
into this concept of self-s supervision
just naturally um comes from here. Uh as
I mentioned before what we're talking
about today uh very little of it is in
the prince's textbook on the
self-supvision material. There's like
one paragraph in 9.3.7 maybe two
paragraphs. So you can look at that but
uh we're going to talk about a little
bit more um than than what's there and
as I said before the uh older deep
learning book.org has good treatment of
classical uh RNN material but the way
that we're going to be presenting it is
different and especially what will
happen next week is very new and uh not
in any textbook.
So
uh recall RNN's before 2018 were one of
the big successes uh of uh deep learning
uh just like CNN's were for image and
their domain was language and speech and
those natural language processing is
extremely important by that time uh
these were deployed in production
systems you know at scale at places like
Google and
the key issue in language and speech
along with many other domains like
control and time series is that you have
data that's sequential
uh in nature and in some of those cases
it's also causal like one thing follows
the other in a very important way.
Language is a little bit iffy on that
but is still mostly causal. So we last
time we mentioned that from a classical
signal processing uh perspective we have
uh two kinds of filters that we use.
There's fir filters which are finite
impulse response filters and those have
a are completely directly map over to
cons and CNN's uh in neural nets and the
weight sharing that that reflects in
neural network is across space. Now
there's also I filters uh infinite
impulse response filters and it's really
important to remember the fact that for
you know the opposite of finite is
infinite and there is a vast range of
possible in principle existing infinite
impulse response filters. However, uh in
engineering practice for tractability,
we can only build things that are finite
in some very real sense. They have to be
finitely implementable.
And so the standard way in signal
processing is to have a finite
dimensional hidden state inside the
filter. So these are filters that have
memory and what you do is you use this
filter with memory in a because it has
memory it's fundamentally sequential and
causal whereas FIR filters you don't
have to think about sequentiality for
them but IR filters in engineering
practice in signal processing are
fundamentally causal um so those are
what translate into this box of RNNs and
the important thing here is weight
sharing exists across time not across
space.
So let's just uh think about what's
inside an IR filter. So we said there's
a hidden finite dimensional state in the
kinds that we use in uh SP and
these are linear filters. So there's a
hidden state and the hidden state
usually we set up as having a recursive
update. So a linear update. So we have
an input. So we want to take a filter
that takes entire long sequences UT and
causely maps them into an output
sequence Y that has desirable
properties. That's the goal of a filter,
right? Takes something in across time
and return something else across time.
And the way that we do it is first we
update the hidden state. So we have a
generic linear update on the hidden
state. There's some weight set of
weights that tell you how to take the
previous state you had and do an update
to them. And then you have another set
of weights B that tell you how to digest
an input and combine it into your state.
So what this is doing is the hidden
state is a constantly running summary
of the appropriate parts of the input.
Okay, that's a way of interpreting it.
Now you have to generate an output. So
in traditional uh linear filter uh
design you think of the fil the output
as having a combination of two things.
It's a linear projection of some kind of
h some matrix C that takes the hidden
state and does a linear map to it.
Remember the dimensions of U, H, and Y
can all be different. the matrices have
the right sizes to make things work.
So that's one part of it. So the but you
can also have a feed forward component
represented by D which is just uh
representation of the current input
transformed linearly in the current
output.
So for those of people who've taught
about uh you know linear uh filter
design in other classes you know this
kind of structure if people think about
in terms of like if you've seen it
you're not required for this class
things like rational transfer functions
and things like that you know the
this is where the poles are coming from
and this is where the stuff in the
numerator is largely coming from. Right?
This is like a in case you're trying to
if you've seen that stuff, it's a way of
kind of bringing it back into memory in
case you were thinking of it
fundamentally in transfer function land
as opposed to as a recurrence.
Okay, so this is the kinds of
linear IR filters that we know from
engineering practice for decades. Yeah,
>> I think could be zero because we have
>> Excellent question. The question is you
could set d to zero and that's totally
reasonable. you you can have d be zero
but d actually does add a little bit of
expressive power uh to this setup than
just b because think about the sizes
right if suppose u was uh suppose h is
very small in size and u is bigger and y
is also bigger
okay so if uh h is small u is big and y
is also big then this is squishing
information down into just h. So to only
have that represent in the output is a
limitation. Whereas here you can have
more of you come through but only in the
current. The past is going to be
dependent only on what the hidden state
can summarize but the current could be
more. Okay. Um so this is a generic
picture uh that one can have.
So what we're going to think about now
is how do we take this idea and map it
into neural netland. Okay. And the basic
thing that we want to do is to keep this
picture in mind.
So this picture is saying I want to
populate this box with something
in which what I want to do is to ask the
question whatever I was doing with a con
in a CNN I want to do with this. Does
everyone see the kind of analogy we're
doing? So wherever we have cons we want
to replace it with this kind of thing.
This is the kind of spirit of uh
you know what we're doing.
So if we do that
the kind of standard minimalist approach
is going to be all of the design ideas
and principles we learned in CNN's which
we then generalized one way into graph
neural nets. We're going to generalize
them a different way into RNMs. So we'll
try to keep everything we can just
replace space with time and we'll have
to because of the limitation of this
kind of processing we're going to have
to enforce causality. Everything will
have to be causal and time will move in
one direction for processing.
It's not that we necessarily want this
causality. We have no choice. We have to
live with it. And so there are
workarounds that people used to do in
old school um RNNs to get around that
when you wanted non-causal uh
processing. They kind of run time in one
direction and then they run time in the
opposite direction and they run time in
this direction again and they kind of
interle time in different directions.
Okay. So what I want to do is just draw
a symbol like a pictorial picture here
of what we're talking about. Okay. So
here is the uh picture.
So in this picture, what we're going to
do is we're going to think about how
things are flowing.
So I'm going to put time on the
horizontal axis.
Why? Because we write English this way.
Okay. Um this causes a change because
then what you saw in continents because
in continents for historical tradition
you think about information processing
and depth in the horizontal axis in
continents but here we're kind of
conflicted. We have to put depth
somewhere of the network and sequence in
some direction. And the convention is to
put sequence in the horizontal direction
and put depth in the vertical dimension.
Okay, just to take a picture of what's
going on.
So what we're going to have is we're
going to have each of these boxes is
going to be
you can think of this entire thing here.
This is just a box.
Okay, does everyone see this? And you
could have imagine the output coming out
of this side as being y
as an example.
Does everyone see how we can think about
this as a box?
So now what we're going to do is we're
going to like just stack these boxes as
components.
So we're going to make these are going
to be neural net layers that we're going
to stack up and those boxes are going to
play the role of a con
everyone. This is really important that
everyone understand what we're doing
here. Okay.
So I'll pause for questions. Yeah. Is
the box just a single weight plus bias?
>> So the box that entire box is represents
this thing. We'll add a bias in a bit.
The traditional way doesn't have a bias
in the traditional signal processing
when doesn't typically have biases, but
we're going to add a bias. So yeah,
there'll be this kind of stuff which is
a bunch of weights and a bias in the box
down here. We'll we'll soon get to that.
But yeah, the big picture is that this
is replacing a con.
And what we're going to do is that
little purple box, you can think of that
purple box as being
inside here.
Okay, that purple box above goes in
here. And so it's the one
that's
connecting in the horizontal direction.
But like we did in CN in CNN's, we can
put other things inside this box too,
right? So we could put an MLP inside the
box. We could put, you know, other kinds
of objects that only act on information
from
this particular
stack.
Does everyone see that? It's like the
same thing we did in continents. We can
do the same thing here.
We could have other stuff. I just mark
it as some other stuff
inside the box.
So first is let's just think about other
design things that we had. These are
things that carry over. If I want to add
residual connections in the vertical
direction, that's just the same as we
did before. We did them in GNN's also we
said we could do them in GNN's we did
them in CNN's we can do them here so
this just works we can have things like
vertical one by one MLPS one by one I'm
using con language here this is like con
language
okay
and we can also put normalizations in
the vertical direction
okay where the normalizations they're
like the same kind kind of thing we said
for GNN's we just do like an RMS norm of
the vector but you don't look at other
things in the graph here that's very
important we're not allowed to average
across time into the future because the
future doesn't exist yet
okay so that's not legal we can't look
into the future so we have to just be
looking right here for the
normalizations any questions on these
kinds of things these are basic
ingredients that we had in CNN's we can
just use
Now
the key question design question that
has been recognized recently as a key uh
design question um but not u wasn't as
clearly recognized in the past is where
do the nonlinearities go?
Okay, so
we know that to have our neural nets
have expressive power, we need to have
nonlinearities in them. Otherwise, you
can't express very much. So, we're going
to have to put nonlinearities.
And the question is where do they go?
So, in some of these blocks like MLPS
and so on, they have their own
nonlinearities. That's not a problem.
Those blocks are they're the same as
they were in convent. The question is,
is there something about the recurrent
aspect that you want to have a
nonlinearity in?
You can everyone see this is like a
question a design question that one has
and
the traditional RNN perspective is you
put a nonlinearity in the state update.
So if you start with linear dynamics, so
I'm going to change them up a little bit
to reflect closer to what's in PyTorch.
So I'm going to drop the D. you were
saying you know why am I dropping the D
because from the point of view of neural
net architecture if I wanted a linear
layer going in parallel as a skip I can
just add it myself so if I think about
the basic building block I don't this is
a redundant building block so I'm not
going to put it in in my core building
block um
I in principle I can just do this I can
add biases because we like biases we
found them useful in other contexts so
we'll add them here too learnable biases
so we start with linear dynamics ics
like this with some biases
and then you add a nonlinearity.
So this is the classic um traditional
RNN perspective. So this nonlinearity
where is this nonlinearity? It's this
thing sigma.
So what this says is instead of just
taking the state and
having it a linear operation happen to
it after do the linear operation apply
nonlinearity component wise.
So this is playing the same rule um role
that in a classic connet you have a cond
a bias and then a relu
right and the relu acts channel by
channel
so this is like that
any questions on sort of the mechanics
of it
now the next thing uh Again you realize
is that just as was brought up before
that you don't need the D. You can also
think about this entire Y part as being
a linear layer.
So the core representation of an RNN
layer building block in PyTorch doesn't
have this part. It just says we need an
output. What's your output? Your output
is just the state. Just send out H. If
you want to do processing on it, go
ahead and add a linear layer explicitly.
Okay,
so
we'll just call these vanilla RNNs. Like
it's a classic basic RNN structure.
Any questions on what this is? Yeah,
>> sorry, I might have missed this, but why
is only W subscripted with the
>> Sorry, W scripts. Uh sorry I'm going to
follow I'm following pietorch notation
here a little bit on that one. So let me
make it very clear of what I'm written
here. This is w subscript h. So in
pietorch this is sometimes called whh.
It's the mapping from h to h. There's a
this b I'm using b because that's the
normal systems theory way of writing it.
But the b in pietorch is w um uh or hu
there's like a weight associated with it
that's learnable.
>> So just to be clear like WB and C will
all be different for each layer, right?
>> Yes.
>> Uh for for the layers they're different.
They're always So just like in CNN's in
connets, we don't reuse the same con
from one layer to the next. We use
different cons just like that in RNN's
we use different W's, different filters
for different layers. The weight sharing
is across time, not across layers. Just
like CNN weight sharing is across space
not across layers.
The community where weight sharing
across layers is done more is in the GNN
community. Often there they will play
around with doing more weight sharing
across layers.
Good questions.
Okay. So this is the basic story. Now
a comment here is important that
let me write this in
nonlinearity.
So in CNN's relu's and relu like things
took over
okay as the functions to use. In RNN,
classical RNN, the nonlinearities are
typically
like sigmoid,
tanh,
that kind of stuff is typically what's
used
in RNS.
So why is that? For that we will just um
think about back prop. So everyone
understand the story with the the basic
what is that RNN layer look like?
It's just doing this
update recursive update with a
nonlinearity as the counterpart of a
conf.
So now how do you do back prop during
training? How does this work?
Again as always the easy answer is that
PyTorch takes care of it for you. So
don't worry about it, right? Um but
let's just like make sure we understand
it.
So here we've drawn the network
as we've drawn it and
for training you have to have a loss.
So there's a couple of different cases
that can happen. One is where you
actually expect to make some kind of
prediction at every time step.
There's problems like this in which this
is a reasonable thing to do in which
case we have a loss layer up on top
which has supervision for every single
time step of what you want.
There's other problems in which you just
want an answer at the very end.
Okay. And in there you know these are
not doing anything and there's one at
the very end that is doing all of the
actual supervision work.
Everyone good?
Okay. So
what happens with backrop?
So when you do back prop uh in this
setup
the of course the gradients are going to
go back this way
and just as in a CNN the gradients are
going to keep flowing back
this way all the way down through the
layers. Everyone good with that? Okay.
If you have residual connections,
there's going to be a gradient
superighway that'll carry the gradients
back in this direction very nicely.
Everything is as before.
But in a connet, remember, you also had
gradients going across the convex.
Okay, here the role of the conf is
played by the RNN the RNN layer and what
that RNN layer is going to do is it
means a gradient is going to go back
across this way.
Now this is happening for all of these
losses and as was commented before you
know superposition applies.
So all these gradients are
superposed with each other.
as they go through.
So all these gradients are moving in the
system because that's the way the
dependence is. Now here there's
something that's you might think is a
little bit interesting which is that
in a convey
layers to have the receptive field grow.
Everyone remember that? But here you
have an infinite impulse response which
means that everything in the past
actually influences what you're doing
here. And so the receptive field for
everything is just everything in the
past not the future because it's causal.
was everything in the past. So the
gradients on each of these layers is go
are going back all the way.
Everyone sees this.
Okay. So
what that means is that if you if you do
this uh
you have to be a little concerned about
how gradients are propagating over long
periods of time. So the difference is
that you get to control the number of
layers you use in your network. You can
make it five, you can make it 10, you
can make it 50, you can make it 200,
whatever. You're free from that point of
view to add these residual connections
um for whatever expressive forever your
gradient superighway in the vertical
direction. That's all fine.
Now, in the horizontal direction, the
length of your input depends on what
your data is actually like.
And in language type problems oftentimes
you have uh text which is quite long
right so it might be 100 200 300 500
uh you know inputs long or even longer
and so there is a question of whether
the gradients how gradients behave when
they're flowing backward.
Everyone sees this. Now
the challenge is that if you just
naively added a residual connection to
create a gradient superighway going in
the uh in this axis in the in the
horizontal axis you would shape and
change the inductive bias of this
network quite substantially. you change
what it expresses
because suddenly you have you're adding
something into this uh recursion here
that's basically like some identity type
thing into this W. So what happens if
you add an identity to a general set of
weights W? You're probably going to move
the igen values out to be bigger outside
the unit circle.
Which means now you're worried that if
you do this over and over again, you
might blow up,
right? In straight activations will blow
up. Everyone see that? So how do you
combat that? One of the ways you combat
that or just to combat that fear
generally is by having these
nonlinearities like sigmoid or tanh
which saturate. So sigmoid and tanh
refuse to get big. And so this is one of
the reasons why people would uh even
without putting a residual connection in
the horizontal direction would use
nonlinearities that are sigmoid or tanh
to help with making sure that things
don't blow up. whereas relu you're
worried they might blow up
because this is a bit of you know
historical perspective here. Okay, so
this is what's going on with the sort of
backdrop in um RNN's.
Now what happened historically right is
that when you set up these traditional
RNNs for sequential problems especially
problems in language they sort of worked
but they didn't work very well.
Okay,
they just, you know,
so
what happened was there was a lot of of
work on this and we're not going to be
talking about that work, okay? Because
uh
so for example there is this idea that
was extremely important historically was
the idea of what are called LSTMs
which are uh stands for long shortterm
memory. Okay, where the idea was
if you had these long flows of
information in your network, people said
it wasn't training and it wasn't
learning what what they thought was as
long range dependencies. So, it would
learn very local things, but it wouldn't
learn things very far away. And the
reason was that if you look at the
gradient flow going back here, you
forced it to be stable, right? It has to
be stable for it to work. Which means
that in linear type things stable means
dying exponential.
So by the time you got to something far
in the b past the gradient from in
whatever happening in that loss over
there was very very small and so it just
didn't change. It never learned these
long range dependencies.
This is the classical problem that
people saw in uh in RNNs and so they
tried to come up with solutions. So like
I said, you just can't naively add a
residual connection because it won't
work. So they wanted to add something
that was like a residual connection, but
in that it would try to carry gradients
back further, but it was very very
delicate. And so just an example, if you
want to, you can look at the code in
PyTorch uh for LSTMs.
And an one way of telling that something
is super delicate is when the LSTM paper
disagrees with the LSTM code.
Okay, so the paper has a description of
certain design choices and things one
would do and the code is subtly
different.
So that's like an indication that okay,
people were working on the code, right?
The code had to work, right? Right? And
they fiddled with it until it worked.
And there was no good explanation for
why you had to change some things, drop
certain things that were completely
reasonable from a thinking point of view
and are in the paper, but don't work.
Okay, so there's a lot of study on how
to trying to understand LSTMs, but LSTMs
really were a very important historical
breakthrough that they finally allowed
you to have these networks perform
reasonably on long range tasks. and some
of the idea and there's a simplification
of LSTMs called GRUs
gated recurrent units that also seem to
work and there's a lot of work trying to
understand what's going on what's
happening and some of the ideas in this
LSTM GRU um context are actually present
today but we can talk about them in a
way today that doesn't have to go
through this um way of thinking but you
should be aware of it so a traditional
lecture on RN RNNs would spend a lot of
time at this point talking about okay
what's wrong with basic RNN's how do we
fix it here are strategies here's things
you would do okay however we are not
going to be giving you those lectures if
you want you can read the deep learning
um book that we pointed to that has a
treatment of some of this and there's a
lot more out there you can find
we're going to take a different
perspective
we're going to take a modern perspective
that says is there something wrong with
this choice this design choice of
where one puts the nonlinearity
in the horizontal direction.
Okay.
So
to understand that
the way to think about it is in terms of
parallelism
during training. So what do I mean? So
back prop during training works like
this
and let's think about the computation
you have to do during training and ask
yourself the question of what's the
dependency graph you understand the idea
of a dependency graph like what what has
to be done before something else
happens.
So when you get the first so in training
you have the entire input all at once.
At inference time it might be coming to
you sequentially but at training you
have the entire sequence.
Does everyone see that you're training
you have the data. So you have all of
this at once.
Okay. Can you execute this box? Yes, you
can execute this box because everything
is causal. This box runs.
Okay. Once you have this box, which box
is unlock
to execute? This one and this one.
Importantly, you can't execute this box
without this box being done.
So what we're going to do is we're just
going to take this diagram and we're
going to draw it with the like
dependency graph of what depends on what
for execution more clear. So that just
means we turn it around.
Okay.
So now everything above is unlocked when
everything when things below are done.
So at the beginning you just have this
box you can run.
After you've done this these two have
unlocked. Does everyone see what I did
here? Just a visual representation. So
do the same thing just rotated.
Okay. So now these two have unlocked.
I can do both of those in parallel.
Everyone see that those can happen in
parallel. Then
this unlocks.
those three unlock and so on going up.
So this should remind you of something.
If you've taken a you've seen computer
architecture, the kind of pip
parallelism you have here is like
pipeline parallelism,
right? You can only the only amount of
parallelism you're ever going to get is
the number of layers.
So you have a sequence that's super
long, like a thousand, you have 20
layers. You're only ever going to be
able to execute 20 things in parallel.
And annoyingly they'll be different
things,
right? It'll be won't be the same matrix
applied to many different things. It'll
be a matrix for layer two and another
matrix for layer 1.
Then this will be a matrix for layer,
you know, three, two, and one.
So this isn't very friendly to hardware.
Does everyone see this kind of just
issue?
Okay.
So
this particular problem of how you this
challenge just one should recognize it's
a challenge. It has nothing to do with
whether it works well or not as a
network to do a actual job. It's just
that it's annoying to train.
Okay.
And the LSTM solution which got these
things to work well on practical
problems maintained this annoyance about
training. It's still hard to train
in parallel when you have long
sequences. So if you wanted to get
parallelism, you'd have to get it with
batches,
right? You'd have to have batches. But
you have very long things and you have
batches, it's kind of it's very tricky
to get it to um actually use utilize the
hardware in a very efficient way.
So we will return to this problem later
and how we resolve it.
Um
the
key comment here is that
in this operation
if you wanted to do this calculation
here at this level the reason that what
made this dependency happen was the fact
that there's nonlinearities in this path
because I can't execute the nonlinearity
like programmatically.
But if there wasn't a nonlinearity,
linear systems have all kinds of tricks
you can do to get them to like collapse
together and do stuff. So at the expense
of computation, you can do something and
that we'll talk about later. Okay. So
to help you understand what's going on
here, I'll just keep is I'm going to
like change pace a little bit on what
we're talking about.
I'm just going to make sure you
understand what's going on by sticking
to the purely linear case because I just
told you the nonlinearity is something
that we're going to question. So it's
worth thinking about just the linear
case first to make sure we understand
even the ideas.
So I'm just going to step back and ask
yourself what for you know filters like
what have you seen before?
So how many people have seen the common
filter in some class?
A few of you. Okay. So if you uh it's a
I think it's a standard topic in the um
probability courses like 126 uh to think
about common filtering but at some level
the details here are not of specifically
of common filtering is not important but
the problem is important.
So we're going to think about a little
toy problem. The toy problem is there's
an underlying true linear process. Okay.
So there's a true matrix A, there's a
true matrix B U, there's a true matrix
C, a true matrix D that exists and the
output is related in this way to the
input U.
However, there is also in this problem a
random
drawn according to a known distribution
disturbance that's entering the state
evolution and corrupting my
observations.
This is just the reality.
Now in a traditional treatment of common
filtering, I know all of these things. I
know the KW, KV and all these things.
And then one sets out and this is you
know like one or two or three lectures
uh to do it. You say okay if you observe
the 's and the y's
and you know all of these matrices
there's an optimal steadystate filter
that will estimate XT.
Okay, you can just work out a bunch of
math thinking about Gaussian
expectations and say basically this is
Gaussian, this is known.
You know, you can remove this the
Gaussian. The Gaussian means all of
these things are Gaussian conditioned on
what you know. Joint Gaussians have
linear estimates that are optimal and
you can just grind out a bunch of
calculations to compute what happens
and you have uh an optimal filter that
has a linear structure. Right? So
there's the matrix
the matrices A, B,
C and D all figure in and there's
another matrix F that also comes in that
you have to compute and you can just
write out this is the best estimate for
predicting what the state is given the
observations
by linearity because things are
appearing in many different places. You
can fold things together and collapse it
into a matrix A tilda that applies to
the previous state of my filter, a
matrix B tilda that applies to my uh
observation and a matrix F applies to my
control and a matrix F that applies to
my observation and just have a recursive
update. So what does that mean? It means
there's a re interesting filters that
have this shape that we're studying.
Now there are formulas for these which
we don't have to worry about. Okay, if
you want to look them up, this is called
the discrete algebraic ricotti equation.
There's a solution to it. This is all in
talking about common filters. Okay, this
is not the subject of this class.
Important thing is that there are
formulas for these in if you knew what
all those matrices were. Okay, this is a
known classical problem when you know
what all the matrices are. So now we can
ask the question from a deep learning
class point of view that says
we have this filter if we knew what it
was. But what if we don't know these
matrices?
So I don't know the underlying A
dynamics, the B dynamics, the C, the D,
the coariance of the W or the coariance
of the V. I know none of these things.
So if you have no none of these things,
it's hopeless. I have to have something
right to be able to make this filter. So
it's a deep learning class. So I have to
be able to learn the filter. So I have
to learn the filter from some kind of
data.
Everyone with me? So what kind of data
do I want? Well, the best data that I'd
like is I'd like data that looks like
this.
And this is data where I have the ground
truth state for some reason for a trace.
That's the thing I want to predict,
right? I want my common filter predicts
what the state is.
the state isn't directly observed. But
for my ground truth data, my training
data, let's suppose I actually had
proper labels. So I have the true states
and I have the things I want to that are
my inputs, which are these inputs U.
Oops, I'm using the wrong mode,
right? I have my inputs U and Y.
These are the inputs to my learning
system, right? And I want to learn from
traces of u's and y's how to predict
x's.
Everyone with me in terms of setting up
the problem. So this is a sequential
prediction problem where I'm get given
u's and y's and I want to predict x's.
Any questions on the problem?
So I can have batches of them. I have a
large set of these sequences. So I have
you know J indexes over these traces
that I have captured and you know
there's some large number of them.
The traces might be of different
lengths. I some short traces, I have
some long traces. It doesn't matter
because I'm weight sharing across time.
I don't have to have the same length of
trace in my training data.
Okay. So what do we do?
I need a tilda, bilda, and f. I don't
know what they are. Once I have a tilda,
b tilda, and f, of course, I can just
write this equation down and I'll have
the filter I want. So my whole problem
is I need to figure out what a tilda bf.
So I deem them learnable parameters.
Good.
I want to estimate.
What sense do I want to estimate x? Mean
squared error sense. That's what common
filter optimizes. So I can put a loss a
squared loss on my prediction xhat.
So now I have a loss function.
So now I have a formula which has
unknown learnable parameters in it.
And
I can run it
for inputs u and y. Everyone with me?
And I have a loss. So I can just go.
Does everyone see this? I just like set
it up and run.
So
what does that look like?
Looks like this.
I have losses squared loss up here and I
have
these boxes that are parameterized by a
tilda b and I have different u's and y's
that go in them.
Everyone sees this? This works. So now
what do I do? I have to initialize a
tilda b tilda and f to something
right. I do some random initialization
of a tilda b tilda and ff. I then
proceed to run uh gradient descent. So
I'll get losses you know that uh
back prop this way
and so on
losses will back prop the system I'll
get updates I can run and I can see what
happens
okay any questions on this this will
help make the kind of problem extremely
concrete there's no nonlinearities here
of any kind. It's just you can do this.
Yeah. what's the connection between this
and the previous
>> so the previous topic was just talking
about RNN's
and now I'm restricting for an example
to a very concrete example where I want
to learn an RNN a linear RNN with one
layer whose job is to solve this
filtering problem I want to make sure
you can everyone understands like how
you would do that is an example yeah
>> are we considering the access to as part
of the training data.
>> In this case, the X's are known as part
of the training data. There are labels
because I so this is following the
standard paradigm of supervised
training. I want to make a network that
predicts something
to train it. I need to have ground
truths for something.
Everyone with me? So in this case, the
common filter tries to give estimates
for the state X. So to train it, I'm
going to have ground truth for the state
X. That's the story that we we start
with here.
Yeah, we'll come to that next.
>> Right. Right now, we just have we have
use and Y's and we have labels X. And
given the fact that we have labels X, we
can set up a loss on a per output level
and run back prop and have this thing
converge and run.
Okay, we can choose the optimizer we
want. Like all the normal choices we
have in setting it up, we can do. We
have to make sure our gradients don't
explode.
So that means we have to initialize it
properly. Initialize it properly so that
a at initialization is stable. A tilda
is stable.
And the nice thing is that if you look
up here for if you knew the formulas,
the formula you have uh for what the
optimal value looks like is also
something that's uh stable.
Common filters when they run correctly
are are stable.
If the as long as the underlying U's and
Y's aren't blowing up, right,
everything's good. Yeah.
ality show up here. So everything in
this network operates causally. So
everything flows this way. The losses
here are individual. They just tell you
there's a loss on the individual output
of this box. There's a another loss on
the individual output of this box
because you know this box is supposed to
predict xhat at time t plus one. I know
x actually at time t plus one. So I can
put a squared loss here.
>> Great question. The question was what is
the relationship between all these
losses at one level from the level of
code there's just individual separate
losses
underneath the x's are actually
correlated across time very much but
that correlation is captured in my
labels themselves not in my loss
function in any way my loss function is
just memoryless
my labels have memory and my underlying
predictions also have memory
But from the perspective of gradient
descent, I don't care about any of that.
Just run this and it'll it converges.
I have to choose usual things. I choose
learning rate, right? All that stuff
happens. But this works.
Um,
okay. Hopefully that's all good. Okay.
Now, here comes the more interesting
question.
What if you didn't have any of the
labels?
All you have was use and wise.
Okay. So here
the states are unobserved to you. You
don't see them at all.
Can you learn how to do common
filtering? And the answer is clearly no.
Right? You can't. But why is the answer
no? Right? You don't have the labels of
what this state is but why is the answer
no? So right now take two minutes talk
to your uh neighbors and ask why can't I
do this?
Why is this not possible? So question
I'll write write the question
question.
Okay. So, talk talk to your neighbors.
I will set a timer.
I'll just put the equations up here so
you can see them.
We don't know.
Oh,
So think
question everyone. Is everyone done
thinking? Talk talk more to your f
neighbors. Another 15 seconds or
something.
Okay.
So
let's come back together and say so we
have input output behavior traces of the
underlying system this guy
and the question is can we learn to
predict its state
right from this data that's the question
can we learn the full common filter so
how many people think the answer is yes
we can
think the answer is no. We cannot.
Okay, some people are kind of
tentatively no. So now the question no
is correct. We cannot. So the question
is why not?
Right? So if you want to generally how
do you think of meta question if you
want to answer the question that says
it's impossible
to learn X
from this right? What is the nature of
the argument? the standard argument that
will tell you it is impossible to learn
this from this.
Okay. Yeah.
>> Contradiction.
>> Contradiction. That's
that's kind of the right spirit. But
what do you mean contradiction?
>> I assume it's true.
>> Okay. That's a normal way of showing
that something is impossible. But here
has to be more specific like what
you want to say that it can yeah how do
you show that something isn't learnable?
>> Yeahep.
>> Independence. Okay. So when you say what
do you mean by independence?
>> Okay. So independence is a very strong
form of something where you say what I
have is completely independent. Now here
it's clearly not
okay because the underlying behavior of
this filter. So again for those I'm
going to for to help some people um if
you've seen this from the perspective of
transfer functions remember this thing
is determining where the poles are
right of this thing and this is so you
can actually see a lot of it about this
transfer function from the input output
behavior. In fact you can see the entire
behavior. So you're certainly a it's
definitely not independent.
Okay.
Yeah.
>> Okay. Very good. If you want to show
that it's impossible to learn something,
one way of saying is that there's it's
impossible because there's two answers
at least that are compatible with the
same behavior. All your data would be
identical under these two options, but
these two options are different. So
there's no way you could tell these
apart. Does everyone see that? So it's
underdetermined, right? Is the
perspective. This is a weaker thing than
independence. Independence is very
strong. Nothing to do with each other.
This is like well there's something
you're not seeing. Okay. So who can tell
me why this is underdetermined?
So think about X as having state
dimension of having two. It was two
dimensional state just for simplicity.
Do everyone see the nature of the
argument? You have to tell me that
there's you can't predict the state
because it could be this or it could be
this and there's no way you'd ever know
the difference.
>> Um, yeah.
>> Ah, the question is because there's
noise. Okay, now that's actually quite
subtle, right? Because there's noise,
what that usually means is you can't
predict X perfectly. But even the common
filter doesn't do it perfectly. common
filter has some no some error. So saying
that I can't do it perfectly isn't the
doesn't doesn't work. What you want to
say is you can't do it in any sort of
reasonable way. There's no way I'm going
to expect imperfection. So that doesn't
work.
>> Yeah,
>> maybe you need some initial state.
>> Okay. So one question is maybe it's
because the initial state is not
observed. Okay. Let's just assume that a
this a is stable very stable and so the
initial state will be forgotten soon
soon enough and the traces are long so
then it doesn't matter okay or I can
just tell you I say the all the initial
states are always zero it's not the
initial state that's the issue here
think about this is two dimensional
why can't I do this
Yeah.
>> C A X which means depending on you can
kind of either tune X or A there's not
really much distinction of like which
one is which in terms of that overall CA
matrix that's actually making your
effect.
>> Okay, good. The important thing is the
observations Y connect to X through C.
Okay. And they connect to you through C
A B is what you wanted to say, right? B
in U encounters B then it encounters A
or you know encounters B and then C and
so on. Right? So the important thing
here is that this path the path that
goes through X involves products of
matrices.
And so the question is maybe there's
things you can do to the individual
matrices so that the effect on the
product cancels out. That's the spirit
of what you're saying, right? Okay,
that's that's really good intuition, but
can you make it more concrete? Can you
give me a specific example to start with
one example
of a kind of thing you could do?
X is two dimensional
for the example.
Okay, so just a meta thing. When
something is small dimensions, you have
a few go-to things you can do. Okay,
whenever you have linear algebra things,
you always want to say ask the question,
does change of coordinates change
something? This would be your go-to
thing. If I change coordinates,
will it be visible to me? And your go-to
change of coordinates in terms of
intuition is for two dimensions is swap
the role of x and y of the two
dimensions.
Does everyone see like this is just
heristics? How do you think about
things?
So
in this case if you swapped the two
dimensions in the state you say actually
the first dimension was the second
dimension
that would be a permutation of rows
of this thing.
You could correspondingly permute the
columns of C and you wouldn't tell the
difference. Does everyone see that?
Like suppose one of them is the Yeah.
You see? So clearly I can permute.
There's no way to know the internal
structure of X to permutation.
Does everyone see that? So it's clearly
not possible to get it.
Okay. Now you can go deeper.
Suppose I did a change of coordinates,
a generic change of coordinates. So
instead of looking at X, I look at X
through an invertible map.
I can definitely change coordinates
here. Change the A matrix appropriately.
Change of coordinates. So this dynamic
gets preserved and make sure that
coordinate transformation shows up in B
appropriately. If I chose that
coordinate transformation for example.
Yeah. So, and then that coordinate
transformation will also affect the
effective W, which would just simply
change my coariance matrix.
So, this thing I can definitely update
for a change of coordinates. But that
means I can put the inverse of that
change of coordinates here to get back
to the original coordinates and change C
appropriately. Does everyone see this?
And the endto-end behavior of U all the
way into Y would not change because it
gets reversed. the change according is
reversed. So, okay, ask questions if you
don't understand this. This is like very
basic, but it's going to lead to
something immediately for us.
>> Yeah.
>> Are you basically doing a change of
basis twice?
>> We're just doing a change of basis once
on X.
Okay. And we're saying that if you do a
change of basis on X, it doesn't change
the behavior of this thing. And we can
account for that change of basis and
see.
So there's no way of learning what's
going on in X up to changes of basis.
>> Yeah.
>> You say like a bigger picture because
there's like different solutions
matrix.
Yes, that was the first comment right
that somehow yeah the the fact that
information is flowing through a product
of matrices means that you can have
cancelling changes in these
right in particular any change of
coordinates of x
will not be you can't learn them
because you won't see them
okay but now you ask this question
question
>> if you are trying to find
Why does it matter if you change it to
basis?
>> Excellent question. So what I'm saying
here is that our goal is to learn about
the system and ask what can we learn if
what we want to learn is the common
filter which is totally reasonable. I
have input output data. I want to know
what the state is. You know to a lay
person it's like yeah why not? I have
the input I have the output. Tell me
what the state is.
Right? you will say I'm sorry I cannot
tell you the state right because it's
not unique I could reparameterize the
state up to a change of coordinate and I
won't get it
do you see that like that's the problem
so the question is what do we actually
want is the question we have to ask so
we can't get this we simply can't get it
so the next question becomes is there
any hope to get anything at all
right is there anything that doesn't
that's actually there that I could try
to get. So you ask yourself the question
if I have a matrix A
and I can apply change of coordinates to
it and it won't change the behavior for
me is there anything about that A that
is actually learnable.
So if I take a matrix and I do
similarity transforms to it
is anything preserved?
>> Yeah. EN values are preserved. The IGEN
value structure entirely is preserved.
So there is something
that you can learn and the something is
useful.
Why is it useful? Think from a practical
point of view in real life in problems.
The challenge is hey I don't I have a
lot of unlabeled data for the system. I
have a lot of input output behavior for
the system. I don't have like looking at
the state. But maybe you can have a
small amount of data that will actually
tell you what the state is.
And the learning problem becomes is
there any way of leveraging a mass of
unlabelled
data to help me get more use out of the
label data.
Okay, this should sound familiar to
people.
Okay, so now the question is is go back
to this question. You know what? Can you
you can't learn this. So this the answer
here is no. Let me just uh sorry.
Okay. So the answer here is no.
Can change coordinates.
X
and
this is unobservable.
Okay. So I can't do this.
But suppose we say
okay I can't do this
but I want to learn something.
Right? I know there's something that
might be able to be learned. How can I
rig it up to learn something?
So, this is a kind of a weird situation,
right? So, I have the U's and the Y's
and they're definitely the inputs here.
Okay? Like, that's for sure. I have
boxes here that have these different
parameters in them. I know I'm not going
to get these parameters good enough to
be a common filter. Okay? But I still
have three par three matrices in here
that I can learn in my filter.
So
the kind of highle question is is there
anything that I could try to predict
that would give me a way to get this
process to run.
So you ask yourself
if I have this xhat t and the xhat t is
sort of correct right you go back up
to
you know how one deres the idea of the
common filter
there's aspects here
that are predictable
right I've updated the state in some way
and if the next input were something
different here's the way to think about
it if the next input were something
different you could predict its output
does everyone see that if I've learned
the dynamics that the endto-end behavior
of use's to y's if the next input were
different I could predict the output in
particular if the next input were a zero
I could predict it or something so now
you can use that idea
here.
So you can say look what I'm going to do
is I will give access in the loss I have
to pick a label. So the label
these two 's and y's have a different
character. The u is an input. It's
arbitrary. It could be anything.
The y is determined once all the 's are
determined.
So, the thing I might want to predict is
the next Y.
I have it,
right? I have the next Y. So, I could
try to predict it. So, this one I can
predict try to predict Y t plus 2.
Here I can try to predict yt plus 3.
Does everyone see that?
Now
this thing is trying to update its
recursive state. The recursive state has
the wrong type at the very least. It's
the wrong size to be a prediction of y.
Suppose the state is two dimensional and
my y's are fivedimensional.
So I need some kind of translation box
at the minimum
to get something I can run the loss on.
Does everyone see that? I've decided I
want to try to learn whatever I can
learn. So I have to see what could I
even hope to predict in this setup. I
can hope to predict the y.
But actually
if I also added this arc
and I said this is a linear
Okay, does everyone see what's going on
here? Here I'm saying that I have my
estimate for what the state is.
If I knew the next
input,
right, I could predict something about
the next output.
So I can go ahead and use that and I
have a linear layer here.
If I run this, what I'm going to try to
get is something which is trying to
basically distill out what is the
dynamics of the underlying state up to
coordinate transformation
because that's the best I can hope for.
What is it that I'm never going to see
the extra information in this? So here
I'm trying to predict this Y. The extra
information in this Y is carrying
information about the underlying
disturbance and the underlying noises.
I'm never going to predict the noise.
That's an irreducible loss.
But you learn from your ML class. You
don't care. They give you reducible
loss. That's not a problem. Doesn't stop
you from learning. You just hope they
cancel out with the appropriate
averaging.
Similarly, there's an irreducible loss
that comes from the disturbance,
right? The next disturbance. You're
never going to see that. That's okay.
You can still learn the core pattern.
Okay. So, this example of trying to do
filtering sequentially actually shows
you
that you can learn something. This what
this gives you is a some kind of the
filter
up to some invariance. This is
definitely not unique. There's many many
solutions here. So, this is where things
so is this a convex problem? No, it's
not a convex problem. But that doesn't
scare us in deep learning,
right? It's not convex. Nothing is
convex. Nothing we ever do is convex
because everything we have is always has
these symmetries that we can't learn,
right?
Does everyone see that? Even in
continents, it's not convex. Nothing is
convex. Doesn't stop us. So, we can just
do it. Now, we have to see what happens.
Does it converge to something, right?
Does it work? How do you test? You have
validation data. All that stuff is still
available to us.
Does everyone see that? So for example,
here we could hold out entire traces,
right? We have many traces. We hold out
entire traces. We run this and we see
how well does it do at predicting for
those held out traces. If it's doing a
good job, you probably learned
something.
Now the important thing is we just told
you that what you're kind of spiritually
learning here is what is this filter up
to coordinate transformations
but that means given a few actual golden
labels that told you what the x's were
for some trace you could probably get it
okay everyone with me so we've talked
about it in the RNN context here, but
this should remind you of things that
you've seen a little bit before. Okay?
And this is a general principle here
that's called self-s supervision.
You might not have seen this principle,
but you've seen things that it's related
to.
So the general principle of
self-supervision goes like this.
There's a pattern. I think I can learn
some aspect of this pattern.
I might not be able to run all of it,
but there's something I can learn here
in my data.
That's a precondition. If there's you
think there's nothing you can learn from
this data, go home. This is a deep
learning class. There's no learning of
something that doesn't matter. Okay? So,
you think there's a pattern you can
learn,
but you need labels to train. All your
pipeline depends on having losses.
Losses are comparisons with some labels.
So you need something that's like doing
the lost job which you think of as like
labels.
You need labels to train. I don't have
them.
So what do you do? The answer is you
make your own labels from the data.
Because there's an underlying pattern,
you make it in a conscious way of based
on the data you have something that you
can synthesize that can do the job of a
label. So you can set up your deep
learning pipeline. You need something
you can run into a loss so you can pass
gradients.
Okay, this is the idea of self-s
supervision. It's called self-s
supervision because you don't have
external supervision. So you do it
yourself.
So the example above
says you know
there can be a partial pattern that
could be useful. In that case we said
look there's definitely something about
the igen values of this a matrix that we
should be able to p pull out. Maybe some
other stuff too, but at least we can
pull that something about that out.
Second concept is you might need some
scaffolding. So I put it in yellow
because this linear layer that we built
here for prediction was just
scaffolding.
It's not the thing we wanted to learn.
It's structures that are present to help
us learn the thing we wanted to learn.
So the way you build buildings, you
build scaffolding around them and then
at the end you don't care about the
scaffolding. The scaffolding can go away
but the building remains. So in doing
this kind of self-supervision you might
need scaffolding. This example already
shows it.
And in this particular case, when you
have things that are causal sequences,
one way of having the thing you want to
predict, the target, if you want to
learn a causal pattern, the natural
thing to try to predict is the next
thing because the next thing depends on
the previous stuff.
Okay? So, it's like a generic choice.
Predict something about the next thing.
In this case, it required some kind of
conscious thought because you said the
next thing that I want to predict is the
Y, not the U, because they have
different characters in this problem.
One is an input and one is an output.
You know that the causal connection is
one way. So you predict the thing that's
causally dependent, not the thing that's
independent.
>> Yeah.
>> So this linear layer we put here for
training, it has learnable parameters in
it.
Those will be learned. We don't care
about their values.
That's not the pattern we're trying to
get at. The pattern we're trying to get
at is what's happening in the dynamics
of the underlying state that this filter
is trying to get at.
But we can't train without that linear
layer
if only for the simple reason of
mismatch size.
Right? The y is five dimensional. Our
state is two. I have to I'm taking a
loss against a fivedimensional thing. I
have to have a fivedimensional thing. I
need something.
So I need additional structure.
So this will happen in many uh cases
that we talk about. Yeah.
>> It seems like in general subsision self
supervision follows this principle of
like you have some like in this case
we're looking at some sort of sequence
but in imaging for instance you could
have that sort of hidden like lat trying
to predict some like of the image that's
not necessarily sequential but it still
follows this general pattern of you have
some inputs like context from the image
and you have some mass portion of the
image that you're trying to predict from
state that you learned as an embedding
is there any example of self-s
supervision that doesn't follow that
general format
>> we'll talk about that you're looking
ahead we'll talk about all these things
in a bit for I can't answer that
question without doing the rest of the
um rest of the lecture um but
yes and no right we will have ways of
doing uh this for more general settings
than this one but we have to wait a
little bit for me to answer your
question.
Okay. So
what I wanted to connect to next is to
say look all of this
problem of not having labels and having
a pattern you want to learn this is like
unsupervised learning in classical ML
and so we mentioned at the very
beginning we'll be talking about this
unsupervised learning stuff so so far
we've already introduced it a little bit
we're talking about this pooling idea
but now we're kind of going to get into
it a little bit more so how can we make
this conction
And
you have to remember that there's
basically two approaches you learned in
classic ML dimensional reduction
and clustering. Both of them were about
figuring out the kind of structure
that's intrinsic in your data. Just
different kinds of structure.
Dimensionality reduction was saying look
in my data there's certain dimensions of
regularity that where the action is and
others that are less variable.
And in clustering it was that my data
isn't sort of uniformly distributed. So
you think of dimensionality reduction is
my data isn't uniformly distributed.
It's on a thinner thing.
Clustering is my data isn't uniformly
distributed. It's in blobs.
Okay. Two different perspectives on the
kinds of patterns you want to get.
So
I will not be able to talk about
everything. So I will just like maybe
start a little bit and we'll have to re
we'll have to continue. Um
if you think about like PCA
that's the algorithm you learned for
dimensionality reduction
you have these XI just X's
they're unlabeled data from some
interesting distribution in particular
from a PCA point of view it's thin
it's not covering everything equally
some area some directions are more
represented than others so the classic
recipe you learned which is not have the
form of loss function was you
constructed an X matrix of all the data
then I'm going to ignore the mean parts
you computed it SVD
you said I'm going to keep the large top
singular vectors
and that's how you do dimensionality
reduction everyone remember this
so
if you're given some other problem how
do you actually do dimensionality
reduction some other problem not this
unlabelled data some other problem you
have a new X what you do is you extract
the features from it by doing
projections onto the V's the top V's
that's how you actually do the
dimensional reduction so you started off
with some X which is large dimension and
you end up with K dimensional things and
you use that for your learning problem
everyone remember this
so the question is can we think about
this as self-s supervision
Okay, here there is no gradients,
there's no labels and there's no
supervision.
Everyone see that? We want to say is
there a way of understanding what we did
here in terms of a loss
that we could train using gradient
descent
where none of the ingredients are
present. Okay.
And the answer is yes
because of this.
So the justification you saw so you
might have seen PCA justified by it
works totally fine. Um you might have
also seen it justified by the echerty
young mirki theorem for forbinius norm
okay which is that given a matrix x if
you look at the best rank k
approximation it's going to come from
looking at the top k singular vectors
and singular values and just keeping
them and that's the best in the sense of
minimizing the difference between this
rank k thing and x in forbinius norm
squared or forbinous norm doesn't matter
if you see an optimization class You
might have seen this in two different
norms in Fbinius norm and in spectral
norm here forbinius norm is the one
that's more useful for us because it's
going to treat every row as a vector.
Okay, that will give us a loss. Then we
can interpret what PCA is doing as
self-supervision.
This will then connect us to
autoenccoders
which is useful. Okay, that's the next
part of the class. I was too ambitious
in what I thought I could cover in in
one lecture. But that's the next little
segment before we then go back to this
question of hey great what we learned
here about we can learn things up to
IGEN values maybe we can think about
that how to make better
uh recurrent networks. Okay all these
things up together.
Okay.