A lot of people are busily working on
their project. So I'm gonna
unfortunate but well deadlines have to
be sometime. So um I will start with a
couple of announcements. Uh I didn't
announce this uh last time, but we we
told people to fill out the survey and
we said that we'll give extra credit if
for everybody in the class, 3% uh if 75%
of the class does the survey. I forgot
to give a deadline. I put it on online.
So this is
due
Friday of Thanksgiving week.
And uh the other uh important uh
reminder is
today your draft reports are due. We
will quickly turn around and assign you
a report to review uh using the
conference management system. So you
have can do that over the weekend and
sort of by uh Tuesday before everyone
goes off Thanksgiving break submit read
the report of that you're assigned and
write a review. This is important to
give everyone feedback so that they can
make their projects better. Uh there
were some questions about when this uh
report is due. So it's uh due uh tonight
at the midnight. I think we will maybe
accept some submissions if they come in
late, but tomorrow morning we're going
to be assigning people to a review so
that we have to have it by then.
Um, okay. So, that's the the expectation
we have for everyone is that you've
worked very hard. You're working on your
reports and you are finding that there's
a lot more you want to do than you have
already done and that is to be expected.
But you have to write up what you've
done and what you're planning to do more
based on what you've seen so that
someone can give you feedback usefully.
Yeah. Question.
>> Approximately what percentage of the
class?
>> Um right now the percentage is uh sub
20%.
>> Barely maybe 20. Okay. So you have to
tell your peers and your everyone in
your project group, hey you better uh be
doing this. Uh it's actually it's not I
look I went and I looked at the grades
last semester and 3% actually would have
moved quite a few people across grade
boundaries. So um it actually will
matter.
Okay.
So now I want to uh continue where we
left off. I kind of raised at the end on
the generative stuff. So I will slow
down and talk about that a little bit
more. Um we're going to do this uh
switch up of the order of material a
little bit in that we're going to
introduce VAES because they're useful
and important to introduce key ideas but
then we're going to switch for a little
bit to an interlude to talking about
post-training of models because then
we'll have the ingredients we need to
talk about that and then we'll switch
back uh to talking about generative
models and diffusion models in
particular. That's kind of the order in
which we're going to be going uh through
the class.
Okay, so
we talked about the idea of generative
models and it's important to remember
that when we talk about generative
models, we're talking about models in
which the goal is not like
classification or regression where you
want to assign a label to something.
It's instead to generate something new.
And we conceptualize this as sampling
from an unknown distribution. And the
problem of training a generative model
is to both both have an approach that
will let you sample from a distribution
as well as figuring out how you can
learn uh essentially a parameterized
form of the distribution from data.
Okay, that's the problem of general
models. And there's two categories of
this that we can think about um kind of
coming from probability. There's
sampling from an unconditional
distribution which is just that we have
a generative model. We've learned we
have we feed randomness into it and we
get a new example and that's it. And for
a lot of the teaching of the ideas we're
going to focus on this case but
practically the important case is
conditional generation where you're
sampling from a conditional
distribution. So you have some
conditioning and some randomness and out
pops a new example that is appropriately
drawn from the conditional distribution
conditioned on the conditioning that
you've given it. So you already know
examples of this uh which is the
conditioning can be like the prompt
in LMS and if you've ever used an image
generation model you can think about the
prompt you use to prompt an image
generation model is also a kind of
conditioning. So okay hopefully this is
clear in terms of what uh what the goal
of understanding generative modeling is.
And last time we talked about this uh a
couple of ideas that didn't work which
is important to understand and one was
this idea of using a classifier. And so
the idea was why why would you use a
classifier? This is the deep learning
philosophy of what do I know how to do?
I know how to train a classifier. So if
I have labeled images, I can train a
classifier. And now you can think about
doing conditional generation by saying
that an image of a cat I can think of as
being an image that the cat classifier
says is a cat
and then I have a natural strategy which
is I can sample a random image using
whatever distribution I want and then
ask whether it's a cat or not. That
doesn't work too many images. Next thing
you can do is say well I can sample a
random image. So in this picture that I
drew last time, you have all possible
images. The problem is the manifold of
natural images is very very thin. So
most images are not natural images. They
just look like random noise. So you
sample some image here and you're like,
I would like to make you cat-like. And I
can try to make you cat-like by doing
gradient ascent on the cat classifier
that I learned. That'll move me. And
what I want is for it to move me from
here onto the manifold of natural images
in particular that subset of the
manifold of natural images which
consists of cats.
But what actually happens is it just
moves from here somewhere here and says
this is very confidently a cat and it's
just random noise. So this doesn't work.
I mentioned last time that we can think
about uh when we talk about diffusion
models, we can think about diffusion
models as our attempt to make something
like this work.
Okay, to make it so that we can take
small steps and move towards the
manifold of natural images successfully
and to train something to do that. Okay,
but this idea very natural people tried
it at the beginning it uh did not work.
Okay, so the other idea we talked about
last time was the idea of using an
autoenccoder.
Okay, so the idea of using an
autoenccoder said that well I have I I
recognized before that when I have a
lowdimensional structure I can learn an
autoenccoder that tries to exploit that
lowdimensional structure to do
dimensionality reduction.
And by doing that I feed in examples
from my distribution into my encoder. I
get a latent Z and then I run it through
a decoder and I get an X hat and then I
try to minimize the loss between X and
Xhat.
And the idea is by doing this I distill
out from X from the point of view how we
use it traditionally. The decoder is
just scaffolding. I use the the encoder
distills out what's important about the
image and what's important is what lets
you reconstruct it
and puts that into Z. And so one
perspective is to say well well the
decoder's job was do the opposite. It
was to take something that expressed the
important information and to actually
generate an image. Okay. And so the
natural idea is try using the uh
the decoder to generate samples. So
again to make it explicit I don't have a
Z. So what I do is I draw Z from a
random distribution and I say I run it
through the decoder and I see what I
get. So I train an autoenccoder for cats
and um it I try a validation for
example. I take a held out cat image. I
run it through the autoenccoder uh for
cats and out comes a reconstruction that
looks like a good reconstruction of the
cat image. So I think I've got a good
autoenccoder. Now I say great, I'm not
going to use the encoder. I'm not going
to run an actual cat in here at all.
I'll just take random noise and throw
that into Z. What happens? And what
happens is that you will get something
that just looks like a noise-like image.
And the reason is that we have this uh
manifold hypothesis for natural images.
But even after we do the dimensionality
reduction, if we're in a category where
we get we're getting good images of cats
out from our autoenccoder,
we're still in a very low dimensional
subset of Z. The encoder is only
producing things in a very low
dimensional subset of Z.
And so when we draw something that's
from a random distribution like a
Gaussian for example, we'll get
something that looks nothing like the
Z's that the decoder saw during
training.
And so this is this kind of wild
extrapolation that neural networks are
bad at doing. All machine learning
methods are bad at doing. Like it
doesn't know what to do. So it just you
get something out that's not necessarily
a a cat. So you get a noise-like image.
You can also get images in some cases
that break a different way where they're
like, you know, blurry
Gaussian blob type things. Um, so lots
of ways, but it's never a cap.
Okay, so this everyone everyone good
with this these ideas that don't work?
Yeah.
>> Does that hypothetically if you had the
exact correct internal dimension size C
then you this might hypothetically work.
>> Okay, it's a great question. So the
great question was I'll repeat it is
that if you if you had exactly the right
dimension Z, would this work? And the
problem is that the answer is no. Um and
the reason is dimensions go one, two,
three, four, five. So people done the
experiment where you try. Okay. And what
happens is that as you increase the
dimension of Z, the autoenccoder's
validation performance gets better and
better, right? And
but it doesn't get better and better.
First, it doesn't get better and better
in a dramatic jump way. It's like, okay,
it's getting better, better, better
better better, you know, better better
better better better better better
better better better for a while. And so
there isn't a crisp right thing even.
There's not a crisp right dimension from
the autoenccoders point of view either.
So that's your first indication this
probably not going to work. And what
happens is that the as a result the
trying this approach it just get you bad
image bad image bad image bad image bad
but they're like they start changing in
how they're bad but they're still all
bad.
So that doesn't work. Now one act one
way of thinking about it is that
discrete dimension isn't the right
thing. So you could imagine doing other
kind of regularizers to try to have a
softer way of controlling the size of
this bottleneck. And one way of thinking
about what a VAE does is it's kind of
like that a little bit.
But another way that I personally find
more useful to thinking about a VAE is
that we want to make sure that
if we sample something here,
it's
the decoder has to be robust to the
things we're introducing in in Z that
might not it might not have seen during
training.
So you can think of it, one way of
thinking about it is I want to do a data
augmentation
during autoenccoder training which is
designed to make the decoder more
robust. Okay, that's one lens to think
about it. Another lens to think about it
um same words just said diff kind of
same idea but just said differently is I
would like to make the decoder more
robust to uh kind of variations in Z and
I want to make it see more like what
it's going to see during generation
time.
So
the key ideas that I mentioned last time
very fast is that
first we need to somehow make Z random
during training too. We're gonna it's
going to be random during testing when
we generate a new image. So we need to
make it random during training. So it's
like what it's going to see later. So we
have to add some randomness to Z. Some
things out of random Z.
Second is that when we're going to be
using it,
we're going to be using
Z by sampling from a particular
distribution.
We have a lot of freedom in choosing
what distribution it is, but it's going
to be some distribution.
So we want the Z's that the decoder sees
during training to be like Z's from that
distribution. It's not just it should be
random. It should be like the
distribution we're going to use. So we
have to add some kind of loss on the
distribution of Z that makes it move
towards the distribution we're going to
be sampling from.
Okay? So we have to make this choice of
what to sample from and we have to have
a loss.
And the third thing we have to do is we
have to make all of this work with SGD
style training because implicit in what
I'm saying is that we're going to be
doing some random thing here which
involves some kind of you can't just
feed a distribution into a decoder. You
have to feed something into the decoder.
So your mind should be thinking uhoh
we're going to be doing sampling.
But remember we talked about auto
reggressive generation. We said sampling
you can't run a gradient through.
Okay. So we have to be careful in how we
do this to make sure that we can run
gradients. So it's like a a warning in
our mind. We have to make sure we can do
this.
Okay. Any questions on the sort of the
ditterata here we're trying to do.
>> Yeah.
>> Um I guess this is us kind of trying to
uh find a distribution of Z itself like
would something like a patch normous
approach where uh where we see oh this
is the kind of Z that we saw during
training and we try to like sample from
a distribution which is similar to that.
>> Okay that's a good question. So the
question is and people have tried to
approach it like this. So the question
is to say instead of trying to pick a
distribution that we're going to sample
from and then make our decoder generate
from that, why don't we try to have a
distribution that's like the
distribution that we saw from our
encoder itself. So in particular we have
an empirical we've trained this thing.
Suppose we didn't do any of this stuff.
We just trained this thing and we have a
whole collection of images and so we
actually have a whole collection of Z's
that those images generated.
So we could say that let me draw from
that distribution first try. Let me draw
from that distribution. Well, you
already know why this is not going to
work. If you drew from that
distribution, you're just going to get
back a copy of one of your training
images.
So that's not good. It doesn't work for
us. We need to be able to generate novel
samples, not just samples that we've
used to train. Okay. So then you'd say,
well, maybe I can try to fit some kind
of local density, use some kind of local
density estimation techniques to try to
fit a local density around this thing.
But then you've just reduced the same
problem we had at the beginning,
right? Just to have a distribution
around this. All we've done is
dimensionality reduced it. Okay? So it
still doesn't solve our problem. We just
return the same problem again. Okay. But
let's just you know hold on to the idea
about thinking about this distribution.
This will become important. We talk
about latent space diffusion later.
Okay. But first we have to kind of solve
this problem of you know actually making
having some control on Z.
Okay. So here's the picture
that we want. So
this path
looks very similar to the autoenccoder
path we had before. The difference is
that instead of just having the encoder
generate something that goes straight
into the decoder, we have the encoder
generating a distribution whose samples
go into the decoder.
Okay, so that's like what happens on
this main path. That's the difference.
And we decided to add instead of just
our usual you know loss of
self-supervision adding a new loss that
takes in a new ingredient which is a
desired distribution.
Okay this is the kind of approach that
we're going to take. Now notice
something here. You'll notice something
which is that you might say, "Wait a
minute, this isn't exactly what we
wanted."
Right? What we actually said we wanted
was to have the something so the
distribution of Z that comes over all
the X's we ever use is like the
distribution we want. Does everyone see
this distinction? Whereas here what I
have is the conditional distribution
conditioned on this X
is like the distribution I want which is
very different.
Everyone see this? You should be aware
of this challenge this difference. And
so from a deep learning perspective, one
way of understanding what we're doing
here is to say yes that is a challenge
but I can do this.
Okay, operationally I can do this.
Trying to have a loss on the
distribution of X
averaged over all of the things entering
this encoder and those the kind of
mixture of distributions. that's hard to
do to put a loss on that. So I'll just
do this and see what happens. That's one
way of thinking about it. The other way
to think about this, this is actually
where the name variational autoenccoder
comes from, is that this kind of
technique has been done in statistics
before and so there's like reasons to
believe things like this will work.
Okay. If you've seen EM, it's related to
things in there. Yeah.
>> So we're saying you're taking a loss on
the distribution. Is it like a loss of
the output of the encoder opposed to
like samples from the distribution the
desired distribution or
>> so far I'm being vague about this. I'm
saying that the output of the encoder
has to be something I can sample from.
Okay, we call that a distribution.
I have to parameterize it somehow,
right? And I have to parameterize this
somehow so I can compute this loss
somehow. But right now I'm just thinking
that it's at the level of distributions.
A distribution pops out.
We have a target distribution and we
have to compute it loss somehow.
So now
we have to choose both the loss and the
desired distribution to make this kind
of thing work.
So we can think about what is some of
the derata. We have freedom here. We get
to choose the distribution
for things like images. And in general,
we want the distribution to be something
that's continuous and easy to sample.
Why? Because we know that from a
continuous distribution, we can generate
from any continuous distribution, we can
generate any other distribution we want
by some transformation.
Okay, so we continuous distributions are
nice. Also, we're looking forward to
having gradients and continuity might be
nice. You can eventually get around this
problem, but just for right now, we'll
uh we'll say this as our first thing
that we want to do.
definitely want it to be easy to sample
because we want to use it and we also
want it to be easy to compute this loss
somehow
because you have to implement it.
Okay, so now comes the question of how
do I think about losses on distributions
and what are my go-to things? So here we
had you in discussion look at uh KL
divergence,
right? You might have seen this before.
You saw you seen entropy before. KL
divergence just kind of goes off of
entropy. So I'm going to write KL
divergence in sort of integral form
here.
And
it's a one of the natural kind of loss
functions we have when we think about
distributions and how close
distributions are from one to the other.
So when you have a loss, you have to
have two things. The thing you're
measuring the loss of and the target.
Okay. So here we have KL has two things.
It has a Q and a P. And what it does is
it says how close are Q and P to each
other. So you can think about if Q and P
are the same, we want the loss to come
out as zero.
Okay? Like that's something we want. So
in this formula, what we're going to do
is we're going to look at the ratio of Q
and P. So if Q and P evaluate to the
same probabilities on everything, the
ratio will be one. Everyone good with
that? And we take the log of that
because the log of one is zero.
So if these two are the same, this is
always zero. And then I take an
expectation over it with respect to some
distribution. I pick the distribution Q.
So if Q and P are the same, I'll get
zero.
That's like one basic fun feature of a
loss function I care about. Um but you
know there are more. Uh so you can think
about it many different ways. From a
deep learning perspective, you can think
about what's nice about KL is that it
exists
and you can compute it. Okay? And then
you can see how well it works. Like you
have to pick something. You might as
well pick things that have worked. You
pick things that have worked elsewhere.
There's many other distributions one
could distances one could use, but this
is one. Um and there are many variants
and people do use many variants.
So
one thing about this particular uh
distance from a deep learning
perspective and in general is that it's
not symmetric
and you saw that in discussion it's it's
not symmetric and so there's a question
of whether you want distributions to be
symmetric losses on distributions to be
symmetric or not and kale divergence if
you haven't seen this before actually
captures a very natural asymmetry that
exists in probability itself. And you
can think of it this way. If I have a
coin that I'm tossing and the coin is
equal heads or tails probability,
okay? And I toss it.
And I have another coin that has some
unequal heads and tails probability.
It's natural to ask how far apart are
these two coins. Is that good? Now, why
would you think of this as being
asymmetric? One way to think about
telling two probabilities apart is you
want to know something about the chance
you'll get confused learning from data
about which one it is. Everyone see
this?
So the question is is this asymmetric or
is it symmetric? And the answer is it's
definitely asymmetric because if I tell
you I can toss a coin twice.
Okay, that's your data. It's tossing a
coin twice and one coin has
heads on both sides and one coin has
heads and tails.
Okay, you only toss it twice.
Is there a chance when you toss the coin
that's fair that you'll be confused
about whether it's the two-headed coin?
The answer is yes.
But if you toss the two-headed coin
twice or a hundred times, right? Is it
ever going to look like the coin that
has heads and tails? The answer is no.
See, there's a small chance the heads
and tails one will give you all heads,
but the heads heads one's going to only
give you all heads. So, there's
definitely asymmetry in probability in
in what's close to what. Does everyone
see that kale divergence is capturing
exactly that kind of asymmetry.
Um, this is probably talked about more
in 126, so I don't want to dwell on it,
but this is uh the from a deep learning
point of view, there's an asymmetry, and
it kind of makes sense for there to be
asymmetry.
So from our point of view though as in
deep learning we have a practical
problem which is we have to choose which
one is the desired distribution and
which one is the one that we're trying
to make look like the desired
distribution. And so the choice we do is
we put the desired distribution in the P
spot.
And the reason we put the desired
distribution in the P spot is that
we don't want we want a high loss on Q
generating things that look very
unlikely under P.
Okay? Because we want it when we use it,
we're going to use P and we want to have
seen things like P
during training. Everyone see that? Like
that's important to us. So we put the
desired thing in P and we have Q be uh
that distribution the one up on top.
Okay. So now we have to choose a
distribution.
So we we picked a loss a default loss.
People use others. I just want to start
with one. Um so
what's a good choice? So in generally
for continuous distributions, we have
two go-to choices that we like. We like
uniforms and we like Gaussians. You've
seen this before. And only after those
two don't work practically do we say
maybe I'll try an exponential, right?
And if the exponential doesn't work,
you'll like go beyond that. But you kind
of like to sit with these two if you
can.
Uh so we make a choice. And a pragmatic
way to make the choice is to say for
what do we have nice formulas for KL
divergence.
Okay, Gaussians are really nice because
you can have you have very nice formulas
uh for KL divergence. So you say great
I'll choose a Gaussian and what Gaussian
should I choose? Well the easiest
Gaussian is just isotropic.
Okay so I have a zero mean and it has an
identity coariance. So a bunch of ID
gaussians easy to sample from. I'll use
that.
So, what's great about that is that you
can just look and see that there are
formulas
that will tell you if you have uh
Gaussian on this side and a Gaussian on
this side, what's the divergence between
them? So specifically for the case of
the uh identity uh coariance on that
side and a generic mean and a generic uh
coariance matrix you have this nice
formula. So you take half the trace of
the coariance of Q. You take the inner
product the the the two norm squared of
the mean. You subtract K and you
subtract the log determinant of this.
So again if you think about it
you know if the two distributions are
equal if this is zero
right then this will all zero out. Okay,
you can do that as an exercise to see
that it all it all zeros out.
The only important thing here is that
this is something which you can compute.
Okay, this is this is computable.
So now you have a formula you could use
for a loss.
And now the question is can I make a
neural net such that this distribution I
have here
is this. So I'll parameterize it by two
things the mean and the coariance
matrix.
So I've partially drawn the uh the
answer.
So you can definitely have something
emit the mean,
right? This is the vector.
How do I get it to emit a coariance
matrix is the question?
Everyone see why this is a question. So
can someone tell me why is it why can't
I just draw something out of here just
naturally that says
I'll try something
Why can't I just do this
like just fine the coariance matrix is a
matrix
so just have the neural net here emit a
matrix I could structure that matrix in
some form but that's all okay why can't
I just have it emit emit a matrix
Yeah.
>> How can the encoder turn X into a
matrix?
>> How can encoder turn X into a vector?
>> That's that's not the problem, right? So
the encoder this is like what is this?
This is something that's you know has
you know cons in it has attention in it
has lots all the neural net stuff is in
here. It's going to emit vector type
stuff. Vectors go in, vectors come out.
That's not a problem. You can think of a
matrix as a whole collection of vectors.
That's all that's not that's not an
issue. The question is I want this to be
a coariance.
So anyone can point out like what what
might be a challenge here.
>> Yeah. Here
>> like coariances are like
so it's like you have some properties
that
>> does everyone hear that? Very good. So
the important thing is a coariance isn't
just any matrix. A coar a coariance for
a Gaussian is a symmetric positive
definite or in this case I'm positive
semi-definite matrix. I'm fine with
semi-definite
although that will like make this blow
up which is fine but the loss will do
that. Um so does everyone see I need to
have it be positive semi-definite. If I
just emit a random set of a random
matrix, it will not be positive
semi-definite. It'll just fail being the
wrong type.
So I can't quite do that. Okay, so that
doesn't quite work. So let me go in here
and erase this.
So now the question is
symmetry I can always get. That's not a
problem by itself. So I'm not worried
about the symmetry. How do I get it to
be? How can I emit something such that I
can parameterize
positive semidefinite matrices somehow?
>> Yeah.
>> Take a matrix and multiply with a
transpose.
>> Yeah.
>> PSD,
>> right? If I take a matrix and I multiply
it by its transpose, I'm going to get
something that's PSD.
So I can just say the output of the
encoder isn't
the coariance matrix but the square root
of the coariance matrix.
No. So that way the coarian matrix
itself is going to be
the square root
times
its transpose.
Now I'm guaranteed that when I want the
coariance, I parameterized it this way
and I'm going to get something that's
going to be uh PSD.
Wonderful. So now I have something which
will work with the loss.
So instead of take I'll take the log
debt of this thing over here. I'll take
the trace of this thing. All fine. I can
pass gradients through that. it will
work
and if I want to have any structure uh
to the coariance that's practical for
the problem I can also do that right
it's it's
this is a very generic transformation if
I want some other additional structure I
can impose it it's not a problem
okay so now I have uh a way of
parameterizing the output so I can do
this now I can tell if you tell me I
have a mean and a coariance I can make a
sampler for this
so the question is how am I going to
make the sampler for this that's going
to help me satisfy the constraint I have
that when I'm eventually going to run
back prop the loss from here
right will back prop through the decoder
fine but I have to run it through the
sampler somehow
and come back and hit the encoder.
So how can I make my sampler which uses
randomness the square root of the
coariance and the mean to have something
through which gradients will flow?
That's the next question.
Okay. So let's just uh put in what we
have.
So here's the thing, right? I know how
to do the mean part.
I can sample from a Gaussian which has a
mean and a coariance by adding the mean
to a Gaussian that has the coariance I
want. Everyone good with that? So this
part I got.
Now the question is how do I get a
Gaussian with mean zero and a desired
coariance.
You know I have to draw something. I
have to draw something. I can draw kind
of computationally easily. I can't say
my generic object is draw from this
coariance. That's the whole problem,
right? So I have to draw from something
that I know. So let's just make it easy.
I know that all jointly normal things
are linear functions of a standard iid
normal
right so let's try to exploit that so
I'll tell you that my input here
is some
v
normal zero
identity coariance
So now I have this as my ingredient. I
know that any Gaussian I want
that's zero mean is a linear function of
this guy in this dimension. I have the
square root of the coariance.
What do I do
to get what I want?
How do I do and remember? So let's just
start with the basic suppose a scalar
and I want to have a Gaussian with
square root of coariance of standard
deviation. I have a standard normal and
I want something with standard deviation
is 10. What do I do?
Someone
>> multiply
>> multiply it right multiply 10. Okay. Now
what's the answer here?
>> Multiply. Yes.
Okay. This is vector matrix
multiplication.
Right. Vector matrix multiplication
of the square root with this will give
me a Gaussian that has the coariance.
Okay. Again basic property of uh
multivariate gaussians.
So
this is nice right? So I have uh
something that uh I have a way of
sampling. Now let's think about what
happens to gradients.
Oops. Use a different color.
Okay. So, back prop goes happily through
here. No problem.
Back prop goes happily
through here. No problem everyone.
That's all. Not a problem. So now it
encounters this plus. What does backrop
do on a plus?
Just splits. goes in both directions. So
it happily continues straight through
along the mean and it also comes
through out here through this multiply.
The multiply will also split it in two
directions, right? Differently but split
in two directions. And so it'll happily
flow
out this way
into the square root of the coariance
and it'll flow in principle onto
the noise just like the gradient in
principle will flow onto the data back
here. Everyone good with that?
So important point is gradients make it
all the way through
the encoder.
So now you might wonder, wait a minute,
I have this random V that I sampled.
So in principle, I have a gradient going
towards this V, but I don't do anything
with it.
So how am I thinking about it? The way
I'm thinking about it is I'm thinking
about the V as having the same status as
the X, the input.
It's just another part of the data.
Okay, so the idea is that for stochastic
gradient descent and stochastic type
approaches, what I know is that the
expectations that I take will be like
the true gradients. So the expectation
of the gradient going here will see the
average effect of all these V's.
Remember this matrix multiply will have
the V's coming into the gradient,
right? And that will be the gradient I
want.
And that's all I need for SGD type
things to work. Okay, so the fact that
I'm doing SGD and I'm already kind of
happy using SGD means I'm happy doing
this. And now I have a way of taking a
gradient through sampling. Now you saw
this idea in your homework also where
you talked about doing optimizations
over functions that are not
differentiable.
Okay, so now you have all the
ingredients you need to train a VAE.
So to summarize, you set up a
distribution that you're going to draw
from. Standard choice is Gaussian.
And you say, I would like to have this
resulting distribution look like normal
01. Normal iid normal01.
But there's a tension now, okay, in
between these two losses. These two
losses are not synergistic to each
other. They're in tension. Why are they
in tension?
because this loss wants your
reconstruction to be perfect.
Okay, for the reconstruction to be
perfect,
there has to be a lot of particularities
of X that are communicated through this
mean and through the and whatever this
distribution of Z is.
This loss wants this to be zero
and this to be the identity
always.
In fact, this loss will wants this to
have no variation at all. Clearly, these
cannot both be satisfied at the same
time. Does everyone see that? If I make
this loss have more importance,
this loss is going to get worse. If I
make this loss have more importance,
this loss is going to get worse. There's
a trade-off between these two losses.
Okay, so note.
That means there's a hyperparameter you
have to set which is what's the balance
between them.
Okay, so you set some amount some you
can think about multiplying this loss by
some constant
as an example and then when the
gradients come back these two different
gradients are competing with each other
in changing this encoder.
Okay. Yeah.
>> How are we defining our desired
distribution?
>> Oh, this is just normal.
>> I'll just write that out. Sorry, I
didn't
we just made that choice. We pick it.
This is what we're going to sample from
when we're going to do generations.
So then in that case we're saying we're
both trying to get it to look like
normal but also trying to get it to look
good.
>> Yes. So these are conflicting. So you
have to you can play with this but now
this gives you so back to the question
that was raised earlier right is there
like a right way of setting that
information bottleneck that we can draw
the samples. So if you think about it,
choosing the weight you put on here,
right? The more weight on I put on here,
the more I want this to look like it's
completely uninformative,
right? This was zero. This is something
that doesn't change. Then seeing Z's
tells me nothing about X. That's what
makes this thing be happy.
So you can think about this is
modulating the strength of this loss is
controlling the amount of information
that can flow from here to here.
Okay. So this is like anformational
bottleneck not just a dimensional one.
And in fact you can connect it. This is
if you look at the relationship between
some of you might have seen this in a
class between KL divergence and
something called mutual information.
This is what's happening here. You're
constraining the mutual information
between Z and X
and that's a fine the important thing is
that's not a discrete quantity. That's a
fine control you have. Okay. So that's
one way of thinking about what's
happening here. Okay. So you have a fine
control on this bottleneck by adjusting
the weight of this loss.
And so what people find is that if you
do a VAE and I think we'll make you do
it in the homework in the next homework
uh for like emnest you can play around
with this and kind of get the
generations to be much better than what
you would get with a straight
autoenccoder
and there's many many tricks people have
done on VAE to make them be very good
but in general this tension is still
present. So if you make this,
why is this tension? If I make this loss
have a lot of weight, it's forcing there
to be less information that goes through
here, which makes the quality of this
reconstruction bad. But it also makes
this distribution that I see here or
that this is seen during training very
close to the distribution I'm sampling
from, which is what's letting the the
reconstructions be good.
Now if I from the generation point of
view, so if I want to make this
reconstruction be very good, which means
I want this to generate very high
quality images, then there has to be a
lot of information from here to here.
But high quality image generation on
that side means that this distribution
is not going to be right.
Okay. So from a picture point of view,
come back here and copy this picture.
Oops.
Okay. This picture
shrink it.
Okay.
doing VAE training. You can think it's
in a different space, but what it
effectively does is it makes this
distribution
be more blobby around it. It creates
some width to it
because small variations are represented
in the training data because you added
this noise effectively. This is not
quite right. This is in the latent
space. So without adding doing VA
training in the latent space, you'd have
the same picture replicated in the
smaller dimensional space. And now by
doing this uh variational autoenccoder
training, I'm basically making this
instead of being a very thin set be like
a thicker set,
okay, that I can generate. And so
in that sense, you made the problem
easier even if you haven't fully solved
the problem. And that's the secret
behind why latent diffusion works, which
we'll talk about later. It's easier to
sample to learn to sample something
that's not you don't have to get it
exactly right. You just have to get
close.
Okay. But that we'll talk about later.
Okay. Now, any questions on how uh VAE
work? Yeah.
>> So, at generation time, you're sampling
V.
>> At s at generation time, all you're
going to do is sample V. And in this
particular case, and you're simply not
going to do uh I mean, I guess you can
you're not going to set this mean you're
set this mean to zero. You're not going
to do anything here. It's going to run
straight through.
>> Okay?
>> Because you're going from the desired
distribution. You're going to pretend Z
is coming from a normal zero. So there
there are tricks, okay? So um that
people used to do in the past. So I give
you a flavor of some of these tricks.
Um, one trick that people used to do,
um, is they would say, I take the
desired distribution, I run it through
the VAE. Okay? And now I get an image.
This image isn't quite right. So what
I'll do is I'll take this image and I'll
run it through the encoder.
And now I'll get something that's like
the distribution in the neighborhood of
that image. And I'll do this again with
another noise. So do a two-step
generation. There's like old tricks that
people used to do. They don't do these
trying to tricks as much anymore, but
because you have better ways of doing
this, but there is this tension and
people try to fix it. The current best
correct way of fixing it is to actually
use another method to sample from a
distribution that has some thickness
like a diffusion model.
>> Yeah.
>> If during inference time we're just
using the standard distribution, why
don't we just like that? That's a really
good question. So the question is why
don't you just train it in the following
way? Okay, so I'll repeat the question.
The question is if during generation
you're just going to be feeding it a
random noise in why don't we train it
that way? So let's think about what that
kind of training would look like. That
kind of training would eliminate the
encoder entirely.
Okay, so now think about the task you're
asking the neural to do. I have this
specific picture of a cat.
Here's some random noise.
Predict this cat. Dakota will try. Okay.
Now you say, here's a picture of a dog.
Here's some new random noise that has
nothing to do with a dog. Please predict
that dog. It'll be like, how is it ever
going to do this? And then then then the
next batch comes around, right? You do
multi-pic training. The same picture of
a cat comes. Here's totally different
noise. Predict that same cat. It's not
possible, right? There's no way for it
to succeed at that task.
So, you can try it, but it doesn't work.
So, you have to have something to make
this distribution have something in Z
has to actually correspond to this
image.
It can't be pure noise.
>> But during inference, nothing really
corresponds to that.
>> Yes. So during during operations you say
that this randomness will correspond to
hypothetical information that could be
in some image. So this is unconditional
generation. How to make this work
conditionally is like other you just add
conditioning into both. Okay. But like I
want to focus on the unconditional to
get the key idea of how VAS are working.
Any other questions on how VAS are
working? Yeah,
>> I know you explained this earlier. Can
you explain again why we added noise in
the first time?
Ah, so
the entire problem of doing generation
requires you to sample from a
distribution. Your computer is doing
deterministic steps. The only way you're
going to sample from a distribution is
to feed in some randomness and do some
transformation to it to get something.
So fundamental to the problem of doing
any generative model is drawing upon
some source of randomness and
transforming it.
This is like it doesn't matter what
technique you're doing. You must do
this. Everyone understand that? This is
it's a very basic thing. It's not a that
has the consequence that I need to have
some randomness and feed it in. And
practically speaking, since I'm dealing
with vectors, I have to be able to put
that randomness in somehow. In this
case, I do it by having a vector, namely
Z, that I draw from some distribution.
In diffusion models, it'll play out
differently. how we do it.
Okay, so I want to recap what are some
new tricks that we've learned and sort
of think we have way of thinking.
First is we have talked about using kale
diversions as a regularizer on
distributions.
Okay, just you know we've had auxiliary
losses before. We introduced them in
diff pool. Now we have a new auxiliary
loss that we can use and it has the goal
of kind of making distributions go to
what we want. So we learned this trick.
We've also
learned in lecture now you've seen it in
discussion not discussion you've seen it
in a homework a way of treating sampling
in a way that allows gradients to just
pass through it. So you think about it,
what happened here is that
the gradient because of this plus where
we reconceptualize the sampling as
involving something with a plus and then
the gradient just flew straight through
because of the plus.
Okay, so we have a way of treating
sampling or a certain kind of we think
about sampling on from the mean
perspective. The mean there's the mean
and the coariance on the mean
perspective. The sampling is a kind of
perturbation that happens that's noisy
and the ideal version with no noise
would just be the same thing comes
through. And for the mean part, it just
passes the gradient straight back
through.
Everyone see that? I'll talk more about
this in a moment to show you how this
idea generalizes.
And then we had this approach which said
that
if I'm going to have uh randomness in
the sampling, I can just think of it as
more stoasticity that I already have
with SGD.
And now I can train. I don't have to
like having already ex accepted that SGD
works, I'm like okay fine more
randomness that's okay too.
So the key the key conceptually if if
you didn't have an already existing
acceptance of SGD this would be a hard
step to accept but you're already
accepting SGD and so it's no longer as
hard just treated as part of your input.
Okay. So I just want to point this out
explicitly. Um because as a student I
know many students will this you you'll
keep getting you'll find yourself
thinking about you'll get what's going
on here just to remember okay if there's
something you don't quite understand
think if you can see if you can think
like it like an expectation if you're
happy with it when it's an expectation
just say std expectation to examples we
did this before for example we tal we
gave you homework problems when you're
working about thinking about data
augmentation right we added noise to you
this is like it's treating this
expectation remember it's just that
again.
So we've warmed you up to accept this.
Okay. So I want to spend a little bit of
time talking about how these tricks are
useful beyond this VAE setting. Um we're
going to use them more when we talk
about post training, but I want to make
sure you understand it's not just about
post training.
So one thing that you may or may not
have heard about um is quantization
aware training.
So what's quantization aware training?
Uh let me uh rather than giving you all
the text I'll just like talk what the
problem is first. So quantization aware
training is a very practical problem. It
says in real life when you have these
models that are big. So when people saw
these models when they got big were
having high performance they became a
real question of how big of a model can
you run? So you have a laptop how big of
an LM can you run on your laptop?
So the the difference between using
floats float 32 and using int4 which is
a four bit integer. So four bit 16 only
16 values. It's like okay four bit
integers are a lot less expressive but
they're a lot smaller.
So I could fit a model that's eight
times larger
than 30 floats. So it's a big deal,
right? Also, the GPUs can do the
processing on 4bit a lot faster than
they can do processing. So I can do
mixed precision. So there's lots of
reasons to want to use lower precision
practically once big models become a
thing. Before big models are a thing,
it's not a big deal. But big models are
a thing. So it is a big deal. So now the
question is how are you going to get a
model to fit on a constrained piece of
hardware?
old style was you trained the model some
way and then you said okay now I'm going
to quantize it and just straight up
quantized it took all the values and
quantized it then it was like oh wait
this doesn't work that well when I go to
drastic levels of quantization so what
can I do one way that people used to do
it was they would take the model and
then progressively quantize it and
fine-tune it on data after being
quantized to make sure it was like still
working okay to shape it a bit
quantization aware training was That
idea was that if I'm going to be
training a model, so it's going to be
quantized, is there anything I can do
during training that will make it better
at being quantized.
And so the idea is the best thing I'd
like to do is to train how I'm going to
test, right? So I'd like to quantize it
during training, but that's absurd. I
can't quantize it during training
because if I the quantization step,
rounding is not differentiable.
Does everyone see this? This is the
problem. So the idea was how do you have
your cake and eat it too, right? And the
way you do it is you say that during
training I'm going to stay in high
precision
so I can do the training
but when I do the forward pass I will
quantize my 32-bit numbers down to in 16
in 8 you know or you know four bit
floats whatever I'll do the quantization
in the forward pass.
So the actual action will be of the
quantized weights.
But now this is not differentiable. So
what am I going to do? I'm going to say
I can think about quantization as adding
noise.
And then I'll just pass the I'll just
pass the gradients straight back through
it
as though it were differentiable as
though it was just the identity.
Okay. So I'll conceptually I'll say I'll
take quantization treat like additive
noise
then I'll just have the gradients pass
on the additive part they'll go to the
noise and the noise will tank it doesn't
have any gradients on that nothing no
effect and it'll just pass through I do
that
this approach helps and current models
that are um used do this because they
know they're going to be quantized I
think the Kimmy paper and many of The
latest papers talk about how they
explicitly do this during their
training.
Okay, any questions? You see how this is
the application of the same idea. Once I
can think about sampling by adding
noise, I can think about other things
that I conceptualizes adding noise like
quantization which is in DSP thought
about as a way of adding of noise along
with rescaling and I can just treat it
the same way.
Very practically important. In homework,
you saw how the same ideas can be used
to do deal with non-ifferiable losses
which we're going to talk about next.
All of these ideas are useful across the
board. We'll we'll be hitting this. So
that's why VAS are a good place to teach
start for teaching. Like lots of ideas I
can introduce in a simple setting.
Okay. Now I want to switch in accelerate
a little bit ahead of the schedule that
we posted on the website because I want
to give myself more time. Um start
talking about uh post training ideas
because they're very very important. Um
so let's see if we can start doing that.
Okay. So my goal is to help you
understand post training including
what's called RLVR which is the e easier
way to understand things and from my
perspective for you and the students in
the class we would we would like is we
would like you to understand um RLVR
first because it's easier to understand
and then think about RLHF which is
reinforcement learning from human
feedback as tweaks on RLVR as opposed to
historic the historical order of
development.
This is easier to understand.
So
let's think about the problem. Remember
we had this basic approach of doing uh
supervised fine-tuning for instruction
following. Remember we had a model, we
pre-trained it with next token
prediction um on corpuses of natural
text. Uh and then we want to make it so
it actually answers questions. Question
answering is not that well represented
in natural text. So we have new
supervised examples which have questions
prompt tokens and answers that we want
and we just train the model to answer
these questions and don't train it on
generating the questions themselves.
There's no reason to do that just on the
answering. So you do this kind of thing
for instruction following.
So this everyone remembers this.
Okay, great. So when people did this,
when the in the sort of wild era of
human prompt optimization, people
discovered that if you told the model to
think step by step, it would give better
answers
because in this training data when it
saw let me think about this step by
step, it saw a bunch of steps written
out and so it starts doing that and then
by following the steps bit by bit, it
could get better answers. Okay, this is
called chain of thought.
So because of the fact that people saw
that it's good to have chin of thought
prompting was working to make better
answers, people said, you know what,
even in our pre-training mix, we should
have more examples that look like this,
that have stuff worked out step by step.
And so you generate synthetic examples
that look like this. So you add that to
your pre-training mix.
Okay, so this is the reality of actual
uh training today doesn't cleanly divide
into pre-training and post-training.
It's like shades. There's pre-training
and there's like something called
mid-training where people will adjust
the mix of data to have more of this
kind of stuff mixed in that it's going
to see and then shifting into you know
post-training afterwards. So this is all
stuff that people do.
Okay. So now the question becomes how
can we make a model better at solving
problems beyond just doing this.
So this is supervised fine-tuning only
so far
and um historically this is sort of if
you go back to
uh the first model that kind of broke
this door wide open was fall 24 the
introduction of
uh GPT 401.
Okay, GPD 401 was what was the first
kind of thinking model, reasoning model
which was trained in a way that got made
it better at solving problems using
techniques related to RLVR
that was followed. It was a black box.
Although we saw talks um at Berkeley um
by Sebc uh who basically hinted very
strongly in the talks that we can't tell
you how you do it but just do the thing
you think you'd do right and that works
okay are you doing this he goes no we
just do the simple thing this answers
the question I can't tell you what that
is well the deepseek paper came out
which told us what that was and
demonstrated working at scale so people
some speculation but then the Deep Seek
paper kind of nailed it for everybody.
So what people did a little bit of
history is useful. People
said that you could do this RLVR
technique which is reinforcement
learning with verifiable words. I'll
explain what that is later to make
things better at solving problems. Um
the key was to have problems that had
verifiable answers and to practice on
them like math problems and coding
problems
where you could tell the answer was
right. Um
but when people did this uh a very
important question emerged right and
very important parts like how you think
about it. So it was that there's
actually two different dimensions to
this.
First is
you have to be willing to spend more
compute while answering.
Okay, that was already present in
hindsight in chain of thought where you
asked the model not to give the answer
immediately but to think it out. So
you're spending more compute generating
these tokens of chain of thought and
then reading the answer. So this became
more one very important times. This is
called test time. Compute scaling is the
name people use for this.
Just uh write that out
test time compute.
And the other is given that you're
willing to spend more compute while
answering do this test and compute. How
do you train the model to be better at
using this?
Okay. And the RLVR is about this part.
But this is also a very key ingredient.
So intellectually
uh a question emerged which was how much
of the gains are coming from this part
by itself and how many are how much is
coming from this part. You see that like
it's important to know and whether
there's a way of playing with this
bounds.
So let's think about just test time
compute a bit first, right? And I'm
actually probably not even going to get
to in this lecture the RLVR part, which
is fine. Um, but I want to kind of spend
a little bit more time on the test time
compute. It was already mentioned. So
um, just want to recap some of it and
kind of go beyond.
The oldest approach is just pure
prompting. You know, this classic chain
of thought. You add think step by step,
be careful, stuff like this. Check your
answers. just things that make it
generate more tokens.
Okay, good. Next,
next simplest approach says
don't solve the problem once,
right? Solve the problem n times. So
just run many many many many
generations.
Okay. So there's a problem that I want
to recognize here with uh making many
many many generations which is
if you're evaluating how well can the
model solve the problem
uh if you do many generations and you
know the right answer you can ask how
many of those generations got the right
answer. Does everyone see that?
And so that's certainly you can do that
if I know the right answer. But there's
also the problem of if I'm going to use
the model at inference time when I don't
know the right answer, if I generate it
a thousand times,
what do I actually give to the user?
Does everyone see this? Or what do I
actually use?
Okay, so there's a difference here
between at training when I know the
right answer, I can grade all of those n
and I can ask the question, were any of
them right? um and at inference time we
have to give some answer. So if the
answer so for this thing there's a
couple of choices that one can do. I'm I
want to note those down
at inference time.
One is
I can take majority vote.
So for certain kinds of questions like
multiple choice or where there's a
numerical answer that's in a very small
set, I can just say, well, I have n
generations.
What did the crowd want? majority, you
know, does everyone see that? I'll pick
that one. That's a way of resolving it.
So, okay, that that's one thing. Uh
there modifications thereof. There's
many modifications of this that people
do. Um I can only touch the surface. You
can talk you can see people talking
about how they use different LLMs to
rate the generations and critique them
and then take majority vote. So, if I
can't If if I want to create a story,
okay, and I want to say pick the best
story, I can't take majority vote. Every
story is different. What can I do? I
could ask an LLM to rate the stories
and then choose the one that had the
highest rating. Do you see that? So,
I've turned a problem of I can't have a
majority into add a greater and then
take the majority over the graders.
Okay? Okay, so people have all kinds of
tricks that they do um to to do this
very useful in practice large set. Then
you can have well maybe I could make
them discuss with each other. So I have
graders talking to graders over and over
again and building consensus and then
choosing the response that's the highest
consensus. Then I have I do this and
then I feed that back and say make a
better one based on this. Lots and lots
of prompt engineering here that can be
done. But just you should be aware of
it. All of this is in the category of
test time compute.
But from a mathy point of view, there's
another thing you can do
and this is related uh to what you guys
saw with this beam search idea. Okay, I
you saw it in discussion. I want to
recap it here. Um
the LM isn't just generating these
sequences, it's also evaluating their
probability for you,
right? because it's sampled according.
So you know the actual probability it
assigned to that sequence.
So you could instead of taking the
majority or plurality vote you could
just choose the highest probability one.
You see that I do a thousand
generations. I see as a sequence which
is the one that had the highest
probability
and say maybe that's the one you like
the best.
See that? Okay.
So
once you think about this idea of taking
the highest probability there becomes
this question of maybe I can sample from
the distribution that the LM is
generating in a different way.
This can be thought of as a way of doing
a different different distribution
different sampling right? So instead of
just sampling I sample a thousand times
and I pick the highest probability one.
But maybe there's other approaches like
that. Yeah.
>> When you say pick the highest
probability, what do you mean? Like you
mean as a sequence you go through and
you look at the probability of the next
as you march through and then like you
add them all together or
>> Yeah. So exactly what I think highest
probability. I say remember this thing
is generating basically a conditional
probability distribution. It says at
every step what's the probability of the
next token given all the previous tokens
and then I sample from that
distribution. Then I compute again
what's the probability of the next token
given all the previous tokens. Sample
from that. So I'm generating the
sequence of probabilities. I can
multiply them together or I can take the
log and add them together. Same thing.
So I can just pick the one that's the
highest probability.
It's like it's a kind of majority vote
style thing except it's acting on the
probability and it's saying that the
model probabilities are also a kind of
grade.
Okay.
So this became interesting because
people observed that when you did RL
post training on the model, they made
this interesting observation. You do RL
post training on the model to make it
generate better things. And they asked,
let me ask the original model what the
probabilities are for the generations
out of the RL post-trained model.
And people observed that actually the
generations from an RL post-trained
model seem to be among the higher
probability sequences
of the original model. They rate they
rate higher. They're distributionally
different than just sampling from the
original. It's as though the RL post
training is moving probability around
which it clearly is. That's all you're
doing in training is moving probability
around. So it's moving probability
around towards places that already had
higher probability.
So this is philosophically interesting
because there's this big open question
of can you in uh post training get
things to learn new capabilities or are
you just refining and sharpening the
capabilities that the base model already
had
and making it not be embarrassing,
right? Um or like can you get new
things? Very important question. you
know trillions of dollar type of
question. So people are interested. Yeah
>> I know they use like KL divergence or
like other similarity methods when they
do I know at least RHF I'm not sure
about RV.
>> So is this just like an an efficient way
of moving probability within some
constraint?
>> Yeah that's a great question. So when I
talk about the way one does RLVR and
RLHF u one of the things that people do
during training is they put a KL
divergence regularizer that makes your
probabilities not move very far. So one
could say this is a consequence of that
regularizer. This is an active area of
research right now. People are very
interested. You'll see this when I start
talking about some of the papers. So
here here's a paper that's very
interesting October 16th. Okay. So
this paper um by carindu
says that
how much oomph can you get by just
thinking about sampling alone don't
don't try any RL VR
just play with the sampling
can I sample from a model in a way that
gives me better answers based on the
observation that it seemed that the RLVR
models We're actually sampling higher
higher probability spaces distribution
parts of the space.
Okay, so here's the thinking intuition.
You want a good answer that includes
some thinking.
If you're sampling from the original
model that you're trained on, what can
go wrong? Remember, auto reggressive
generation moves step by step forward.
Okay, so as it moves step by step
forward, it could choose something that
was the wrong step.
Okay, it makes a mistake, right? Could
just be by randomness, right? Sampling
with some temperatures. This is the most
likely thing here is four. I'm just
going to say three, but now it's
committed. Three is in the context,
right? So it has to like keep going. So
one thing that people observed is that
if you make a mistake after the mistake
the model might flounder it's like ah
you know I don't know what to do right
and so that manifests sometimes as whole
bunches of tokens that are all low
probability
so when you saw a beam search you saw a
one way of kind of getting around that
is to say look I'm going to keep doing
the generations but then I will pick
higher likelihood sequences
So
that's the older approach and
the point of it is to sample not from
the original sequences original
distribution but sample
disproportionately from the higher
likelihood sequences. That's what beam
search is trying to do. That's what best
of n is trying to do if you do this
highest probability. The question is are
there other ways of doing this? And the
answer is yeah there is. And one way of
doing this is to say
instead of sampling from the original
distribution, I'll sample from the
distribution raised to the power four.
Okay? Why? Probabilities are numbers
between 0 and one. If you raise them to
a power, you shrink them.
And so bigger numbers will survive
longer than small numbers when being
exponentiated being raised multiplied by
each other over and over again. So by
raising a probability to a power I'm
favoring higher probability and I'm
disfavoring lower probability.
This is also a very important thing
connected in probability to something
called tilting of distributions.
Okay. So in probability if you want to
sample from a distribution you can also
sample from a tilted distribution. This
is related to temperature. That all
these ideas are connected to each other.
Um although I'm not sure you've seen
tilting of distributions in your
previous classes. Has anyone seen
previous classes? No. They come from the
natural if you do a kalebased
regularization or penalty term and then
do lrange multipliers you will see
tilting emerge naturally as the thing
that happens. But that's one way you can
see it.
This is sometimes done in information
theory classes. Um, but all you need to
know here is that raising something to a
power weighs up high probability and
weighs down low probability.
So there's a question which is in the
paper and I'm running out of time. Is is
this just like low temperature sampling?
So low temperature sampling is
effectively raising the probability for
a given token to a power.
Remember the temperature is like a one
over term. Um
but what you care is not individual
tokens, it's the sequences.
Okay. So I don't have I'm out of time.
It's fine. I will continue this. Uh
what they find in the paper is that you
can use other techniques associated with
something that's called um marov chain
Monte Carlo. Okay, which allows you to
sample from a distribution you don't
have access to. It's also useful from a
teaching point of view because it
introduces ideas that I'm going to I'm
going to find useful um related to
important sampling. But what it does is
it's another technique that lets you say
if I can't sample from a distri if I
only have access not to the distribution
I want but to something that's
proportional to it raising to a power I
have you have to do the normalization.
So that's why you don't have the
distribution.
Then can I take lots of samples of some
other distribution that's not the
distribution I want and get approximate
samples from the distribution that I
actually want.
This is another kind of test time
compute. And what they find this paper
I'll assume just just to end on
something is they did an experiment
where they said on certain benchmarks
they took quen
and they said base model is this and you
do deepseeek style training on it GRPO
and you get to 78.5 on this benchmark.
You just do sampling raising to the
power four in some approximate way that
already boosts your accuracy close.
No, no training at all. Same thing on a
different evaluation
competitive. And on held out evaluations
that weren't trained for, there's this
transferability of RL knowledge that no
one cares about RL tuning for math. They
care about that transferring to other
things. this also transfers and
transfers better. So this opened up a
new avenue current extremely current
avenue of research of trying to tease
apart what's the difference between
uh sampling and not I'll come back to
this next time and then move into RLVR.
Okay, so end here. Sorry for going a
little bit over.