[clears throat] Okay,
>> Berkeley time. Let's get started.
So, we're going to continue talking
about attention today and then talk
about transformer architectures and
finally conclude with talking about
positional encoding which is a a big
part of these transformer architectures.
So just to recap where we were last
time, we started out with talking about
these sequencetose sequence problems
particularly in the context of RNN's and
we talked about a um
setup like this where I have a series of
uh RNN blocks here. This is unrolled in
time. Again I think I should just
highlight this.
This is the time axis X- axis. This is
the layer axis.
Okay. So [snorts] here we're showing
this unrolled in time
and our motivation was to realize that
in this kind of encoder decoder
architecture there's this bottleneck and
we had to pass all this information
through this one state and that was a
problem right because that made if you
wanted to pass a lot of information that
would make the state very big making the
state very big makes things difficult to
trade we don't like that so we wanted to
have a better mechanism by which we can
think about um you know information in
terms of time. Okay. And we wanted to be
able to pass that forward. So just as a
reminder these things um there was a
point here. So these are things when I'm
feeding when I'm doing this auto
reggressive generation I'm sampling. So
uh I forgot to talk about that carefully
last time but [snorts]
thank for so thank you for the question.
But basically we're generating
probabilities and then we're sampling
from that to be able to get um the input
to the next u next time step. Also we're
training this basically all with a cross
entropy loss. Right? So we're training
on the uh output probabilities of this
and we talked about this teacher forcing
idea for uh for training these things.
Okay.
All of this basically led us to be able
to think about this idea of attention.
And we talked first about this idea of
cross attention, right? So we want to
have
keys and values basically that are
containing information about whatever
our context is. And then we have a query
coming in and we want to be able to
understand well which of the keys and
their associated values are the ones
that are relevant to us. And for this we
wanted to have some kind of similarity
score between the query and the key. so
that we can understand where we should
pay attention to. Okay, everyone
remember this kind of setup that we
talked about.
Okay, any questions about this? Cuz I I
went a little bit fast at the end
because I was running out of time. So,
I'm going to go do a little bit of that
a little bit slowly in [snorts] a few
minutes here. But any questions? Yes. to
calculate you. Are you uh feeding input
or are you feeding the input for the
different from the input for the encoder
>> to calculate the query? Am I I'm I'm
feeding the input, but I will I will
first my first layer in a transformer
will actually be an embedding layer. And
so we'll come to that. Um but I'm so I'm
I'm taking my my input which will be
we'll talk about this it'll be one hot
encoded then I'll move it into the
embedding dimension and that was what
will go into my um query computation.
>> Yes.
>> And the W's are the weight matrices for
key query and
>> W K WQ and WV are the weight matrices.
These are learned. Remember, we want to
be able to have when we talked about our
attention mechanism, we talked about
well, we want to be able to basically
somehow identify which values are
relevant to us. And we want to be able
to say we want to have nicely gradients
passed through this so that we can
actually learn these things. But we
never really talked about how to get the
Q and the K and the V, right? We just
assume that we had these and then what
do we do with that? So, we want to be
able to learn these queries, QES, and
values. And to be able to learn them, we
learn them basically as these linear
transformations of the inputs.
[snorts]
Okay,
good.
So to be precise, how we calculate this
is let's say I have my query vector
which is some bias term which I hadn't
really talked about but there's often a
bias term here that is also learned uh
times this weight matrix Q and then
times your um input here I'm calling it
XN [snorts] then your key is again your
key your bias for your key plus your
weight matrix for your key times
whatever your input is
and then you have a corresponding value
that is again similarly learned. Okay,
beta Q, beta K, beta V, WQ, WK, WV are
all learnable.
Okay, and gradient descent is what is
going to decide what the entries of this
are.
Good.
>> Yes. Question. What does it mean to have
the keys and the values from the encoder
and the queries from the decoder for
positive?
>> What does it mean? Okay, let's talk
about this. What does it mean to have
the keys and the values from the encoder
and queries from the decoder? [snorts]
So, let's look
here at this picture.
So, this is not the transformer
architecture. We'll come to that in just
a minute.
What we're saying is that we're putting
in inputs that are so my my think my
target task is translation right so
let's say I am translating
um some sentence the cow jumped over the
moon okay and I have something uh I have
some output that now I want to um and I
want to translate this into some
language
so the encoder is taking the origin
language anguage in this case English
and let's say I'm translating to some
other uh other language. The cow jumped
over the moon. The encoder is going to
take this process this and generate
uh keys and values for this. Okay, for
this input
now when I'm at the decoder stage what
I'm going to do is if I'm doing training
I will have the uh target output right
and what I'm doing there is I've shifted
everything. So I'm putting in my first
thing is a start
token right. So whatever the decoder
generates some query start is my first
thing that is my first query. Now I want
to see what should start look at.
So what it's going to look at it's going
to look at the keys and the values that
have been generated by the encoder for
the input sentence because start needs
to know that I am jump translating the
sentence the cow jumped over the moon.
So it is looking at that entire sentence
the keys generated by that sentence
to then generate whatever the intention
matrix is and go forward. Does that make
sense? So then then you have the second
thing then it goes in and then you move
on.
>> Yes. Question
>> are the weight matrices to learn like
your I guess your keys the same between
both the encoder and decoder or does
each one have its own like key? they
have their own key matrix matrices and
they and in fact I mean that's one of
the things in in multi head attention
you in fact will have within the encoder
you will have multiple query matrices
multiple uh key matrices so on and so
forth because there's value in having
these be uh having these be separate
does that answer your question okay so
we talked about so this this is this
cross attention is that basically I'm
When I'm here in my decoder, I'm doing
my translation. I have had my start
token come in or I've had maybe a word
from my target language, whatever
Chinese come in and I want to predict
the next word. I'm looking now back to
my encoder to my input sequence. And
that is why it's called cross attention.
It is looking from the target output
sequence to the input sequence. Okay.
>> [snorts]
>> Self attention on the other hand is
saying okay um I'm translating a
sentence into
uh some language. I guess I only speak
so many languages so I can't really give
general examples but um let's say my
again I'm
uh let's say let's let's say I'm
translating from some unknown language
into English. Okay, English is my target
language just so that I can have an
example that everyone can understand.
But let's say my output is now the cow
jumped over the moon. And let's say I've
generated the and cow and I want to
predict what the uh next word is which
is over. It's relevant for me at the
decoder to look also at what is my
decoder just produced. Right? The fact
that I just produced the and cow is
going to help me produce over. So the
decoder self attention is looking back
at what has been produced historically.
And on the decoder side when we do self
attention we will do causal or masked
self attention because it's not fair to
say I'm going to look at the future of
the sentence
um and then learn to predict right what
I'm going to do is I want to look only
at the past. So I'm going to not allow
myself to look at anything in the
future. On the other hand, when we do
self attention for the encoder side,
there I get my entire input sequence all
at once. So there everything can look at
everything else. Which is why there's
regular self attention which is used in
encoders and there is
masked or causal self attention which is
used in decoders.
Does that make sense? Yes. Question. Um
in typical encoder decoder architectures
are all readers being used at once.
>> In typical encoder decoder architectures
are yes
>> because you will have um just full self
attention in the encoder cross attention
to do the translation task and then mask
self attention so that the decoder knows
what it just said.
>> Yes.
>> Why not have like multiple input tokens
to the decoder and then do self
attention across those? like why only
have one star token? If you can do self
attention in decoder, why not have like
five and then produce five words in
parallel and have them self attend to
each other?
>> So, I'm not sure I'm fully understanding
your idea, but if I understand your
idea, it's like saying, let me have the
start token and then the first word
token and then the second word token and
then the third word token and just say
just produce the third third word out of
nothing just looking at the entire
sequence.
>> Yeah, we'll produce all of them. Um so
the challenge is that you're you want to
in the end put produce one sentence and
now if you produce all of these things
separately you're going to
uh end up with this issue and and at the
end of the day all of these operations
are um like the on the encoder side
you're doing all of this parallelly
anyway on the decoder side you're
waiting to have your to have your input
um but you want to have one coherent
sentence and I guess if you did that you
would have to then do some kind of other
combination to figure out then because
all you're producing now is
probabilities and how do you pick which
probability is where
>> right now you like there's this the
sampling problem now shows up
>> okay
so with that let me just reiterate what
this attention formula is which is that
I'm basically using generating a score
based on how similar my keys and my
values are and then I'm turning that
score into a probability using the
softmax. Okay, and the softmax is just
I'm saying like I'm taking the x of this
and then I'm normalizing.
Okay, but we talked about the fact that
this actually doesn't work right and why
doesn't this work? So if I think about
my embedding dimension
[snorts] for example this is like,024
right is a typical um embedding
dimension that you might have
so this dotproduct is now the sum of a
thousand entries right
and so this has the possibility of
becoming quite big
and in a soft max if I have some numbers
become come very big.
I'm going to end up by kind of
saturating my dynamic range, right? I'm
in the end working in finite precision
floating point. So I don't want to be
saturating things out.
I want to have things that look like a
nice distribution, right?
So how do I make sure that that happens?
So if I'm
taking a sum of let's say each of these
are um approximate let's say each of
these are normalized they're RMS norm
one so it's like I'm adding a bunch of
ones
right so if I look at this this could be
this is something like a thousand
right I have 1* 1 1* 1 I'm adding up I'm
adding up all of these things and I
don't want to have these things get
super
So what's the standard way of
normalizing things? If I have a sum of n
things and I want it to look like a
distribution that I know and love,
what's the what's the thing that we
always use?
CLT, right?
We say that if I have a sum of many iid
things and I want them to look like a
standard normal, what is the right
scaling?
I'm going to use the square root n or
square root the number of things that
I'm adding, right? That gets me things
looking like a nice normal distribution.
So if I was to so I, you know, there's
many different scaling factors I could
choose here, but the CLT is basically
what is suggesting that I should choose
the square root D. I could if I
normalized by D, I risk making
everything too small and not being able
to resolve things.
Square root D hits the exactly the sweet
spot that we want.
And we kind of talked about the scaling
ideas like back when we were talking
about muon right and muup scalings
Xavier initialization all these things
of like making sure things don't get too
big things don't get too small this kind
of same thinking is leading to these
scaling factors and giving us what the
right scaling factor is.
Okay
questions.
Okay, good.
So, we want to prevent these entries of
the softmax from getting too large.
Good. Then we talked about self
attention. Any questions about this
picture?
Basically, you have an input.
You generate your queries, your keys,
and your values.
The queries and the keys generate a
score that give you an attention. And
then the attention gives you the weights
by which you can combine the values
which give you the output.
>> Yes.
>> Uh I think the input of Q and K is
similar. So at that time it's very hard
to distinguish. So the to make the
difference between Q and K it's
so
>> so the sizes of these things are all the
same right. So conceptually the
difference between the queries and the
keys is in some sense all conceptual
because the query is
like what is looking for attention and
the keys are telling you where to give
attention to.
The queries are the questions, right?
They're the queries. Um but they they're
they're all representations of the
input.
Uh but they're trying to do different
things and they're they're they they are
different in that sense.
>> Yeah. Yes.
>> Um as for D so like with multi head
attention are there just going to be
like different embedding sizes
basically?
>> Okay. So yeah let's go to multi head
attention. So multi head attention what
we're saying is look in practice it
turns out that there is value to having
many different kinds of information that
one might want to process right so there
might be some attention that you want to
give in certain
um is you might you just want to be able
to differentiate different kinds of
information
so if I look at this input What I'm
doing is I'm giving it opportunity. So
if I generate like this is this is a
query related to this input that is also
a query related to this input.
This query might want to look at
different parts of the past or or or my
or my neighbors in my context compared
to that query. I'm allowing myself basic
to basically to look at different things
by having different attention heads.
And the important thing to remember is
that I'm going it's important that
whatever my attention does right
whatever the size of the input is the
output had better be the same size. One
simple reason for this is that you want
to add a residual connection. So you
want to come have the input come and add
itself in again. And for that to work
the shapes have to match. Okay. That's
one simple reason.
So if you want to have this output be
the exact same size,
there's only so many degrees of freedom
that you have in terms of how to
distribute your your resources or your
your um I don't want to use the word
attention, but
um and so one way is to say that if I do
multi-head attention, I'm going to give
you know if I have let's say if I do two
head attention, I'm going to give
half of the uh channels to this guy and
half of the channels to this head.
You could do it some other way, but the
standard way is to just distribute them
all evenly.
Okay?
And n is basically the number of my
inputs, right? So the important thing is
that this attention matrix is is n byn.
So that this this works out and you get
this and then you just concatenate
these. So you can have, you know, this
is looking at like the pink stuff. This
is looking at the yellow stuff. This is
looking at each of these is having their
own separate stuff that they're trying
to look at.
>> Yes.
>> What is like the difference for having
like two head and two head attention but
like each one has like a thousand point
then like having one concentrated like
20 20 48
attention. So if I if I had all of these
combined into a picture like this,
right? Then
I'm only basically I'm not allowing the
different channels that I have. So every
you know I have I have multiple channels
per
uh per input token
and by having multi head attention I'm
allowing different parts of that
embedding vector to focus on possibly
different things
right I have a24 dimensions where I can
store information
and if all 24 of those dimensions said
that okay you have to pay attention to
the third and the eighth token
because that's how my attention matrix
worked out. Then all of those will have
to do this. But what this allows you to
do is that I can have um this like I can
say that okay the first 10 channels you
pay attention to the third tok to token
and then the next 10 channels you pay
attention to the eighth token and the
next 10 channels you pay attention to
the 25th token and you can do these kind
of different different things. things.
It allows you to have a finer
granularity of representation of
information within that embedding
dimension within your channels. That's
what this these multi heads get by you
as opposed to just one thing where you
have all those dimensions but they're
all doing the same thing.
Does that Yeah.
>> Is there a convention around like how
many heads you want to have in your
multi head attention or is that just
sort of like a hyperparameter you mess
with for a while? I think that that's
just a hyperparameter you mess with for
a while. People have tried different
things and intuitively there's a
trade-off between like just spreading
too thin versus and not having enough
representational capacity versus
collapsing everything into one thing and
like losing things to averaging. So um I
don't know if there's any obvious rules
of thumb of what to do
but I am going to try and talk about
different architectures in the next
lecture. So maybe by next lecture I will
have a better answer to that. Yes.
>> Uh when you do the concatenation for
multi head does the order matters? Which
one is on top? Which one is
>> when you do the concatenation for multi
head? It does matter. You want to have
kind of you want to preserve the
ordering. you're not going to mix up the
ordering because you want to I mean one
way to think about it is that you're we
have this intuition in convolutional
neural nets of like uh channel-wise
convolutions right or depthwise
convolutions so like you can have one
channel of information and if it it
keeps process like it's doing its thing
>> yes
>> so when you are multi do you split the
input like do you
>> yes so I'm splitting the input I'm
literally saying look
this is my input this is my D this is my
embedding position this is 1 124 okay
I'm going to send 512 of you to this
attention head and 512 of you to this
attention head each of you are going to
produce 512
components and then I'm going to
concatenate those together to get my
output
does that make sense
Yes. Uh
>> wouldn't it be better to like just allow
all of our heads to like look at the
entire input and they can like choose
which parts of the input to look at?
Wouldn't it be better to allow ah so
you're saying that instead of having you
know having this d over 2d over2 just
have a dlength attention head here and d
here and d here and d here look at the
whole thing and just have many many
attention heads that are all looking at
the entire vector as opposed to just
half of the vector.
>> So so the output that they're giving is
still d over h but
>> but they're looking at half of it. So
looking at the whole thing that would
make that I I can see how that would
make sense. One of the reasons to do
this is computational efficiency like
you know that then you have bigger
matrix multiplies you have more stuff to
do. So one like one motivation for
splitting this is so that you're you're
kind of keeping the total computation
the same.
Uh
so it's an easier it's an easier apples
to apples comparison.
Yeah
but you it makes sense that if you had
more stuff you could you could do that.
>> Yes. I had was also that by splitting
the multi head you introduce like an
inductive bias towards specialization
right which because I think what he's
describing is what you just get if you
have a single big attention right is it
just everything depends on everything
unless that's maybe not what he's saying
>> um I mean you don't know what what is
happening under the hood right it's
conceivable that if I gave you the full
vector you could choose to ignore half
the channels if that was what was
important to you these networks
typically don't do that. But um
I have I have I don't know anything that
says that this is Yeah, it it might be.
But I I um
I I guess I don't I think there is
probably some inductive bias to her
specialization and maybe there's been
work that has looked at this. I don't
know necessarily
of that, but I don't think that giving
everything to everyone would necessarily
push you away from specialization. I
think that the capacity and possibility
for specialization still would remain if
you had multiple induction heads still
with a large
uh like with the whole embedding
dimension available to it is my
intuition but that's just my intuition.
>> Yes. Um, I often see in the attention
literature that people do an MLP after
the concatenation to mix like to uh
allow for all of the different channels
that were that were split up to
>> the transformer will have that. Yes.
Yeah,
>> it it's coming.
>> Yeah. Yeah. So, is there any reason not
to do that beforehand to kind of do the
same thing? So like to allow an MLP to
project from D into D over H for each of
the heads to be able to mix the input
channels before doing attention.
Is it just the scalability cuz
>> that's what the key matrices
>> no cuz the query and key matrices only
get to CD over H like you you split them
before but couldn't you do that as a
projection rather than
>> so you want to put an MLP here.
>> Yes.
to project into D from D to D over H and
then so that each head can mix from the
input channels. I guess
>> I guess so I guess you could add MLPS in
many places but the thing is that um
then you're you're adding computation
for necessarily unclear what the um gain
is. The nice thing about this is that it
can it's being done all in parallel.
You're not waiting on on anything.
Okay,
so
with that, just a couple of uh things
that I wanted to point out. I uh didn't
really get to talk about this last time,
but nowadays people don't necessarily
just use self attention or cross
attention. The most common thing that
people use is multi-query attention and
multi-query group attention. And
basically you're using the same keys and
values throughout, right? And you're
only changing the query for each head in
multi head attention.
So you're not recmputing the keys and
the values. And that's that helps.
A variation on that is to do multi-query
group attention. So instead of saying
that, okay, I'm not going to compute the
keys and the values for everything, but
I'm going to have these three heads have
the same keys and values and these three
other heads have the same keys and
values. So I group them so that groups
of the heads have the same keys and
values. Um but I allow some variation in
them. And again these are just different
ways of getting basically computational
efficiency in terms of uh getting these
things to work faster. Yes.
>> Why is it okay to reuse keys and values
but not queries?
but not queries? Because the keys and
values are kind of what has happened
already in some sense, right? and I'm
looking at the context. So the context
is represented some way. It is what it
is. But maybe I'm asking diff by having
a differentiation in the query. I'm
allowing different perspectives of
myself to interact with those. If I just
had the same everything, then what's the
point of having multiple heads?
Okay.
So with that now um
let's come to this basic building block
or basic transformer architecture. Okay.
So this is a picture that you're
probably going to see online a lot
probably. How many people have seen this
picture somewhere right? Like this is
[snorts] so this is the famous figure
one from the attention is all your all
you need paper and this is the first
transformer architecture that was
proposed. There are now variations that
have happened from this and it's been
modified quite a bit but this is the
kind of key um thing and so we're going
to try to walk through this uh one by
one. Okay.
So you have the inputs here and
the inputs then go through an input
embedding layer. Okay. And I'm going to
talk about this input embedding layer in
maybe 10 minutes. So hold questions
about that. [snorts]
Um
then comes this
positional encoding.
Okay, I'm going to talk about this in 15
minutes. So hold questions about that as
well. [snorts]
Um but then what you have is basically
you have this multi head attention
coming here and you have this residual
connection that is going into an add and
norm block. So this is the normalization
block. So what happens is that you have
this whatever this X is here it comes
and gets added in and then the whole
thing gets normalized. Okay. And then
you go into an MLP and again you have
this come in and then the whole thing
gets normalized. Okay. This is your
encoder block.
So what you see here is that why this
paper is called attention all you need
is that they have removed any state
right? There's now no RNN.
There is nothing that is remembering the
past explicitly. There's no state.
There's no recursive recurrence
operation there at all. And so instead,
it's just replaced with these attention
blocks. Which is why this paper is
called attention is all you need.
Because previously, attention blocks
were used in addition to recurrent
blocks in recurrent neural networks.
Make sense?
And so here in the first in this
attention, I believe there were six such
enclos. So you have six of these stacked
on top of each other.
And then you take the output of the last
encoder
and encoder block, not the last encoder.
This whole thing is the encoder. I have
six of these.
NX means that they're they're just
saying that do this n times where n is
in this paper equal to six.
And then you feed that
to have cross attention for the uh
decoder part. Okay. And what the decoder
is doing is now I have these outputs,
right? I'm doing translation. So at
training time I actually have outputs
coming in and they're again going
through uh a multi head uh attention
first and then they're going into this
cross attention block where now they're
looking at what has come out of the
encoder and then they're going into an
MLP. Okay. So at the decoder you have
first a self attention block. It's
masked so you cannot look at the future.
You can only look at the past. Then you
have a cross attention with what has
come in from the encoder and then you
have the MLP.
Okay. And this picture is a little bit
confusing but what I want to point out
it it is not every layer of the encoder
that is connecting to every layer of the
decoder but it is just the last layer of
the encoder that is connecting to every
layer of the decoder.
Okay.
And then from here you have a linear
layer that then gives you your scores
for each of your target words. And then
you have a soft max and that gives you
your output probabilities. And of course
when you're running this at inference
time, you know, all that's going in here
is a start token. There's nothing else.
>> Yes.
>> If this works so well, why did it take
so long for people to realize you don't
need the RNN components?
Everything is simple in hindsight.
Um that's like this is just once you
understand something it makes sense. But
uh
innovation takes time like that's just
I [laughter]
yeah it takes time uh and you have to
you have to think through things. I
don't know why this was the particular
sequence of uh ways in which things
worked out but yeah
>> wait sorry this already but what is
mean
>> just an MLP
>> one second
>> you say only the last encoder is
connected to the uh all the decoders yes
>> for the cross correlation right what
about the the previous encoder are they
connected to?
>> So the previous encoder is like think
about this this way, right? So I have
basically I have my input coming in
and then I have block one,
block two,
block six, right? So I have six copies
of this whole thing that stack one on
top of the other. One only feeds to two.
two only feeds to three and then six
goes to decoder.
Does that make sense?
>> Yes.
>> Six goes to each block.
>> Six goes to each block of the decoder.
So six goes to um I can
six goes to here and here and here and
here and here everywhere in the decoder.
>> Yes. So in the part where like the the
last the sixth encoder goes to the
decoder we also have the like the
decoder multi attention goes to that
multi attention as well then how does
that like work
>> I'm not sure I'm understanding the
question so
>> the yeah in that three arrow part three
arrow part yeah how does that work
>> so this is the keys and the values are
coming in from the encoder and the
queries are coming from the decoder
right so this is cross attention
so here The here the car queries keys
and values are all just based on the
decoder. So this is self attention. This
is the cross attention part.
And for for cross attention part is done
individually for each decoder, right? Or
alternate physics.
>> Uh I'm not sure I'm understanding your
question.
>> For the cross uh for the cross
individually for each
>> so each decoder block. Yeah. The decoder
has six blocks. Each of them has
separate weights, separate things,
separate parameters that are learned
separately, independently. They're not
the same over and over again.
>> Yes.
>> We still need to make encoders and
decoders have the same numbers of layers
because now you only take
>> No, you don't need to have necessarily
>> I mean in fact like now there's modern
architectures that are encoder only or
decoder only, right? So, and we'll talk
about this, but yes, but you don't need
to have them necessarily be the same
because here, for example, it's not like
there's a correspondence. It's not like
it just so happens here that there were
six encoder layers and six decoder
layers. It was the first paper they were
trying something.
>> So, the NXs don't need to be the same.
>> They do not need to be the same in
general for a general transformer
architecture. So for a general
transformer architecture which we will
talk about probably next time. Um a
couple of things to keep in mind is that
here you're noticing that this
normalization is coming after the
attention and the MLP blocks. Uh more
recent architectures now the kind of the
the norm is to put the normalization
before the attention and before the MLP.
And one advantage of this is basically
when you're looking at the path for the
gradient to come through on back prop
here if you put the norm after this the
gradient is hit by the normalization
whereas if you put it before then you
can have this gradient superighway that
doesn't that isn't affected by the
normalization. So these normalization
blocks are now typically before the uh
attention head and before the MLP.
>> Yes. Um, in this image, what's the input
exactly to the mass multipension? Like I
say embedding, but wouldn't it be the
previous decoder block like the output
of the attention?
[clears throat]
>> Sorry, I'm not sure I'm understanding
the
>> so like the input to the mass multi head
attention.
>> Yes.
>> Uh, like wouldn't that have to be
because that would be self attention,
right?
>> Yes. So that would be the output from
the previous decoder block
>> from from not the decoder block the
previous input the previous se sequence
right. So if my
uh so this
remember this n here
and I look at this picture
this n is telling me how many how long
my sequence has been. So if it's just
the first token, there's just one thing
there. If it's two tokens, there's two
things there.
>> So like my my I'm looking at the
previous tokens in the sentence. No, it
has nothing to do with with which
decoder block I'm in.
>> Yes.
>> Why we choose six blocks
better?
>> They liked six.
>> I have no idea. uh but like as you will
see this is just this is the first paper
there's many many different
architectures
okay yes
>> so during inference time do they like
feed whatever output eventually out go
back to the output embedding and goes to
the decoder again
>> during inference time do they feed
>> like the the output from the output
probabilities like the eventual word
coming out of it go back to the Yes.
Yes. Yes. Because you will you will then
you will basically sample from those
probabilities, take whatever it is and
do auto reggressive generation because
the the training is only on next token
prediction.
Okay, good. So, I'm going to skip this
and see if I have time. I'll come back
to it later. But I want to actually talk
about any last questions about this.
We're going to talk about it more.
Um but I want to talk about this
embedding layer. Okay. So this
architecture uh and I'm using this
architecture as an example of the first
transformer architecture. Again like
please note that this is not the one and
only set in stone way to build a
transformer. This is the spirit of it
and there are many variations uh on how
this is done. But I want to talk about
this uh embedding layers. Okay.
So what is our input really coming into
this transformer? Our input is a word
from our vocabulary, right? Or a token
from our vocabulary.
And so this is something for example a
size for a vocabulary. It can be much
larger than this. But let's say it's
like 32,000, right? Is the size of your
vocabulary. So what does that mean in
terms of inputs? What is coming in? What
is coming in is a 32,000 long vector
that is one hot encoded. it is telling
me which token is it. Okay, so this is
what my inputs are looking like. If I
have a vocabulary that's 32,000, I have
to somehow represent that in vectors,
right? What is the natural way to do
that? I'm going to take a one hot
encodic. Does that make sense to
everyone?
I do not want to be going through with
32,000
length vectors where most of the stuff
is zero, right? I want to somehow have
some a better embedding and a better way
of representing this information.
And that is what this
um input embedding is basically doing.
This input embedding is essentially a
linear layer, right? It's saying take
this 32,000 dimension thing and project
it into something that is smaller
like,024.
Okay, which is a typical embedding
dimension that you might see. Okay.
Similarly, here at the output
you have this linear layer, right? So
everything that's going through this
network like this, like this here, these
are all these thousand dimensional
vectors.
But now I need to produce scores. And
how many scores do I need to produce?
32,000. Right? I need to know what is
the most likely next token from my
vocabulary. So again, I need a way of go
taking a thousand dimensional thing and
converting it into a 32,000dimensional
thing.
That's what this linear layer is doing.
Okay, everyone with me till here? Okay.
So now
when I think about this, how how am I
going to think about what these what
these input embeddings um should be and
how do I really um uh go about doing
them? So when I have this input coming
in,
I have this 32,000 long vector.
Okay.
But is it like I know that everything
there is essentially zero, right? I only
have this one entry
that is non zero. Most of it is actually
zero. Okay.
I want to be able to get from this an
input to my attention heads that is
essentially something like RMS norm one.
I don't want the entries to be too
small. I don't want the entries to be
too large.
So how do I think this? What does this
tell me about how I'm going to you know
initialize this W uh weight matrix that
is going to uh be my linear layer
essentially. Okay.
So for this matrix or this vector sorry
my RMS norm is essentially like 1 over
32,000 right? But I don't really want to
think about this in the RMS to RMS norm
perspective because now I have this very
strong structure on my input vector,
right? I have this I know that
everything is zero and only one thing is
one. So instead I'm going to think about
this is that if I have this vector here
and I'm it's being hit by a matrix,
the fact that only one of these things
is one means that what this is going to
be doing is it's going to be picking out
a column from this matrix W, right?
So this Y that I'm going to get out is
going to be just basically pulling a
column from here. And so I want to
basically have the columns of this
matrix W to be approximately RMS norm
one. And that will give me the right
kind of properties
uh for my uh for my setup. Does that
make sense to everyone?
Okay, good.
questions.
Um, okay. And then similarly, let's
think about the dembedding, right? Like,
so this this linear layer here is
basically the dmbedding. I've embedded
everything and now I want to expand back
out to my vocabulary to get my
probabilities.
So now I have this dmbedding layer. Now
here I have a very tall matrix because I
have a thousand dimensional vector and
I'm blowing it up into a 32,000
dimensional vector.
And I have a normalization layer right
before. So I have some maybe Q matrix
time alpha equal to beta. And this alpha
has RMS norm one. Okay. And so now we
want to make sure again that the entries
of this thing are not too big. Why do we
want to make sure that the entries of
this vector are not too big? What is
what is what is this 32,000 dimensional
vector going to be an input for?
>> Soft max.
>> The soft max, right? And so what's bad
for softmaxes? Stuff that becomes really
big because then you just saturate and
you don't get any uh information out of
this. Okay. Um I mean eventually you
want to be saturating because eventually
you want to say this is the best token
but at initialization you don't know
what is what. Right? Okay. So this is
like an a variation on the kinds of
exercises we've been doing. So maybe
take a minute and try and do this on
your own just for a break or you can
just chitchat.
But is the question clear?
Right. How how should we think about
initializing this dmbedding matrix?
Yeah.
>> Yeah.
[clears throat]
Because this is this
Yeah.
So now we're right.
So we
want this to have
we want this. So now we're
[music]
probably
not.
>> Okay. So, let me let's talk about this
together.
Okay,
>> so here we're thinking of this guy and
this guy has RMS norm one. And basically
that means that we have approximately
every entry is oneish, right? That's
like kind of the intuition that we have
when we're thinking about this. And so
when we're doing this matrix vector
multiplication, I have a row times this
column, a row time this column, a row
times this column. this row times this
column gives me this entry for this this
vector. So if I want to make sure that
each of these entries now is not too big
right I want to make sure that this is
basically like RMS norm
one over th00and right so that when
I multiply it by this thing this is a
reasonable size and if I have that
initialization then all of these are
going to be coming out roughly similar
size and roughly equal okay so I want
basically each row
of Q
to be
uh RMS approximate
and that will give me the right uh
scaling and [clears throat] I mean one
question that you might have is like why
not think about this in the spectral
norm way that we've been thinking about
right so it turns out that here in this
case because you are going to be
initializing and you're going to be have
this is going to be a tall matrix. So
it's going to be very well conditioned
and so you're going to have um
uh basically no no zero singular values
[clears throat] and all of them are
going to be about the same because of
the fact that if you're initializing
this randomly your singular values are
going to all come from the sums of a lot
of random numbers, right? And so they're
all going to concentrate. They're all
going to be roughly the same. So it's
going to be pretty well conditioned. And
so you can basically have the frobinius
norm be uh just a multiple of the uh
spectral norm because the probinous norm
is all of the singular values squared.
The spectral norm is the top singular
value but all of your singular values
are exactly the same.
Right? So yes the spectral norm thinking
will also give you the uh give you a
similar intuition.
the looking at it row by row is
essentially looking at the probinius
norm instead of looking at the spectral
norm. Okay.
Okay. So this is really just a way of
you know remembering things that we have
been doing and thinking about how we
want to get to um having these things be
well behaved. Okay any questions about
embedding layers and dembedding layers.
So one interesting thing to note is that
um historically
the embedding and the dembedding layers
were often weight shared
um in the sense that it's like well I am
they're they're trying to do the same
thing right they're translating back and
forth from this 32,000 language to the
1000 language
and so these these two things are
they're actually inverses right like you
want to do an inversion operation
but the way it was thought of is that
well you do the transpose which the poor
man's inverse. So let's just put the
transpose there and and h and have these
things be weight shared. Nowadays you
actually end up uh having
different um different embedding
matrices that are that are embedding and
dembedding matrices that are separately
learned. I should mention that when
things were weight shared, you would
often scale the uh input embedding one
uh up a little bit because you have this
extremely sparse vector coming in,
right? And so if you're weight sharing
with something that doesn't have that
kind of sparse vector coming in, you
want to make sure that your scales are
okay. And so you would upscale the uh
the input embedding layer. But these are
all details and these are this is I'm
not going to go into details on it
because nowadays the state-of-the-art is
to actually have independent things that
are learned for the embedding and the
dembedding because in some sense the
transpose is only the poor man's inverse
right and you know having an actual
different allows you to learn the better
inverse in some sense.
>> Yes.
>> Do you typically add a bias or or is it
not in practice like for the embedding?
>> Do you typically add a bias? I don't
think so. Yeah.
>> Yeah.
>> So, we're thinking of like the embedding
vector. You said all the entries are
like on the order of one,
>> right? Or the embedding the I me I the
input vector, right? Whatever the this
this this
alpha vector is basically what is coming
out of here.
Sorry, it's coming out of here. It's
this is this is the D- embedding layer.
And so this has been normalized. So
that's why I'm saying that it's
approximately.
>> So do we also want the output the 32 to
also have each entry be like order of
one or
>> I want it to be order of oneish is right
because I I I'm not I'm not feeding it
into an MLP but I want to have again I
don't want to have huge range or I don't
want to have some things dominating it
because I want to put it into a softmax.
So I guess when you're saying like that
the the rows of Q should be RMS one over
a th00and it's the same as like the
entries of the rows should each be order
of like one over a thousand because when
you add a thousand of them you get one
>> oh should this be one over
so I'm thinking that the RMS norm
of this should be 1 over th00and
So that means every entry
Oh, did I make a mistake? Should this
piece be one over a thousand?
Let me do it out.
So I have basically
let's call this uh I have some q1 * 1 +
q2 * 1 +
uh q1^ 2 q2 q1^ 2 * 1 and I want this to
be about 1.
So I have sigma qi squared to be
about 1 which means that I have
uh qi squared to be about a th00and
which means that I want qi^2
oh 1 over 1. No sorry what am I doing
wrong here? I have 1,00 * this is equal
to 1. Qi square is 1 over 1,00 which
means that qi is approximately 1
over
1000. So I should not say rms. I should
just want every row every entry of Q
should be approximately this is a better
way of writing it.
>> Yeah. Thanks. Is this clear?
>> Yeah. And I was also curious because I
know they originally put this like a one
pot. So it's just a single one and a
bunch of zeros. But now our output it's
a bunch of entries that are each like
one.
>> Yes. Yes. Which is why originally when
there was this weight sharing that was
happening where the embedding and the
dembedding were basically the same
matrix transposed. You would scale up
the input embedding because of the
sparsity of the input vector.
Okay. Good.
So now let's move on to talking about um
positional encoding. Okay.
So there's a couple of different
standard positional encoding strategies
that have been used. Let me talk you to
you first very briefly about the
original positional encoding in this
paper and what this positional encoding
here means. Okay.
And this picture actually kind of is a
is a good caricature of what that is
because the position encoding in the
original setup is basically trying to is
is is is is additive. So what you're
trying to do here is you're trying to
say look when I think about attention
the attention the Q key the Q and the K
and the V m V vectors and the uh
associated weight matrices they're all
just linear operations right I have my
entire input sequence and I'm just doing
a linear transformation
of all of these things I'm not really
paying attention to which was the first
word and which was the second word I
mean it matters in terms of what is hit
by what? But these are all learned
weight vectors,
right? So
should I be thinking about explicitly
somehow telling the model that wait this
was the first word and this was the
second word and this was the third word
because in language order matters. So
how do I additionally encode position?
Right? there's no no longer any state
that is keeping track of the position in
a recurrent network like I have you know
by just running over and over again I'm
keeping track of time in some sense
but now
where am I going to keep track of time
right there's nothing in this attention
I'm executing it all in parallel where
is my time that was the motivation for
these positional encodings okay
how do I tell the
what came first.
And so the desire was to be able to say,
how can I somehow differentiate
between the different input tokens that
are coming in at different times.
The idea what that was in the original
paper was to say okay let us add a
vector to your input so that there will
be some small variation based on where
you were in the in the actual sequence.
And something nice that varies with that
can vary uh with time is basically
taking a suicide or cosine.
And so
what this did was it literally said
let me just add a vector to every single
one of my inputs that has some sinoide
associated with it depending on the time
okay or the the time your position in
the sequence.
That was the highle idea and I'm just
not going to spend too much time on it
because it is now outdated and obsolete
and no one uses it. Um, and it was
proven to be like all of these other
things I'm going to talk about have
superseded this. But this was the highle
original idea and I just wanted to get
that uh to you. There's the Simon Prince
book has a has a nice figure showing
kind of how this uh
what these position embeddings really
look like. But even the book doesn't go
into much detail about it. Okay,
it turned out so that people said,
"Okay, this is interesting.
But
what if we tried something else? What if
we tried another embedding strategy?"
And this embedding strategy was called
nope.
Can you guess what it was based on the
name?
>> No positional embedding. So we said that
okay you know yeah the attention like
maybe just the structure of the
attention itself it does kind of matter
um what your position is because it does
matter which layer of the uh which row
of the matrix you're going to hit uh
will vary based on your uh position your
distance from the start token is yet
another way of keeping track of where
you are right you know that I'm I just
follow the start token because I can
always look at I can always have an
attention that is looking at
uh how far I am from the start token,
right? The start token will always get
encoded. I there will always be a key
for that. And so I can keep track of my
position by looking at my distance from
the start token. So actually attention
has embedded in it a position encoding
already.
And so this motivated people to say like
why don't we just try nope no position
encoding at all. And turns out that this
actually matches performance of the
original per position encoding in many
many cases.
Okay, so once this was realized then
kind of that old position encoding was
simply never used because nope is almost
the same.
Okay,
so nope is the second positional
encoding.
The third position encoding that I want
to talk about. So here nope is just let
me just say no position encoding.
>> I I have a question about that. So does
that did they never try that? Like I
would have imagined that in the
attention is all you need paper that
would be the first thing that you do,
right? It's just not have that.
>> No, unfortunately. And probably like
probably what is to blame is like the
crazy conference deadline pressure,
right? They needed to get a paper out.
Uh I mean I have no idea. I don't know
the authors there. I don't know what
happened. But the way research is done
these days is that you're just trying to
get something out before the deadline
and you're you're rushing rushing
rushing rushing rushing. This kind of
worked. Let's publish it. Right? We're
not doing a systematic controlled
ablation on every single possible thing
that may or may not work. We don't have
time.
Which, you know, is probably not the
right way to be doing things, but uh
this is uh I'm just making the story up.
I don't really know. But that's my
guess.
Okay. So let's now move to the second
idea which is or the third idea which is
learned relative positional encoding.
So one thing that people were thinking
is that okay they they notice that nope
works
but maybe something that could be
important is more so than the absolute
position of whether I'm the third
sentence or the fifth fifth maybe
whether I'm the third token or the fifth
token or whatever maybe what does matter
is am I you know three or four or five
tokens away from you or am I 15 tokens
away from you or am I you know 200
tokens away from you. the relative
positions between tokens maybe matters
more than the
absolute position uh between that I'm
actually at right it doesn't matter that
I'm the 25th word but it does matter
that I just came after a full stop
right so how can we capture this
relativity or the relative position uh
and that was the kind of motivation here
and So the idea was okay the previous
kind of position encoding just tried to
add something directly um in but maybe
what we can do is really just think
about can we modify the attention
mechanism itself somehow to be able to
capture the relative position of a query
in a key. Right? The reason that
positional encodings were added
externally was that the naive attention
didn't have that uh anything about the
indices in that formula itself. Does
everyone see that? So if I think about
just basic attention,
right? Um I was computing a score
basically score
si
of my
uh
query at time t with my key at position
i. And this was divided by this square
root d. This was my score.
Um, query at time t.
I
or ki is
key at position i.
And then from this I had a probability
that I computed which is pi
is e to the si divided by
e to the
let's say sj over j right I used a soft
max to then compute this probability.
Okay. So what learned relative position
encoding said let me modify this
and let me instead say pi
is equal to e to the si
plus
something.
And it'll have to be I'll also have to
add those things to the denominator
because I want to make sure that my
normalization still works out, right? I
still want to have a probability come
out, but I want to modify this
probability that's going to come out and
I want to modify it in a way that
depends on the relative positions.
Okay,
does that make sense to everyone? So, I
want to somehow change this thing.
I don't know how I want to change it
exactly, but I have some idea that I
want to change this in a way that the
relative positions matter.
So, what are we going to do? We don't
know how we want to do it. We just have
some idea that we want to do it. So,
we're going to do the same thing. We're
going to learn the something, right? So
I want to instead of this I want to
write pi is equal to e to the si plus
some I want to call this b uh maybe
shift
and this b shift is a function
of t
and i or t minus i really is the uh what
you want to think about it as Maybe I
shouldn't even say T and I, but I want
to think about T minus I because
I want to say that
I want this B like let's say I'm at
position 10. Okay? And I'm looking at
position 7 behind me. The B for position
10 compared to 7 should be the same as
the B for position 11 compared to 8, 12
compared to 9. Basically everything with
a minus3
should be the same. Everything with a
minus4 should be the same. All I care
about is this relative relative
distance. Okay. So I'm going to weight
share. I'm going to have the same
parameter based on just this difference
t minus i. And I'm gonna learn this
particular um
so I should call this maybe this will be
better if I I should not call this pi I
should call this P of T comma I
and I'll call this
P of T comma I
and here let me label this B
of T minus I
and here this sum is over J
um
E to the SJ + B of T minus J.
Okay.
And these guys I'm just going to learn.
That's why it's called learned relative
position encoding. Okay? Because it
matter cares about the relative position
and you're just learning what that
appropriate factor should be.
>> Yes.
>> So it's a function of just like t minus
i.
>> It's just a function of t minus i. Yeah.
And you want you care about the sign,
right? Because you care it's not
absolute value of t minus i. You care
about whether I was first or whether I
was whether I came first or whether I
came after.
So this will this will go positive and
negative and that matters.
So this learn position em uh embedding
or learned relative position embedding
did outperform the original and did
outperform nope in some cases. It still
wasn't a runaway success but it beat
those things a little bit.
>> Yes. Question practice. What does the
model end up learning from V subshift?
like what does it look like?
>> Um I don't know. I I don't know the
answer to that. I there might be some
pattern. I just don't know the answer.
I'm sure that the original papers that
introduced this will talk about it, but
I don't know. I'm
>> curious if it resembles the signal
pattern of the original
>> I would be very surprised if it did
because I think there's just so many
ways to keep time. Um
>> yes. Is there a reason why we choose to
learn the difference between T and I?
Because um I mean I would imagine maybe
sometimes if you have like an adjective
and another word, it really matters that
you look at like one directly after, but
maybe for let's say a subject and the
object of its verb. It actually matters
more that you don't look at the word
right after it but maybe like the word
to
>> and that will be handled by the
attention mechanism. Right?
This is all this is saying is giving you
a way of saying that
you were [clears throat]
you know it's giving you an option to
depend on
the relative position. So it's not
saying that you have to
uh care about it in some sense
>> that makes sense
>> because you're going to learn it. So in
in the cases in for the attention heads
where the relative position doesn't
matter
these things are going to you know not
be anything you're going to end up being
zeros or close to zero and when it
matters it will adjust like that's magic
of gradient descent.
>> Yes.
>> But how is that going factoring into the
attention mechanism when we're adding it
here in the soft max which is after the
attention?
>> No no this is in the attention score
calculation. This is when I'm
calculating the attention value.
>> This is changing my attention matrix.
>> Okay, I see
>> this changes.
This is not the softmax at the end where
I'm computing uh probabilities.
Good question. Okay. So that brings me
now to the last one which is rope which
is the thing that is now used all the
time. Okay.
Okay. So what is rope?
Basically, we want to somehow modify
the attention calculation
to capture
um
the relative position
and we don't want to learn it. Okay,
that's what like we uh we tried this
learning thing but we want to do better.
Okay.
So what is currently capturing what is
the currently the heart of the attention
mechanism? Well, one thing one way you
can think about it it is that this this
inner product, right? Actually I should
write it as Q K. Not that it matters but
I have this Q of K T at time T times
this or this inner product with uh K at
time I. And I want to modify this
somehow to capture
um this T and this I somehow in
particular T minus I. Okay.
So one thing that kind of that was the
motivation for this or one way to think
about this is that when I think about
this this is an inner product, right?
And the inner product is something that
can that has two components, right? When
I think about the inner product between
two vectors, the inner product between
two vectors depends on the magnitude of
the vectors and also depends on the
angle between the vectors, right? And so
can I somehow modify this inner product
in a way that can maybe pull in the
information about
relative position.
And so the key idea was to think about
let's just think about two dimensions
right so let's say your embedding
dimension is two which will never be the
case but just for a thought experiment
let's say d is equal to two and so I
have my uh my q t1 and my qt2 this is my
two-dimensional
uh vector here
I have this rotation matrix r
I can think of this is cosine let's say
omega - sin omega
sin omega cosine omega right and if I
take a vector and I multiply it by r
what does r do r ro rotates the vector
by omega right
so if I rotated for example so now if I
had let's say I had some Um
if I considered the following if I
considered
RT * QT so I'm going to think about how
I can make this R depend on
an R I * KI.
This is equal to
qt transpose rt transpose
r i ki right this inner product.
And so what is this? Now
this rtranspose ra is basically a
rotation by
omega t minus ome or omega i minus omega
t
right here if I maybe if I should write
this as r t omega t omega t omega t
omega t
rtpose is going by minus omega and r i
is going forward by omega i. So this
rotation now I'm capturing basically
something about the relative position
into this score into this inner product
in the attention calculation itself.
I have I have time right? Yeah. Okay. I
have three whole minutes. People are
coming in. Okay.
So this is the key key idea that
basically we want to be able to exploit
to be able to get relative position
encoding. Okay. So in two dimensions
basically if I choose a particular omega
by choosing different ome by by having a
different value for omega
I can change the relative angle of my Q
and query vector like right and so I can
change whether they're very aligned
which will lead to a high inner product
or whether they're not aligned which
will lead to a low inner product. Okay.
So how does this work in our setup? So
in our setup we have D is not equal to
two. We have a very very very long
vector D. Right?
And what I'm going to do is I'm going to
So this is I these are all my different
channels. And I'm going to break this up
into packs of two. So this is a
two-dimensional vector. This is a
two-dimensional vector. This is a like
I'm going to think of this as 22 222 22
two22 and I'm going to think of each of
these essentially as a complex number
right basically when I think about my
two dimensional vector I can think of
that as a complex number right it has a
it has a magnitude it has a phase um
every vector in the 2D plane is just a
complex number similarly I'm going to
think of this
just as a complex number or a two
dimensional vector what have you and I'm
going to have a rotation matrix
with with a specific omega for each of
these. And now that I and I think about
different channels encoding different
um
different parts of information that's
relevant, I can have certain omegas that
are high frequencies be the ones that,
you know,
uh only are going to care about like
very short-term things and otherwise are
going to decoher. And I'm going to have
other omegas that are going to be lower
frequencies that are like varying very
very slowly. And therefore I can put
information into those channels that are
uh that I want to look at longer term
correlations. Okay. So I feel like I'm
running out of time to go through this
full thing. So I will do it again uh in
a little bit more detail and write out
some equations for you next class. But
the key thing I want you to take away
is, and maybe it'll be helpful for you
for those of you who are like, I forgot
complex numbers. Think about them before
class next time and it'll help us.
>> Yes.
>> Say like um so when you're decoding
this, right? Um I the star token comes
through here, right? And okay, it gets
embedded. It does the norm. You get all
the information. You do the cross
attention. It comes out here, right?
>> And then this
gets like where does there's six of
these layers, right? So that gets fed
back into the next layer.
>> No, no, this goes Yeah. Yeah. Yeah. So
this is like this the output of this
goes to the next layer. Okay. This is
only at the end. These are not
>> Yeah. Yeah. That's I'm just No, I'm just
making sure that this if that is what
you that is what they're like.