Yes, I will announce that
I thought I turned it on. Is it better?
Okay,
wonderful. Okay, so before we start and
jump into lecture, a couple of
administrative things. First, we have
cleared the weight list. This means that
if you are on the wait list and you did
homework zero, you are guaranteed a
spot.
Um, I don't know, and this is true for
both weight list students and concurrent
enrollment students. I do not know if
people have officially been enrolled.
Like, can you show hands if you were on
the wait list and you were officially
enrolled? You got some email or
something? Only one person. Okay, we
enrolled way more than one person. So,
and are there people who are still on
the wait list and are not officially
enrolled? Okay, we are expecting I mean
we've we've done all of the paperwork to
get all of you in.
So, you should be in the class. Um, as
long as you did homework zero.
Okay. Any questions about enrollment
specifically before I start? Because I
know that we have now a timeline before
enrollment
before we had a like there's a clock
ticking on that.
Okay. So keep your eyes out for being
officially enrolled and if you're
somehow not enrolled before the
appropriate deadline, feel free to reach
out to us and let us know and if there's
something we need to do, we will do our
best to to do it. Okay, good.
Um, second thing is that the reason that
we are able to expand is that we were
able to hire three amazing new staff
members. Is anyone here today from the
new staff? No. Joey, okay. Okay. Hey, do
you want to come up?
So, we have three new staff members,
Joey, Lance, and Kevin. Whoops.
Um, Joey, do you want to introduce
yourself? Uh, here. Wait, you can use my
mic.
>> Hello. Oh. Uh, yeah. So, I'm Joey. I'm
currently a P student in like bear. I
mostly do like reinforcement learning
type stuff, but it's very connected to
deep learning. So, I'm pretty excited to
be helping out with the course. You
>> want to talk about who your advisors
are?
>> Oh. Oh, my advisors. Oh, okay. More
>> yourself.
>> Yeah. Yeah. So, you
>> Okay. Okay. Yeah. I'm advised by uh
>> What are you working on?
>> Sergey Lavine and Ana Draon. If you guys
know any courses that they kind of teach
uh I mostly do, yeah, like reinforcement
learning primarily for like training of
LM agents. So, like agents that can kind
of like web browse and like uh use tools
and participate in dialogue. Uh, so
yeah, if you guys have any like
questions about that as well, I'll be
happy to talk about that.
>> And Joy's going to be doing both
discussions and office hours. Okay, we
have Let me just put my mic back.
We have two more TAs.
Uh, the second TA is Lance. Lance is a
fifth year master student um in the
theory group I believe advised by Prasad
Rahavendra and so uh he will also be
doing discussions mic is not on
it's just not appropriately placed
okay now can you hear me better no
ish okay thank you thumbs up I
appreciate it and then there's Kevin
France Kevin France will be
largely supporting us remotely. So, he
will not be holding discussions, but he
will be supporting you on uh Ed and with
the projects. So, keep your eyes out for
these awesome folks. We're really
excited that they were able to join the
course at the last minute. And
basically, they are the reason that many
of you are in the class. So, you know,
if you want to say thank you to someone,
there's a great candidate in the second
row who you can shower your appreciation
on. Um so with that TA office hours will
be starting today. Um again with the
last minute expansion all of the office
hours are on Tuesdays but they're at a
different set of times. So please go to
the ones that make sense to you. I
strongly strongly strongly recommend
hanging out in office hours. Go there.
Go with your friends. It's a great place
to make and find study groups. And you
know the TAs will be there sitting there
twiddling their thumbs. If you don't
have a question about class, you know,
you don't have to have a question
prepared before you walk in. You can
just go and start working on the
homework there with people.
There are three new discussion sections
that are going to start as well. They
are all on Wednesdays. There we already
had 3 to 4 and 4 to 5. There's now a new
11:00 a.m. and a 6:00 pm, I believe.
Don't go based on my memory. This is all
posted on ED. You should have all
received that information. So, everyone
that was aware of where the discussion
is and how to go to it, give me a thumbs
up if yes,
okay, for those of you who didn't give
me a thumbs up, find it out ASAP. Show
up to discussion. Discussions are
critical. The way we're building things
up is that there will be something in
lecture and then you know the discussion
is primed to build on that. So, please
definitely go. Um, the last thing I was
looking through Ed and I noticed that
there's the there's the thread about
study groups and I noticed very few
women have posted into that thread. So
that either means that all of you
already have study groups or you're
looking for them. I haven't had a single
woman student come to my office hour
either. And I clearly see uh people in
the room. So, you know,
come hang out with me in office hours. I
like it when people come to office hours
and you don't have to have a question.
Just come to say hi. It'll be nice to
get to know you. You know, in this room,
I can actually kind of see your faces.
It's not like when I'm teaching um 127
and we're in this giant room and I can't
really see everyone here. I can actually
see see all of you. So, it'll be nice.
Please come to office hours every day
after class. Okay, good. Any logistics
questions?
We're set. Yes,
>> I made a post about the women study
group
at the same time each week in the same
place that just show up.
>> Okay, let me amplify that because that
might not be but Sammy right uh Sammy
has a post on ED about a women
identifying study group and so if you
would like to join that they are
welcoming uh more people. So please do
go if that is of that is appealing to
you. Wonderful.
Okay.
So with that I'm actually not going to
start on this. I'm going to start here.
So last time we talked about you know
gradient descent the implicit
regularization of gradient descent and
SGD convergence. What we're going to do
today is we're going to continue to
build on what we talked about last time.
I'm going to first go through this proof
that I only kind of started last time
and didn't complete. And then what we're
going to do is we're going to build to
talking about Adam and a
perspective on neural networks that
allows you to think of them as
linearized models or generalized linear
models that can help you that can help
us basically understand how the
optimizers behave on these and this is
going to pay off in the coming lectures
as we go forward.
So before we get to what I'm going to
talk about the new stuff we're going to
talk about today picking back up where
we talked what we talked about last time
we talked about stoastic gradient
descent and we said look there's many
advantages to stocastic gradient descent
the first and foremost being of course
computational the second that stocastic
gradient descent can you know lead to
help you escape things like local minima
or saddle points but what's the downside
of sarcastic gradient descent well it's
noisy right and a lot of Common
knowledge about stoastic gradient
descent or a lot of you know in lot in a
lot of cases one of the challenges with
stoastic gradient descent is that when
you're close to the optimum it can kind
of bounce around or to get a proof of
convergence for stoastic gradient
descent what you need to do is you need
to have a decaying step size or decaying
learning rate built into it.
But it turns out that in some nice
special cases we can actually get a
proof that says that stoastic gradient
descent can converge to an
it can converge I guess um in the case
where you have a set of systems where
the loss can actually go to zero and
you're using only constant step side.
Okay so you're not having a step size
that is decaying as time goes on. And so
we set this up last time. So I have a
underdetermined system of equations XW
equal to Y. And I'm thinking of a wide
um X, right? So I'm assuming that I have
full row rank, no degeneracy here, but
it is an underdetermined system. What
does this mean? I have an infinite
number of solutions. I can pick one
solution. And the solution that we
typically like to pick is the minimum
norm solution, right?
We know the uh formula for this. You've
done it all before in 127 or whatever
classes. And we can write war star is
exactly equal to this expression xrpose
xxxrpose inverse time y. And now let's
say we iterate on this with stoastic
gradient descent using the batch size of
one.
And I keep my initialization at zero.
Okay.
So now what I want to do is I want to
think about this and I want to think
about in this particular case I actually
know where the optimum is. So instead of
thinking about SGD as just taking a path
in the weight space in the W space I
want to think about the error space. The
error space is basically what is my
distance from the optimum.
So I can just take my equation XW equal
to Y and reparameterize it to instead
write it in these new coordinates which
I call the Q coordinate system. Does
that make sense to everyone? So I'm
thinking of X Q equal to now zero
because X * W is Y and X * W star is
also Y. So I'm instead I'm just tracking
how far am I from this minor norm
solution that I'm hoping to get to. So
this is completely equivalent. But of
course I have to also adjust my initial
condition now because I've adjusted my
coordinates right. So I can't start with
uh this condition condition. So now w
knot instead becomes minus war because
when I start out at zero I'm negative
warst away from actual war star. Make
sense?
Good.
So if you've learned one thing from last
week's lecture, you've learned that the
SVD matters, right? Directions matter.
Singular val values matter because they
actually affect sometimes in good ways,
sometimes in bad ways, sometimes in we
don't really know ways how our um
function is going to uh behave under
gradient descent.
So if we really think about this
problem, we want to think about it in
essentially the SVD coordinates. So for
that I say let's take this xq
and I'm going to write it I'm going to
write the singular value decomposition u
sigma vranspose. Okay. So I'm going to
try I have a lot of equations written
out here but I'm going to try to make
sure I lecture at a speed such that you
can actually also write these down.
Okay. Um, so I'm going to try to trace
out things, take pauses because it will
all seem like, oh, of course it's making
sense, but that is called the magic of
lecture. Okay? And then there is the
despair of homework where you open it,
you're like, this actually doesn't make
any sense. So taking notes is a way to
bridge this gap. It will go better into
your brain if you write it down
yourself. And looking at your own
handwritten notes will help you learn
better. Okay?
So I'm going to write out this SVD here.
We know now that X is a wide matrix,
right? So what does that mean? When the
SVD, the SVD is also going to be uh or
the sigma matrix is also going to be a
wide matrix. And basically my zeros are
going to be on this right side. And this
part, this n byn part here is going to
be the diagonal part, right? I split it
up. Basically, I'm trying to get rid of
the zeros, the stuff that doesn't
actually matter in terms of the steps
that I'm going to take.
And now, this actually helps me out a
bit because I want to think about things
in the SVD basis. So, I pull this
vranspose out
over here
and I'm going to call this vranspose Q
Z. I'm basically rewriting things in the
SVD basis, right? So I'm just doing a
change of basis. And so now vranspose q
I'm going to set to be equal to z. And
I'm going to call u * sigma 1 sigma 1
this matrix
x twiddle.
Okay. So xq I can write as x twiddle 0
time z.
What is this doing? This is basically
telling me what parts of this vector Z
are going to matter and which parts are
not because this is basically going to
get by get hit by zeros.
And similarly, I can look at my initial
condition and I'm not going to do this
algebra out here. You can do it out um
on the homework on your own time. But I
take my initial condition Z.
Again, I change of basis. I do the
change of basis to put it into the SVD
basis.
And basically by plugging in the formula
for warstar and plugging in the SVD of
X, I can show that this new initial
condition will also have zero entries at
the bottom. In fact, the last D minus N
entries are going to be zero. Okay? And
it's coming basically from the fact that
the SVD has this zero here. Okay?
Everyone with me?
>> How do I know that there's D minus N? is
because when I look at this sigma here,
this is a um it has n rows and d columns
and this sigma 1 here is n byn. So the
remaining must be d minus n. Yeah.
>> What does a zero mean?
>> A zero when I say this zero matrix here
I mean basically let me write this out.
I mean a it has n rows and
D minus N columns.
>> Z.
>> Oh, Z0. So, I'm tracking this initial
condition. Remember, when I'm doing
gradient descent or anything, what
matters is where I start.
So, I started here. Then I did one
coordinate transformation to move it
into the Q coordinates. Then I did a
another transformation to move it into
the Zcoordinates.
Does that make sense?
Other questions?
Did I see a hand or no?
Okay.
So, what matters is now this new
equation
where I'm looking at this x twiddle time
z equal to zero. Basically, all that
matters from this equation is this times
this. The rest is zero. And the initial
condition cannot bring in any stuff into
those last D minus N spots either
because the initial condition itself is
zero over there. Okay, so I really don't
have to worry about those last D minus N
coordinates. I might as well, you know,
put them on the bench and focus on the
stuff that matters. So I have XZ equal
to zero here. And the row of this is
basically the same as the row of our
original equation.
You can justify this rigorously. That's
part of your homework here. I'm just
going to assert it.
The essential thing is that all you've
done is you've dropped the zeros.
So now what do we want to do? We want to
say okay this is just our system of
equations, right? We haven't even
touched gradient descent or SGD yet. We
want to say what happens when we run SGD
on this problem. So what is our gradient
descent update? Well, our gradient
descent update would be ZT + 1 is equal
to ZT minus 2 A XRPOSE X time ZT. This
needs an arrow here.
And the loss function that we care
about,
we're thinking about this squared loss.
So the gradient of my loss I can just
write as this, right?
Okay.
So now I want to think about with this
loss what happens when I take a SGD
step. Okay? And I want you to think
about that and write it out yourself
because this is just you know just to
reme make sure that everyone's with me
on what SGD is.
So take this you know let me hide this
for one second
and given this loss function what is the
SGD update equation that you need for
this particular problem.
Let me put a timer on.
I highly recommend talking to the person
next to you. It's a good exercise. You
will get to know someone and you might
get a new idea or you might help someone
figure out the answer. So find a person
and talk to them. It's a requirement.
Don't
believe
what you do.
[Music]
That's my timer, but I'm giving you one
more minute.
I'm just here.
>> And now she's just
explain
Okay, so
>> what's the deal? What's happening with
SGD, right? We have this gradient
descent update, but with SGD, we're
saying look, I don't want to take the
gradient over all of the data points.
I'm going to just pick one data point at
a time, right? And since I'm choosing
batch size one, so what we're going to
do is we're going to say let's represent
the particular
data point that you're choosing by this
random variable it. Okay, this it here
is now random in this SGD update.
And so here instead of this xrpose x
here, I get this xit xitpose. And
remember the transposes here are there's
a xrpose x here but this is xxrpose
because the matrix x is the rows are the
data points right so that's why this
transpose switching is happening here if
you're confused about that yes
>> is so data we're going to work with the
most
>> mostly yes
because it makes it easy to think about
the least squares example right when you
have x w equal to y x the row of x * w
is equal to y so that's like one row is
one data point.
So here what everyone I want and I hope
all of you got from this the the
discussion with each other is that
there's now a randomness. It's not easy
to write that equation. You have to
introduce a new variable when you're
writing this SGD equation, right?
Because we do not know which data point
we are going to get. Okay.
So now we have this basically dynamical
system. This is a dynam this is an
equation that's describing to us how Z
is evolving.
Can we say something about what happens
to this loss which is the squared loss
that we care about as we traverse the
path dictated by this dynamical system.
That's what we want to try and
understand. Okay. So it's important to
understand this and I feel like this can
get this can get confusing of like
there's SGD what are we conversing? What
is the loss? But like is everyone with
me? I want to make sure that this part
is clear. Yes. Thumbs up, thumbs down.
Okay, good.
So to show this, what we're going to do
is we want to say look at this quantity
and what do we know about it? Well, it's
a square, right? So that means it's
always going to be non- negative.
If we can somehow show that this
quantity
must go to zero, right? It must uh well,
I want to show it goes to zero, but if I
can say that at every time step, I'm
just going to decrease. I'm always going
to go down
and I'm lower bounded, right? I have to
every step I have to go down, but I can
never get below this table level. That
means I must eventually hit the table,
right? if I must be constantly
decreasing.
This strategy of proving things that um
that shows basically that something
converges by showing something like a
potential function must be decreasing
and is uh always non- negative
is called a leapon function. It's
commonly used in dynamical systems,
control theory, so on and so forth. You
don't have to know what a leapono
function is, but just putting that
terminology out there. Yes.
>> Couldn't it be asically decreasing to
some number that's not a lower bound?
>> If you're showing you you you'll show
that it can be uh strictly decreasing.
>> Okay.
>> Yes.
>> Can't you have like a monotonically
decreasing function that asmtoically
approaches some value that's not the
bound? Can you have a monotonically
decreasing function that is
asmtoically approaching something?
>> Right? Like wouldn't you have to say
something about the decay rate of the
you see what I'm saying?
>> Um
>> like couldn't you
>> Yes, you're right. Um
you're worried about a case that's like
this, right? Let's see.
and I go and stop here.
>> I'm saying like you have some lower
bound, but couldn't it asmtoically
approach something that's above the
lower bound?
>> Not if you're strictly decreasing at
every point at every time point
because wherever you approach you have
to keep at every time you have to keep
going lower.
>> Yes. What if it's approaching like
>> What if you're pushing loss equals one?
>> Yeah. Yeah. Yeah.
Um
That is a good question. Maybe I am
missing a condition here that I should
be including.
>> I feel like there must also be some
condition on the decay like that. It
must be not decreasing to a
>> it must be decreasing fast enough. There
is a there there is there there has to
be a condition like that. You're
absolutely right. And maybe I forgot to
write that down. But yeah, you see the
point you're raising is is correct.
And so you must also show that
this is decreasing
fast enough at some appropriate rate.
That's correct. Yes. Question at the
back.
>> Uh is this like requiring
like a constant step size or like if you
have a decreasing step size, does this
still hold true?
So you mean for the SGD part?
>> Yeah.
>> So here, yes. Here we're assuming that
there's a constant step size on SGD.
>> Okay.
>> We're not we're not including a
decreasing step size here.
>> Because you're worried that if you have
a decreasing step size, you might like
converge prematurely.
>> Yeah.
>> Yeah. So here we're assuming that you
have ADA is the same. ADA has no time
dependence.
>> Okay.
>> Yeah. Um right.
Okay. Sorry about that. I should also
say that there should be a basically
like you you need to have a condition on
the on the gradient of your function
that says that it is decreasing fast
enough
and I did not write that down. So sorry
I will correct this and put an updated
note um
updated note on the website.
Okay. But let's proceed forward with
what we want to show.
So I want to show that this is basically
going down.
For this what I'm going to do is I want
to say okay let me look at the loss at
time t + one and I want to connect it to
the loss at time zt right I want to
basically be able to track the evolution
of the loss as we go ahead
and to do that I'm going to write this
loss function as basically zt plus one.
I'm going to add and subtract ZT so that
I can kind of put these connections
together.
And then I can do some algebra which I'm
going to not do right here and say that
I can write this as L of ZT plus some
term A and plus some term B. Okay. And
what are these terms A and B? Well, this
term A is linear in the update or in the
kind of difference between ZT + one and
ZT.
And so I have A is equal to 2 um ZTRpose
XRPOSE X and I have B is equal to ZT + 1
minus ZTRpose XRPOSE X um and again this
difference. Okay, so the second term B
is quadratic in the update.
And now what we want to think about is
we want to think about what happens to
these when our updates are you know uh
relatively small because we want
gradient descent to be working. So in
this case what we want is we want
basically this linear term to dictate
what's happening because if zt + one is
very close to zt this is pretty small.
So I want this quadratic term to
essentially be not too big. And I want
this step, this term to bring me the DK.
Okay. And I want to say that this term
isn't going to undo any progress done by
this first term.
So everyone clear on how I'm splitting
this up into two parts?
Okay, good.
So to show this now I'm going to first
look at this expected value of a given
ZT. So I want to understand what is
happening to this term
when I'm at point ZT. Right? Remember
what I'm trying to show is how these two
are connected to each other. And for
this I have to show that A plus B is
basically essentially negative. Right?
because then I can show that I have I'm
always going down.
Does everyone see that?
Okay. So now to understand what I'm
going to do with this expected value of
a,
I have the expected value of a given ZT.
And why am I taking this expected value
here? This expected value, what is the
only randomness in the problem? Is there
any noise in our evolution that is being
externally added? There is none. Right?
The only randomness is coming from the
SGD step. There's nothing else that's
that that this expectation is only over
that. Okay? So that's important to to
keep in mind.
How do we then go about handling this?
Well,
I take this a term and I just put it in
here, right?
This is exactly a
And now I'm conditioning on ZT.
So ZT transpose is a direct function of
it. It just pops out of the expectation.
It's like a constant.
XRPOSE X is just our data. It has no
dependence on where my gradient descent
is. So it pops out of the expectation.
So only thing that's left inside this
expectation is this ZT + 1 minus ZT.
Right?
Okay,
but now I can use my update equation
to basically substitute
the value of the update into here. So
that's basically minus 2 ADA
times the expected value of the data
point that I've chosen times ZT which
also pops out of the expectation.
So only thing that remains to understand
is this quantity which is the expected
value of this um outer product of a data
point with itself.
So when I look at this this is what I
have right there. I want to look at this
expected value of x twiddle it x twiddle
transpose it. And just as a reminder
this is a column times a row right? So
this is giving me a matrix here.
So how can I understand this
expectation?
Is this obvious to everyone about this
expectation or is this like wait I need
to think about this? Just give me a
sense of where everyone's at.
Okay. So let's walk through this. So
this expectation here, what is this?
This is now I'm pulling a data point,
right? SGD is picking me batch size one.
So I'm picking a data point and I'm
going to traverse the gradient in that
direction. So this it is what my random
variable is. So that means that it could
be one or it could be two or it could be
three or it could be four or it could be
n, right? I have exactly n choices
because I have n data points. Everyone
with me there?
Yes. No.
Okay. Good.
So I say, well, what does it mean to
take the expected value? Well, what is
the probability that I take the first
guy is 1 /n. The probability to take the
second guy is 1 overn. So I have this 1
/ n here
and then the probability that this is
one is 1 / n. The probability this is
two is 1 over n and the probability this
is three is 1 overn. I get this term
here. Okay.
But now what is this? This is just these
outer products of these data points.
That's exactly just xrpose x, right?
So that's just doing that's just another
way of writing exactly this. And so this
expected value is just 1 / n times that.
Okay. So it just a very nice thing just
kind of pops out uh there for you. And
so when I substitute that back in,
what I get now is I get that this
expected value of a given ZT
is I pull all the constants together
over here. And now I have this ZTRpose
that comes from here. I already had one
xrpose X and now this expectation has
given me a second Xrpose X and I have
this ZT from here that comes over here.
Okay.
Now is so this was this expectation is
the first interesting thing that I want
you to understand and notice that's
coming from the randomness of SGD. The
second interesting thing that I want you
to understand and notice is what's
happening here. So I'm looking at this
expression and I'm trying to think well
how do I analyze this? What can I do
with something like this?
It's kind of unwieldy. There's a lot
going on. What I want to say is let's
pick out and let's look at xrpose x and
what it's doing to this matrix dt.
What do I know about xrpose x? Well, I
know something about I I can I can
characterize what this is doing to this
vector in terms of the singular values,
right?
And I know actually
that when I think about this matrix
xrpose x and what does it do to a
vector? Well, I know it's lower bounded
by the smallest singular value and it's
upper bounded by the largest singular
value.
Right? Everyone see that?
So I can basically say look therefore if
I multip here I have this negative sign
and so I want to say that this sigma
min^ 2 * z is actually greater than or
equal to this minus xrpose x * z. Okay
so I can substitute this with this upper
bound of sigma min^ 2 times this zt.
Does that make sense to everyone?
I'm just saying what is the worst that
this vector can do
and I want you to focus on understanding
these kinds of things because this is
going to become important as we come in
the next few lectures that's coming up
but now when I look at this particular
expression here this is just my loss
function so I can substitute that in and
so I have minus 4 a / n this expression
here okay
everyone with me on that clear
for the second term. The second term is
now quadratic in this error and I'm not
going to go through it in as much
detail. It's going to be on the
homework. But what I want to point out
again is that here we want to show an
inequality of this sort.
Again, what's going to show up is you're
going to get an xrpose x ter like term
which is actually in the b term and
again you're going to use the singular
value to say what is the worst that this
particular can do this particular uh
matrix can do but now you're you're
trying to show that this is smaller than
the positive quantity you don't have
this negative sign hanging around and so
you're going to end up with the largest
singular value.
You're going to do a little bit more
processing and what you're going to see
is this term of this form where this is
again all that all the randomness here
is coming from this data point that
you're choosing. So you have this
expected value of x xrpose x xrpose.
Again
the nice thing here is that because I
have four of these in the middle I have
not an outer product but now I have an
inner product here. Right? So I can take
these two and I group them together and
what do I get?
I get the norm of my data points. And
now if I can say that this norm is
not too large
then I or if I can bound this
I can use that norm to get a appropriate
bound. Okay, that's the general gist and
way in which this proof is going to go
through.
So the thing I want to point out here is
two things
is that first we care about these
singular values and second the size of
the data points also comes in and we
will talk about normalization
um in the coming lectures and this is
one place where you can see in an easy
way that well you know the sizes of your
data points are actually going to matter
in terms of whether you can converge or
not because how the nonlinearities are
going to affect your data points is
going to is going to come in. Okay.
So then you can put this all together
adding this up and I can basically show
that my loss conditioned on ZT my loss
at ZT + one is basically this quadratic
times the loss at this is a typo here.
This should be ZT
at ZT.
And here I have this ADA here. But if I
choose an ADA
small enough sorry then I can make sure
that this whole thing is smaller than
one.
And so basically if my step size is
small enough I can guarantee that this
converges.
So what we have here is now the
takeaways are we have an interesting
dependence on the norms of the data
points. Right? That's something that we
haven't seen before. the sizes of the
data points mattering for a convergence
proof. So I want to highlight that and
and bring that out and again coming back
to the same point that we've been seeing
over and over again that you know
decoupling into the SVD coordinates can
help us bring things out.
Okay. So a very close version of this is
going to be on your homework. So you
will have to go through this in somewhat
some level of detail. I want to give you
a a highlevel idea so that when you're
doing that homework problem, I don't
want you to be focusing on the algebra.
I mean, okay, I do want you to be
focusing on all the algebra, but I also
want you to be getting the big picture
of what's going on and why you're doing
the algebra, not just the algebra for
the sake of the algebra. Make sense?
Yes.
>> Is there a reason why we didn't take the
sort of system convergence approach to
this problem?
Um is there a reason that we didn't
directly show that um the loss function
is just decaying
>> or what do you mean by that? Because I
remember like last section we talked
about this idea.
>> Yeah.
>> So I mean if you did any analysis on
this
You're like you would show that the Z is
going to I'm not sure I'm following you.
>> So you want to show that the loss is
going to zero in some sense.
>> Although the loss is the X
>> this will also go to zero. The Z will
also go to zero.
>> Yeah.
>> Both will go to zero.
>> Yeah. So you're saying why couldn't we
just use this equation to show that Z
goes to zero
>> because that app that also implies that
you're going to the minimum.
>> Um
you could uh this is the easier proof.
I mean there's I I'm not claiming this
is the unique proof for this.
Yeah, there might be another there might
be another proof. In fact, if you want a
story, um we were playing with this
proof and trying to uh actually get GPT
to see if it could come up with an
alternate proof that is simplistic.
And turns out that uh you can talk to
GPD and try GPT GPD. No, it wasn't GPD5.
It was Gemini Pro. Gemini 2.5 Pro.
And
as far as I think Gemini 2.4 for pro
produced a different but correct proof
uh approximately correct proof for
for the problem. So
I chose not to do that one because it
doesn't bring out the it's it's a more
crude bound and it doesn't bring out the
dependence on the SVD. So this is
definitely not the only uh elementary
proof for this.
Okay, great.
With that, I will now move to the next
part of the lecture. Um, any questions
about this SGD stuff before I move on?
So, we talked last class about momentum
and I said that I would talk about atom
in today's lecture, which is what I'm
going to do.
What we said last time was that gradient
descent has basically a feature and a
bug which is that it takes larger steps
in the direction of the large singular
values and it takes smaller steps in the
direction of the smaller singular
values. And there are advantages and
disadvantages to this. For example, you
know, it leads to this implicit
regularization if we kind of do some uh
early stopping. At the same time,
this can make it very hard to choose a
learning rate if you have a very, excuse
me, if you have a very wide spread of
singular values. There might be some
tiny singular values that you don't care
whether you move in those or not. But
you might still have some medium
singular values. And if you choose a
learning rate that is dominated that is
dictated by your largest singular value,
you might make extremely so slow
progress in these other directions where
you still want to move but you cannot
move fast enough. Right? So this there's
this challenge in terms of uh choosing
the learning rate because if you if you
try to uh have a larger learning rate
then you might blow up in the directions
of the large singular values.
So how could you solve this? Actually
why don't I I'm going to actually I yeah
I want you to take a minute to try and
think like what could you do to solve
this problem. So take talk to someone,
ideally a different person than the
person you talked to before, and just
brainstorm.
How could you possibly solve this
problem?
>> H
>> What's the problem?
>> Oh, okay.
Well, I don't
really
It's really
So that's why for a lot of things
you don't know that
they're very small and
That's
>> okay. That's my timer.
>> So, what are what Yeah. What are some
ideas on, you know, what do you do when
you have some values or some singular
values that are threatening to blow up,
others that are just not moving?
Someone else, someone else who hasn't
been participating as much.
>> Yeah, you've been asking a lot of
questions. Yeah. You pick a different
learning rate for
>> Yeah, it would be great if you could
pick a different learning rate for every
different direction, right? So, how
would you pick a different learning rate
for every different direction? What's
one way that you could try to do that?
>> Yeah.
>> Based on how fast they've been learning.
Could you elaborate more on what you
mean by that? like this concept of
momentum that changing a lot perhaps you
increase the learning rate for that
specific weight but it doesn't blow up
as much. So somehow somehow you have to
tweak based on the based on I don't I
I'm not sure I understand the momentum
connection but somehow you want to tweak
based on how fast things are moving in
each direction,
>> right? So what like what dictates how
fast we're moving in each direction?
>> Yeah,
>> the singular values, right? So what
would you do in some ideal world?
But what like if you wanted to say I
want to move approximately the same in
every direction.
One thing that you could do is you could
say well let me take the SVD
and then say I will appropriately say
okay I will have a different learning
rate in every single direction
and it will be based on what is the
singular value in that direction right
and I will basically normalize and
equalize all of my steps based on that
does that seem like a reasonable idea
right because you're basically saying
you're the problem is coming because
you're coupling all of your steps
together by this one learning rate.
So don't don't do that. So why don't we
do that in practice? Why is that not
like the standard thing that everyone
does?
It's really expensive, right? Because if
you have these giant data matrices, if
your data is gets bigger and bigger and
bigger, computing the SVD of that thing
is a monster. So you you can't compute
the singular values
to you know do this process at all. So
it would be great if we could do that
but we can't. I forgot to show this
picture which is
uh what is happening when you have these
unbalanced singular values. Right? So
basically here I have um kind of this
this ellipsoid showing the singular
values and with a small step size I
converge very nicely to the optimum
but I make rapid progress in this
direction and then I'm just extremely
slow making progress in this direction.
Right? It takes a long time to converge
along this coordinate. Whereas if I
increase my learning rate
then I'm bouncing around and not really
converging.
So just that picture I forgot to talk
about but okay.
So what the key idea that is motivating
u Adam and some of the precursors of
Adam is to say well okay the SVD is
maybe too expensive but what can we do?
Well can we normalize our gradients
somehow? Okay.
And it might be too expensive to compute
the SVD and say I move in equally in
every direction in the SVD. But what I
can do is I can try to do that in the
coordinate system that I am in already.
Okay.
So
let's see what I actually mean by that.
So let me take our gradient descent
equation. This is my normal gradient
descent update equation. Right?
And instead of taking this gradient
update,
let me compute the following. What I'm
going to do is I'm going to define this
term MT and I'm just going to call that
the gradient. Okay? And I'm going to
have this term VT.
and vt is just going to be the value of
the squared gradient. And I'm thinking
here of an element wise square. Okay,
I'm not taking u an inner product but
I'm taking an element wise square.
So if I take
a number and I divide it by the square
root of its square, what do I get back?
So I have a / a^ square.
I basically get the sign back, right?
The absolute the square root of the a
squ is going to give me the absolute
value of a. So I get basically like if I
have a divided by absolute value of a.
What's that? It's the s of a, right? So
when I take mt
divided by
square root of vt.
What I'm getting back is basically the
sign of the gradient. Does everyone see
that?
Yes. No.
Okay.
And so if I compute instead of looking
at instead of taking my gradient step
what if I can say look I'm going to look
at the my gradient and I'm going to look
at every component of it and I'm going
to say wait are you positive or are you
negative are you positive or you
negative just tell me generally which
way I should go in every coordinate
right that's what the sign of the
gradient is telling us
what this is is a quick way to get that
sign of the gradient out.
So to normalize what I can do is I can
instead take steps
in this direction along the sign of the
gradient and I can think of this as
basically sin SGD. So if I look at this
particular equation,
that is what I want to call sin SGD
because I'm taking a step in the
direction of the sign of the gradient.
You notice here that I have this little
epsilon that I've added in the
denominator. And why is that epsilon
there? Well, because I want to make sure
that my algorithm is numerically stable
and I don't want to get my denominator
too close to zero and then have start
things start to blow up, right? So just
for practicality of implementation, I
have that epsilon there. But really what
I'm trying to do is I'm trying to say
move in all of the coordinates
approximately equally because you're
moving now
exactly ADA in every coordinate. Right?
It's not the SVD coordinates. It's in
the like native basis that you're in.
But you've somehow equalized how you're
moving. Does that make sense to
everyone? Okay.
This is a great idea, but what is the
problem with this?
What is a possible problem with
something like this?
Right? Why do why why is there still
lecture to give? Why don't I say like
great now we do sin GD and let's go
home.
>> Yeah.
>> What's the value of
epsilon?
>> Oh, epsilon is just some it's like a
hyperparameter. something tiny just to
make sure you don't divide by zero.
That's that's not um that that I guess
that could be a problem, but that's not
the problem I wanted to get to. But the
issue is that because now I'm doing the
sign, right? Once I get close to the
optimum, I might just keep like I might
overshoot and then I have a positive
gradient, overshoot, I have a negative
gradient, overshoot, positive gradient,
ping pong, ping pong, ping pong, and I'm
just going to I might just keep bouncing
around right near the optimum, right?
And that's not good.
So I want to do something that is
basically a smoothed version of this.
And what have we talked about as a way
of doing things smoothly? There's like I
mean it's been three lectures. There's
not that many things. The answer is
either the SVD or one of the two things
we've talked about. So what is the other
thing we've talked about?
>> Momentum.
>> Momentum. Right. So instead of taking
exactly the gradient, can I take
basically the averaged gradient and do
the same thing? And so here what Adam is
doing is it's saying or to get to Adam
what I want to say is look instead of MT
representing just the gradient I'm going
to have it represent the average
gradient by doing the same kind of
exponential decaying u averaging that we
talked about for momentum. This beta is
exactly the same. and I'll do the same
thing for the square of the gradient
and that gives me Adam. Okay,
so it's taking this idea of sin SGD but
saying let's do it a little bit more
smoothly and that's what you get.
There's one more thing to talk about
here which is that this particular
update now that you've introduced these
betas and these gamas
can be a bit biased and it can lead to
this problem of having a slow start. So
to illustrate what that means,
for example, if I say choose beta equal
to uh 0.9,
then what does this equation start to
look like?
At my very first time step, do I have a
momentum term? Is there a historical
gradient that I'm averaging with?
No. Right? So at my very first time
step, what is m of zero? Basically,
that's just zero. I just average with
zero. and m of one is well whatever the
gradient is there
but now my beta is 0.9 so I have 0.9 * 0
plus 0.1
times whatever my gradient is and so my
step at the beginning
isn't going to be on the order of
magnitude of the gradient right it's
going to be a tenth of the gradient
once I' once I have a lot of history
then this averaging is going to get me
to somewhere where I'm approximately
uh taking steps of the right order of
magnitude but at the beginning I could
be taking very uh small steps and that
could be boring because I won't converge
as fast and the whole name of the game
in this business is converging fast
right so what Adam further does is it
does a bias correction where it says
look at the beginning if you're being
very very slow
correct it by this term by dividing by 1
minus beta to the t + one right As t
becomes larger and larger, beta is
between zero and one. As t becomes
larger, this denominator is just going
to become one.
But when you're small, this is going to
amplify your gradient just a little bit.
Does that make sense?
So questions about this, questions about
Adam.
We're basically trying to do something
that is saying do sin SGD with a little
bit of of smoothing. That's the
intuition behind great behind atom. And
we'll talk about a different intuition
or a related intuition more in the next
lecture, but I have to still set up some
things to be able to get to that.
>> Yes.
>> Is this a still a fixed learning rate in
this case or a scheme to
>> um here we will just use a fixed
learning rate? Yes.
Other questions.
Okay,
another couple of things that I want to
say that you know typically Adam is Oh
yes, question.
>> Explain one more time.
>> Could you explain again what beta is
equal to?
>> Beta t
>> it's beta to the t + one. Beta to the
power t plus one. So beta is a constant.
Here I'm saying that. So when uh at time
t equal to zero, this is one minus beta,
right? So you're basically correcting
for this tiny thing here. Does that make
sense?
>> Yes. Question at the back.
>> Why is it called bias? The question is
why is this called a bias? Is because
your um
your beta is making you biased to the
gradient being too small. So you're
correcting that bias. That's really all
there is.
Other questions.
Okay, good. So this is Adam and this is
basically
one of the most popular uh optimization
algorithms that is used today.
Normally you will use it with SGD. Here
I presented it using gradient descent.
Normally you would compute all of these
with mini batches, right? So there's
going to be noise in this as well.
And this normal um
so that's basically one thing to say.
The other thing about Adam um and
basically this idea of sin SGD is it can
help you with uh to some extent with
what is thought of as like the vanishing
gradient or the exploding gradient
problem. So if I have a neural network
and it's very very deep as I go further
and further in my layers I'm constantly
multiplying when I'm doing back prop
right and so I can have things that
start attenuating and becoming really
small or depending on the IGEN values
either blowing up does that does
everyone remember this from whatever 189
or whatever machine learning class
they've taken
what Adam does is it says look I'm going
to try to normalize I'm going I'm going
to not depend too much on the magnitude
of the gradient itself. Right? I'm going
to I'm going to try to extract more the
direction
than the exact magnitudes. And so this
normalization basically reduces the
impact of a gradient that might be
becoming too small or too big.
So as you have deeper layers, this is
helpful for you. Does that make sense?
That's one of the other reasons that
Adam is u people like Adam.
So here for example this picture
shows the same initialization what would
happen if you took just the sign SGD.
So it still gets you there but at the
end what happens is that you don't
actually converge and you just keep
bouncing between these last two points
whereas Adam just smooths out. It takes
a similar trajectory but smooths you out
a little bit and gets you to the actual
uh minimum. This picture is again uh
from the prince book.
Okay. So now I want to point out is that
you know it's great atom is great
momentum is great but there is a there's
in some sense a price that you're paying
right? It's not like you're completely
there's no free lunch.
So when you're doing just SGD all you
care about is the direction of the
gradient from your mini batch. And so
that's just there's just that one
equation that you're keeping track of
right.
However, now if I was doing SGD plus
momentum,
well, I'm keeping this one equation to
keep track of the running average of my
gradients and then I have another state
that is keeping track of where I'm
actually at, right? Where is where what
is my state of my uh gradient descent?
Everyone see this?
So, basically, I've doubled the memory
that I now need to use to be able to
implement the algorithm.
And then for atom what do you see? Well,
how many things do I have? I have this
momentum term. I have the squared
gradient term. And I have my actual
gradient distinct equation. So now I
have I've tripled the memory.
So I am paying a price in terms of the
memory that I'm using when I'm
uh implementing atom.
Okay.
One last thing. Any questions about
this?
One last thing I want to talk about is
what is called atom w because this is
another algorithm that is very commonly
used uh and useful these days. Atom w is
just basically atom with weight decay.
So weight decay remember we talked about
last time if we have ridge regression
you have a gradient descent update
and the gradient descent equation for
ridge basically looks like the following
where I have this term 1 - 2a lambda
that shows up on wt. Does everyone
remember this from the last lecture? We
did this.
And this is basically pushing my weights
down. It's making them go to zero.
Right?
What I want you to notice here is that
this term depends both on the
hyperparameter lambda and on the
learning rate ADA that you've chosen.
Okay.
In atom, if you wanted to implement some
kind of regularization or weight decay,
it turns out that adding a direct ridge
penalty is not the right way to do it.
Why is it not the right way to do it?
Because if I added a ridge penalty in
the gradient that is associated with
that ridge penalty also gets averaged
into all of these averaging equations
and it doesn't actually have the desired
effect. All these things get two coupled
together. you have the learning rate and
you have the lambda. So instead if you
wanted to regularize this what people do
is you just explicitly have a separate
weight decay. So I take the um atom
equation.
And what I can do here,
I can explicitly add
a separate weight decay on top of this
that's just completely independent of
what everything is happening, everything
else that's happening. And this can help
with convergence. Okay,
so that's another thing that I wanted to
talk about.
So one since I have a couple of minutes
I'm I'm going to just one thing that I
found very interesting when I've been
preparing this lecture is just the
history of this and how nonlinear
progress has been in this particular
field like when you think about gradient
descent I read in one reference that
gradient descent is attributed to Kashi
which is I guess like 1800s
uhish but I actually find it hard to
believe that gradient descent wasn't
known before that like I'm sure that
people knew about gradient descent and
used gradient descent in different ways
um even before that because I like
Newton would predate that so and um so I
don't know but then stochastic gradient
descent the first reference is in the
50s like 1950s so you know think about
that
and then atom is actually a fun like it
it builds on uh this algorithm called
Adagrad which is basically adaptive
gradients
uh which is you know coming to the same
problem that we were just brainstorming
about is like what do you do like
everyone noticed that this is a problem
like you don't want to move too much in
one direction you want to move a little
bit more in the other direction so how
can we adapt
um and Adam is just adaptive and
momentum so that's that's where this
Adam comes from but that's actually
fairly recent like 2011 2012
and now what we're, you know, then AdamW
is is even is even more recent and kind
of as we've needed stuff to to work,
there's been this push to get these
algorithms working. And then what we're
going to talk about in the next lecture
and the the following two lectures we're
going to try to build to talking about
this uh optimizer that is becoming very
popular or becoming very powerful these
days called muon which is from the last
203 24 203 or 24 do you remember 24
right so very very recent but it's all
all of these things are building on
going back to these fundamental same
fundamental insights or
What are the singular values? How are
things moving? Um what kind of behavior
do we want? How do we get
our our intuition on how these
algorithms should behave to be kind of
how do we squish them into the math so
that the the things can work and going
back and circling and circling and
circling and iterating iterating on
these ideas. So I I find this history of
how these algorithms have actually
evolved to be quite uh quite interesting
and something worth thinking about in
terms of how we get here.
>> Okay, any questions about Adam?
>> Yes.
Yes.
>> So you're losing the singular value
connection.
>> So you mentioned I believe lasting
the information actually helps you
achieve a better.
>> Yeah. So, so there is a lot of debate in
some sense on I I guess in some sense
it's we don't know exactly why it works.
But
one thing to keep in mind in deep
learning is that the the goal of deep
learning is slightly different from the
goal of optimization. The goal of
optimization is to find the minimum.
The goal of deep learning is to find a
solution that generalizes
that may or may not be equal to the
optimum. Remember like we're our goal is
not to find the best fun fit to the
functions to the training data. Training
data just happens to be what it is. You
know, we don't actually want to be too
married to that. So
in some sense the answer is it it works
because it it works. Um it's interesting
actually. So there's I was reading and
the original atom paper actually had a
bug in the like a small bug in the proof
but it it still works right and then it
was later patched and fixed and it
wasn't a big deal but like it it it it
still it still works and so what what
matters is that it works and I think one
of the really nice things about Atom and
one of the reasons it's become so
popular is that the default
hyperparameters just work
and there are I think there's been
papers ers and studies that have shown
that there are cases where SGD with
momentum actually beats Adam. There are
cases where atom beats SGD with
momentum. Like there's all kinds of
basically you can craft functions where
atom will be amazing but SGD with
momentum will fail and and vice versa.
So it's not that any one of these
algorithms is necessarily uh perfect or
special in some in some way. Um
does that help? Yeah,
>> because we lose the connection with the
singular values, does that also mean we
lose the implicit regularization?
>> Um, because so do we lose the implicit
regularization? Um,
theoretic like from a theoretical
perspective that early stopping
regularization
we would lose. But there is actually a
perspective by which you can think about
uh implicit regularization of gradient
descent
in um in another
sense and I'm I need to think to see
whether you are losing that as well. I'm
not I'm not I'm not 100% sure. One thing
says to me that because Adamw is
necessary, it means that maybe you need
like sometimes you need to add add an
element of extra regularization. Uh I
don't know an do you have a direct
answer to that question?
>> Yeah.
>> So
there's the explicit sense in which a
singular value connection is lost
because you're doing something
different.
>> But if you try do you do experiments
where you You can try to do it for like
a squares type problem. If you make
problem big enough then
actually some effect of the singular
value decomposition that are underneath
still carries through because in a way
the sign is like can be thought of as
it's kind of a quantization it's like a
one bit quantization of what's happening
to these individual values. And so
there's a tradition in digital signal
processing for example we can view
quantization as a scaling and adding
noise and as long as the quantization is
relatively incoherent to the underlying
pattern it will behave like that. So if
the underlying matrix has such it has
very large singular values in certain
directions and small ones in the other
implicit quantization of the gradient is
happening with sign SGD will also not
lose that structure it'll just be like a
noisy version that underlying structure
will still be there the correlated
directions will still be correlated and
uncorrelated directions will still be
uncorrelated so the the longer answer to
the question is although the over direct
in your face connection to the singular
values that is present in STD's analysis
that's not there. A variant of it by
quantization is still present. It's
still going to help reverse some of the
behavior.
>> So this is like a longer answer to the
question.
>> Thanks.
Okay, I have five minutes and I need
them.
Okay. So what I want to talk about to
set up for next lecture is
how do we think what are we want to now
understand how these optimizers are
behaving on neural networks right we
want to be able to get to solutions good
solutions that generalize well when
we're working in these non-convex loss
landscapes that are given to us by
neural networks.
So the one standard approach that we
kind of know when to how to think about
this is to say like can we think about
this in some some simpler way some
simplified way that kind of helps us
think about this and what's the standard
simple thing that we like thinking about
well it's linear stuff right it's always
the easiest stuff to think about and so
how can we look at these neural networks
but think of them in some way as a can
we take a linear perspective on them.
They're clearly not linear, right? We're
not trying to make them linear. But can
we nonetheless try to take a linear
perspective?
And so for this, if I think about some
neural network, let's say I have my
input X and I have multiple layers. I do
have my last layer that is my linear
layer, right?
And so one perspective that I can use to
take to to look at all of my of to look
at my models
as a linear uh or as a linear model is
to say well can I view this by saying
look I take all these nonlinear layers
and I think of them as they're just
computing or they're just extracting
some features from the data. So you know
this transforms the data transforms the
data transforms the data transforms the
data whatever comes out here at this
penultimate layer that's just some
complicated nonlinear feature that has
come from the data and instead of
predetermining what those features would
be as I would do let's say I was doing
polomial regression or if I was say
lifting the features from one feature
space to another I could do that in some
predetermined way that I have decided or
alternatively I could Okay, let the data
speak for itself and let's learn some
features. Okay, and so I can think of
this as okay, I'm learning a bunch of
features and then at the end I'm just
going to use my uh you know I'm going to
have a linear model that works on these
features to do my classification or
regression or what have you problem that
I that I want to do. Okay.
And this perspective leads us to one
nice thing that is very practically
useful. It leads to this idea of linear
probing that says that look if you have
a model and you've already trained it on
something but you now want to train it
on a related task maybe on similar data
what you can do is you can freeze all of
this part of the network. So you you
train it, you keep these weights and all
you do is you retrain
the linear layer only, right? And that
can allow you to take what you've
learned from a set of data and fit it uh
to a new problem. Okay? Now, in general,
this is this is in some sense a
classical perspective. Nowadays, we're
in the era of fine-tuning, which I'm
everyone here knows what fine-tuning is.
Yes. No, we're going to talk about it in
much more detail, but um just to that's
the idea of, you know, I'm taking a
network and I've trained it on some data
and then I'm going to fine-tune it to
fit another task and there I'm not going
to just, you know, focus on training one
layer. I'm actually going to train
everything. Okay.
But is there another perspective that I
can think about for linearizing? And I
guess I'll talk about this a little bit
more next time. Um
but basically I want to say that if I
have this network um and I'm going to
call it f of x comma theta where x is my
data and theta are my parameters.
The other thing that we can you do to do
linearization is to or to take a linear
perspective is to say well let's look at
the tailor expansion right let's look at
the uh basically the the linearization
and what's happening as I'm as I'm
training my network well I have my data
it is whatever it is and my parameters
my thetas
are kind of what are changing and so if
I I can think of my network as it's
training as well what is happening to
this f as my parameters are changing for
my theta if I let's say I'm starting at
some theta kn and I go to delta theta
well I can actually take a tailor
expansion where I now have this f ofx
comma theta kn around my uh point and
then times this first order or linear
term where here I have the inner product
of the gradient with now my delta theta
Right?
And this second perspective says that
okay I can take this as a linear
approximation of our network and it
points to this gradient or really its
transpose which is the derivative
and that can be thought of or the
entries of that can be thought of as the
features of the network in the training
that I'm going to be now doing. So I
will talk about this a little bit more
next time since I'm uh I have I have one
minute. Okay. Um so what I want to say
is that this holds this holds basically
only in when do tailor expansions hold
tailor expansions hold when I'm not
moving too far from where my theta kn
is. Right? If I'm here my gradient my
linear approximation holds only in the
small neighborhood. For that to work
there's what is called this lazy
training assumption which is saying that
your parameters are not moving too much.
And next time we will talk about why we
care about these assumptions holding and
what are the implications of that on
other optimization algorithms. See you
next class. Come to office hours.
>> Almost ahead of time.
>> I'm sorry.
>> Is there any possibility of posting
ahead of time?