language models. There's many that are
supported and so
>> came out last week.
>> The Yeah, the
>> Yeah, the API came out, you know, like
in a very short time ago. So, it's very
very new. Uh and
so I think we we can get people $250 of
credit per student. Uh so for a group of
four, this is $1,000 of credit that you
can have um using Tinker. So I strongly
recommend people if you can find ways of
taking advantage of that you know adding
a section to your project that can use
that in some interesting way we
encourage you to do so. Um, not saying
you have to, but
>> the important thing is that we need to
confirm who is going to be using this
>> to use that. If the announcement hasn't
gone out already, it will go out very
shortly um on ED telling you how to, you
know, appropriately sign up for these
slots. Um, this is through the national
um AI research support uh organization,
but it's it's not as convenient at all.
Um but it's general purpose.
Okay. So very important be on it. Uh use
use all the compute you can you can uh
to do your do your projects because you
can iterate.
Okay. So now the topic I want to kind of
move towards is I want to talk about a
little bit about in context learning and
prompting which you've all heard about
at least the prompting part uh but sort
of connected to what we've been talking
about a little bit.
And then we'll start into discussions of
fine-tuning. And this is going to be the
topic of uh this lecture and uh the next
lecture. But we're going to kind of keep
keep building.
So I'm going to start with just recall
how pre-training works. Here's like a
full picture of pre-training for these
GPG style models. So recall you have a
model. The model has different parts. So
you have discrete tokens that this thing
deals with. It can also be continuous
tokens. You can also think about things
with continuous inputs. We pointed to a
paper for projects that did that.
But you know, let's think of a discrete
case.
And so these tokens have to get
converted into embedding somehow. They
go through an embedder and all the boxes
uh here are learned. So and then after
it goes to the embedter, you're now in
the embedding dimension. I think
thousand 4,000 something like that as
was talked about last time. Then you
have many many layers of these
transformer
layer type things. Now these don't have
to be just attention and MLPS with
residual connections. They can also have
states base models and mixtures of
experts. All things we've talked about
last time we showed you how these can be
constructed in some hybrid way.
The important thing is that everything
here the entire network is weight shared
across time right as was you know very
clear before but there's interactions
across time that happen through
attention as well as through par
carrying state across
so then things go up at the end you have
to dembed so this is like a linear layer
that will go back out to remember this
is like this 32,000 possible tokens.
This takes 32,000 long vectors and turns
them into 4,000 long vectors. Then this
has to go the opposite.
All these are learnable parameters. This
gives a set of scores associated with
every single token that might be an
output. You run that through a softmax
to get probabilities and you can feed
those probabilities into a cross entropy
loss for training. And the cross entropy
loss has to have something to compare
against. Okay, everyone remember this?
So in this particular case what we
mentioned last time you you train this
using next token prediction. So here you
know the it was like the famous poem
from Jabberwock Jabberwaraki from Louis
Carol to bleague was you know and then
and the sly toes did gyron gimble in the
wave you know all that stuff. So the
start would want to predict tw because
that's the first word of the poem and
the twaz wants to predict brillig and
and then brilleg wants to predict and
and so on.
At the very end there's a period that
ends the poem that ends the entire
document and then that should predict
stop.
We're done. Okay. So this is
pre-training. So everyone cool with
pre-training. Okay. So you pre-train
this on lots and lots of data. Now
things that people have learned
since the time they first started doing
this is that the quality and the nature
of the data that you pre-train on
matters. And so there's a lot of work in
trying to figure out good pre-training
mixes that you know give rise to good
generalization in the model. So that's
all stuff that's happening. Yeah.
>> Call this process of training teacher
forcing as well. I know we called it
that during RN. I
Great question. The question is, is this
teacher forcing? The answer is yes, this
is teacher forcing because it's
you you for the input you put in the
entire document that you want to do next
prediction on and for the output you
also do the entire document. You don't
care what it actually at any step
predicts here out of the softmaxes. You
just say whatever you were predicting I
want it to be brillig and then the next
thing I feed you is brillig in
Okay, so this is the the way that uh
pre-training happens. So comments just
little little bit of comments here is
that
the data mix matters
and there's lots of work and empirical
work trying to figure out what is a good
data mix. Um so there was a very famous
paper that came out that was called uh
textbooks are all you need which was
arguing uh came out of Microsoft
research and it was the one of the
foundational
uh papers associated with the fi family
of models for example and that said that
showed pretty decisively that high
quality data
is helpful in training. And so one of
the things that you should be aware of
is when training these kinds of models
today
people will often mix in a lot of
synthetic data. So by synthetic data
this is data that we ourselves generate
from from another model uh that has the
right kind of qualities from the mix
point of view. Okay. So that's that
really that idea really came into full
force in the textbooks are all unique
paper.
So okay so data mix matters you do this
okay now
that's the story for what you do at the
training time for pre-training time then
what do you do when you want to do
inference time recap this very briefly
so here it's important to understand
that the way these models are are
typically used is in what we consider an
autocomplete style auto reggressive
generation Okay, so this again was
mentioned before. I just want to
emphasize I want to bring out the idea
of what a prompt is in this picture.
So the way it works is you start with a
prompt. This is the thing that you want
the model to autocomplete.
So you start with start. Sorry, I don't
want to write anything right now. Just
use this. You start with start and then
you have your prompt tokens.
And so you feed this into the model.
This is part of the context of the
model. and the model runs. But notice
here
that on the prompt, for most of the
prompt, you don't even have to run the
dmb.
You're not asking for anything at this
point. And everything after the block,
the dmbs
across time. So you could run it, not
run it. It doesn't matter. You never use
it. You don't do any sampling.
However,
the last token in the prompt, whatever
the last thing is, that's the thing that
you want to start completing.
So, you want the generation for that.
So, that goes all the way up through the
dmbes into the softmax.
And a comment here, just wanted to make
it um explicit based on some questions,
is that the softmax can take a
temperature parameter in. And what the
temperature parameter does is it says
remember softmax takes x and then it
weighs it and it normalizes it by all
the other xs.
However, you can choose to take x of
five times something or x of 0.1 times
something. And by changing that
parameter, the thing you multiply by,
you can move it to either if you set it
very close to zero, it'll basically go
to uniform distribution. And if you set
that thing you're multiplying by to a
very big number, you're pretty much
going to go to whatever the highest
probability is, right? To maximum
likelihood kind of decoding.
So you have an adjustment there that can
be done. So you have a temp goes to a
softmax. The output of the soft max is
probabilities. So these are
probabilities
and those goes go into the sampler.
Again, it was talked about last time. I
just want to make sure everyone's on the
same page. And the sampler then gives
you a token. You then take that token
and you feed it in here. So, the
important thing that I want to make
clear is that the prompt doesn't have
any of this coming back
here. Once you're doing generation, you
have this sequentiality.
Okay? So, you keep running it and you
stop whenever this thing generates a
stop token.
So the instant it generates a stop
token, you're like, I'm done.
>> Yes.
>> Basically,
>> great question. Um, I only drew these
blocks. And so all you really need to be
able to do the thing you want over here
is you need all of the state from a
state space model and all of the key
values for attention.
So you're right in technically we could
have decapitated this like a little bit
below and not done that final or the
final things there. Basically as soon as
whatever was carrying state with it key
values or anything we could have
stopped. Okay. Does that answer your
question? Okay. So everyone good with
this? Yeah.
Yeah, great question. So, let me maybe I
can write this out.
Standard softmax is e to the
x i divided by sum
e to the xj
sum over j. Right? That's a standard
softmax.
So what we're going to do is we're just
going to add a parameter
one over t
in front.
So when t is zero, this is a very big
number
and that will basically make it pick out
a max. the soft max will become a max
and meaning that it'll give all the
probability to the maximum entry and
zero probability to everybody else. But
if you make the temperature parameter
higher, it's going to make the
probabilities more uniform. That's what
it mean. So it's a hyperparameter,
but you don't you shouldn't really think
of it as a hyperparameter necessarily
because it's not something that we're
adjusting during training. We're just
using it. It's something we tune at use
for our purposes.
So it's not like anywhere.
>> It's a knob that we turn. So if if you
ever use any of the um open source local
running things of you know like Olama or
something, you'll see you can adjust the
temperature and it'll adjust the
generations. You should play with it. If
you haven't played with it yourself, you
should play with it to see what happens.
Okay, just making sure everyone's on the
same page. It's all my only objective
right now. Everyone good? Okay, so now
we know what a prompt what I mean when I
say prompt. So let's like take a little
bit of history, a tour through history
here. Um, and kind of how we what
happened.
So the transformers key paper, attention
is all you need that came out in 2017.
in
right soon after you had the BERT paper
and BERT was revolutionary in terms of
its impact because suddenly it became
the case that these better embeddings
you had these nice features you got out
of BERT no matter what natural language
problem you were doing you could write a
paper that was basically I take the
exact approach as we were doing before w
with some featurization and I'm just
going to use BERT featur ization and
performance gets better and in many
cases better in a way that's shifted
from this isn't really usable to this is
now usable.
So at that time GPT1 came out in 2018
and what GPT1 said was it set up this
architecture decoder only and it said if
you just pre-train this way just do next
token prediction instead of BERT style
pre-training
then you get something that has good
embeddings these embeddings are also
good they're like BERT quite quality
good embeddings
that was GPT1
So GPT1 was taking the perspective this
is pre-training. We can use this to get
something that we could then fine-tune
for another task or just to use its
embeddings.
Okay.
GPT1 was released open source.
Then came GPT2
and GPT2 in 2019
was basically made everything bigger.
the embedding got bigger, the number of
layers got bigger, the all the parameter
counts increased
and it said that suddenly in GPT2
that many new behaviors seem to emerge.
One was you could actually do this
autogressive completions and when you
did it you it resulted in things that
were at the time shockingly natural pros
or poetry. It could track genre. So you
could start writing a poem and then say
complete and it would continue writing a
poem.
And if you started writing a story and
there's a very famous example about a
story about unicorns, right? It will
continue writing a story about unicorns.
And
that was one thing that it had at that
point. So the autocomplete aspect really
began to shine at GPT2.
The second thing was that
the paper showed that this model clearly
knows facts about the world. So the
example was like this.
You add have the prompt be the capital
of France is.
Okay, that's the prompt. Capital of
France is and you say autocomplete
and it autocompletes with Paris.
So that showed that the model knew these
facts, many many facts.
So this idea that the model has
knowledge about the facts that can be
elicited with the right kind of prompt.
This is sometimes called zeroot
learning. Like you don't have to train
it to do this task at all. You take the
model off the shelf and you ask it a
question and it does the answer for you.
Everyone with me?
Okay. So very brief aside, GPT2 when it
came out,
it was not immediately open sourced. In
fact, when this behavior of being able
to generate natural looking text came
out, the people uh within OpenAI that
were concerned with uh AI safety said we
should not release this because suddenly
you'll get a whole bunch of AI generated
text that could be used for
disinformation or all kinds of other bad
things. Other people claimed that the
concerns were these concerns were a good
way of getting press and so calling
causing controversy causing it to be
more popularized. Whatever it was, there
was some degree of controversy
associated with GPT2, but eventually it
was released openly.
Okay, so that was GP29.
Then you had GP3. So GP3 was talked
about the architecture of GP3 was shown
minor variations of architecture largely
it was just bigger um and
the paper was entitled large language
models are few shot learners or
something of that effect and it said
that hey by making the model bigger it
isn't just that it knows facts about the
world but we can teach it something in
the prompt and have it continue the
behavior.
So this is different than the
completions you already had here which
were kind of like genre style. These are
more artificial.
So this idea of incontext learning was
brought out. So just to give you a clean
example I a very classic example that
people use for this is for GPD3 you
could do things like this. You could
have the prompt be red colon Ruby
semicolon blue colon
and tell autocomplete.
So this isn't at the time people thought
this isn't very natural like text.
um but it completes with Sapphire.
Whereas if you do red colon raspberry
blue colon it'll complete with
blueberry. So does everyone see what's
happening here? So you're telling it
you're giving it some examples. We're
doing a problem for this problem which I
haven't told you what it is. I've not
described the problem at all. The answer
to red is Ruby. What's the answer to
blue?
Here's a problem. The answer to red is
raspberry. What's the answer to blue?
And what it's able to do is just by
looking at the context learn that what's
being happening here is we're talking
about gemstones
and it has in its uh weights the
knowledge that the blue gemstone is
sapphire. So the way you would elicit
this information in this zero shot style
would be a prompt that said the blue
gemstone is
or the famous blue gemstone is and
sapphire would come out and the most
popular blueberry is blueberry.
Okay, you have to you have to you have
to prompt it a particular way. This is a
different way of prompting by examples.
Okay, everyone with me? So this ability
is called in context learning. So one of
the projects we said was, you know, this
is a very important um ability of large
language models. It's considered the
root ability actually from which all of
the other nice abilities that you really
care about grow from. So people care a
lot about it. And GP3 was the one that
kind of showed that this was happening
cleanly. This sometimes called fshot
learning because you gave it a few
examples.
Okay. So, pause here for a minute. Any
questions
on what is meant by in context learning?
Okay. Great. So, now
I want to talk about like why was this
considered revolutionary at the time?
And the reason was that
before the idea of ICL of incontext
learning, the way that everybody solved
a machine learning problem was that you
collected a data set.
You then said, "Okay, I want to train a
model on this data set to do
predictions. I'll hold out some data,
all that stuff." And you train a model.
You say okay what features do I use for
the features? You might say I will use
the following pre-trained model or
embedding to get features. That's how
people used to do things.
Now
in context learning lets you solve these
learning problems with a few examples
without any fine-tuning and no gradient
descent steps at all. You just use the
model. You stuff the examples into
context
and then you say
go give me the answer. Everyone with me?
So
from GPT3 the idea of thinking about how
to make a good prompt, how to engineer
context became a big thing. It remains a
big thing. Okay. How to think about the
context and the prompt. But this is
really the point in history when that
happened.
Okay. So now I want to mention one
challenge to make this happen. We're not
going to talk that much about this
challenge at this minute, but we will
get back to it.
To make this work, you have to take all
of your examples, your training data,
and they have to fit inside context.
Does everyone see that? It's just that's
how you it's great. If it's doing in
context learning, it has to have the
thing it's learning from in the context.
So if you have a very small number of
examples,
they might fit. And these early models
were trained with contexts that were
reasonably short uh by today's
standards, right? They were contexts of,
you know, a couple hundred, a thousand,
2,000. For a long time, 2,000 was the
kind of context length that of tokens
that things could handle. But depending
on how many examples you have, 2,000
isn't that much. And even then there was
a question of whether does it really get
all the value it can from the examples.
So lots of work was done at this time
talking about okay you have this in
context learning ability. You can use it
to do these problems. But everything has
to fit in context problem one. Second
problem that people realized is that if
you use the embeddings from the model
and trained a classifier
as opposed to having it do it in
context, the train classifier almost
always did better. Okay, but that's just
uh what's going on. So this prompted a
huge need uh thinking about how can you
make the context longer. That was one of
the things that made people go to things
like rope
for example because in rope because the
interpretations of frequencies it was
more natural to think about how you
could make the context longer
and nope as well. Um, okay. So,
a whole bunch of lines of active
investigation started after GPT3,
but I want to acknowledge uh the main
story that I want to get to, which is
that there's a couple of very natural
questions that happened, which is
one question is how can you find better
prompts? Clearly these models are now
promptable in that you can by picking
the right uh context you can get them to
do interesting things. That was already
true starting at GPT2 but it came very
true after GPT3.
So then there's this question how do you
do this? We will come back to this
question. It's an important question. We
will come back to it.
Um the other question that people had
was
how can we make models that are more
usefully promptable.
Okay. Suddenly you can find the fact
everyone see the kind of evolution of
this start by saying I can prompt these
things and this is useful.
This the question of how can I make
these things more useful in this way
this prompting way.
So I'm going to start with B and talk
about this a little bit. This I think
people should be on board with the
history. We'll come back to a lot of the
stuff technically in a in a moment. So
there was a very critical paper that
came out in 2021. Notice everything is
like in one year, right? Um which is
called the instruct GPT paper.
and instruct GPT was a paper. It was a
collaborative effort of the research
teams at uh Google and OpenAI
and what they wanted to say is how can I
make something more usefully promptable
which they viewed it as instruction
following.
So if you think about it, this kind of
uh analogy
is a kind of implicit instruction
and the autocomplete above is also a
kind of implicit instruction like I'm
telling you something just complete
this. So the idea was maybe we can make
it actually follow instructions.
So if you take a model like GPT3 or any
pre-trained model and you ask it, you
say the prompt is write me a poem about
a cat. Okay, if that's your prompt,
write me a poem about a cat. The
autocomplete answer is not going to be a
poem about a cat.
It'll almost never be that.
So they the idea was maybe we can make
it so that if you tell it write me a
poem about a cat it will give you a poem
about a cat.
So everyone of you who seen so think
about this 2021 fall 2022 is when chat
GPT came out.
Okay. So after this paper was late 2021
um essentially became an all hands-on
deck effort in uh open AI to
commercialize that technology.
uh so this paper uh instruct GPT is
actually is actually another very very
critical paper
and
before I move forward I want to
acknowledge that there's many aspects of
this paper that are
were very important and interesting at
the time remain important and
interesting but it turns out you'll see
in a moment that you didn't need to do
all of this in order to get the effect.
Okay, so I'll tell you what you actually
need to do in a moment but then but I do
want to acknowledge this. So this paper
instruct GPT what it did was it used a
combination of techniques many
techniques including a very key idea
called reinforcement learning with human
feedback
which we will talk about later because
we need some more technical tools before
we can talk about human reinforcement
learning with human feedback. But what
they said was we're basically at a very
high level. It's that the model isn't
very good at doing this task
to start with, but maybe we can reward
it when it does it well. And by
rewarding it when it does it well, it'll
get better and better at it. And then
with enough of these rounds of rewarding
it, it'll be able to do the task. But
it's too expensive to have a human
reward it every time. So we'll train a
machine learning model to act like the
human and the machine learning model
will reward the other machine learning
model until it gets good enough and have
enough human supervision in all this so
that it gets better and better. Very
short form of what happened in that
paper. We'll talk about all that later
because we technically we're not able to
express what all the technical tools
there are.
So, instruct GPT and then the release of
uh of chat GPT in fall 22 was you know
huge impact um on the community. But
people were also very dismayed in that
they said the amount of effort both in
terms of human raiders paying people to
do this job and the size of the models
and the amount of compute needed to
train was viewed as being completely out
of reach of ordinary people
until people
figured out that there's actually a way
to do because that's um easier.
Okay,
so
core to all of this
is
fine-tuning a model of this type
and you can think about it as
fine-tuning for instruction following or
for answering questions. Okay, both are
the same category.
So suppose you wanted to fine-tune a
model and you already have it's already
been pre-trained on a whole bunch of
data. You want to make it good at
answering questions or following
instructions. Basically responding to a
prompt in a particular way.
Let's assume you have all the data you
would ever want. Let's make that
assumption first. You have all the data
you would ever want. What kind of data
would you want?
Anyone want to get if you want make
something good at answering questions?
What kind of data would you want as
training data to make something good at
answering questions?
>> Yeah,
go ahead.
>> Question pairs.
>> Question answer pairs, right? Does
everyone see that question? Here's the
right answer. So, let's assume we have
that question answer pairs. How do you
tune a model to get better at answering
questions? You're answering question
answer pairs. And the answer is well
you set up exactly what you would do at
inference time
and you follow a teaching forcing
strategy. So remember the inference time
picture,
right? Inference time picture is you
have a start, you have a prompt,
you don't care what happens at the part
of the prompt because that's coming from
something else. Then you have the last
token of the prompt
and then something. Okay, so before up
here what we had was a sampler.
But now I have a question answer pair. I
don't need to sample.
Does everyone see that? I I know what
the answer is. I want to follow the
teaching for forcing strategy. So, I'm
going to do the exact thing I did at
pre-training,
which is I'm going to stick a cross
entropy loss here on top
and I'm going to give it the right
answer
to compare to.
Okay, does everyone understand this
picture?
Very important.
There's no loss on the prompt.
No loss on the prompt. Why is there no
loss on the prompt? Because we're not
trying to make it make prompts.
We're trying to make it answer
questions. The prompt is just the input.
Okay. So, this is the key distinction
when you're doing this kind of uh
fine-tuning.
You want to get good at doing the task
that you want to do, which is give
answers, not the question. At
pre-training,
if it saw things, it's it was had a loss
of next token prediction on everything
that it saw because it wants to be able
to replicate all the patterns in the
data. So, there's a difference.
Okay,
everyone with me? Good.
Some people got this a little bit wrong
when they did it in early experiments.
They tried to do pre-training on the
entire question answer pair and they
would find weird behaviors like you ask
it a question and it like asks you a
question. It's like a follow on
question,
right? Um so this was like in hindsight
very clear took some time for people to
realize that you you should do this.
Okay, as as many things are research
wise.
Okay, so why does this work? This works
because
these cross entropy losses,
they generate gradients.
Those gradients flow back, hit the DM
better, they hit all these layers going
down,
right? And then via the attention this
loss then goes back
to all of these things. Okay, loss goes
down goes back to everything and so on.
All the losses the gradients flow
through the entire network
just as they were during pre-training.
So you can do this kind of fine tuning.
This is called supervised fine tuning
generally.
Maybe I'll write that one down.
sometimes shortened to SFT.
So this is the
story. But what happened?
What actually enabled this uh to work
was in 2023
llama model released.
So in 2023 what happened was that so
this is this is already a part of the
technique used to train as one part of
instruct GPD. Okay, there were some
examples of human question answer pairs.
The llama model released in 2023 and in
by 2023 you also had GPT4 and GPT3.5
were available on chat GPT and people
made websites on Reddit and other places
where they would collect and share
interesting prompts that they gave to uh
chat GPT. I was like, "Oh, I asked it to
write this story. Here's my prompt.
Here's the story." Right. Oh, I asked it
to give me a recipe for this. Here's a
question. Here's a recipe. And people
went and scraped Reddit and Twitter and
collected data sets of the answers that
it would give to these kind of prompts.
Right? Everyone's with me?
And in 2023, the llama model gets
released. And the law model when they
released the law model meta they
released it in two versions. They
released one version which was just the
pre-trained version and they released a
second version that was llama after they
had done all of the expensive effort of
instruction fine-tuning.
So both models released. Um
so people said hey we can experiment on
the pre-trained llama model
and
a very important piece of work came out
in 2023 which was called alpaca.
So alpaca a kind of llama right and what
they did in alpaca this is work out of
uh Stanford they said we're going to
take those collected data sets
filter them a little bit and we're just
going to use those data sets only this
is all the Reddit scrapes right and
curated a little bit and we're going to
just do an SFT of the pre-training only
llama
So let me mark make sure this led to
alpaka
and lo and behold
just fine-tuning llama on GPT4s and
GPT3.5's answers I think I think they
finally uh collected it to just GPT3.5
answers for having a better experiment.
Um, GP3.5 answers.
Suddenly, Llama could follow
instructions.
Everyone see that? So it turned out to
get a model to actually follow
instructions, you don't need to actually
give it all of the RL with human
feedback and all having a reward model
that's trained with humans and
comparisons and all the machinery that
was part of instruct GPT. All you needed
was a whole bunch of data that was
instruction following. And then people
stepped back and understood, oh, now we
know what the problem was. The problem
was is that the large corpus of
Wikipedia and text that's out there
doesn't have instruction following well
represented because it's not normal pros
like you don't maybe in sometimes in a
novel someone says hey do this and then
someone does this but it's not like a
common thing but it's a really common
thing for what you want. So there's a
huge mismatch in distributions.
So getting the right kind of data
distribution was critical.
Um
so this showed
instruction
following
examples.
are key.
Now the important thing here is that
alpaca
does definitely generalized, right? What
do we generalized? So maybe it was asked
in the training training data set, give
me a recipe for something.
You could ask it for a totally different
recipe and it would follow the
instructions and give you a recipe for
something totally different. It wasn't
that it just knew how to replicate the
examples that it was taught. It had
captured the idea of instruction
following itself.
So alpaca one cannot like the importance
of llama in the history is kind of very
important because the first very large
model that was open that had both the
pre-training GPT3 was not open still is
not open. Um
yeah question. How do you know?
>> That's a great question. So the alpaca
data set was scraped out of this very um
powerful model GP 3.5 which had all the
work that was done and so it might have
hallucinations and bugs in it. So when
people cured the alpaca data set they
actually chose high quality examples.
Okay. So they had they had they went and
chose high quality examples. None of
this doesn't cure the problem of
hallucinations. Those are those are
there still today, right? They're always
there. Um but you bring up a very
important point which is there was a key
question here which was did this work
because these these generations were
actually out of a synthetic system?
Like what was happening here? Was it
happening because there's a kind of
alignment happening between Llama's data
set which I don't think they released
the exact full nature of their training
data set but it probably had the same
kind of stuff that GPT355 was trained
on. It's different architecture but had
similar stuff. It definitely had
different human raiders because OpenAI
didn't release their human raiders. So
their reward model is definitely
different but there's some amount of
overlap in the training set quite
substantial. for example, we know both
of them have very heavy emphasis on like
Wikipedia and archive papers and stuff
like this, right? Because high quality
stuff that's out there.
And so there was this question of
was this working because you had enough
instruction following examples
or was it working because you had
instruction following examples from a
model that was trained this way. Does
everyone see the qu the thing? There's
some like magic sauce that's in this
specific generations that are happening.
Yeah.
>> The ability to specifically learn
question answering from these prompts
answer
your best.
>> You're right. There's a there's a sense
in which hallucinations are an
orthogonal issue to uh question
answering but there is a an issue here
of whether the ability is coming
>> from
>> the specifics of so that's a kind of
>> you consider that a kind of subtle
hallucination right subtle patterns of
you know GPT3isms
right or GPT4isms that were actually the
key to have it unlock instruction
following you didn't
So amazingly
this was solved in the most creative and
interesting way as a story. I really
like the story is that data bricks made
released dolly. So the problem here was
actually due to copyright and licensing.
So usually we don't talk about history
but here the history is interesting and
it's good for people who didn't live
through it to know it a little bit. So
data brick said look there's a problem.
The GPT3, five, and four license on chat
GPT says you will not use this to train
competing models.
Okay,
there's a separate question. The
copyright office had issued a ruling
that said all AI generated text is not
copyrighted. So what does a license mean
on something that has no copyright?
Okay, se separate question. So people
weren't that worried, but data bricks is
a company. They have a large valuation,
you know, that kind of matters for them.
So they're like, would it be cool if we
could do this without using
instructionated things? So the size of
the alpaca data set is in the tens of
thousands.
So the question was, can you get a human
generated fresh data set of just
instruction following?
And data bricks said, hey employees, if
you want to write some instructions, go
ahead and write some human written
examples of instruction following. And a
lot of people stood up and did it. and
they collected a data set of 10,000ish
human written instructions and lo and
behold and they took a better model than
llama in the sense of licensing anther
AI model um and they trained that
and lo and behold the eluther AI model
also acquired instruction following that
decisively answered the question that it
was just examples of instruction
following that you needed and it wasn't
a GPT ism because they lo data was you
knew exactly what the training data set
was because it was open and released.
So
this showed
it was enough examples
that mattered.
Okay. So
after these results came out and this
SFT, this launched an entire
sea of lots of people doing all kinds of
fine-tunes, collecting data sets, trying
to get models to take certain do better
in certain genres, do better with
certain kinds of instructions and so on.
So huge amount of people work on this
problem, many of whom are just hobbyists
because there's code released that made
it easy for people to do this. People
got code like this to run on collab and
like just a whole so if you go on
hugging face you can see thousands upon
thousands of fine tunes that do all
kinds of like small crazy things.
Okay, so this is a basic technique
though. This is what you're doing. Now
there's more nuance
um which we'll talk about later that
this work showed that this is the key to
get instruction following but to get
really good instruction following
needs more. Okay. And that's we'll talk
about when we talk about RLHF but we
need more tools before we can get there.
Okay, so
now step back. Let's talk about
fine-tuning. So fair trade models, how
can you use them? Now in our world, so
when we started the class, we talked
about kind of these two approaches of
how you do a fine tune.
An approach here which said, hey, I'm
going to treat the model, the
pre-trained model, freeze it, and just
use it as a feature generator. I'll take
its features and do classical ML to my
problem.
Okay, this is also sometimes called
linear probing
because oftentimes the classical ML
technique you're going to do is just
going to use a linear classifier
or basic linear model
and you can choose where to look for the
probe. So for example in BERT
you can look at the embeddings at the
last layer. totally normal thing to do.
You could also look at the embeddings at
the layer before the last layer. You
could also look at the embeddings in the
layer before that. You could choose to
average the embeddings across the top 10
layers. Lots of such choices exist and
work better and worse in certain cases.
So lots of creativity can happen as
using a feature extractor, but you
freeze the model. You never touch the
pre-trained model. So we talked about
stuff like this before. And then we
talked about doing a full fine tune. You
take the entire model and you fully
fine-tune it. you let all the weights
move and adjust for your new task.
With GPT3,
you had this pure prompting strategy
also.
So now what we're going to talk about is
how to go beyond these three basic
things.
And a way to think about it is we're
going to think about first uh 0.5.
Okay?
And then we're gonna talk about how to
do a 1.5.
Okay. After we see what happens with
0.5.
So pause here
everyone see the big picture. So now in
the history of what's going on, we have
models that are pre-trained on lots of
data. It turns out that if you want to
get them to be good at something, you
give lots of examples of that and
fine-tune them, they can get good at it.
That's all this in this full fine-tuned
strategy.
Once they're good at that, you could
then use it a pure prompting strategy or
you could again use it as an embedding.
Okay, so
return to our question A from above. How
do we get better prompts? Look at the
pure prompting strategy.
So
again the history of this is
interesting. When people started off and
it turned out that prompting mattered
people did all kinds of chat was
released and you had a whole group of
people online just ordinary people
playing with this that are not
researchers and they were reporting
their findings on Reddit and Twitter and
all these other places. And you had all
people people saying,"Wait, it turns out
if I tell it, you know, if I'm mean to
it, it sometimes helps, right? If I'm
rude to it, it helps. Or if I flatter
it, it helps, right? All kinds of like
weird behaviors were being reported. And
so, how to get better prompts was uh
became a kind of a craft skill that
people had to figure out and learn.
And
then of course people's like okay how
can we do this more systematically? Can
we do it more systematically? So here
before I talk about 0.5 I want to talk
about something which is not in scope
for the class but you should know about.
So, this is an aside.
If you actually want to do a better
prompt and you have only API access to
the model, which means you can't
actually look at the model, look at its
weights or what's going on inside of it.
You just have you only have the model
itself,
then there are actually tools out there
that will help you systematically get
better prompts.
So one of the most popular kind of
packages families is something called
DSPY.
Has anyone here used it? Few of you, a
couple of you. Yeah. So you want to use
this because it has it always
incorporates new algorithms into it. So
just in terms of like if you want to
know like time frame, there's a new
algorithm that came out this summer
called GPA. It's a Berkeley algorithm
and what it does is it actually it does
like an optimization of prompts and it
actually uses an LM inside the
optimization. So it asks an LM to
generate prompts and ask LMS to modify
prompts based on what it observes from
the behaviors of other prompts.
So just keeps running.
So this idea of using an LLM to
uh
reflect on what's happening and suggest
a correction. Another group of uh people
you look up text grad
text grad means what if your gradient
was text.
So let me back that up. So you think
about machine learning you think about
you have something you want to make a
change. The direction of change is
gradients are like vectors and then you
go through and you apply that change
through everything. The idea here was
what if your delta
was text like that was pretty good
except you should do this.
How can you back prop text
through a prompt to get a better prompt?
So textual gradients. So the techniques
that are used here are all based are
based on approaches to optimization that
don't require actual gradients.
So there's Beijian style optimization
which we don't talk about in this class.
There's also genetic algorithms which is
another way of doing optimization that
don't require um gradients and it's
basically exploring the comtorial space
of like prompts in a efficient manner.
So if you just want to do pure prompting
you can do stuff like this. I'm not
going to talk about this anymore.
Okay. So, and this is not in scope of
the class
because we kind of live in gradient
land.
Okay. So, let's assume we have the
model. Okay. So, we actually have the
model.
So, here's my model.
And the problem is I don't have the
prompt.
I want to get a good prompt. Does
everyone see like can I see everyone see
like the picture here what I'm trying to
do. So
we need this
we have only uh this is needed.
How can I do this if I have access to
the model?
So,
anyone have a suggestion?
Like I know the behavior I want. Okay.
So, let me make make it a little bit
clear. So, we're thinking of an example
where
there's something we want to do
and we have a question and an answer,
but we need a prompt that's more than
just the question. There's like a
context for the question that we as a
human understand, but the model needs to
be told what the context is someway.
Does everyone see the picture? So in a
in a normal
handcrafted prompt engineering, it would
be the kind of text that's like, "You're
a machine learning expert. It's really
important that you do this job. I'll be
mad if you don't and if you don't,
kittens will die." You know, stuff like
this kind of stuff that people do. If
people have seen this kind of stuff that
people post, right? You have like bunch
of text that people write that kind of
has some parts that are important in
terms and some part that seem weird and
then after that it says and said then
some more context oh and what I'm trying
to work on is all these questions have
to do with my database system for which
I need to have a good way of extracting
queries.
Okay. Then you say my question is given
this table what's the what should I do?
Okay. So the actual question you have is
the given this table what should I do
kind of question.
Suppose you have answers for many of
these kinds of questions. It comes up
many times. But it's that other text.
Okay. So I'm going to take this needed
text. I'm going to divide it into two
two parts.
Let me erase this.
Let's make it two parts.
I need a pre-prompt
and then I have
question.
This question requires context.
So I'm trying to get this pre-prompt.
That's the thing I want to optimize.
Is it clear we're trying to do? Okay.
So now
let's think
we have data we have lots of question
response pairs that are correct suppose
we have this so we have examples
I want to get what goes here what can I
Anyone
have an idea?
>> Yeah.
>> Question about the question.
>> Sure.
>> So we're saying are we saying that we
want a model to give us that?
>> Oh, great. So let me the model we have
is uh let's say llama 33. Okay. So we
have it a specific model.
We think the model is quite capable. The
model however if we just give it our
question how do I make a query for this
particular table that extracts blah it
does a bad job. It doesn't actually give
me good answers.
And
so I could try to just do a fine tune of
llama 33
train all the weights to get better at
these question answer pairs. However, I
don't want to do that. I want to only
get a better prompt.
Okay. So if I had these question answer
pairs, I could do a full fine tune. So
let's assume that I do that and it
works. So I know it's possible to
fine-tune this model except I can't
afford to do it
or I actually although I can run llama
33 and fine-tune it I don't have the
capability of hosting full inference of
this thing at scale of my of my custom
model. So what I want to do is I want to
use somebody else's llama 33 inference
and just shoot stuff into it and get the
answers. Everyone see kind of I'm only
trying to get a better prompt.
>> Yeah.
>> Very good. So the idea is we want to do
something like a fine-tuning run except
we want to do a fine tuning run on the
pre-prompt. We don't want to change the
weights inside the model. The question
is how can we do that or what's the
challenge we have and how do we resolve
that challenge? That's the question.
Okay, so I want to freeze the entire
model. I want to change only here. What
can I do? And what what's what's my
obstacle?
>> Yeah.
versus
>> yeah the problem is so if I do this I
can definitely get gradients right I can
have gradients flowing you know from
oops I don't want to do that
I can get gradients flowing you know
from all these places
down into this pre-prompt but the
problem is the gradients can't cross
the embed properly
because this thing is discrete on this
side. So I can't change it a little bit.
Does everyone see this issue? So if I
want to do
this problem, but I can't.
Okay. I want to make sure everyone's
everyone's clear on the challenge. Ask
me a question if you don't understand
the challenge here
or the basic approach. I want to do it
using gradients. Yeah. Question. I was
see.
>> Sure. So what you're describing of
seeing what it does, you pick a prompt.
So you start with a human engineered
prompt, then you run it and then you
human reflect and you see what did it
get wrong and then you human change the
prompt. That's what people did.
Okay. And but it's annoying. And second,
it's not very scalable. And third,
humans aren't necessarily that good at
it.
So, DSPY is a way of automating that
particular process. And this textual
gradients and other ideas are a way of
trying to do that. What I'm trying to do
is I'm trying to use good oldfashioned
gradients to solve the problem, not this
kind of textual reflection.
>> Yeah.
from the question.
>> I'm not following. So I have this I want
to get this pre-prompt. So you're saying
I could ask the model to say I have
these questions and these answers. Give
me a prompt that will give me those
questions and answers.
>> Based on your question, there's some
part of the model that will generate
prompts.
So the model is just this stack of
embedded transformer layers dime and so
on.
Okay. So this is not the output of
anything.
The only way to make it the output of
anything is to ask this model a question
that involves this as an output. But
this is not an output.
So you can't So
all of these approaches that you're
describing are all in the style of
things that are done systematically by
things like DSPY.
Okay. Using Beijian optimization,
genetic algorithms and other approaches,
you know, textual gradient like
thinking. So I want to use this straight
up regular gradients. Yeah.
Excellent. Okay, that's what we're going
to do. So here's a way of thinking about
it um in a way that you can generalize
thinking. It says I would like to have
gradients go back to the pre-prompt.
However, they get stopped here.
I can't go back. So fine, stop here.
Say, okay, can't do this.
just
have a soft prompt
that just consists of the embeddings. So
I take the initial human prompt, I get
embeddings for it. I call those all
special tokens.
Okay, these are special tokens. I'm
adding to my token table. I initialize
them as copies of the embeddings that
they used to have.
But then I let gradients fall into the
embeder in those special tokens. This
gets frozen into special one, special
two, special three, special four,
special five, special six, special so on
just specials, a whole bunch of
specials.
So if I'm going to optimize something
that's 100 long, I have 100 specials
and I have gradients falling into the
embedding table only. Okay, now does
everyone see that idea? the gradients
can can go to the embedder.
I've added these special things and now
they will move continuously.
This is called a soft prompt because it
can move continuously. It's soft and not
hard in terms of discrete.
Also, it's called a continuous prompt
but soft prompt is the standard term.
Now you were suggesting something that
goes beyond that which is also done
which says after I have optimized my
soft prompt for a while. I can choose to
quantize it back to discrete tokens
to say what is this what is the actual
discrete token in my actual embed that's
closest to this one. take some of them
and quantize them back down to that and
then continue to do gradient steps on
the rest to adjust to the things I just
froze and again project them and keep
doing this until finally I projected all
of them down and now I have a frozen
prompt that's actually
in token language it won't be human
interpretable it'll be weird
but it may might have the same effect
this is done okay but I'm just going to
stop at the soft prompting I'm totally
happy. So I'm going to say if my API
lets me inject not just tokens but
actual embeddings in
then I can just prompt it with a
continuous embedding sequence.
Yeah. Question.
So there
>> that's a very good question and in fact
this approach is restricted to having a
fixed length of these prompts. So my
pre-prompt is fixed length. My question
can be variable length.
This is a human readable question that
is coming in. But this is fixed and it's
just trying to get it to do the task I
want. If I want to play with that
length, I can just treat that as a
hyperparameter that I have to sweep over
and train. So people have played with
this soft. So everyone understand the
key idea of soft prompting. No. Okay. So
someone who doesn't understand what
we're doing ask me a question because
I'm not sure I don't understand.
>> Yeah. What do you mean about special?
>> Great. Let me make it clear
[snorts]
to be precise.
Let me switch my color.
If
is length 100. Okay.
Call it
special one
through special 100
where
the embeder
has
100 new row new columns.
added
for
these guys.
So explicitly I'm saying I'm going to
introduce new tokens. They did not exist
in pre-training. They're new tokens.
They have to be represented in the
embedder. So I add 100 new columns for
them. I initialize those 100 columns
somehow. For example, I initialize them
with a human engineered prompt. I copy
the embedding of the human engineered
prompt pre-prompt and I drop them in.
But these are now learnable parameters.
>> So they're just like the mask tokens
tokens.
They're just like the start token or a
mask token. Yeah, they're special.
They're like any token. Okay. Um so
they're learnable parameters. Everything
else in the model is frozen.
So gradients are flowing to everything,
but these are the only ones that are
learnable. What does that mean? The only
thing I'm tracking in optimizer state is
these guys. So I have momentum for these
guys. I have magnitude squares for these
guys. I track these hundred parameters.
Everything else is frozen. I don't do
any updates to them. I only update
these.
>> Yeah.
>> Excellent question. Are these weight
shared? Um, if you want to think about
them as being weight shared, you can
think of them as there's hundred special
ones and they're weight shared across
all of these embedders, but they're
never actually used in two different
places.
every position has its own. So in that
sense it doesn't matter
and they're not used at they don't
they're not weight shared up at the D
embed because they don't exist at the D
embedter. They're never predicted
just that there's like ampken
token
when it goes in the gives us our ideal
soft.
>> Yes. Exactly. You can think of it this
way. You can also think of it as you
assume you have API access that lets you
inject things not at the prompt level
but at this level unless you inject an
embedding directly into your model.
>> Yeah.
>> I'm trying to understand exactly how
this is because it seems like this is
now tailor engineered to this specific
question. So it seems like it's only
useful if you're going to repeatedly ask
the same question. Exact question. Very
good question. So the question is why am
I doing this? I'm doing this because all
fine-tunes
are only done in the setting where
there's a task that I want to do many
many times and I would like to have a
model that can do that task many many
times. If I have a task I want to do
once that's not a fine-tuning problem
typically. So there's a particular kinds
of question I need to ask many many
times. So for that I would like to have
a prompt that will let me do this many
many times. In particular I'd like to
have a pre-prompt that lets me ask many
questions of this kind of genre
>> and have it do well.
>> People use MCPS where like you want the
output to be formatted like a JSON and
so you use like this as like okay give
me JSON.
>> That's a great example. So JSON is
actually so important that the models
themselves are trained to generate good
JSON but the that's an example. there's
a specific format. You want to be able
to get it to do that format. You would
like to have a model that's very good at
that format. And so you can't afford to
make an entire model, but maybe you can
find a good way of prompting it. And
this is a soft prompt approach of doing
it. Yeah.
>> Transfer across models if
>> Yeah, great question. Do soft prompts
transfer across models? If so, how well?
They do not transfer across models. So
basic answer they can sometimes transfer
a little bit across model variants that
are both fine-tunes of the same thing
but they generally are restricted. In
fact even if you quantize them to
something they won't transfer. The
amazing thing about DSPY and those
prompts is that sometimes those do
transfer across models.
Um
yeah okay so everyone's good with this?
So now,
amazingly, people saw that when you did
this, they worked. I'll skip ahead.
Okay,
so there's another another version of
it. It's called prefix soft prefixes.
I'll explain that in a moment. Um, but
the amazing thing is they have far far
far fewer parameters in the entire
model. So here's an example. Suppose I
have an 8 billion parameter llama model,
okay?
and my embedding is length 4,96
and I choose a pre-prompt length of 100.
How many parameters in this embedding do
I have to learn? Well, 4,96 times 100,
40,000 parameters. So, I just have to
tune 40,000 parameters
as opposed to a full fine tune which
would be seven or eight billion
parameters.
And what people found was that for many
problems, the soft prompt was getting
performance very very close to the full
fine-tune
at a radically reduced parameter count.
And what they found was that the bigger
the model got, the better the soft
prompt was doing.
So the bigger huge models, a small soft
prompt was able to control it very well.
So people said okay if I don't want to
just do the prompt
remember the picture
what is actually going
how is this pre-prompt actually
influencing everything over here it's
only influencing through the states and
the key value cache right all this is
going to go up and get turned into keys
and values and those are going to come
over here to interpret the question and
to give answers.
So if you wanted to have the full
tunability,
instead of just tuning just the
embedding, you just let the gradients
follow the keys and values and just copy
them. Say there's a special key value
pair for every head
and the gradients will fall into that
key value pair. That's it.
Does everyone see that qu? See, see, see
the as the gradient flows back this way,
the way it flows back is it hits the
keys and the values in the attention.
So just let the keys and the values
themselves mutate right there. Change
make them be learnable parameters.
If I do that,
suppose there's 32 layers in this model.
I have 4,96 for all the keys of
multi-headed attention.
4,96 for all the values of multi head
attention
times 32 layers
which is 262,000.
Yeah.
>> Ah because the queries aren't the query
the queries are generated by the
question and the queries are generated
here.
Right? The queries are generated this
way. The past queries have no influence
except how they influence the keys and
the values. The state is the keys and
the values.
>> No, the important thing is state, right?
In a transformer network attention, the
state of the past is captured by the
keys and the values.
There's no past query state. The queries
were consumed in the past. They don't
proceed in the future. They influence
keys and values at the next layer. But
only keys and values go from the past
into the future.
So soft prompting extended to the entire
prefix is just all the keys and values.
Nothing else. Yeah. Question.
>> No, no, no. Very important. Okay. Again,
you have a choice. What does it mean
precisely? You can think of it as that
there's literally a key. I just make
that key learnable. Alternatively, you
can think of it as I add a special
column to my key matrix. That's what the
key that would be generated here is.
And only that one will ever get looked
at. Your choice. It's easier to think of
it as just the key, the specific key
that's going to be generated for this
token at this layer and this head and
let that be a learnable parameter.
>> Uh I believe the answer to your question
is yes. So you have that. So, let's just
be precise. Um,
inside here,
zoom in. There's I don't know what the
answer for llama is. Let's suppose
there's 90 head. There's not 90 heads.
There's 60 heads.
64 heads, suppose. I don't know if
that's the right number, right? And so,
there's going to be
64 keys and 64 values.
generated
on top of start at this layer.
I make all of those specific keys and
values learnable parameters.
I I they're not they're no longer the
output of the key matrix times the
embedding. They're just their own
parameters.
>> This is just for
>> no for everyone for all of the all of
the um pre-prompt
for all of the preprompt I make them all
special values
so that
what I get is I have 32 layers of
times 100 sorry I didn't I didn't put
the final times 100 in here
so this is let me label this this is
keys
this is values
this is layers
and this This is 100
26 million.
Okay. So I have 26 million which is
bigger than 40,000
but far far smaller than 8 billion.
>> Yes.
Is each of the learning
prompt?
>> So okay, this is called soft prompting
up here
and this is called prefix.
Okay, or soft prefix
in a soft prefix. I'm just going to
learn the kvs
because these soft prompts, what did
they affect? They affected the kvs.
That's how they actually affect what's
going to happen in the interpretation of
the question and the generation of the
answer. So I can just change the state
itself. This is making the entire state
learnable.
So the entire state is learnable
basically on all the gradient paths.
When the gradient comes back to hit
these points, it just stops. Okay, I
will continue with Laura's next time,
but
comes back here and just stops there.
Okay. So, yeah, we'll continue next
time.