That's kind of
>> Okay, we're at Berkeley time, so let's
get started.
Before I start the official lecture
part, a important announcement. I wanted
to put the projects back on your radar
in case you've forgotten. But everyone
remember that we have projects in this
class. Yes. Okay. And that you have a
proposal for them due pretty soon. And
you have to meet with a staff member,
core staff member before submitting the
project proposal. Right? So we want you
to meet with us before you even submit
the first version so that if you have an
idea that is going to never work or
going to be impossibly hard or is going
to require infinite compute to be able
to
uh do we can try to have you know help
you have a proposal that is actually
feasible doable within the scope of what
you have access to within this class.
Okay. So make sure you sign up. There's
a bunch of slots. Uh I have a bunch of
slots today right after class during
office hours. Um and the way we have it
set up is we've have have these set up
into 15 minute time slots per team,
right? So that you have to choose a time
slot so they were not, you know, 10
people don't suddenly show up to office
hours and there's you know not enough
time to talk to each of you. So we have
a sign up strategy so that everyone will
get time. Make sure that you sign up.
One sign up per team is required. So
basically one team member signs up and
invites the other people to to join.
Does that make sense? Any questions
about the project?
Okay, good. So just please remember to
uh to do that.
Um okay, great.
So with that then I'm going to start up
with the actual content of the lecture
and what we're going to be transitioning
to talk about today is attention
mechanisms. Okay. And building towards
talking about you know transformer
networks uh and transformer models in
the next lecture.
So we finished up state space and we
thought of state space as trying to
solve basically
one of the challenges with recurrent
neural networks right and this was um
what state space models did was that
they allowed you to you know use this
convolution perspective and therefore
parallelize your your training and have
a lot of benefit over uh or get around
some of the challenges in training
recurrent neural networks and the
strength of these state space models
really comes from the fact that you can
make this state very very large,
right? And by making the state very very
large, you can cram a bunch of different
information into it. And that allows you
to get the kind of performance that you
can out of the state space models. And
the interesting thing is that remember
when you have the state space you have
the x which is your input you have the h
which is your hidden state and then you
have the y's which are your output the h
can be very big but the c matrix is
going to can shrink the y back down
right so you can have uh this
dimensionality reduction when you are
actually uh maybe going through the ml
so you don't have this massive
parameters and massive amount of u
massive size of the model even though
your state is actually quite big, right?
So that is one of the things that the
the state space models did. Today what
we're going to talk about is we're going
to talk about attention which is another
basically a different approach to uh
dealing with some of the challenges of
recurrent neural networks or in the
sense that it emerged also out of well
we're having trouble with recurrent
neural networks how can we uh get around
them and historically actually attention
in some sense came first right so uh
this attention is all you need and
attention was a thing even before this
famous attention is all you need paper
that came out of uh out of Google. So
attention had been being used and it was
being used along with basically RNN's to
try and improve their performance. But
then what people realized and we'll talk
about this is that actually you don't
need to have the RNN structure around
it. You can just have attention and that
can get you a lot of performance. and
the state space models work was done
separately and in some sense happened
after uh the
uh attention work happened. Okay, even
though I'm sure the ideas were in the
people's heads even before. Okay. So I
want to focus now on sequence problems
using RNNs. The key example that I'm
going to talk about is translation. So,
I'm thinking about translating a
sentence from English to Chinese or
Marati, which is my mother tongue or
whatever other language that you uh
might want to do.
And the RNN style networks to do this um
use what we call an encoder decoder
architecture. Okay.
So here what you have basically for this
is you have [snorts] you have some input
and then you have a recurrent layer one
and a recurrent layer two and a
recurrent layer three so on and so forth
going up and this we will think of as
our encoder
and then you have a decoder which is you
know you have to start somewhere so you
will have what we call a start token and
then an RNN and RNN RN RN layers going
on top of each other and when I really
talk about an RNN block here. What I'm
thinking about is something I have my
input coming in. I have some hidden
state here. Here is kind of my uh loop
that is by RNN. Uh and then I have maybe
an MLP or something. I might also have a
normalization in here that I'm not
really showing. There'll be residual
connections. I'm not showing all of
that, but I'm just trying to give you
the spirit of what an RNN style network
for a sequence problem might look like.
Okay, just at a high level,
what I want to show here is that how
would this information from this encoder
get to this decoder? Right? So, what do
we want to do? we have a we have some
sentence um like
I don't know uh give me the book or give
me the paper and I want to translate it
into some uh some other language. So
what I'm going to do is I'm going to
have this input sentence and I'm going
to feed it to my network. it is going to
generate some
um hidden states in my RNN
and then after I've put in all of my
initial my sentence that I want to
translate then I'm going to try and
basically have the state information
that is present in my encoder move over
to my decoder so that then I can use
that as the state as the initial
condition to help me start up my
decoder. Okay? Because I want to
basically take information from my input
sentence which is in say let's say
English and then I want to use that
information about that sentence to
generate my translation in whatever
other language that I want to use.
Right? So I have to have a way of
connecting these two these two things
and the way that an RNN style network
would do that would be through
connecting
these uh RNN states. Okay, does that
make sense to everyone?
So if we think about this in some as
basically unrolling this, right? Let's
say I have some input sentence and my
input sentence is
says X1, X2, X3. This is representing my
input sentence. Let's say my input
sentence is length T long, capital T.
Okay,
I'm trying to show this yellow block
here [snorts] unrolled
over here. This is my encoder. The green
block is my decoder and I'm showing it
over here.
Okay, so this we is representing all of
the weights in that uh encoder block.
Everyone with me?
I'm unrolling I've unrolled this to
through time. This is my input sentence.
But what is a key challenge that we're
going to to face here, right? So I have
I put in my first token. I do something.
Then comes the second token. Then comes
the third token. Then comes the last
token. So on and so forth. And then I
use
all of this to set the initial
conditions for my decoder
that is going to lead to the actual
translation. Okay,
it's important to remember here that the
first input that I put to my decoder,
I'm going to call it a start token. Um,
as is always the case, we don't know
what to say for our start tokens. We
often choose to just learn what the
start token is.
So let me just talk a little bit about
how this decoder is going to work.
Actually before I go to the decoder, let
me just talk about this this first
encoder thing. Okay, so I have an input
sentence of length t.
Now I need to somehow
have all of this information about this
sentence. Give me the paper. And so
maybe I' I've I can say something about
okay, this is about maybe this is about
a paper. Maybe it's about some kind of
transaction. There's some information in
that sentence. And the only thing that I
[clears throat] have by which I can
communicate this to the decoder
is this red dotted link in some sense,
right? And what am I using that red
dotted link to represent? I'm saying
that I want to be able to take all of
the state that has been generated here
and use it to set the initial condition
here.
Okay. So is that it's all of the
information about that sentence has to
be captured into this one little state.
And so the only choices you have if you
want to communicate lots and lots of
information through that one state is to
make that state very very big but making
the state big makes things very very
difficult to train. So do you see the
tension here that one is facing
>> questions I feel like people are not
with me fully yet.
>> Yes.
>> Is that the the last layer and the last
time.
>> It is not the last layer. Okay, let me
do this again. So this yellow block is
that whole yellow block.
I make this smaller.
This yellow is this yellow.
Okay. And I'm so using we to represent
all of the weights of all of the RNN
everything there. And what I'm going to
do is I'm going to say let me run this
RNN for t time steps because I'm going
to unroll it. So horizontal the the x-
axis is is my time dimension. The y-axis
is my layers, right? Vertically I'm
going by layers. Horizontally I'm going
by time. So this is all just what is
happening when I you know give me the
book. Okay. So this is I'm advancing in
my sequence
and then I essentially have basically
like a dotted red connection from here
to here and from here to here. So that
whatever at time at sequence position t
or at time t
whatever the state here is I use that to
make the initial condition for this for
the decoder.
Right? So I I run this until the input
sentence is done
and I'm then moving that information
over to the decoder to start the
translation
through the state. So all I have to
communicate between the encoder and the
decoder is whatever ends up inside here
after t time steps.
>> Yes.
Yes. So does that limit our length of
our output sequence?
>> Does it limit the length of the output
sequence? No, it does not. Right? That's
the magic in some sense of RNN's
because I can keep generating as long as
I want because
this is the unrolled version
but the non the the tight version or the
compact version you have like the the
RNN you can keep running the RNN until
you're done right
so it does not like and and this is
really important for translation because
a short sentence in one language might
be a longer sentence in a lang another
language. And the other key problem that
we're going to talk about is that and
one of the motivating things for
attention is that sentence word order in
in sentences is not preserved when you
translate. Right? So you can have the
same words but they might be in
different orders. It's not like you
translate one sentence to another
sentence. The first word is the first
word and the second word is the second
word. [snorts]
>> Yes.
the length of these decoded sentence.
>> Um, so you will either decide to just
generate an end token
and then your model will your model
itself will learn when to end. We don't
know what we don't set in advance what
that is. [snorts]
One of the tokens it can possibly emit
will be an end token.
>> Yes. You might have mentioned this
already, but how do you set the start
for the first decoder?
>> How do you set the start for the first
decoder? Good question. So, we can say
there's multiple different ways in which
we could start a translation, right? So,
I basically need to feed the decoder
with something to start. It's an RNN. It
has to have some input. So, what do I
put into it? The idea of a start token
is saying we want to just get the
decoder going. And so this is just some
way of saying let's go
because we don't know what is the right
start token. We often will just learn
the value of the start token.
It's another parameter that just
gradient descent plows through
>> and so the number of decoders like isn't
necessarily
right because it stops once you
>> so don't confused between the unrolling.
This is unrolling. So this is time
right. So here
this you know this part um
maybe this has four words in the
sentence.
But here, this could have 10, 20,
whatever. It'll go on as long as you
need to have the sentence translate
appropriately.
Here there's a correspondence,
but these are layers. These are not this
is not time unrolling.
>> Yeah. Like what I mean is like so the
number of time steps that like WD goes
forward is equal to the number of times
W.
>> No, it is not equal. That's the
important thing. this um
uh
note
t depends
on length
of
input
sentence.
Uh
unrolled
length
of
encoder
and decoder
might
be different.
Sure.
Yeah. You can say that this will
eventually stop.
>> Yes. [snorts]
>> Say that the number of the blocks in the
encoder depends on the length of the
input. The number of the blocks.
Exactly. The number of the number the
don't think of it as blocks. This is the
unrolled, right? So the number of So
remember we talked about RNN's and we
had like this unrolling perspective. So
I am all I'm doing is unrolling. I'm
trying to visualize the unrolling and
that makes it seem like there's
different blocks, but there's not
different blocks,
right? It's the same RNN just at
different time steps.
It's not different blocks. It's really
important. These are not different
blocks. This is the same block at
different times.
>> Yes.
>> Is um are the layers like they're like
they have the same amounts of layers and
the encoders and decoders?
>> Yes. The number of layers. So here there
is a correspondence,
right? I I think everyone's getting
confused between horizontal and vertical
directions, right? Horizontal is time,
vertical is layers. So these here,
these are layers. This is the first
layer. This is the second layer. This is
the third layer. So on and so forth. And
there's a correspondence between layers
of the encoder to layers of the decoder
because I'm using the state of each
layer to basically jump start the
decoder.
But there is not a correspondence
between how many time like this has
nothing to do this part how long this is
has nothing to do with the architecture.
This has to do with your input. Your
input will change every time.
So for short sentences this will be
short for long sentences it will be
long.
>> Yes.
>> Architecturally required that the input
and output have the same number of
layers or is that just like a common
convention?
Um, in this kind of network they are the
same.
In
like modern transformer networks now
where you have an encoder decoder
structure they are not necessarily
always the same but we're not like in in
this one this is yes it is it is
required to be the same.
Okay. Okay, is everyone with me now?
Yes. No. Thumbs up, thumbs downs. Okay,
did the discussion helped? Okay, good.
So, horizontal is time, vertical is
layers. What we want to do is we want to
translate a sentence.
Okay.
[clears throat]
So, the key problem that we have is that
this thing is a is a bottleneck, right?
This is the only thing I'm drawing this
arrow here and this is I'm drawing a
dotted arrow here because it is not like
I'm taking this and passing this
forward. I'm just drawing this as like
this is the way this is where the
information is being passed but the
information is being passed through the
state of this and that state is being
used to populate this state which then
again gets unrolled. Okay, but all I
have is that state
to communicate to the decoder. And if I
have a really long sentence, then that's
a lot of information that has to be
crammed into this small bottleneck.
And that that's challenging. Okay.
So, what do we do to solve this
bottleneck? Okay. And that's what we're
going to kind of uh try to try to get
at. Before I get at that,
I wanted to just explain this idea of uh
training this kind of network and it's
called it has a funny name. It's called
teacher forcing
what this is done. So how would you
train this kind of thing, right? How are
we going to train this kind of thing?
What I'm going to do is I'm going to at
train time I'm going to put in my input,
right? So, I'm going to put in give me
the book. [snorts]
And then I'm going to go to my decoder
and I'm going to put in the start token
and it's going to output something,
right? It's going to maybe output this
Y1 hat. Now, there's a couple of things
to think that I want to point out. One,
we've already said we don't know how to
start. So, we're going to learn the
start token. That's thing one. But then,
what do we do for this next guy? What
are our choices for what to put in here?
There's a couple of different choices,
right?
One is what we do at train time and one
is what we do at test time. So at test
time or at inference time, what we want
to do is we want this decoder to just be
able to generate stuff one after the
other, one after the other, one after
the other. So for test time, what we're
going to do is going to have auto
reggressive generation. So, what I'm
going to do is I'm going to say, well,
here I said start.
Whatever comes out of here, I'm going to
feed it back in
to here. And then that's kind of the
input for the next thing to start,
right? Because essentially I'm saying,
you know, give me the book. Mari would
be so I will take that first word, feed
it back in, and then hope that the next
word would come back out, right?
And there I'm just hoping that whatever
I generated in from the first time step
was the right thing. Okay. [snorts] And
that's that's what's going to happen at
inference time.
At train time, it turns out that you
don't want to be feeding the decoder
with mistakes,
right? You want to try and align what
the decoder has to to be as close to the
correct stuff as possible. So
even at test time, at training time,
even if let's say the first time step
outputed some kind of garbage,
I'm not going to take that token. I'm
not going to take this yhat and feed it
back in here. What I'm going to do is
instead I'm going to say, "Hey, look, I
have training data. Lucky me. I'm going
to feed in the true y."
And then I'm going to take my loss on
that on the y on the on the y2 hat
that's generated from my true y1. Okay.
So when I'm computing the losses on
this, I'm going to compute losses on all
of these that's going to what that's
going to that is what is going to make
my gradients flow back through.
But then I'm going to have these true
wise and those are going to be given as
inputs so that I'm not putting the auto
reggressive generated stuff back into
the network because it might be wrong
and then who knows like and I'm just
learning to predict the wrong something
from the wrong thing and like doesn't
work out. So it turns out it works out
works better to do what is called
teacher forcing. It's called basically
you're forcing the right output, right?
That's why it's teacher forcing.
So even if this was wrong, you put the
right input in here. And this is a
standard technique that's used for this
kind of uh problem where you have you
want to be able to generate auto
reggressively. So at test time, at
inference time, you're not going to be
doing this because you don't know what
the ground truth translation is. But at
train time, this is what you're going to
do.
>> Yes,
>> you have mentioned this. You wrote with
sampling. What did you
>> Okay, good. Sorry, I did not mention
this. I forgot to mention this. So,
thank you. So, when we have these uh
RNNs, what is this generating? Right?
This uh layer is generating
um I'm doing some let's say I'm doing
some kind of soft max. I'm getting a
bunch of probabilities on output tokens.
Okay.
But now when I'm doing an actual
generation, like if I was doing a
classification task, maybe probabilities
are good enough.
But now that I'm doing a generation
task, I need to choose something to
actually feed in to the next layer,
right? I can say, well, there's 50%
probability of this and 30% probability
of this and 20% probability of this.
That doesn't get me a translation. That
just gets me like some distribution of
words. So to generate the next token, I
need to choose one of these words. And
so what I need to do is I need to sample
Ah, so how do I sample? There's many
different ways to sample, right? So
let's say I have different tokens. So
how do I sample? Let's uh
let me
so let me
sampling
what I have here.
is probabilities.
So, let's say I have um
y1
with 50%.
Uh I don't like this y subscript.
Let's say I just have um
let me just use this example
in harchy. This would be
okay. So this is word
one, two, three, four.
This is one, two, three. So now I put in
my start token to my decoder.
It goes into my decoder and it produces
something. And now it has produced what
this produces here is it produces let's
say
uh
let's say this is 50%.
and then uh
with some 60%
and I don't know whatever else produces
different it can't produce this with
60%. It produces this with 20%. Okay, so
it produces some words.
Now I need to be able to take all of
this
and actually generate something that I
can feed in to the next layer,
right?
How do I do that? I basically need to
sample from this distribution this
discrete this distribution um that is on
these words that have been generated. So
how can I do that? Well, one way is to
be greedy and say I'm always going to
choose the thing with the maximum
probability. It turns out in practice
that that doesn't work as well and some
amount of randomness actually helps you.
Does that make sense?
How do you So, so basically I I I So
what do I say? I I don't add a
randomness. I say like look here here's
my distribution and I literally draw a
sample from it. So I I I I roll a
dieice.
Yeah, I'm just sampling from that
distribution. Right. This what what I
get as the output is a distribution on
my output uh token tokens.
reason why
brand sampling is working but the
highest probability might not work
sometimes because you know you're just
uh it's just the nature of the data that
like you might not uh
have
yeah just I guess there's no I don't
have a rigorous explanation for you
because it's just an observational thing
there's no proof of why this is better
one might think that if you were doing
some kind of maximum likelihood do
coding and if if you know in some kind
of uh uh
probabilistic sense you wanted to have
the best thing well you have all these
rules right you can have the best match
be you have the maximum likelihood rule
or the maximum a posterior rule you can
do all of these different kinds of rules
and those those are provably best in the
sense of some kind of metric often
squared loss but here it's language and
squared loss or these metrics they're
they're just mathematical notions and
somehow those are not what is best for
language. So I there's there's no way to
prove to you that randomness is better.
It's just that that's what's observed in
practice. And so what you might observe
is like if you've played with these
things, you have this temperature
parameter and you can set the
temperature to zero. You can set the
temperature to be high. The higher the
temperature is, the more the randomness
is in what you're generating. The lower
the temperature is then the more uh
you're close you closer you are to just
choosing the most likely output.
>> Yes. When you say roll the die, do you
mean like between the top five
probability?
>> No, you have a probability distribution.
You draw a sample from that distribution
>> for the entire alphabet or
>> for the entire set of probabilities that
have been generated by so you have so
you're by by your uh outputs, right?
Yeah.
>> So whatever you have your dictionary,
you have some probability that has been
generated for all of these. Many of
these will be zeros.
Whatever is non zero you pull from that
distribution
>> with no weight or just
>> no no weight just you use just use the
the weights are basically the
probabilities that are generated by the
uh RNN that's just what the softmax is
doing.
>> Yes.
>> Do you calculate loss with respect to
the probability distribution you output
or just the one label that you sample?
Here we're just going to use the one
label. Um but in the sense that yeah
we're just going to use that one label
and we're going to check for that. We're
not
>> yes.
>> So sampling you cannot run gradient
descent through this right. So we will
not be having like you cannot run the
gradient descent through this link
>> this link but therefore that is why you
have the true wise here that you're
putting in right and that allows you to
run gradient descent on this.
>> Yes.
>> So so like there's like multiple time
steps
descent all the time. It's the same kind
of gradient descent. Back prop through
time, whatever the R and then uh
gradient descent is. It's I forget what
it's called. R and then backrop.
>> No, what is it called? Backdrop through
time. No, what?
>> Just it's just back prop, but there's
like it's exactly the same. Nothing
different.
>> Yes, it
>> seems like the sampling the like
rationale for sampling kind of makes
sense from the perspective of like
you're kind of mixing the distribution
that's out there. You're not just taking
like Yeah. like the maximum likelihood
or whatever. Is there other has there
been exploration in doing that mixing in
a more like I don't know like in a
different way other than sampling like
for instance if you just added all the
tokens weighted by their probabilities
and fed that in as the input even though
that's like not a token in the
distribution. I don't know. You see what
I'm saying?
>> The artificial token that you're
creating that's a combination of things,
>> right? Because I'm thinking just from a
language perspective like maybe the
distributions are representative of the
kind of different sort of semantic
meanings encoded in one particular kind
of word. You see what I'm saying?
>> Yeah. [clears throat]
>> I you know it seems like a thing that
one would explore. I have not read a
paper about this but that doesn't mean
it's not out there. It might be. Do you
have you read something like this? Yeah,
there's recent work on this trying to do
this thinking in continuous token space
where they did stuff like this. So
people have explored it. They claimed
good results. Other people replications
were kind of fishy. So it's not clear
how much benefit it's actually giving.
It's like a
>> Okay,
good. Anyways, this this is like not the
focus of the lecture, but let's move on.
Okay. So, what we want to do now is we
want to be able to talk about um how do
we handle this bottleneck. Okay.
And you've seen a bottleneck like this
before in one of our architectures. What
was where did we see this kind of
bottleneck in one sense? Come back to
things that we've seen before. So, when
we looked at units, right? What did we
have in units? Well, we had a
convolutional neural net and it's
basically downsampling, downsampling,
downsampling, and then upsampling,
upsampling, upsampling, and you you
brought everything down to this one
pixel, right? And you had it had many,
many channels, but it was just one
pixel. And that was what was responsible
for sending the information to the rest
of the future layers. Everyone remember
this in units like you're and let's say
you're trying to do some task like image
segmentation, right? So you need to look
at the whole image to understand well
where like maybe the segmentation you
want to segment the dog okay you want to
label something as a dog you want to
label something as a tree so you have to
look at the whole image
and then in your unit you're saying okay
I' I've now process process process
process process I've identified that in
this picture there is actually a dog and
now what I want to do is I want to be
able to draw the boundary of the dog and
so I'm blowing my image back up to draw
the boundary of the dog and understand
where is the dog ear and where is the
sky that is behind the dog ear. I need
to look at the neighboring pixels,
right? I it's not enough for me to just
say that this entire image has a dog in
it. I need to now look at it again on a
pixel by pixel basis. So I'm blowing
this back up.
And what was the thing that we did in
units to get around this problem? we had
basically let it said that okay now I'
I've come down to this small resolution
and now I'm blowing back up so let me
look back at the last time I was the
same size right so I I'm and maybe
there's relevant context there and so
you know I look at where I am currently
and I go back and I say let me look at
the side at at the previous time I was
the same size and what were the
neighboring pixels around me
And then I blow up again and I say, "Let
me go and look back at where what was
what was the what were the pixels like
when I was the same size again?" And we
have these kind of going back
connections that help establish the
right context for each pixel. Everyone
remember this from from units?
So what I want to bring out is that
basically this is um this is the the
same kind of challenge. It's not the
same challenge, but it's the same nature
of challenge where you have a bottleneck
and you want to be able to pass a lot of
information through that bottleneck. So,
you want to be able to give maybe some
side information or something or maybe
you want to add connections back to the
appropriate places. Okay?
And in a unit
appropriate place was kind of natural,
right? Because you can think of an image
as you know you have every pixel has a
position. It has an index in an array
and it's natural to say well let's look
at the exact same position right when I
was in the same size.
So this appropriate position is kind of
natural
but now we have this issue with language
and language is much more complicated.
language is complicated because I mean
the word order is simply not the same
right and to be able to translate a
sentence I need to look at the entire
sentence sentences can be long
does everyone understand the challenge
here and why we can't just have like a
unit like connection that will we want
to be inspired by units but just there's
no obvious way to just take the unit
idea and force it onto this Okay.
So the question is now what can we do?
So maybe take a couple of minutes and
just like think through this problem.
I'm going to give you that time. I'm
going to write some stuff about units on
my paper so that you all have notes
and
yeah.
If I say
Oh my god.
Okay.
So, we have this challenge, right? We
want to be able to be inspired by units.
But we have the problem that with
language and translation in particular,
it's not at all clear that
or it's not clear how we can define what
the appropriate position is, right?
Because things change places. Okay? So
our challenge is that
we cannot
set
a topology
of connections
in advance.
We need to somehow
this somehow will depend on the input
itself.
Okay.
So now we have to think about what kind
of data structures or what kind of
machinery do we have that can allow us
to
take some input and find the relevant
positions
by computing something from that
input itself. Right? for a array the
relevant positions for a pixel are given
by the index of the pixel in the
[clears throat] array essentially right
and so I can just map and look that the
index is has all the information
but what are other ways in which we can
do this kind of lookup this is something
that you've all seen before
so maybe take a minute to think
Just to give you an aside. So we were
just talking before coming to to coming
to lecture and one of the things that we
were talking about is the challenge of
keeping up in this field like we were
talking about just the rapid things like
I'm I'm reading the prince textbook for
example and some of the things that are
very nice or some of the most latest
advances are simply not in the textbook
or it's really it's really hard to find
current information because it's
changing so rapidly. And so what we're
going to try and do is we're going to
try and teach you in a sense the
historical
thought process. This is not really
written out
in many places or anywhere that and that
led to the design choices
that give us the architectures that we
have today. And so what I'm hoping is
that you will see this therefore as a as
an evolution of one thing after another
after another as opposed to this is one
thing and this is another thing and
these are not discrete silos that you
all have to memorize because that's not
an approach that is going to have you be
up to date in the way that you need to
be in this field. It's just insane,
right? like
uh and so
just trying to think through like this
process of why is for example attention
in this case an evolution of what we
were thinking or what the community was
thinking in RNN's is what we're trying
to trying to get you to see which is why
this lecture is being given the way it
is I could have just written a formula
for attention and then we'd be done with
the lecture
so that's why I want you to try and
think through this and have these
minutes.
Uh was there a question at the back?
[clears throat]
>> Something very similar to GN.
>> Yes.
>> Yes. So exactly we talked about this in
the context of GNN's and in one sense
that attention is you can think of as uh
a com like a or transformer network as a
GNN with a complete graph. Um, and so
we're we're going to get there, but I
want to get there a little bit slowly.
Uh, going a little bit step by step.
Okay.
So, the thing that I want to use instead
of an array with a lookup is I want to
use a hash table,
right? So, what I'm going to do is I'm
going to say I have some input.
What does it match with? Right? I'm
going to look at the hash of it and I'm
going to see well, what is similar?
Okay, so that's the idea that we want to
use. We want to use something like a
hash table or a dictionary to understand
what the connection should be based on
the input. Does that make sense to
everyone?
Because we don't have this parallel that
we have in units of like oh we can just
look at the index question. I was
curious. I remember earlier on we also
talked about this idea of doing skip
connection just around an individual
block because then there's like a clear
path that the the gradients could kind
of follow.
>> Yeah,
>> I was wondering maybe whether that works
here or like I guess why that idea
wouldn't work where if I just have a
skip over my own block then I wouldn't
be able to just kind of put those end to
end and let the gradients flow smoothly
as far as they need to go. So I'm I
think I'm not understanding your
question. So this like in these RN
networks there will be residual
connections we have that that's not what
we're
uh trying to think about. So what we're
what we're thinking about is when I'm
looking at a input sentence right I want
to be able to so like here
>> you want a super high
>> no I don't want a super highway. don't
want a super highway. The super the
gradient superighway and the residual
connections are important but they are
for a different reason. They're trying
to solve a different problem. The
problem that I am trying to solve right
now is this bottleneck here
which is when I'm putting in a long
sentence I'm not increasing the layers.
This is not about the layers here.
Right? The gradient superighways help me
here. These are I do have these residual
connections here,
but this is in the time direction in
some sense.
And so I all I have here is an RNN. It's
something like this. There's no there's
no way to put these super highways in a
sense back or that all that information
that is being shoved into that into that
state.
Does that
>> like the rest of the functions are
solving a completely different problem
>> or
like the vanishing gradient
>> but they're they're going in the
vertical direction. Here we're talking
about information in the horizontal
direction in some in the time direction.
>> Yes.
>> So is the issue that we don't want to
encode everything in just one hidden
state? We want don't want to encode
everything in just one hidden state
because that's a lot of stuff and not a
lot of state
and if we made the state really big then
everything is a nightmare to train.
Okay. So this bottleneck this thing this
bottleneck is the key thing and the
bottleneck on that is the dimension of
the state in here and that can only be
so big.
Okay.
So what we're going to do is we want to
use our solution
is to use a hash table.
And we want to have some nice properties
of this hash table, right? Like in most
specifically, if I told you, oh, come up
with a hasht to help with English to
Chinese translation. What's your best
guess of how to come up with that hasht?
Why don't you just do it right now? It's
a quick exercise.
You have obviously no idea how to come
up with this appropriate hash table so
that you can, you know, hash the Chinese
words to the appropriate place and the
English words in the appropriate way.
So, what's your solution?
>> We're going to make it learnable, right?
It's like our basic we have one trick in
this class make it learnable and so we
want something we want need to have a
hash table that somehow we can learn it
needs to be uh differentiable it has to
have something that we can uh pass
gradients through right so and so this
is a need basically need this.
Okay.
So,
let's think about how to do this. And
let me start with
idea. Let's call this idea minus one.
Okay.
We're going to say let us look
for
the exact match
[snorts]
of
query Q
among
the stored
keys.
[snorts]
And then
return
value
corresponding
to exact
match.
So I'm going to use the query. So so in
a hash table um we have keys and we have
values, right? The keys tell us the key
the keys correspond to the input and
they tell us where the value is stored,
right? And then we can go and look up
the key and we retrieve the value.
That's how a hash table basically works.
Here we're going to think about queries,
keys and values. And what the queries
are, we're saying, well, I'm a word. I'm
walking along. I'm a Chinese word. I'm
doing an English to Chinese translation.
I need to know where I should pay
attention to. what is the relevant
context for me? Okay, so I am the query
in some sense. I need to compare myself
to the keys that have come before me or
the keys maybe in the input sentence.
The keys are generated from those words
and I need to find out well which ones
are relevant for me, which ones are good
context and which ones are less
relevant. Okay, so this query, key and
value are the three things that you have
to think about. Okay,
queries are related to the question who
should I pay attention to? I am the
query if I'm thinking about that. Keys
are what is there already that I need to
look up? And the value is saying, well,
if you pair these things together, what
is the it's just the I don't know. I
can't it's just the value. I don't have
a better word for value. Okay, so I'm
calling this idea minus one and I'm
calling it idea minus one because it
doesn't work. So why doesn't this
this idea work, right?
Yeah. Or actually maybe we should give
everyone like a minute to think about
it. So take take one minute and that way
everyone gets some chance to think about
it.
Okay.
So,
why doesn't this idea work? Yeah.
someone or
>> returning a value corresponding to an
exact match is problematic and I think
we should instead return a distribution
over matches.
>> Okay, we return the distribution but why
is it problematic? Yeah,
>> there aren't exact matches between
>> there basically aren't exact matches,
right? How are you going to find these
exact matches? It's really really I mean
it's basically like my input, right?
Everything here
these are all English words
here here everything I'm doing is is uh
in a different language let's say it's
Chinese words or marati words right so
then
there's never going to be an exact match
right uh so exact matches you're
basically just never going to find and
even if you did basically there's
another big problem here which is that
the initialization problem is terrible.
Like how do you start with something?
You have to start you if you even if you
want to learn these you have to start
with something
at initialization you're never going to
have any exact meshes. You're not even
going to have uh so it's just a
disaster basically. Um and we we
uh we don't want and even if you had you
could never even improve right how could
you improve on this even if you had bad
initialization.
Uh so this is just a basic bad idea. It
doesn't work. So the problem with this
is that
we'll never have exact match
initialization
doesn't work.
Okay.
Okay. So, you're just going to keep
basically returning like not found, you
know, not found, not found, not found.
Therefore, you have nothing to improve
on. There's no uh good gradient. Okay.
So, then does anyone have an idea zero
or what we can try to do next?
Yeah. Or maybe someone else is you.
Yeah.
vectors.
>> Keys and values. So you're never
comparing keys and values. Your
>> queries and keys are what are being
compared to each other. So you could
look at queries and keys and you want to
compare them.
>> You want some kind of similarity
measure.
>> You want to get some kind of similarity
measure. And we're gonna we're gonna get
to a similarity measure because you many
of you probably seen the tension before.
But what's the idea that's like what's
the idea in between that isn't quite a
similarity measure but um you can just
say you can't find an exact match. So
the next idea is just to say return the
closest match,
right?
But just returning one closest match
also doesn't really quite work. And
what's the problem with just returning
that one closest match?
>> Yeah,
>> I have one word mapping to several words
in the output or vice versa. So like
only attending to one
um
only attending to like one word in the
input sequence isn't necessarily
sufficient to generate the the proper
output.
>> So we might we might uh like you know we
might want to do this. There might be
several levels of this that we want to
do. We might want to attend to several
things. But um there's a even more
fundamental problem in some sense that
like this just won't work
mechanistically. It won't work.
>> Problem of like non- differential like
it this won't be not differentiable.
>> Yeah, it won't be differentiable and it
it'll be basically I mean so what's
going to happen is that if I'm returning
the closest match and then you perturb
the query a little bit, right? the
closest match is still the same. So you
have this basically like peacewise
constant type of thing where you're
going to have a bunch of zero gradients,
right? So you're not going to be able to
learn this thing if you just return the
closest match.
So even though that seems like a really
reasonable idea, learning it is a total
failure. Okay. So the idea with this is
that or the problem with this
uh this is like this has bad gradients.
Small
changes
to the query
will not
change
match.
Okay.
So then now we come to this idea one
let's call it.
So we don't want to return just one
closest match. So what's the natural
next idea?
>> Yeah
possible matches.
>> Return a distribution over possible
matches. I'm going to take the simpler
version of that which is just to say
return me the top K mattress or K is
keys here top return me the top L
mattress right
um so let's say look at the close look
at the multiple closest matches look at
the top
L
matches okay
and then you know if I look if I have
one query and then I have K1, K2, K3, KL
keys that are the top L matches for
that, then that gives me L values,
right? And what do I want to do? I want
to be able to somehow use these values.
So what's the I want I want to get a
value. So what's the way to combine
these values? That's the natural thing
to do.
dotproduct values are all the they're
all just uh
like I have many of them right I have l
of them
yeah
>> you could just average them right so I
have
um so I have l different values
and so
I can try to do
1 / l
and that could be the value
corresponding to this
one to let's say L.
But the problem with this is while it's
a good idea, it still has the problem of
not really helping, not being easy to
learn because now even with this, a
small change in my query still doesn't
lead to big changes here or small. So
again, I have this problem of zero
gradient even with this setup. Okay, so
I'm not really by averaging I'm not
really using the fact that I fanned out
to L different matches.
Okay, so if I want to use the fact that
there's L things and not collapse them
into one, what's a way to combine them
that can do that? Well, one natural way
is to do a weighted average, right? So
that I'm kind of I can choose how much I
care about each value. Okay.
So, what I'm going to try next is I'm
going to try next try
is a weighted average.
So I want to have something
remember L
some alpha I b I and I want this thing
to be a scalar
and what's one way that one might want
to think about waiting these values well
I mean this has come up in the
conversation already Right? I have a
query. I have keys. Each of these values
is associated with a different key.
Well, maybe I should care more about the
keys and the values that I'm very
similar with and I should care less
about the keys and values that I'm
less similar with. Right? Does that make
sense? Yes.
What is the difference between this
method and the previous idea regarding
the gradient?
>> What is the difference between
>> this method and the previous idea?
>> Ah,
>> so you will see the difference as soon
as we choose
what these alphas are going to be.
We haven't really talked about how we're
going to learn this yet, but you'll hold
hold on a minute and I think your
questions will get answered.
>> Yes. It's not obvious why a small change
in a pairing will not change the closest
match or top closest matches. Can you
>> So, so if I have um let's say I have um
I have no exact matches, right? So, I
have some vector somewhere. I'm in some
extremely
high dimensional space and so basically
all the vectors are all far away from
each other and so I have some small
perturbation to my query.
Odds are the closest thing to me is
still going to be the same because I'm
looking at things that are all very far
away from me comparatively
>> due to dimensional space
>> because everything is very high
dimensional.
>> Yes. But just just the fact that when
you have extremely high dimensional
spaces, everything is basically a a
finite number of things essentially
everything's orthogonal to each other.
Yes.
Okay.
So, what we're going to do here is we're
going to fix this by saying I'm going to
do um
1 / L
sum of some similarity measure
between Q
and K
and the value. Okay,
so this allows me to weight the
different values based on my similarity
with my query. Okay,
here I guess this is query I. This
should be I. This is sum over i.
Okay, so I look at my different uh and
so how do I pick this similarity
measure? Well, the standard similarity
measure that we're very used to and we
like using is
dotproduct, right? Inner product. So
this we're just going to choose to be
inner product.
But it doesn't have to be inner product,
right? there's like choices that you
that you could make.
Inner product turns out to be a good
natural choice. It's easy to implement.
GPUs like doing matrix multiplies. Um
you know this is this makes this makes a
lot of sense. But what we're the reason
we're doing in our product is we're
trying to get at a similarity measure.
And then what we want to be able to do
is we want to be able to actually turn
this into something like a probability,
right? We don't want to have the problem
with in their product is that they can
get very big.
And so to be able to make sure that our
numbers don't blow up because neural
networks never like when things blow up,
instead of using just the inner product,
what are we going to use? We're going to
use the soft max over the inner
products, right? So that we're going to
have we're going to make sure that all
the values remain in nice contained
intervals.
Okay? So we're really going to go from
here to a soft max.
Okay.
And now what we are left with is well
you know we said like let's say we had
the queries keys and values and then
what do we do?
So far I haven't really told you about
what the learnable parameters here are.
How do I get Q, K, and V? That's where
we're going to put the learning in. So,
we're going to say, how do we get,
we're going to learn them.
And so the way we're going to learn them
is we're going to just have them be some
linear transformation
of our input. So we're going to have
some matrices. So for example, I have my
input
and I'm going to put this
into some matrix
W K. This is going to give me my key.
Similarly, I'll have some
ah
And these W K, WQ, and WV are going to
be my learnable parameters.
Okay,
that's how we're going to have gradients
uh going through all of these things.
Okay, so this thing what I've talked to
you about this is basically this key
idea of cross attention. Okay, so we
talked about this saying look we are
we're trying to go from we have this
encoder and we have this decoder
and I want the decoder to know where in
the encoder should I be paying attention
to.
That is the key idea of cross attention.
So I'm looking at queries that are
originating from the decoder and my keys
and values are all things that are
computed from my encoder. Okay,
this ended up working well and so
building on this there was the natural
next step of understanding self
attention.
Self attention was basically where the
queries and keys and values are all
coming just from the decoder. So maybe
it's worth it for me to not just pay
attention back to the encoder, but also
what did I just say before this?
So that's the idea of self attention.
Okay? And so you know often when you
read about this, you'll read about self
attention first and then cross attention
later. But the historical development
was that cross attention came first,
then came self attention. And then it
turns out that you know you sometimes
it's useful to have these self attention
connections also in the encoder and that
can also be helpful. So now there's
there's self attention connection in the
encoder self attention connections in
the decoder as well.
And so if you want to have an explicit
formula if I want to have the attention
between you know let's say xm and xn
then that's basically
this. This is where we come to. It's
basically the soft max of these things.
Okay. So I look at the inner product of
the keys and the queries and then I take
a soft max
and compute the attention and that's how
I decide how much attention how much
weight to give to the previous tokens
that I have seen.
>> Okay.
Yes. So the X's are X is the input to
either the encoder or decoder attribute
like some time set.
>> Yes.
>> Okay. Any questions about this so far?
>> So there okay. So self attention do we
only look at previous inputs? So I will
come to that but basically within self-
attention there are different there's
basically masked self attention or
causal self attention and then self
attention and so if you want to make
sure that your system does not get some
undue advantage by looking into the
future what you can do is you can set
attention weights for looking uh into
the future just freeze them to be
negative infinity
right and that's what is called masked
self attention
self attention ention allows you to look
everywhere. In a decoder, you would use
masked self intention because you can't
look at the future.
Yes. See, in this case of self-
inention, you're not actually attending
to exactly yourself though, right? Or do
you also include yourself like or just
the neighbors like every other cycle? I
guess
>> I not like you're saying does a token
look at itself in the case of self
attention?
>> Yeah.
um
you would not include that because
otherwise your soft max would not work
out
>> in matrices are different. So it doesn't
it doesn't automatically
>> actually that's true the quiz and car
the keys and query matrices would be
different so it actually wouldn't matter
they would be still be different so it
would be fine even if you did it that's
true
>> yes
cross dimension. Let's say we already
generated like next to then how we know
like the second looking at like the
sentence we want to translate. How would
we know the second we just like
what we want to translate? How would we
know that this is like where this
>> following your question? like attention.
So like if we're translating then like
the phrase we want to translate would be
in the encoder and then out of the like
decoder is where we're like
>> so the decoder if the decoder is doing
self attention
um it's only looking at the things that
is generated previously. If the decoder
is doing cross attention and looking at
the encoder it's looking at everything.
It's not cross attention doesn't have
this masking aspect. It's looking at
everything in the encoder because you
can think of it as that you know we
always think that the encoder the full
input sentence is available to us
already.
So it doesn't need to know that it we
don't need to cut it off at only the
third word or the fifth word or so on
and so forth.
>> Yes. Exactly. Because because the word
like you know maybe it's generated some
words but maybe the next word it needs
to generate is in the past. Right. You
don't know the word order. That's the
point in translation. The word order can
be completely everywhere. So it needs to
look at everything in the encoder,
everything in the input to be able to
generate the output.
>> It it can look at the whole past. Yes.
Yes. Okay.
So I want to point out one very
important thing. I've written this here.
This doesn't work. Okay.
Why doesn't this work?
This is not actually what we use.
This doesn't work because of one key
problem which is that these uh dot
products can get very large. The inner
products can get very large. Therefore,
the soft max can be such that it only
you know focuses on one input.
Okay. And so that is not good. And the
reason this can get or one of the
reasons this can get large is that you
can have these very long vectors
uh for your uh keys and your queries. So
what is used now is what is scaled self
attention which is basically where
you're normalizing everything by square
root d where d is the dimension of your
um
>> um no it's what is what do I want to say
so here I'll show you in this picture
but basically you have um
d is your embedding like how how big is
your vector
Okay, so this is a really nice picture
from the prince book. Uh, so this is
your input X. And so I have
these are the different sequences. So I
compute my query matrix, my key matrix,
and my value matrix. Then I look at the
inner product between the queries and
the keys. Use a soft max to get my
attention. Then I look at the attention
times the values and that gets me my
output.
Okay.
And so this dimension D
is what we are normalizing by. And what
I want to point out is that what is
important here is to get an N byN matrix
out here. So this
dimension D can actually change Right?
This doesn't have to be like I could
have this be longer, this could be
shorter. I could change this
while maintaining this n byn matrix
product that ends up here, right?
Because to be able to compute the
attention, I need one I need to have an
attention times values computation,
right? What's important here is to get
this n byn matrix here, but I can have a
different number of rows here and still
get the same n byn attention matrix out.
Okay? And so that's one observation that
then leads to um
this idea of multi head self attention.
Right? So we talked about self attent or
just multi head attention in general. We
talked about uh attention and we said we
want to know where to pay attention to.
We want to know what is the right
context.
And we're doing this by learning a
particular uh you know WQ, W K and WV
which are telling us how to compute our
queries, how to compute our values, how
to compute our our keys.
Turns out that if you do this on in some
sense a channel, not a channel by
channel basis, but a group of channel
basis by group of channel basis,
you can do better. And now everything
basically uses this multi-head attention
idea. And so what we're doing here
is I'm taking my input and I'm saying
let me look at this like let me look at
these channels and these channels and
these channels and I'm going to process
all of them through different attention
heads. Okay. So instead of this being D,
I'm going to have this be D over H.
Everyone see that?
I still get an N byN attention matrix
out here.
But what I've done now is I get this for
maybe just some part of the input
and then I concatenate all of these
again at the output to get d-dimensional
things.
So I'm looking at things I'm not looking
at things channel by channel. It's not
just one at a time, but I'm looking like
basically at a group of channels
and allowing for this different pathways
to uh look, one reason that this seems
to work better is maybe it allows for
different different initializations help
you be better, but it's also that you
can have different pathways for
different information and different
channels can capture different things.
Okay, so this is what is called multi
head self attention.
Does this make sense? Yes.
>> By channel here, I'm meaning basically
like dimension of the embedding.
>> So I'm I'm using different different
components of my my embedding I can
think of as each being a channel,
right? I have whenever I have my input,
I put it into my embedding matrix. And I
can think of like if I'm just doing a
connet well I have my RGB values there's
three but I can think of it in like
whatever whatever my embedding dimension
is will be the number of channels that I
have.
>> Yes.
>> Is this different from just regular
attention with like a block diagonal
matrix
i.e like you would take blocks of it
that are zero
cuz I feel like you could you could get
the whole operation with just one bigger
like mapping.
>> I'm understanding the the question.
>> So this is it seems like it's proposing
like you're kind of breaking up your
channels, right, in your embedding and
then doing attention to them separately.
>> Are you are you referring to this
picture that often shows up? Let me try
to see if I can pull this up. Like this
standard picture that shows up. Is that
what you're referring to?
>> This picture
turns out like is this the diagonal
matrix that you're referring to?
>> Yeah.
>> Right. So, this is this is this is
exactly the same. It's just that you're
only looking you're only looking at
certain places and so there's a lot of
things that end up being zero here.
That's all this is. I I decided not to
go through this picture just in the
interest of time. I'm over time. Sorry.
I didn't even realize. So,
>> just like a sparse version.
>> It's the exact same version. There's no
difference. This is exactly the same
thing.
>> I can
no no no no no.
It's different.
>> We we can talk about it. Yeah. Okay. So
I am an overtime.