Can you see the students at all?
>> Yes, I can see the students.
>> Okay.
>> Actually, maybe
>> it's better to put it here.
>> Better.
I can see the students.
>> Okay. So hopefully this works.
>> Does this mic help you here or No, it
does not at all.
>> I don't think you can hear anything
clearly.
>> Okay. Can you hear?
>> Yeah, you can't hear this mic. Okay.
>> Recording stopped.
>> Okay. I'll just come and repeat
questions loudly to the computer.
>> Recording in progress.
>> Okay.
>> Let's try this.
>> Okay. Thanks everyone. Hopefully, can
you hear me? Raise your hand if you can
hear me. Okay, great. Thank you. Sorry
for not being there in person. Uh try to
deliver the material properly uh
remotely.
So, we're going to continue our
discussion of uh convolutional neur
neural nets. The story is as it was
before. Uh you know, we want to do image
processing. We want to do appropriate
word sharing using the convolutional
architecture.
But I realized there's something that I
didn't uh uh talk about uh clearly last
time and I want to make sure it is clear
to everybody. So when we think about a k
by kcon with c input channels and see
out output channels uh we have two
different perspectives on it. Of course
in terms of the computations both
perspectives are identical. Just how do
we think about it? The number of
parameters is also identical. you know
we have k^ squ cnc see out weights and
see out biases again as before. So the
first perspective is the one that we are
kind of describing. Uh let me make sure
everyone understands it. And the way
that you think about it is you think
about it as see out different K by K
cons each of these K by K cons having C
and input channels and one output
channel.
Um why? Because that's the picture uh
that we see here. Uh hopefully everyone
can see this picture. So here we see a
single output
with uh k by k here's three by uh 3x3
con with uh cn here visually three uh
input channels. So again everything
corresponding to a particular location
in the output comes from a filter acting
on that centered same location on the
input where the filter has a different
uh 3x3 uh matrix of real valued weights
associated with every channel. Those
things are all multiplied together and
added up add together the bias.
So in this picture we have the following
picture for one output channel just
simply repeated see out times to give
you see out different outputs.
This picture uh is hopefully clear.
Uh I want to contrast this with a second
perspective a different perspective.
Again the result is the same but it's a
different way of looking at it.
And this uh other perspective says look
we're going to think about this uh as a
single k by k con except instead of
having weight numbers we have weight
matrices in every box and instead of
having a bias number a single bias we
have a bias vector uh in every box
not every box but sort of for for the
conf. So here's a 3x3 example kind of
worked out together with the kind of
described with the math. So before we
drew this and you thought of each of
these W's, the one corresponding to the
pixel itself, the one corresponding to
north and so on as all being scalar
values, real values. Now we think of
each of these for example let's look at
WN. Uh they all all the W's have the
same shape. They are a CN by C out
matri. So CN inputs. So CN in this case
we're using a vector convention of of
columns. So we have C in columns and C
out rows and the bias for the entire
conf is a vector with the seout uh size
dimension.
So if you think about it in terms of a
formula what you have is the output
assuming nonlinearity here is just the
bias. So remember the output is for per
pixel everything is weight shared across
pixels. So a bias vector plus a sum a
sum over i where i is this whatever this
neighborhood structure is. So for a k by
k uh there's k squ terms in the sum 3x3
there's nine of the corresponding weight
matrix wi acting on the corresponding
input vector from the uh image at the
previous level. So this perspective says
that what happens at cons in connets is
that every you always maintain an image
and the entries of every pixel are
vectors. There were three vectors in the
case of RGB and they are whatever
generic vector size we want for deeper
in the network. Okay, I want to pause
here and just take any questions to make
sure people understand these two are
equivalent to each other. They both
represent a learnable linear uh so aine
transformation from uh one image to
another.
But uh I want to make sure everyone
understand these two perspectives.
Any questions on this?
>> Yeah.
>> I in the summation refer to the number
of channels.
>> Uh great. The question was what does the
I refer to in the summation? The I is
not referring to the number of channels.
Let me write it out.
So in this particular sum I
this is ranging over
the A by K
positions.
in
the con filter.
Okay, so it's not summing up uh over
channels, it's summing up over spatial
positions
here where remember the spatial
position, there's one weight that
corresponds to me, the center of the
filter, and then there's its local
neighborhoods.
So the H out for this pixel is going to
be the sum over I the neighborhoods the
3x3 neighborhoods of the weights acting
on the corresponding pixel in the input.
So the corresponding pixel here for me
is the same exact pixel position. The
one for north, so there's a north in
here, is the pixel that's one above the
current pixel. For south, the pixel
that's one below. For east, one to the
right. And for uh sorry, for west, you
know, one to the left. Does that make it
clear? Does that answer the question?
>> Yeah.
>> Let's try this just to see
if it works. If it doesn't
>> um where in the formula do we account
for the number of channels?
>> Uh I heard something about number of
channels but I couldn't hear the rest of
the question.
>> I can't hear anything right now.
>> Great. Where in the formula do account
for the number of channels? The number
of channels at the input and the number
of channels at the output are accounted
for by the shapes of these uh vectors
and matrices. So the number of output
channels is the size of the bias vector
and it's also the number of rows in the
weight ve weight matrix. The number of
input channels is CN and that's
represented by the number of columns in
the weight matrix. This is using the
convention that we think of at every
pixel of the image sits a vector, a
column vector.
Does that answer the question?
>> Yeah, that's good. You can move on. Yes.
>> Okay, great. Thank you. So, now let's go
back to what we were talking before.
We're kind of at the end of last
lecture. We're talking about uh how to
make training stable and effective. and
we introduced the idea of normalization
layers. So, uh recall the basic story.
We have an uh input that goes through a
deep network and we're afraid of the
activations or the gradients blowing up
as you go through.
Is there a question?
>> I hear some sound. Is that someone
talking?
>> I can't hear what they're saying though.
>> H sorry I was trying to figure out the
mic but it's clearly picking up not
enough. Okay, keep going.
>> Okay.
Um so uh if we uh think about you know
how do we what can we do? We already
have the idea from our discussions of
MUP that one thing we might be
interested in is the RMS norm to keep
the activations all kind of in the right
place roughly of you know size one on
average.
So we could insert uh an RMS normalizing
uh layer kind of inside of our network
wherever we wanted. And you know what uh
what that would be if there's
d-dimensional inputs and you want to RMS
normalize them. We would just take the
vector and you divide it by the RMS norm
for scaling it down. Right? That's one
way of doing it. If you want to think
about in terms of two norm, you can take
the vector and divide it by the two norm
again plus an epsilon. I forgot the
epsilon in the second expression here
where general deep learning rule
whenever you're dividing by something
make sure it's not zero so add a little
epsilon to make sure that doesn't happen
division by zero don't happen
and then we said okay let's think about
images again what are choices we can do
and I wanted to talk about batch norm
that's where we were last time
so for batchorm
uh one way to think about it is to say
that we would like to do input
standardization
for each of the channels that are coming
in.
So we don't have access to the entire
training input. It's just too big. Uh we
can't premp compute this in advance
because the network will keep evolving
and so the output at the hidden layer
will keep changing. So we have to work
on the current batch.
So what we do is we can imagine just
doing averaging over the current batch.
So what this does is this applies a
different uh normalizing in terms of
recentering and uh scaling for every
channel of the input.
So now the question becomes how do you
compute what that recentering should be?
So in this particular formula from last
time that recentering is to subtract n.
The n is a kind of empirical mean. So
you're averaging together over some b
some set which is what's to be averaged
over. This is how you can think about it
working.
And the scaling is done by some s which
is again based on what's averaged over.
So this is like input standardization
that you saw in your machine learning
class except we're doing it on a batch
by batch basis and we're doing it at the
at a hidden layer instead of at the
inputs themselves.
So this how far we got last time and at
the very end I said that what people
sometimes do is they add learnable
parameters a gamma and a delta that
basically reflect the following
question. what should I be standardizing
to?
And we can say I should standardize to
zero mean and uh variance one or you can
say I don't know. And in general if you
don't know something in deep learning
you make the thing you don't know into a
learnable parameter and then
in this case if these are learnable
parameters you you know default them at
let me write that down. So learnable
center
delta and scale
gamma.
So we initialize
to
zero, the center to zero, and the scale
gamma to one. But then you let these get
updated in gradient descent, whichever
optimizer we're using.
Okay, so
uh let's make sure everyone is
understanding what's uh what's going on
here.
Uh, I can't hear you if you're saying
something.
I still can't hear you if you're saying
>> Can you hear this?
>> No. Okay. Uh, can you hear me now?
>> Yeah, now I can hear you.
>> Okay. It's very very directional
microphone. Okay. Um, can you zoom in?
It's hard to see what's being written.
>> Okay. Is that better?
>> Yes, but now we're losing the whole
slide. So, you need to maybe kill the
sidebar.
>> Good point. Kill the sidebar.
>> Zoom out. Zoom out. Zoom out more. Yeah,
better.
>> Okay. Thank you.
So there's a couple of comments on uh
these kind of learnable parameters.
So typically
>> we
we don't use weight decay.
and then these parameters
and if you are going to use weight decay
uh you you see that the paper you're
following does use weight decay for it
then of course you can always follow
them but between the two of them
we we don't like to use weight g weight
decay in particular for the gamma
because having it go to zero isn't
really a reasonable thing that we want
to have happen.
But that's just a a a piece of the
empirical advice that people follow.
Okay.
So this is how
batch norm
uh batch norm works and
what you do. So the other comment here
is that all of these operations are
differentiable.
You know adding things up is
Adding up taking squares is
differentiable. Adding up a bunch of
squares is differentiable. Taking a
square root is differentiable. And so
for all of these there's nothing here
that stops back prop from going in and
adjusting what's going on. So if we
insert these kind of batch norm layers.
So what we do?
Oops.
We insert normalization errors
in between.
So it's a part of the architecture of
where these normalization layers go.
You don't have to insert them between
every two layers, but uh they're in
they're put in. We'll talk more about
exactly how they're the current best
practices for putting in normalization
layers later after we've also introduced
residual connections, but here I just
want you to understand we put them in
between.
Okay.
So hopefully the basic issue of how
bashnorm works during training is clear.
Okay. So now I want to I'll come I'll
come back to other norms. There's a
question
>> in a moment.
>> There's a question.
>> Great.
>> What are the What is that indexing in
the square brackets next to H in the
final? It's like H equals
>> Ah, great. Let me make that more clear.
Sorry about that.
First, let me erase this latencies.
Yeah.
So
there's some pixel position we're
talking about. Okay. So we're talking
about h out at position i, comm, j in
the image. And that uses the
corresponding i, comma, j in the input.
But every position in the image gets the
same
uh mean m and the same scaling s.
Okay.
Is that uh clear to everybody now?
>> Yes.
>> Yeah. Good question.
>> Okay. So, uh we've talked about batchorm
during training. Hopefully, this is
clear to everyone. We will come back to
the question in in just a moment of how
do you use it during actual use or
testing. But for now, we just make sure
we understand training and talk about
some
talk about another very important norm
uh next.
Okay. So this is one choice. So remember
the choice here is what we average over.
But there's another choice that we can
average over. So I'll talk about the
other choice
different color green.
So
this is uh black is batchorm. So in
green we'll talk about layer norm.
So what layer norm does is it's just
like batchorm except what you average
over is slightly different. You still
average over the entire image
but in instead of averaging over batches
you average over channels.
Okay. So this
coverage
over space
and channels.
Okay. So now when you average over uh
space and channels you don't have to
worry about batch what the batch size is
you can you can use this with batch size
one. So that's one motivation for using
layerorm is that in some situations
you're you can't afford to have very
large batches and layerorm doesn't need
very large batches. It just uses batch
size one.
It's fine. You can also use a larger
batch. If you use a larger batch the
layer norm applies separately to every
single thing in the batch. It doesn't
mix them together in any way.
Okay, any questions on layer norm
mechanic loop? So all that changes is
what this uh curly B is
instead of being space and batch it
becomes but holding the channel fixed it
becomes space and channel but holding
the index into the batch fixed.
Okay. Any questions on how what lairm
is?
>> We're good.
>> We're good. Okay. Now
in uh in layer, so that's some more
comments about lairm.
So in layer and arm
we have
can have
different
gamma
and delta
per channel.
So you can have separate learnable uh
gamas and deltas per channels. Uh
because you're looking at in layer norm
you're averaging over
uh everything in the in the channel.
This still makes sense
to have different ones.
But in in batchorm you can have
different uh gamas and deltas per
channel but it happens more organically
because you're only averaging the the
averaging domain itself is not over this
but in there you can still have
different uh gamas and deltas per
channel.
Okay hopefully that's uh clear to
everybody.
So in this uh family the two big ones
are uh batch norm and layer norm. And
when you talk about RMS norm
comment here
RMS norms
layers
don't recenter.
Never compute.
Now we've talked about these kinds of
norms. There are others. Uh there's
other norms that you can get. Basically,
you look at this box. This box is the
range of possibilities you have of what
you can do
in this box. So the easiest ones are to
average across channels or average
across batches.
But you can also choose to not average
across either channels um or batches and
only do space.
You could you could imagine doing
something like this.
I use this
and average for every just for across
space alone.
Instance norm
cross space only.
Okay. Before I talk about the special
issue of how to deal with the
batch norm at inference time, any
questions on the sort of range of
possibilities one has about doing these
norms? There's many more. I've just
chosen three to describe to you. Batch
norm layer norm uh and instance norm and
there's and there the RMS variant where
you don't do recentering. But are there
any questions on this normalization?
>> Question. Yeah, one quick question about
the note um on RMS normal layers. Is
that a different kind of normalization
or are you just saying that if we wanted
to also
um like if if we omit the M in either
layer norm or batch norm that makes it
an RMS norm.
>> Yes. Uh basically the you can think of
it as the latter. When people talk about
doing RMS norm what they mean is I want
to do the norm except I don't want to do
an AMP. I don't want to do a recentering
amp. So I can think about an RMS norm
style for bashnorm or an RMS norm style
for layerm. Typically however it's done
in the layerorm style.
>> Got it. And then add a quick followup.
Um for so just to clarify so for batch
norm then we have one mean one standard
deviation per channel and then for layer
norm we have one mean one standard
deviation per item input element etc in
the batch. Is that the right way to
think about it?
Okay, that's excellent point. So, one of
the things that is a is a constant
everywhere uh in all systems is that you
you don't have a different learnable
parameter across your batch. So,
learnable parameters are always shared
across the batch. However, in the
context of doing this computation of
computing the M or the S, uh for layer,
you compute a different M and a
different S uh for different things in
the batch. Whereas for bashnorm, you
compute a single M and a single S for
different things across the batch.
However, in batchorm, you compute a
different M and a different S across
channels. Whereas uh in layerorm you
just compute different m and different
s's across that truth. Does that answer
your question?
>> Yes, it does. Thank you.
>> Yeah.
>> Any other questions?
>> You have a note that says in layerorm
you can have different like learnable
parameters per channel. Did you mean
batches or do you mean like there's
channels times batches learnable
parameters for layerorm?
>> Am I confused? So great question. We
never have any learnable parameters
associated to batches. This is never
done. Okay. So you you never treat
different batch entries differently
because they have different learnable
parameters associated with them.
Remember batches are drawn by shuffling.
So there's nothing special about
different batch positions ever.
Now when I say we have different we can
have different learnable parameters I
mean we can have different learnable
scales gamma and center positions delta
or different channels in layer
that's still okay
does that make sense
>> so you can think you can think about
what's going on in this uh sorry in this
particular expression
If we think about what's sitting inside
every position as being a vector,
right? There's a vector. So in this J
position, there's a vector. So this is a
vector. This is a vector. And when I do
division by a vector, that means
whenever you have an operation that is
unless specified otherwise always
component-wise. So then if you divide by
s, it's also dividing by a vector.
Uh but you can think or in this case,
sorry, make that very clear.
uh the m and the s in layer norm are
scalers my mistake so when I do the
subtraction by m I'm doing it uh when I
have a vector any operation and a scaler
the default is to do it component wise
so this in layer you can think of as a
single m and a single s is a a vector
minus a scaler so that means component
wise subtract the scaler and I divide by
s that's component-wise divide so Far so
good hopefully for layerm. Now the gamas
however
and the deltas we can think of as being
vectors in lairm and if they're vectors
in layer mortm this vector times vector
that you get you also interpret
component wise
as I multiply the uh third position
inside that vector by the third position
inside gamma. If I want to have
learnable parameters that are different
per channel. Does that make sense to
everybody? This is how you this is how
you can implement layer norm with
different learnable parameters for every
position. So the single formula hides
different cases based on figuring out
how to get the types to match.
>> I think we're good.
>> Okay. Good. Great. So this leaves uh one
very interesting question. So, here's
this question.
What to do
at testing time?
So for layer norm
issue,
we can just do exactly what we did
during training
because layer doesn't look at batches.
It doesn't it doesn't do any combination
of information across the across the
batch. It just looks at everything one
at a time. So at inference time or
testing time we have only one thing at
to work with. So there's no issue of
layer but there is an issue for batch.
You don't have a batch.
So what do we do for the case when we
don't have a batch?
So what we need
is M and S.
We can't do this averaging to get the
M&S. So we still need it to apply the
formula. So if we had MNS, we could
apply this formula for the output of
batch norm.
Okay, so we need to get an M&S.
So the question is how do we get an M&S?
So at this point I'll let you guys think
for a little bit.
Hopefully everyone understands the
question. So now take a minute, talk to
your neighbors and say given that you
have the uh the setup that you have, how
do you get these n and these s's to run
bashnorm at testing time? What what do
we have to do to get them? Now when I
say to get them, you have many choices.
You could probably do something purely
at testing time. You could also do
something different uh during training
to get yourself M&S's. Lots of
possibilities, but just talk to your
neighbors for a minute and talk about
and figure out what you might do.
What is the distribution of their
That's what you
>> Oh, you're testing. Oh, I see.
Okay, I'll try to call everyone back
together.
>> Okay.
>> So, hopefully you've had a chance to
think about it. Does anyone in the room
want to volunteer a a suggestion of what
we could do?
Um, we were thinking we could keep like
a running average of the mean and
standard deviation on like the last
epoch of the training and use that
during inference.
>> Okay, great. That's a great question, a
great approach. So, let me write that
out. One choice.
Just
get
an average
for M
and S
from the last epoch of training.
Uh that's a totally valid uh thing to
do. Um you can also just run one epic
with no updates for this purpose.
Okay. Alternative
training
with
no gradient updates.
Okay. So why do I say that? Because this
is ensuring that the M ands that you
compute as this average is good for
whatever the current parameters are of
the network. The parameters aren't
changing at all. Is everyone clear with
clear with this about this approach? Any
questions on this approach? It's a way
of getting the M&S that you don't have.
Okay. Does anyone have any other ideas
for what one can do? This is the
standard thing to do by the way, but do
you have any other ideas what you could
do? um very similar, but you could run
uh like a running exponential average
over the last several epochs um and use
those values for M&S.
>> Okay, so that's an interesting question
that says that instead of using the M&S
that correspond to the actual learn
parameters that you're using, you could
take some exponential mixture that way
uses some of the older values from uh
the last Q up of training. Is that I
understand your suggestion correctly.
>> Yes, exactly.
>> Okay. So
that's something one could do but one
doesn't do. However, a very related idea
is something that people do do in
practice which is they they do the same
exponential averaging idea but they
don't do it at uh during training. They
do it during actual testing or execution
in the field. Okay.
So can keep
uh
running average
exponential moving
during inference.
So the idea here is that you're not
going to be for your vision problem.
Let's say you're not going to be looking
at one image. You're going to be looking
at many and many many of them. For
example, think of a driving application.
You're driving your car. And instead of
keeping uh a single frozen M&S, you let
the M&S vary slowly based on the current
data distribution that you're actually
seeing into your into your image
classifier or whatever.
Okay, does everyone understand this
idea?
So it can it can allow for a little bit
of test time adaptation
uh by by doing by doing computing in
this way that's sometimes done by people
in deployment if it makes sense if
you're application says you want to
adapt maybe do a little bit of
adaptation this way and the third
approach which is kind of similar uh in
spirit is
just learn
M and test
using held out data.
So treat them like hyperparameters
that you have to set for operation and
use some held out little bit of held out
data to just train them
using regular grading descent.
Okay, all are valid uh choices of what
to do. They depend application wise
which you actually do with batch norm.
Okay.
Any other questions here about uh uh
getting batch norm to work? Again this
issue only affects batch norm because
you have batches. It doesn't affect
layer norm or you know RMS norm which is
usually people say RMS norm layers they
usually mean RMS norm style layer norm.
Any questions?
Okay, great. So, we can keep moving.
So, now uh I want to to kind of think
about it a little bit and say
we saw the inspiration for doing
bashnorm as coming from the idea that
look I did input standardization and it
tends to be helpful. Is there a
counterpart to input standardization
that I can do uh in between layers?
So once you have this analogy set up
that does what you do what normal things
you do to inputs
how can I do them between layers you ask
and ask the same question for data
augmentation.
Does everyone understand what the sort
of spirit of the question is? Spirit of
the question says, how can I get
something that's like data augmentation
except I do it
inside of our network for different
layers.
Okay,
so this brings us to
uh a topic called dropout.
So, dropout is uh you can think of it as
a data augmentation.
I
inside our network
during training.
So what is the what is the purpose of
doing data augmentations? Purpose of
day-to-day augmentations is to make your
network that you've learned more robust
and to generalize better. And dropout is
the same way. It's used to make your
network more robust and to generalize
better.
However, once you're inside the network,
the kind of augmentations that we talked
about for images that were coming from
the natural physics of of an image like
you know adding rotations and this
stuff, those don't tend to make as much
sense.
However, there is one thing that you can
do
and this one thing that you can do is
idea
just remove
slash zero out
random activations.
So this is why it's called dropout
because you drop things out.
Okay. So the first question before we
talk about the the mechanics of it in a
slightly more detail. Uh first question
you have is you know
why would you why does this even
potentially make any sense because the
you know the different activations are
presumably carrying uh some very useful
information. Why would you want to get
rid of it? So the reason you want to get
rid of it is that
this encourages
internal representations
to be redundant.
So this might seem counterintuitive or
paradoxical like why would you want to
encourage your internal representation
to be redundant? Isn't non-redundancy
good? It turns out for neural nets
neural nets like and function better
with redundancy. Redundancy means that
there's you can try to group things
together into a lower dimensional space
like having singular directions that are
more useful across activations.
So this is uh one reason again the
practical setting is it's just it makes
networks work better sometimes.
So uh okay now we can talk a little bit
about the mechanics of how do you how do
you actually make this happen uh but
maybe I'll I'll pause here for a moment
for for questions before going into the
mechanics. Anyone have any questions on
like idea of dropout? Like what we're
trying to do and before I tell you
exactly the details of how we do it.
>> I don't see any questions.
>> Okay, great. Thank you. So I'll I'll uh
uh continue.
So first a comment. This is typically
used
for
MLP style layers.
So this includes you know as a result it
includes one by one convolutions.
When you think dropout, you should think
of it as acting on channels is one way
to think about it intuitively.
So
for an MLP, think of it this way. We
have
some HL
CN channels.
Okay.
What dropout does
component-wise multiplies
HL
with IID
Bernoli?
noise.
Okay. So what does that mean?
HL of J
becomes when the output say the output
of dropout becomes zero
if
coin is
tails
one not one Sorry,
coin is heads
and so there's some probability that
this happens
say probability P of being heads. So
this is this P in this if I put the
probability here this probability P is
the probability
of keeping
and 1 minus P is the probability
of dropping out.
Okay,
so basic story of how to use dropout.
Sometimes it's called introducing a
dropout layer. So why is it called a
dropout layer? because you can think of
this operation as being a layer where
you do multiplication component-wise by
a vector that has either ones or zeros
in it that is generated randomly.
So during training in this conceptual
picture all you do is you realize this
randomness this randomness is
non-ifferiable so there's never going to
be a gradient on this randomness to this
randomness and you just say network keep
calculating calculate your gradients
going back whatever okay any questions
on the mechanics of how a dropout layer
works um in this simplified picture I
will talk a little bit in a moment about
uh a different uh perspective but I to
make sure everyone understands like what
you do here. When I say I want to drop
out and I want to drop out with
probability of dropping being 10%. Then
what I mean is I toss a coin that comes
up head 90% of the time and tails 10% of
the time and I component-wise for that
dropout layer multiply inputs so that
they are kept with probability 90% and
dropped with probability 10%.
>> We have a question.
>> Yeah.
>> Why why isn't P learned?
>> Um great question. P isn't learned in uh
standard dropout because we important
thing is we don't expect it to be there
at testing.
This is something like like a data
augmentation. Remember we talked about
the data augmentations. We take your
data and you rotate it a little bit,
change the contrast or do even more uh
harder things on like cutting out
pieces, stuff like that. We don't do
that at test time. That's just there at
training time. Same thing with dropout.
Dropout doesn't exist at test time. It's
only there at training time. That's why
you don't make plearnable.
Thank you.
It's a hyperparameter we set as a part
of the running of the running of
dropout. Typical values for P that are
used are 50% um and 90%. Meaning keep
10% dropout 10% or drop out half. These
are like standard kind of values that
people try for dropout.
>> We have another question.
Hey, I have a I have some trouble
understanding how this creates
redundancy. I feel like we're just
losing data because we're just taking
some out.
>> Excellent point. The question is, why
does this encourage redundancy? It
encourages redundancy because if you had
very important data in one particular
place and then dropout destroyed it,
that would not be good for your network.
So because you're doing dropout during
training for it to raise its performance
it has to make sure the information is
present elsewhere in a different
activation because the chance that every
it'll get dropped everywhere is is very
low right suppose you drop out uh with
probability 1/2 to have eight different
things drop out only happens one in 256
times eight specific things drop out is
only one6 times did that make sense that
help answer the question at an intuitive
level
>> yeah yeah I think I'm Thank you.
>> Yeah, we're good.
>> So, uh I believe in in not the current
homework that's out, but the next
homework, we're going to give you a
problem where where you'll see how
dropout helps uh in an MLP where we do
it.
We have a special modified version of a
data set which has we introduce cheats.
We introduce ways that the classifier
could learn what to do by cheating
because we just like write the answer on
the image. And when you do it, when you
train it with dropout, it is less able
to use the cheat because the it doesn't
see the cheat uh as well all the time.
So that's an example of how redundancy
is better because you want to have it
take information from across the entire
image and not from a little piece and
dropout encourages that.
Okay. Okay. So now
one finds the same issue that we had in
so what happens uh
at training
do drop out
randomly
and typically
D fraction
of activations
survive
the dropout.
So now the question is what do we do at
test time?
So when you're using the model at at
inference time uh you have to do
something. So one choice so try zero say
try zero
is do nothing
just let all everything come through.
You ever understand how this is a
natural choice you say you do this for
augmentations of images right? for
augmentations of images. If you were
going in and you know adding a bunch of
noise or you know cutting out pieces of
the image during uh during training at
test time you're just going to use it
with images without having this damage
done to them.
So you could one natural choice and try
the same strategy or drop out just do
nothing at test time.
Everyone everyone's with me hopefully on
understanding this is the natural thing
to try. Turns out this doesn't work.
Does anyone want to venture a guess as
to why it doesn't work?
Pick somebody to answer. Yeah.
>> Yeah. I mean, I think it's probably a
bit of a matter of scale, right? Let's
say like you've, you know, a simple
thing. It's like you learn to to add up
numbers and you have 10 items with uh a
pres preservation probability of 0.9 and
it learns like oh I want to keep adding
to nine so I'm going to make everything
one right but all of a sudden when you
go to testing time and you keep
everything activated since your network
has like learned to make each entry one
all of a sudden when you keep everything
you hit 10. So all of a sudden sort of
the scale you're getting to exceeds
because you simply have more of your
values at your disposal.
>> Yep. Excellent answer. It messes up
scale.
So remember one of the most fundamental
things we learned about neural nets that
drove our discussion of optimization and
thinking about RMS norm and so on is
that these neural nets like to have
their activations and pre-activations in
a particular range around zero you know
in some near vicinity. If suddenly you
are not dropping out a bunch of numbers,
it's going to get bigger
and it's no longer going to be in the
range that it was trained for and so
it'll stop working.
So the solution
is to scale
activations
by P.
the probability of keeping.
So this you can think of as
replaces
multiplicative noise
by its mean.
When you do that, the scale doesn't
change
and now you're good.
Okay. Does everyone understand this
approach? Uh, any questions on this
approach?
>> No questions.
>> Okay. I didn't I don't see any questions
yet. So now I want to add a comment
here. So let me make a comment. Comment.
This is not what PyTorch does.
Okay. So, uh what does PyTorch do? Uh
what PyTorch does is instead of doing
the multiplication at the end for quote
for test time, it does the
multiplication in advance at training
time.
So instead
Pytor torch
drop out
does this. The output of a dropout layer
at position J
is going to be zero
with probability 1 minus P
and it's going to be
H L
by you know at the same position J same
same same particular index J that we're
talking about divided by P
with probability 1 minus P So it
probably P.
So it does the multiplication at the
time of training instead.
That way when you use the network at
uh inference time, it's you don't need
to do the scaling.
Does everyone understand?
It just it blows up the inputs during
training to be at the at the same scale
that they would have been had you done
no dropout. Here's
a question.
>> Okay. Yeah. Question.
>> Is there a benefit of doing one way over
the other like scaling at the end versus
scaling um like the between the layers
itself?
>> Uh great question. The question was is
there a difference between a benefit for
doing it one way or the other? Uh
in terms of mathematics they're
equivalent to each other.
Right? There's no difference between the
two mathematically. Uh practically
speaking, the PyTorch way is easier for
a practitioner because what it lets them
do is it lets them for example change
the dropout rate during training if they
wanted to have a higher dropout rate at
some points and a lower dropout later
and then still work.
Really, you don't know what should I
what should I adjust it to? this way uh
you know it's just handled kind of at
training time as opposed to at a special
step after training to set the right
dropout uh uh scale. Does that make
sense to people?
So practically speaking the PyTorch
approach is more useful for flexible uh
training recipes
which is why they do it.
Okay, great. So, I want to comment uh
that dropout as I said before is
typically used for MLP layers or MLP
like layers like one by one cons. There
are variants of dropout that are used uh
sometimes in some papers for image
processing which are basically you cut
out entire blobs spatially but typically
dropout is not applied spatially uh in
in most uh training recipes that people
follow.
Uh okay. So now uh having uh talked
about dropout I want to move on to the
next question which is the next very
important thing for training is the
introduction of residual and skip
connections.
Okay
is any any questions before I move on to
make sure everyone understand we make
we'll give you homework problems to have
you work out analytically what happens
to dropout. You'll see it in code and
you'll get a better better familiarity
with it.
>> I think you're good.
>> Okay. Good. So now I want to talk about
uh skip connections. So the first way
so in in the history of neural nets what
happened was people said okay great
networks are doing amazing um we have
these ideas of normalization uh that
will work and let us train these things.
We have dropout which seems to help with
generalization
and we are we're doing fine and we're
seeing that bigger networks are working
better. So then people started saying
let's make our network more and more
layers long more and more layers deep
and suddenly they experienced this
phenomena which is captured here. So uh
if everyone looks on the figure the
first thing they saw sometimes when they
trained a network and they looked at
what was going on with the test error.
So for test error lower is better.
A smaller network was doing better than
a larger network.
So it didn't sometimes scale didn't seem
to help. Making the network deeper
didn't help. In fact, it made it worse.
So if this is all that people were
looking at, they would have said, "Oh,
maybe I've made the network too big and
I'm getting some kind of overfitting
effect that's going on. My network is
just too big for my data size." which is
something you you've a lot about and
heard from your in your machine learning
class but people said hey let's look at
the training data too the training error
so overfitting is characterized over is
characterized by training error is
better but test error is worse remember
everyone's with me on that what they saw
was that with when they were training
these deeper networks even the training
error was worse
and so whenever you do something that
training error gets worse. In a standard
ML point of view, this is usually a
symptom of something that you think of
as being underfitting.
Make a comment here. So, this figure
feels like underfitting.
Okay. Any questions on this? It wants to
understand this intuition of what's
going on connecting to the standard
machine learning intuition.
Okay, I don't see see any questions or
any hands going up. So, uh when
something but it's kind of weird, right?
My network is bigger, but I'm getting
something that feels like underfitting.
So, traditionally in your ML class, you
said that you thought that when a
network gets bigger, you're more prone
to overfitits, not under fits.
So something must be happening.
Uh so somehow adding this depth to the
network was making it train poorly.
So to see what would why that might be
happening, we have to look um at what's
going on in a deeper network. Okay. So
hopefully everyone can see this picture.
It's like a a stylized picture of what's
going on in a deep network. You have an
input. It goes through layer after layer
after layer after layer after layer in
the forward pass. Finally get an output
layer. The output layer is then passed
to a loss layer and the loss layer
computes a gradient
and then that gradient is backed
backwards through the network to tell
you how to adjust the weights.
Everyone good with that?
Okay. So
something in the network when you add
more and more depth to the network was
making it behave like underfitting.
And there's actually two different uh
pictures or interpretations of what's
going on in these settings.
The first picture says look what's
happening what might be happening is
that this backdrop gradient is getting
multiplied by transposes of matrices
spiritually every time as you go
backward through a layer.
Everyone with me on that? Okay. So
you're still multiplying lots of
matrices together. And one thing that
can happen when you multiply lots of
matrices together is that they actually
things go to zero. So this could be
decaying gradients, could be dying
gradients.
And so the question people had was that
okay, maybe there's something I can do
about this to make the gradients not
die. But there's a different perspective
also that you should be aware of.
Uh the different perspective is that
when you start this model at random
initialization, so this is random
initialized, this is random initialized.
Everything is randomly initialized
including the output layer.
So none of these really know what
they're doing.
Okay?
And the loss layer of course knows
exactly what to do. So it says it passes
a gradient back to the output layer.
But then when the output layer passes a
gradient back to the next layer, you
should if you want to anthropomorphize
it, it goes like this. Well, I really
don't know what I'm doing. I'm randomly
initialized. But assuming that I'm
actually the right thing, this is how I
want you to change earlier layer so that
I get something that's useful for me
relative to this loss.
Everyone kind of understands
anthropomorphizing of what backrop is
doing. And then the next layer says,
okay, I don't really know what I'm
doing. I'm just randomly initialized.
But the next guy tells me that he'd like
his outputs like this. And when I think
of how what would make me give outputs
like that, I'll pass on another message
back to the previous layer. So what you
have at another kind of intuitive level
is
a game of gradient telephone being paid
played back through this network where
none of the thing really know what
they're doing. And so by the end later
parts of this network what you're
getting are gradients that are
essentially you know random
in terms of what what what direction
they're pointing in relative to what you
actually want.
Okay, there's a different perspective on
what could be happening here. So it
could be dying gradients
or it could be you know this doesn't
have any uh standard name you know uh
confused gradients.
And so in this picture, what happens is
that the in the confused gradients
picture, what happens is the last last
layer might tune to something, but then
all the other layers are just in not uh
very good shape during training because
they don't really know what they're
doing.
Okay, so there's two reasons that what
what can one can do, but people
intuitively focused in on the dying
gradient problem because it was more
amendable to some problem that they know
how to solve.
Okay. So,
what was the idea?
The idea was,
wouldn't it be great
if we could somehow get this gradient
here
to go back all the way because that's
definitely a good gradient to go Oops.
to go all the way back earlier in the
network.
So the desire
was to create
uh
gradient superighway
that would take gradients back to
everybody. That would be good gradients.
And so you can think of it as one
approach. Remember gradients follow the
activations, right? If you have a
forward p edge, you get a gradient edge
going back. So one approach that people
said is okay, I know how I can do this.
I might not be able to get stuff all the
way from the output layer, but maybe I
can get it from back here. Is why don't
I add a link? So I say I'll add a link
that looks like this.
Right from the beginning, it sends
things all the way through uh coming
over here to the thing before the output
layer. If I did this intuitively, the
gradient in addition to taking a path
like this through the network would also
just go back straight to this layer.
Everyone with me?
And so why, you know, why stop there?
Why don't we also add
this path
and
this path and this path too?
If we did this hypothetically, what
would happen is that the gradient that
comes through the output layer would
then go back to every single block.
Okay, is everyone with me with the idea
of doing this?
And so you say, okay, then the output
layers gradients would come back and
every single block here would have some
signal at least that's not too far down
the telephone pole, you know, kind of uh
line from the uh actual loss.
And then you say, okay, but what about
gradings to help this guy? So you go,
fine, let's do the same thing for this
guy. So let's add links.
Oops.
Let's add links like this.
Okay. So
idea one is
add links
from output
of all earlier layers
to the input
of a given layer.
Okay, so hopefully this what that does
it creates a grading superighway.
Unfortunately, it has a huge negative
effect which is it means that the input
that what's coming in over here is the
sum of many many things. So if you think
of this network as being 50 things deep,
50 different things are adding up
directly over here and so it's getting
bigger. But if not just the 50 things
are adding up over here, that 49 things
are adding up here. And so if 49 things
add up here and then it goes through
this layer, it gets even bigger
potentially.
So this blows up.
Okay, so that doesn't work. But then
people realize that
all I really care about is the idea that
there should be a gradient superighway.
So I have a different idea that I can
do,
which is to just add a more minimalist
set of connections. So to this output
just add this guy
and to the input of here just add
this guy.
Oops.
Yeah.
and so on.
Okay. And these are called skip
connections.
They add
input
to the output
of a layer.
So what do skip connections do? skip
connections. I'll create a path by which
the gradient can actually go all the way
back to everybody
and this creates a path for the
gradients and this turns out to work. So
next time I will finish up resets and
then uh continue uh forward on you know
fully convolutional networks and the
like. Okay, I'm out of time. So, I'll
just take uh a last question if there's
one, but then I'll stand.
>> Uh yeah, there's one question.
>> Oh, hi. Um, if you were to take this
minimalist approach, why wouldn't you
just draw like the connection like
straight like from I like I I I guess
like from every edge to like to right
before the output layer like why why
would you just draw it like from one to
the next and to the next and so on if
that makes sense.
>> So uh in this picture the way the skip
connections are drawn is they always go
skipping over a particular layer.
We'll talk more about the inside of the
layer later, but uh that's the
minimalist approach. Are you asking for
them all just to go to the end the be
the beginning the thing that's going in
the output layer?
>> Yeah. Yeah.
>> Okay. So, we we added that at the we
tried we tried that as an idea at the as
our first idea. Um and the problem there
is that everyone is now helping to
contribute to the output, but they're
not helping the later layers in any way
using a super highway. So the gradient
if there was only uh there only this
connections and the gradient's going
this way to everybody
but what would help this layer that
wouldn't have a path to go to everybody
except through this backward long chain.
So that's what we thought about adding
paths from everything to the everything
else. That's too many paths. This is
kind of in between. So the gradient here
goes back to everybody, but the gradient
from that's coming through here is also
then going back to everybody.
So everyone gets to help everyone in the
future.
>> Okay. So we'll talk more about this next
time. I'm going to end here. Sorry I
can't have office hours uh today. Uh
we'll try to maybe make them up uh next
week. Okay. Bye.