We're at Berkeley time so I can start.
So before I start uh just enrollment
issues should be settled. um if they are
not settled come see us in office hours
and we put up a post about uh
participation credit and what are the
different things you can and need to do.
So, I'm not really going to take
actually any questions about that in
lecture here, but go read the post, ask
questions um on ed.
Any other pressing concerns before I
start the lecture?
Okay, great. So, today's lecture, we're
building from what we've been doing in
the last class. And today's lecture
really what I would like you to take
home from this lecture is perspective.
uh more so than a particular technique
or a particular mathematical trick. I
think the the key agenda here is is
putting forth the value of perspective
and
what we can what we can do with it. So
we've been talking a lot about
optimizers and initialization. That's
been kind of what we've uh what we've
been doing and we're focusing in some
sense a lot on details,
right? And it turns out that these
details actually really really matter.
You know it might feel like oh you know
who cares how we initialize like it's
some random initialization.
Gradient descent will fix it. Well turns
out that these things actually really
matter. And why do we care about all of
these things? Why do we care about which
optimizer we choose? We care about all
of these things because in some sense
better optimizer means faster training
means you spend less money, right? Which
means you make more money. Um so it's
just very simple capitalism in some
sense that drives us to have better and
better um optimizers. Similarly about
initialization you know why was it
really great that
Xavier initialization came about and
then her initialization came about. You
know when we presented it's like well
you know if you have D things coming in
and you want things to be on average the
same well you know divide by D. is kind
of like what's the big deal, right? Why
did we spend half a lecture talking
about this? Well, just to put things
into perspective before this, how would
we do initialization? We would just say
let's put normal 01 ones every
everywhere. Let's initialize that way.
And then what would happen? Well, you
know, your stuff wouldn't train. It
wouldn't work. You wouldn't you would
there wasn't like wrong initialization
error would not pop up. What would
happen is that well you're, you know,
either your maybe your gradients would
vanish, maybe they would blow up, maybe
you wouldn't even notice it, but stuff
would just not work and then you're
tweaking and you're tweaking and you're
tweaking and you're tweaking and if you
think about it, figuring out the right
initialization is like the worst
hyperparameter search you could have,
right? Think about the number of
parameters you have. If you think about
every initialization as a
hyperparameter, that's a lot to search
over. Okay. So, um just having these
rules of thumb and having things like
the Xavier initialization, H
initialization were uh were a big deal.
And now, you know, these are just all
built in. There's libraries. You don't
even need to think about it, but it
mattered and thinking about these things
in a principled mathematical way
actually led to progress. Okay? So, just
we didn't really talk about that as much
last time and make it explicit. So, I
want to make sure that that's clear to
everybody. Okay.
And so nowadays when we think about
optimizers
um you know Adam W.
>> Okay.
[Laughter]
>> So okay let's turn this off.
Okay.
Um
so nowadays when we're thinking about
optimization what we think about and the
kind of default thing is to use atom w
in some sense with um a specific set of
hyperparameters. You know atom used to
be great and then people noticed that
the kind of having regularization
through the standard L2 loss was causing
complications like it was interacting
with the learning rate. So AdamW came
about which said, "Oh, you know this
weight decay, just pull it out and put
an explicit wake DK not through
regularization
into your optimizer and that will
perform better." And so because there's
such a focus on getting optimization to
work well for neural networks, there's
been tons and tons of work on optimizing
atom W, right? and getting the exact
right hyperparameters, getting the exact
stuff to scale for the standard kinds of
architectures that we have out there.
And it's important to remember that
getting something to work on a small
model is different from getting
something to work on a billion parameter
or a trillion parameter model, right? So
there's, you know, something might work
in in a little class project, but that
doesn't necessarily mean it's going to
work at scale. And so there's all of
these challenges with being able to
scale our optimization strategies to
larger and larger networks.
Now, one of the challenges that you have
when you think about Adam is that
because there's been such an effort to
get neural networks to train and get
things to work at scale,
we as a community have focused a lot on
getting Adam or Adam W right. And so
there's been been a huge effort in
figuring out these parameters. But what
this means is that sometimes
coming up with a different optimizer and
making progress when you have a
finetuned machine that works for this
particular optimizer can be difficult.
Okay? Because you don't necessarily have
the all of that hyperparameter tuning.
You haven't figured out all the
hyperparameters for your new optimizer.
So how do you really compare? because
you have all this investment in looking
at Adam.
So there's there's there's in some sense
that that's that's a challenge and so
what we need to think about or what we
are trying to do is well how do we
continue making progress on
optimization?
Okay. And why do we want to continue
making progress on optimization? Well,
this comes to something we were talking
about not last lecture but two lectures
ago where we talked about this uh lazy
training idea, right? Everyone remember
what lazy training was?
So the lazy training idea was this was
this observation that people had um that
hey sometimes I initialize a network and
I train it and you know my my uh
training loss is going down my
validation loss is going down but my
parameters aren't really changing at
all. Maybe my final layer is changing
but most of my other weights are just
frozen where they are or like changing
by very very small amounts. Okay.
And when you think about this, there's
two different ways in which you can view
this uh lazy training assumption. Okay,
so what are the two different ways? One
is oh my gosh, this is magic. You know,
I chose some random weights and turns
out that basically these are some random
feature computations and as as long as I
do some random feature computations and
tune maybe my last layer, I'm able to do
reasonably well. Okay. And so I am uh
able to like so the the question is well
what kinds of functions can I represent
given that I am doing these random
feature computations is everyone with me
on this or yes no kind of no okay I've
lost some people okay so ask me a
question
okay let's step Okay,
we care about money. Everyone's with me
there. Okay, we Okay, we have a baseline
we agree on. Okay, then the next thing,
what do we want to talk about? We want
to be able to do do we are you with me
that we want better optimizers? Okay.
Okay. Are you with me that Adam is what
people do?
So now the question is how do we get
better? Okay, let's say our question is
just how do we get better?
The question is why do we need to get
better? Right? Why is Adam not good
enough? Okay, why are we not saturated
at Adam? Why is Adam not good enough? Or
why do we have a thought that maybe Adam
could be better? One reason is for
example that you notice this lazy
training perspective that sometimes
the weights don't move when you're
optimizing with an optimizer like Adam.
Okay. And now if the weights are not
moving you can have two perspectives.
Either well great somehow I'm really
good at choosing initializations or
maybe my initial initialization doesn't
matter at all and all that matters is
that I have some nonlinear features that
I'm computing from my data. That's
perspective A or perspective B is that
you know I'm not doing something right
like you know nothing is changing in my
network if nothing is changing there's
no way that this random initialization I
picked correctly this just happened to
be somewhere I'm not using the full
power of this thing how can I optimize
better to be able to use the full power
of this thing okay so is everyone with
me on just this observation if I have a
network and I randomly initialize it and
I'm you know uh training it and somehow
I'm getting
uh better function fits but my
parameters are not changing very much.
Are you with me that maybe something
might be wrong? There's no guarantee but
it's it's way worth investigating if
something is off. Yeah. Okay.
>> When you say lazy training assumption
are you saying Over the whole training
run, the weights barely change or each
step they barely
>> I'm saying over the whole training run
the weights barely change. Yeah, that's
a good question. So, it's true that you
know if I have a large training run at
every step they might barely change but
over a long time they might change by a
lot. But here what we're seeing is that
even over the whole training run they're
not changing by a lot.
Better little bit better. Yes. Question.
>> Yeah. I think um at least for me I was
I'm confused because when we talked
about the lazy training assumption I
thought it was in the context of the
tailor expansion of the function with
respect of the loss function with
respect to the parameters and that that
only the first degree approximation only
holds within a small change of the
parameters. I'm failing to see the
connection.
>> So okay there these are two separate
things but they're connected. Okay, so
thing A is that let me actually just so
thing A is that we have this linearized
perspective on our network and we say we
want to say that this linear
approximation is good enough and so we
say that within this local linear uh or
if we if we don't change by change by
enough we're going to be good. Okay,
that's perspective A.
The other thing is this empirical real
observation that you're running an
optimizer and stuff isn't changing.
So these are two different things. One
is a kind of a theoretical modeling
assumption. The other is a real thing
that you see. Okay. But they're talking
about the same thing. Okay.
Okay. So I'm gonna I'll I'll keep coming
back to this throughout the lecture.
Okay. I'm going to start uh start going
forward. But what we have is that so
remember we have some parameters theta.
We have our data x and we have a loss
function that is a function of both our
training data and our parameters. Okay.
And we have this linearized perspective
that we're taking where I'm looking at
the loss
and I'm looking I'm saying well what how
does my loss change when I have some
small change delta theta to my actual
parameterization. Okay.
What is happening when gradient descent
takes a step. So we talked about this
last time and we talked about the
tension that is that is present in
gradient descent. Fundamentally, we want
to have gradient descent be able to take
a step that is small enough so that the
gradient, the local geometry still
holds, right? Because we're
approximating our uh loss function in
this local linear perspective, but we
also want to converge fast. So there's a
trade-off between you, part of you wants
to take really big steps, part of you
wants to be conservative and make sure
your approximation is still valid.
And so what I'm going to do for the rest
of this for a bunch of this lecture is
I'm following a uh perspective that's
been laid out by uh this paper from
Bernstein and New House just from last
year 2024. They of course build on many
many other works but we're trying to
distill the ideas from this paper um in
the lecture. Okay.
So what the perspective we want to take
is we want to try and capture this
gradient descent
from the perspective of finding the
right way to think about the optimizer.
And so let's say you have this loss
function. You're averaging this now over
all of your data points. And we talked
last time about well we're trying to
minimize our loss function. We're
looking at this
linear approximation to our loss
function and we want to say well I want
to do this while making sure that my
step is not too big right so I'm putting
this constraint
and then we talked about the fact that
well if I look at this this first term
here L of theta does it depend on delta
theta
it does not right what What is my
optimization parameter? Delta theta. So
this does not affect I can just
completely drop this right and does not
affect the argument. Everyone with me
there?
Okay. So I can really just look at this
inner product term here
and that is enough for me to be able to
understand the solution to this
optimization problem.
Everyone with me? Thumbs up, thumbs
down.
Okay.
So we said what is the key? What is one
of the things that we have to do here?
Well, we have to understand what do we
mean by take a step that's small enough
in what sense? In what norm sense,
right? That's a choice that we get to
make because that's that's inducing
basically the behavior of the optimizer.
That's that's inducing a bias on how
this optimizer is going to actually take
steps. and different geometries that are
that come from different norms might be
compatible with perhaps different
architectures for your network. So
making these choices explicit is an is a
good thing. We might not know exactly
what the what the impact of our choices
is but knowing that we have these
choices of choosing different norms is a
good and important thing. Okay, everyone
with me that we can choose a norm here.
Okay.
So what was the first choice that we
decided to make?
Well, we said
let's choose first the infinity norm.
Okay. And so now when I choose this
infinity norm,
what do I get? I get this function to be
let me write it here.
I get this to be args
this inner product.
Okay,
so let's look at this. What kind of term
is this term here?
My variable is delta theta.
This is probably this is exactly like a
problem that you've seen in 127 where
you have
xrpose y here
and then you might have
um
right so if I write it like this maybe
it looks like something more famili
amilar. But what kind of program is
this? What kind of optimization problem
is this? It's a linear program, right?
My objective is linear. And if you look
at all of my constraints,
I can also write them there. These are
also linear constraints, right? In fact,
this infinity norm just says I have a
constraint on every single component of
my vector. The infinity norm is saying
that I have to be within this unit hyper
cube. For example, here I've drawn it
out only for two dimensions. The largest
element, the maximum element must be
less than uh ADA in its absolute value.
So I have a linear program, linear
objective, linear constraints. So what
does that tell me about the solution to
my optimum?
What do I know just from optimization
theory?
>> Yeah, at the back. go boundary of the
constraints,
>> right? I'm going to hit a boundary,
right? My optimum is going to be at a
boundary. And if I'm if I if my if my
domain was somehow unconstrained, I
could go off to infinity. But if not,
basically, if I have a linear objective,
I'm just going to follow the gradient in
the direction and I'm going to keep
improving my objective. And the only way
I'm going to stop is I hit some
constraint.
So that perspective, I'm just trying to
give a different perspective from the
one that we talked about this
optimization problem in the last class.
But that perspective says, look, I'm
going to keep hitting my boundaries.
And which boundary am I going to hit?
Well, I'm trying to minimize this thing.
And so I want to make it as small as
possible. So I want to make it negative,
right?
So if my actual if the component in my
gradient is negative then I want my
delta theta to have a component that is
positive. I want the product to be
negative right
and if my component is negative then I
want to have a delta theta or if my
component is positive then I want to
have a delta theta that is actually
negative.
Does everyone see this?
So what the solution ends up being just
one concise way to write this is to say
look at your gradient vector look at the
signs of all of the entries and use that
basically as your gradient step. Okay
everyone with me on this questions about
this? I'm going to pause here.
>> Yes. Wait, isn't this saying though that
just like in one step I mean you said
like the lazy training assumption is
during the whole run but this is saying
like we're getting there in one step of
sign.
>> So what is this saying? We're not saying
we're getting to the optimum. Okay,
remember what are we trying to do? We're
trying to say
I'm trying to minimize this loss
function. Currently I'm at the point
theta. I want to move
a little bit in the direction. So I I
which way I'm going the direction um I'm
going to move
in a way like somewhere in this norm
ball in this ADA norm ball such that I
minimize my um minimize my loss
function.
>> Yeah. But the delta here refers to the
change in one optimization step.
>> Yes. The delta theta refers to the
change you're making in one optimization
step. Absolutely. So you haven't you
haven't reached your minimum there. This
is just one step of gradient descent.
Then you will once you take that step
you will come to a new spot and then you
will think about a linearization around
that point again. Does that make sense?
Okay.
>> Yes. Technically, I guess is the ADA in
our solution a like off by a factor of
like rad n from the ADA that defines our
boundary in the optimization
or oh actually sorry I I was I realized
what I'm doing I was misreading as the
two norm but for infinity norm it is
just
>> yeah okay
>> yes
>> uh would it be accurate to say that if
our change in theta vector is just um
has a maximum change of uh our learning
rate in every single direction when we
just take that step. There's no there's
no optimum there's no better optimum
than a learning rate in every single
entry.
So the way I interpret this is to say
that
if I am restricted to move within the
infinity norm ball then the best I can
do is what you are saying which is look
at the sign in every entry and go the
max that this norm ball will allow you
to go in that entry. Is that your
understanding? Uh so like you would be
the corners of that box would be the
optimal direction.
>> Uh the corners of this box is what you
will hit. Uh um
[Music]
yes.
Yes. The corner of this box is what you
will hit. Yes.
>> Thank you.
>> Absolutely.
>> Connection. Does s of 0 equal 0 or does
it pick either one or negative one?
>> Um does sign of 0 is this is a
implementation
uh detail that you can pick
>> and in that case you can also be like on
the middle of the
>> yeah but you you won't do that.
>> Okay.
Good. Okay. So everyone with me? Okay.
So what is the takeaway from this? The
takeaway is by choosing a norm, we chose
a geometry and this geometry had certain
properties and that led to a certain
optimizer. Okay. And even though you
know when atom first started being used
people hadn't really necessarily thought
it it this connection is has come up.
this it wasn't that oh we had this
perspective and now let's take this
optimization problem from this
linearized perspective and then let's
uh apply different norms and see what
optimizers come out and oh Adam came out
and o sin SGD came out that's not how
this was developed that's how we're
presenting it to you but just Adam
showed up right someone came up with the
idea and it came actually from thinking
about other algorithms like uh adrad
which is an adaptive gradient which was
trying to think about this idea that we
talked about that well the singular
values are of different magnitude. So
let's try to make them all the same so
that we don't uh have these learning
rate problems. Everyone remember that
like that was how atom was developed.
But it turns out one can look at it and
have this perspective
that brings about the core idea of Adam
which is sin SGD from this different
way. Is that clear to everyone?
Okay. So what I want you to get is the
perspective. The math is also important
but the perspective is equally important
with me. Excellent. Okay. So now you had
this question about the two norm this
normalization that you're thinking of
was going to show up.
So that was just one choice. So we could
make another choice, right?
Instead of the infinity norm, you know
that wasn't even our favorite norm. Our
favorite norm is always the my favorite
norm, probably your favorite norm is
always the two norm, right? is the
easiest to work with.
So instead, we could really think about
this as the um as the two norm. So
actually why don't you take a minute and
actually work this out, talk to each
other and figure out what is the optimal
solution to this optimization problem in
the two norm context.
Feel free to talk. It's valuable for you
to talk.
Okay, there's my timer.
Okay, let's come together. Let's come
together.
So,
let's think about this two norm
together.
This is something that you've seen
before in some sense. Right?
Now when I look at this
is this
is this a linear program?
No. Why is it not a linear program? Just
refresher.
>> The constraint is not a linear
constraint. Right? I have this norm
constraint. Okay. Good. But nonetheless,
is it a program that I like?
Okay. Why do I like this program? What's
the what is this what is the nature of
the constraint that this induces?
>> It's this unit ball, right? Well, it's
not a unit ball. It's an ADA ball
because I'm having my norm be uh bounded
by ADA. Okay. So now I have an inner
product. I have an xrpose y. And when
I'm looking at all of the different
directions, let's say this is one
direction and I'm trying to find a
direction that has the minimum inner
product with this. Okay,
so what are my choices? Well, what does
the inner what is the inner product? I
can write out the inner product
explicitly, right? In terms of the angle
between the two vectors.
So I can really write out this in this
way. Xrpose Y is just the norm of X norm
of Y times the cosine of the angle
between the two vectors.
So if I wanted to maximize this inner
product, what do I want that cosine to
be?
>> If I wanted to maximize it, I want the
cosine to be zero.
>> I want the co you want the angle to be
zero, but you want the cosine to be one,
right? And if I wanted to minimize it, I
want them to be exactly opposite to each
other. So that I want the cosine to be
negative one, right?
being orthogonal would mean that my
cosine is exactly zero.
So to minimize this I want to have
choose these vectors that are pointing
exactly in the opposite direction.
And so we know from koshwarz or you know
whatever whatever particular way you
like remembering this fact whether it's
the just the definition of the inner or
this formula for the inner product or
koshwartz the inner product absolute
values are maximized when you're e when
your vectors are just either aligned uh
or anti-aligned okay in this case
because we're looking for the arg min we
want them to be anti-aligned
so what does that mean so I what I need
to do is I need to say Look
to take the best to find the best vector
take your current vector and normalize
it. Okay, so my vector is this gradient
and then I'm normalizing it to make it
into a unit vector. Does everyone see
that?
And then I scale it so that it's exactly
magnitude ADA. So this has norm one
multiplied by this and now it has norm
ada. So it's exactly within that ada
ball bulb.
So when I look at this step is this the
step of gradient descent.
It is not quite the step of gradient
descent. Right? What is the difference?
If I wanted to do gradient descent I
would not have this term here. Right?
Right? I would cancel this out. That
would make it exactly like a gradient
descent step. So what I have here is
basically a normalized version of
gradient descent. The direction I'm
moving in is exactly the same, but the
distance that I'm moving is slightly
different. If I think of ADA as being my
step size or my learning rate, I could
reimagine this and think about
this as my step size. ADA divided by
this norm of the gradient
and I could I could think of this as
gradient descent in that sense. Okay.
But I can just really think about this
in a slightly different perspective
which is instead of thinking about this
problem as this constrained optimization
problem actually first any questions
about this? Are we good with this?
This is 16A stuff.
Okay, good.
Instead of looking this as a constrained
optimization problem, I can
alternatively think about moving my
constraint here to be a regularizer or
like a lrange multiplier. Right? And now
this is a different optimization
problem. It's not the same optimization
problem. But if you remember from a
127th homework problem, you did prove
that these two problems sweep out the
same set of solutions for appropriate
choice of ADA and lambda. Okay, so the
family of solutions that are captured by
these are exactly the same.
And so I can think of this particular
optimization and it's doing the same
thing, right? It's basically saying it's
capturing the same intuition they want
to capture, which is that I'm penalizing
you for taking too big of a step. Don't
take too big of a step, otherwise you're
going to break your local linearization.
So, it's the same kind of uh thinking
that can go into this optimization
problem.
But now when I look at this, well, I
know that this is just this function is
convex, right? There's a quadratic here.
Lambda is greater than zero. It's a
parabola that faces upward. So I can
actually just easily compute the optimum
of this
and I can compute this gradient
which is just uh this vector plus 2
lambda delta theta.
I can set this to zero and I can compute
this minimizer. Okay.
And now I get basically something that
looks more like the standard gradient
descent. Right? there's not this uh
normalization by the norm uh norm of the
gradient which which is a confounding uh
factor in the way that we wrote it
earlier. Okay.
But whichever way we look at this the
geometry is something that is similar to
how we would think about gradient
descent.
Okay.
So everyone with me on the two different
ways we can we can think about this
constrained optimization problem
and the fact that when we make this
choice of the two norm here
what we get out
is gradient descent.
And this perspective, you know, is not
new in the sense that people have known
this about gradient descent for for a
long time. But it's interesting to look
at it in the same vein of family of
things that we looked at Adam because
we're going to now continue this
pattern, right? One can be a fluke, but
two, you're starting to see a pattern.
And now what we want to try to see is
like is there more to this pattern? What
can we uh what can we learn from this?
Okay. So, I'll pause here and take
questions.
>> Yeah.
>> Not sure I understand. like if we turn
our constrained optimization model to
the unconstrained like because we have
to make sure the constraint still holds.
So you have to
>> so you can choose a lambda like if I
wanted to turn this constrained
optimization problem into this there's
there's a there's a question of finding
the right lambda so that you can get the
exact same solutions. I'm not interested
in matching the solutions. I don't
really care what the value of lambda is
to correspond to the ADA. What I'm
interested in pointing out is that
you can get the same form of descent
algorithm. So yes, there's a there's a
subtlety there if you had to pick the
appropriate like you had to match the
ADA to the lambda to get the same
solutions. Absolutely.
>> Yes.
>> Uh
is it the case that this descent will
always take smaller steps than normal
stoastic gradient descent?
>> Um
The question is is will this take
smaller step than normal SGD? I
no I don't see why. Um it's just it's
doing exactly the same thing. It's just
a function of what you set your step
size to be and all the same constraints
that you would apply to SGD or gradient
descent would still apply here.
>> Yes.
>> Um for the normal approach that we
looked at like isn't the step size like
variable for like each update? um
compared to like regular gradient
descent
because it depends on like the L2 norm
of your gradient as well.
>> Yes. Yes. Agreed. So here you have this
this perspective is bringing in the
magnitude of the gradient and so what
this will do is that if you have a
smaller magnitude you will take a bigger
step and if you have a bigger magnitude
you will take a a smaller step
effectively which may or may not be
actually desirable for you. One of the
nice things and one of the reasons like
when you look at the proof of the
convergence of gradient descent, right?
One of the things that matters is the
fact that in a convex problem, your
gradient is going to zero as you're
getting close to your optimum. So having
this normalization by the magnitude of
the gradient may or may not actually be
desirable for you because if you get
close to the optimum and then your norm
is going to zero, this might not be a
good thing.
>> Yeah. Yes.
Yes.
>> Okay, that's a great question. So, the
question is, uh, arbitrary alert, you
just chose the infinity norm out of your
pocket and then you said true norm was
your favorite, but who cares about your
favorite, you know? I want to do my
favorite. Um, so agreed, right? I
haven't justified to you why we're
choosing the infinity norm and why we're
choosing the two norm.
And in some sense that's the point
because what we're trying to do here is
we're trying to give you a perspective
on optimizers. So Adam wasn't developed
because the people who developed Adam
loved the infinity norm. This idea that
sins GD is this optimization problem
with the infinity norm came after sin GD
was developed in some sense.
Okay. So we're saying oh there's this
atom. Oh look at Adam is amazing. It
works great. And what we're saying is if
you think about Adam from this
perspective and you look at it as from
this particular optimization problem and
you choose the infinity infinity norm
then
sin SGD or the you know the brother
sister of Adam pops out
then the same thing for two norm well
two gradient descent we kind of already
knew this like the community already
knew this that's not
But what this is what this question is
saying well so then obviously you know
there's nothing special about the
infinity norm why aren't we trying all
the different norms here now we have
we're basically generating a recipe for
creating optimizers right we're saying
let's take a norm let's take a step size
let's turn the crank on this
optimization problem.
Optimizer one, optimizer two, optimizer
three, optimizer four. You can just
start printing them, right? And that's
exactly what we want to ideally try and
do. Okay? Now, there are two challenges
in turning the crank on this recipe.
First is that
we need to look at this optimization
problem and we need to say which norms
make sense.
Okay, some norms might be better than
others and maybe we want to have a way
of thinking about which norms we like
and which norms we don't like.
Now, there's one way of finding which
norms we like.
And what is that way of finding which
norms we like?
Yeah,
>> empirical testing.
>> Empirical testing is one great way of
doing it. What's another way?
You use the norms that are tractable,
right? the things that are easy to do
math with and the ones that are easy to
understand, you start with those because
that helps you understand and interpret
things. Okay? So there's the empirical
testing and there is the like how do you
want to how do you want to choose the
norm? And so what we want to try and do
and that's exactly what we're going to
try and do for now this lecture and
moving and that'll set up basically for
the next lecture
is see what we can do with this recipe
or why uh does that does that answer the
question?
>> Yeah.
>> Yeah. Um I understand how like we switch
from an argument on like the delta data
to an argument later on like data itself
and I understand how they're kind of
achieve the same point with the
regularization limiting like how big the
data really but are those like the same
problem or are those just kind of like
similar
>> so the question is what is the
connection between kind of
this perspective here where I'm having
this constrained optimization and this
perspective here when I have interpreted
this as a regularizer right or a lrange
multiplier um and uh two things one for
example you can provably show that for
the two norm the set the solutions that
are possible in this and this as you
sweep ada and lambda you can choose
parameterizations that will basically
get you all of the same solutions.
Second,
again remember we're we're doing
deep learning or even just even if you
just think about optimization.
Optimization
is about finding a solution that works.
You've taken some real world problem and
you've mathematized it into these set of
equations and these equations are trying
to reflect your understanding of the
real world. Okay, this is not set in
stone.
So now if I wanted to say I don't want
my step to be too big, there are
multiple different ways I can
mathematically write this and it is okay
for me to choose the way of
mathematically writing it that is
convenient to me or that I like or that
gives me the answer that is convenient
to implement or convenient to solve
because at the end of the day we're just
modeling. We're modeling and trying to
do something that works in the real
world. If it works, it works. Like this
is the uh you know look where the light
is kind of analogy like if you can make
it work that's great. So there's an
element of that here. We're not you know
it's not like oh this particular
optimization came from the skies and we
care about this optimization problem. No
we formulated it. We were the engineers.
Make sense?
Okay. So I'll move on.
So now building on the question that was
over here of like what's so special
about infinity norm is there another
norm that we can think about and turns
out that yes of course and that's
exactly what I want to get to in the
rest of this lecture.
So one thing that we've been doing is
we've been thinking about here we think
about these theta as our parameters and
we're thinking about them as vectors.
Okay,
but reality is that neural networks and
these parameters of neural networks are
not just one big theta vector, right?
Actually, what we have is we have the
weights and we have the biases. And so
there's a structure to this theta.
But when we think about gradient descent
as just a gradient update to the
parameters, we're ignoring or turning a
blind eye to the fact that there is this
structure, this geometry, this
organization to the problem. Okay? And
so if our optimization algorithms are
not doing enough for us, maybe there's a
value in trying to look in a finer sense
and use the structure that we know is
naturally present in the problem, right?
But we're not even putting it in in some
arbitrary way. If I think about a neural
network,
I can write it this way, right? I mean,
I have ReLU's here, but this is just
think of this as just some nonlinearity,
which is I have my input X and then I
have my weight times my input plus my
bias. I take some nonlinearity. I
compute my network this way. And here I
naturally have this matrix. Okay,
so maybe there's some value in thinking
about our parameters in matrix form
themselves. And if you remember what we
talked about in the uh kind of
initialization lecture was, you know,
the weight matrices are in some sense a
a they have a they have a behavior and
the fact that these are multiplying
matters and so these are the things that
can cause u scaling problems.
So one perspective is like let's just
focus on how we do updates of the weight
matrices. Let's put the problem of the
bias uh updates aside for just a moment.
Okay, let's focus on the updates of the
weight matrices.
So here what I have
is if I take now
this optimization problem that I've been
thinking about the same optimization
problem that I was thinking about when I
did the sin SGD and the gradient descent
but instead of taking the gradient with
respect to this theta vector I think
about my weight matrices as the
parameters that I'm trying to update.
Okay. So now I think of this as in as an
inner product between two matrices.
Okay. This delta w is a matrix.
It's how my parameters are changing with
every gradient step. And here I write
this gradient of the loss with respect
to that matrix w.
And again I'm saying I don't want my
step to be too small. So I'm saying my
delta w instead of my delta theta is
less than or equal to ada. I'm just
writing the same optimization problem
with w instead of theta and thinking of
it as a matrix instead of a vector
because that's the natural structure of
the problem. Everyone with me there?
Okay. So let's just remember what this
inner product means now in this sense.
Well,
I have that the inner product for
matrices is just given by the trace of
arpose time b. Okay.
Just reminding ourselves of what this
means.
And now I again come to the question of
if I want to solve an optimization
problem of this form,
I want to be able to choose an
appropriate norm here.
And the question becomes again well what
norm do I want to choose? Okay. And so
what is a natural norm to choose when we
think about matrices?
There's basically if you look at 127
there's two norms that you learned about
here. We're thinking about how this this
matrix is basically thinking is take
it's taking these hidden layers or it's
taking these x vectors and it's scaling
them. Right? So there's the spectral
norm and there's the probinius norm. The
spectral norm is the one that talks
about how vectors get scaled. So maybe
it's a natural choice to think about the
spectral norm of the particular matrix.
Okay, we could make other choices. We
are make we happen to be making this one
because it gives us interesting results.
Everyone good with me? Questions?
Okay.
So let me just remind you of what the
spectral norm is. It's just this maximum
singular value. Or another way of
thinking about it is when I have a unit
norm vector,
what is the worst that this matrix can
do to it? How much can it scale that
vector by? Well, that is given by the
largest singular value or the spectral
norm.
Just put pulling these u memories of
what the spectral norm means back into
your cache.
Everyone good?
Okay. So with this what I want to do now
is I want to consider this optimization
problem
where now I'm choosing the spectral norm
here the matrix spectral norm
and here I have this inner product of
matrices.
Everyone with me here?
questions about the setup and the
formulation and what I am trying to do.
How to solve this optimization problem
is a separate issue which we will come
to. Why this is an interesting
optimization problem? We will also come
to but what am I trying to do? I'm
building off of this question is what is
so special about the infinity norm. The
answer is there is nothing special about
it. we can choose a different norm and
in fact let us try to take a perspective
that brings in the structure of the
problem naturally the natural structure
of the problem has matrices scaling
vectors let's try to bring that geometry
to the forefront of the optimization
problem
yay nay
everyone's lost
okay I feel like I should take questions
Thumbs up if you want me to continue.
Thumbs down if you want me to stay
waiting for questions.
Okay, I see some thumbs downs. So,
someone asked me a question.
>> Yeah.
Uh yes, this should be a two norm here.
Thank you.
>> Yes. So are we essentially converting
the like idea of trying to optimize for
step size to incorrectly optimizing over
the actual weight themselves just
>> um we're trying to what we're trying to
do is we're trying to take this
perspective this linearized perspective
and this general form of optimization
problem and try different
uh try different norms. and try
different prop like ways of looking at
the problem. Uh we're not we're saying
that within this norm ball. So we're
kind of we're fixing the step size but
we're fixing the step size
in a particular geometry. Right? So
we're saying that the the choice of the
norm is essentially fixing the notion of
distance or but we're saying within this
distance what is the direction that I
should move in?
Okay,
good.
So how should we actually solve this?
We're going to get to that. What I want
to tell you is that if you were able to
solve this, it turns out that Giz gives
you a variant of uh what is known as the
shampoo optimizer. I actually do not
know why it was called that. I meant to
look it up before the lecture and I
forgot. Um but it's called shampoo.
There's also another variant of shampoo
that is called soap.
Um but you know I guess people are
having fun with uh with with naming
convention uh naming conventions
but shampoo was actually proposed in
like 2017 2018. Shampoo again was not
proposed by thinking of this
optimization problem and then asking the
very nice question of what is so special
about the infinity norm.
there was a series of you know other
considerations about geometry and just
trying to get more perspective out of
this um that led to the proposal of
shampoo then there was another
interpretation of shampoo as more like a
second order method with like you know
kind of like Newton's method is a second
order method thinking of maybe shamp
thinking of shampoo in that light and
then this perspective on shampoo is very
very recent okay so again it's not that
we ran this recipe and out popped Adam
out pout shampoo. This was not a turn
the crank but shampoo was developed
independently. This perspective is
coming later.
And turns out that this other variant of
shampoo, you know, did very well in one
of these uh training algorithm
competitions. So that also ended up
getting it a bunch of uh a bunch of
attention. Okay. So now I want to focus
on actually how to solve this problem
and I'm going to give you a hint which
is that what matters is the SVD. Okay.
And turns out then that this is the
actual solution that you're going to
get. So let's now work together to
actually get this out. And I want to
rewrite this problem. Actually I'm going
to maybe add a page here.
Okay.
So here I'm thinking about this
minimization of this um matrix in our
product. I can just as well think about
the maximization of the negative. So I
can think about this as max of let's
just to simplify the notation think
about this as the max of arpose b such
that
the two norm of b has some bound let's
just say one
um and sorry I meant to say here
trace of
Okay.
So, pull out all of the SVD that has
been coming back to your brain from
doing all of this homework. Um, and a
reminder of different properties of
trace. Remember that trace of
a B C is equal to trace of
B CA.
and you know spend a few minutes trying
to figure out how you might go about
doing actually this optimization
problem. So think about it and we'll
come back together to work on it.
Before I do that, any questions about
this setup? We're we're good, right?
Okay.
So take some time talk to talk to each
other. Make sure you've unders you're
with me.
Oh my
god.
Everyone
listening.
Facebook.
Do you know what validator is?
about linearization
because you know you discuss like how
Yeah, let me take Okay, there's a
question.
>> Um, are you on
divide each of the
UI
I don't know how to
feel like
Okay, let's come back together on this.
Okay. So, anyone have any ideas on what
we could do
>> here?
In the interest of time, I guess I'm not
going to write this whole thing out
again. I thought I would, but I don't
have as much time as I thought I did.
So, let's look at the way to um let's
look at the way to do this.
So I have my uh optimization here
and there's a good principle of when in
doubt use the SVD that kind of works. Uh
especially if you're trying to look at
how big your step should be. So B is my
optimization variable. I don't know
anything about B. A is the matrix that I
know. Let me plug in the SVD of A, which
is that A is U sigma VRpose. Okay, so
I'm just going to rewrite my
optimization problem this way. And
remember now that I have a transpose
here, this is V sigma transpose urpose.
Okay, everyone with me there? I just
plugged in the SVD.
Now what I'm going to do is I'm going to
say well
this is one very nice form of the SVD
but I actually want to think about this
in my outer product form of the SVD. So
I'm going to write it as the sum over
sigma i vi ui transpose. Note that I
have this transpose of the outer product
form right? So this different should be
different from how you remember the SVD.
That should be UV transpose. But here
now I have a V ui transpose.
Okay. So the order of this matters.
How many people want a minute after this
step to actually just try to work it out
themselves?
No one. Like just give me the answer
quick. You want to do it yourself? Okay.
Take a minute. Take one minute to just
Yeah. See if you can move from here.
[Laughter]
I'll give you a hint. When you have a
trace of a matrix and it's a big
unwieldy thing,
I don't really know how to take a trace
of a you can't hear me or you can't hear
me. Okay, my mic is fine, right? Okay.
The fa people's faces make me they make
me feel like you can't hear me at all.
Okay. Okay.
But when you have a trace of a matrix or
it's a product of things, what would be
really nice? What is the best kind of
thing? What is the best kind of matrix
to take a trace of?
>> Diagonal. Diagonals are great. What's
better than diagonal?
>> Scalers.
Why didn't
Oh yeah, you can
Okay. So let's come together.
So in that light of how can I make this
into a scalar?
Well, I have this
and I look at this. This is a trace of
these sums.
But I don't like sums of matrices. Sums
of matrices are complicated. So nice
thing about a trace is it's a linear
operation, right? So I can pull this sum
out and put the trace in. Okay. So I can
think of this as a sum of the traces of
each of these individual matrices. Good.
So here we can say this is because trace
is linear.
Okay,
good.
And now
I can apply my other favorite property
about traces which is that I can do
circular shifts of the matrix inside my
trace operation but maintain the trace.
Right? So here I have this sigma i. This
is just a scalar. So again the trace is
linear. The sigma i really just pops
out.
But I can circularly shift these three
matrices that are in here. These are yes
u and v are vectors but I can think of
them as uh matrices
and I can do this circular shift. And
when I move this vi
over to this side,
what do I get? Well, I get upose b vi.
This thing is just a scalar.
Okay.
And now this is just a scalar. So what
is a trace of a scalar? Well,
it's just this quantity.
And now I have this UI transpose B vi
right here.
Well, now what can I say about this
thing? Well, this is a matrix times a
vector.
So what do I know about B * VI? Okay.
Well, I know that the length of this
vector is bounded by the norms of these
individual vectors. So, this is a SVD.
This is a this is this is norm one vi.
And what are we assuming? We're assuming
that the two norm or the spectral norm
of b is bounded by one. So, this is at
most one, right?
And then I can think of u transpose
times this vector here.
And again, koshwarz just tells me that
this is also bounded by one.
Okay.
So what I can get out is here now just
the sum of the singular values.
So I get this as an upper bound to show
that this is actually achievable. I need
to show that well I can actually choose
a B that attains this bound. Right?
And turns out if I choose this B is
equal to UVRpose well I can just plug
this back in here.
If B is UVRpose, this uranspose U is
going to cancel.
And again, the circularity properties of
the trace are going to give me that this
will actually give me exactly the sum of
the singular values.
Just to see that you can see that
write in a different color.
um v sigma transpose
uranspose u v.
If I take the trace of this,
this is equal to just the trace of sigma
transpose.
Okay, good.
Everyone with me on this optimization
problem. Okay. So you can solve this
optimization problem and what we get
question.
>> Uh yeah it was I guess more practical of
like I remember we talked earlier that
finding the SV of your gradient every
step is kind of expensive right?
>> Yeah. So great question. So here the
point that is being made is that look
this B is UVRpose
and you're saying that okay now just
choose this B and choose this step UV
transpose but how are you going to find
this U and V right that's actually an
expensive operation it's not trivial to
find that so you can't just say well
look I found this fancy new optimizer I
just can never implement it uh it's
great to put on my wall but I can't use
it why is this still a good optimizer.
Two things. One is that what uh the
shampoo algorithm and what we're going
to talk about in the next lecture
introduced ways of computing things like
UV transpose that are computationally
efficient.
Uh we will talk about one such technique
in the in the next class.
Um
so yeah that's basically the uh the
short answer and one other perspective
is that even if we're not able to
compute this having this as a
perspective is still useful for us in
terms of thinking about our recipe and
can we turn the crank and turn out new
optimizers.
Good question.
Everyone with me?
Okay good.
So what this is recipe is pointing to
and that's kind of what this uh paper
that I mentioned at the beginning of
class is talking about is that we can we
have this recipe that says okay you can
choose a norm you can choose a step size
and you can generate new optimizers.
Okay so can we use this recipe to
actually produce new optimizers that can
do better. Okay. And to be able to see
this, what one thing we might want to
think about is really what might be a
good norm for deep learning, right? How
do we think about what is the right
norm? How do we think about this
question of which is the right norm to
choose, right? Uh the ones we're
choosing are somewhat arbitrary.
So to think about this, let's recap what
we talked about Xavier initialization.
And there we said look if you have a
bunch of different inputs that are
coming into u the network and I want to
have the output be approximately normal
01 when my inputs were approximately
normal 01.
What we said was well let's scale by
this fan in right
and if we choose an appropriate
initialization for these W's
that that's a good way of thinking about
it
and that will help us get make sure that
our norms are not changing between the
input and the output
if we wanted to think about Xavier
initialization
in terms of norms if you want to think
what is the norm what is the norm like
property of our inputs that is not
changing
at the output. What is the right norm to
think about?
Well,
you know, the natural thing is to say
like, well, if this is norm one, make
this norm one. That's kind of just
and if it's if you think about this in
the two norm sense if you think about
this in the ukidian norm sense well if
this vector had norm one
Xavier doesn't really imply that this
output h is going to be norm one right
because I have this input and I have
this output and they have different
dimensions
okay
instead what Xavier is trying to talk
about is trying to say let's look at the
entries of this vector x and I want them
all to be kind of
roughly
uh you know like roughly of variance one
so mean zero variance one and so if I
want to get rid of the effect of the
number of x's they are or the dimension
I can just scale by the dimension right
so I can think about instead of thinking
about the ukitian norm one what if I
thought about what is called the RMS or
the root mean squared norm. This is
called root mean squared.
Okay. So I define this root mean square
norm as I just take my uklidian norm but
I scale it
by the square root of the dimension.
And what this gives me is that if the
root mean square is one, then that's one
way of thinking about all of my entries
are one. This is now a relaxation,
right? If I want saying that every
single entry has norm one is a stricter
requirement than saying that my RMS norm
is one.
Does that make is is that clear to
everyone?
But
in this perspective of like do what we
can, work with what we can, maybe one
interesting thing to think about is to
think about well can we look at the RMS
norms and make sure that the RMS norms
for example
uh are reasonable or look that look at
that as an interesting norm in the
context of deep learning. Okay, does
that make sense? Questions?
All I'm trying to say is that just take
this perspective of what is Xavier
trying to keep unchanging. It's trying
to say even if I have a lot of things
summing in I don't want the dimension or
the number of inputs to affect how big
my output becomes. So I'm going to scale
by that factor. And that suggests
looking at something like this RMS norm
which naturally normalizes by the
dimension.
Okay.
So what this argues is well maybe this
RMS norm is interesting for deep neural
networks. Remember we started out by
saying how do we choose what the right
norm is? So maybe this is an interesting
norm and we saw from this shampoo
example that actually maybe looking at
the matrix perspective
is valuable. Looking at this the fact
that think of your parameters as
matrices instead of vectors
is actually valuable. So can we think of
a norm that we can apply to matrices
that is like the RMS norm? Okay.
So what I want to introduce now is this
idea of the RMS to RMS norm. So remember
we talked about the spectral norm
earlier and we talked about the spectral
norm as saying we define the spectral
norm of a as for example what is the
maximum that you can scale a vector when
the two norm of the vector is one. So if
I wanted to get the spectral norm I take
this induced norm definition and I put
alpha and beta both as two. Right?
Right. So if I take an input vector that
is norm that has two norm one that is a
in the unit ball in the two norm sense
and I see how big can a make that in the
two norm sense that gives me
uh the spectral norm. Okay. But I can
generalize this idea and get an induced
matrix norm that says that well two was
arbitrary.
Take your favorite norm here and take
your favorite norm here. Take for
example the alpha norm here and the beta
norm here. And if I give you something
in the alpha unit ball, how big can a
make it in the beta norm sense? That is
the induced norm. It's the same idea as
the spectral norm just generalized.
Okay,
with that now can we define an RMS to
RMS norm? And how I'm going to define
that is to say a RMS to RMS is to say
how big can a scale X in the RMS norm
sense
when the input is also restricted in the
RMS norm sense to be one
and remember the RMS norm is just the
uklidian norm but scaled by the
dimension. Okay.
So if the RMS norm of this vector is
one, what does that mean? It's uklidian
norm is
it's just square root d1, right? If d1
is the dimension of this. So I can
rewrite this constraint as this.
Similarly, if this vector is dimension
d2, I can rewrite this as just 1 /
d uh d2 times the uklidian norm of this.
These are just both constants. I can
pull them out of the optimization
problem and recover here something that
is very familiar to us which is what is
this quantity?
If everyone was awake for this lecture,
please tell me that you know this
otherwise this lecture is a total bust.
What is this quantity?
>> The spectral norm right?
We started the lecture with this.
Okay, good.
So
this RMS to RMS norm
is something that is just essentially a
scaled version of the spectral norm. Why
do we like this? We like this because
the spectral norm is familiar. We can do
lots of things with the spectral norm.
We have theorems about it. We understand
it. We know its connection to singular
values. We know how to work with it.
The other thing about this is that it's
coming naturally. It's trying to
naturally take in the architecture of
the network when thinking about the
norm, right? It's saying, well, if you
have a lot of things coming in, more
things going out, few things going in,
basically the dimensionality of this
matrix
is naturally showing up in the value of
this particular norm. And so what if you
wanted to do something we're trying to
build an optimizer that does something
on a layerbylayer basis, right? So each
of these layers has different matrix
multiplications associated with them.
And if you wanted to have an optimizer
that does different things,
by thinking about the RMS norm, you're
naturally bringing in the geometry of
the layer or the structure of the layer
into the optimization problem. And by
doing this, you can maybe have reduce
your hyperparameter search, which is
kind of the heart of the issue, right?
If I can generate this natural scaling
that says here you should move in this
units and here you should move at this
scale and here you should move at this
scale.
Then this problem when you have to
choose one learning rate but everything
is operating at different scales
is it doesn't go away but it's being
mitigated.
And this norm allows you to naturally
bring in the different scales at which
the different layers are operating
into the geometry of the optimizer.
Okay, is that that's what I'm trying to
illustrate here. We will continue this
in the next class and build on this
perspective to get us to uh the MUP and
the muon optimizers. So that's it. See
you next class.