Okay, great.
So um today I'm going to talk about u
muon which is the kind of final
optimizer in our optimizer journey and
talk about how the idea of
um architecture specific optimizers has
basically changed the landscape of
optimization and there's a whole new
world essentially of optimizers out
there but I promised last time that I
went a little fast at the end of the
discussion So, I'm gonna go over that
last bit one more time.
So, everyone remember what we talked
about from up?
Yes. No. Kind of. Okay. Just before we
start, just take a minute and like quiz
your neighbor on what happened in
lecture last time so that you all
remember what happened. Just that
everyone's brains is in the right place
before we even start lecture. Just take
one minute.
small as you increase the size or the
size of
width
of the
deterines the size.
rel.
Okay, that's my one minute timer. What
happened to my screen?
>> Okay, great. Okay, now that you've
remembered what we were trying to do,
the whole idea behind MUP is to think
about
training large networks is really hard.
One of the key challenges in doing this
is the hyperparameter search because
there's too many hyperparameters and we
really don't know how to go about
finding and identifying what these
hyperparameters are. Everyone remember
that? That was a challenging thing. It
cost lots of dollars to train the
network. You can't just do a search and
a scan for hyperparameters. Okay. So,
MUP basically gives a architecture
specific way of saying well what can I
do to scale the hyperparameters from a
smaller proxy network to a larger target
network that I actually want to train.
So instead of doing my hypersparameter
sweep on this trillion parameter model,
I'm going to do it on a much smaller
model. And once I and I can use this
then I take the hyperparameters from the
smaller model and just directly use them
for the larger model. Okay, that was the
key idea behind MUP.
And what this what the part I want to
talk about now is giving you one more
level of intuition for where the
thinking about MUP comes from which
leads nicely into talking about uh muon
later on.
So this is following uh a paper by I
think I talked about uh Jeremy
Bernstein, James Simon and Greg Yang uh
called a spectral condition for feature
learning. And here they're talking about
this simplified linear algebraic
perspective that leads to the same
scaling laws as MUP even though the
original MUP paper used tensor algebra
and was far more complicated. So to
remind us of what this setup here is,
let's HL be some hidden layer. And
what's happening, we have some hidden
layer. It's going into a weight matrix
WL. You have a bias coming in here. Then
you have a nonlinearity here. And what
you get out is the next layer HL. This
is just what's happening at layer L.
Our matrix WL is D out by D in.
And what we want to do is now we want to
focus our attention on how our scaling
of these parameters should behave as the
network width scales because we want to
be able to transfer parameters from a
smaller network to a larger network.
Okay. So we're right now not thinking
about the depth of the network. We're
only thinking about the width. Okay.
Now, we've talked about Xavier
initialization many times and we've come
to this conclusion that look we want to
have all of the entries of our layer be
approximately of the same order. We want
them to be for example approximately
one. And this led us to this condition
of the RMS norm being one. Right? And
the RMS norm talked about is a
relaxation of the idea that every single
entry should be approximately one. Okay?
Here we're saying that on this is
because the RMS norm is just taking the
average over the over the entries.
And remember that the RMS norm is just a
scaled version
of the two norm here. Our HL is now
dimension D out. So here we have the two
norm of this vector will be just square
root D out. Okay. If I assume if I want
to if I want to have the condition that
this hidden layer has RMS norm
approximately one or order one. Yeah,
RMS norm is coming back to everyone's
head.
Okay, good.
So this is one desired thing that we
want. And what's the other desired thing
that we want? We want to make sure that
our gradient descent or whatever
optimization we're doing is actually
moving our parameters, right? We don't
want to just be frozen in some
initialization and not really move
anywhere far from them, especially as
the width of your network increases,
right? So, you want to make sure that
your updates are not becoming negligible
as your network gets bigger and bigger.
I don't know what's wrong with this
projector today.
It's like there's something loose
somewhere, but I can't figure out what.
Okay. Hopefully this stays stablely.
So for that I also want to look at
the update to my parameters as I'm
running my optimization algorithm. And I
want to make sure that the update to my
parameters is also approximately order
one in terms of the width. Of course
remember that your update is going to be
multiplied by your learning rate. Right?
you have your gradient step and you
multiply it by your learning rate which
is small. So compared to
um your HL your delta HL is going to be
small but it's just not small in as a
function of the width right so as a
function of the width both of these are
order one that's the desired properties
that we want for us to be able to say
that we are having we are we are
learning features basically we don't
want to be stuck where we were
initialized and we want to make sure
that things are not becoming too big or
too
These desired properties seem reasonable
to everyone, right? That's what this
paper argues that these properties are
reasonable and desired. And now the
question is well, how can we achieve
this? What kind of scaling is going to
get us there?
So first let's just ignore the bias and
the nonlinearity.
And if we ignore the bias and the
nonlinearity,
we can say that HL is given by WL * HL
minus one.
Right? This is just what is what the
weight matrix is doing.
Now we want to understand basically how
things are evolving. We want to proceed
in an inductive manner. So if our
assumptions are satisfied for HL minus
one, we want to be able to say that
okay, if HL minus one has the update of
the right size and if it has a magnitude
of the right size, if the RMS norms are
correct at level H L minus one, then
they're going to be correct at level L.
And to understand this, I'm going to
look at this particular equation, see
how they're evolving with WL.
So to understand this there's one
there's abs exactly one norm that's
going to help us here right basically
I'm scaling this vector by this matrix
and what is the norm that tells us how
much a vector is scaled by a matrix
it's the spectral norm in general we can
think about any induced norm right
depending on which norms you're using
but if we wanted to think about the two
norms in both cases then I can think
about the spectral norm of wl and the
two norm of hl minus one and thankfully
the RMS norm which is what we're
interested in is just a scaling on the
two norm right so this works out in our
interest
so in general when I look at how a
vector is scaled by a matrix well it
really depends on what direction that
vector is in right it depends on whether
this vector is aligned with the top
singular value or the middle singular
value or the small singular value or how
its components are distributed in all of
the singular value bases Right? So if I
want to get the maximum boost from a
particular matrix,
what direction do I want to be aligned
in?
>> The top singular vector. Right? And if I
want to have the minimum scaling, I want
to be aligned according to the smallest
singular vector. Okay?
So what this paper shows I'm not going
to go into the argument here but you can
show with not a particularly complicated
argument that
in general you will find that your
updates your your your hidden layers
will actually align with the larger
singular vector singular values of your
matrix. Okay. So if we assume this we
can write basically the following
equality which is that the two norm of
HL can be written as a product
approximately of the two norm of this
matrix WL and the two norm of this
matrix of this vector
HL minus one. Okay
just substituting in well I know that
this is approximately uh the two norm is
approximately order square root d out. I
know that the two norm here is
approximately square root D in because
we're assuming RMS norm one u for these
things and so if I want this to be RMS
norm one basically I want this to be
approximately square root D out that
gives me this condition on
the RMS to RMS in or the uh the spectral
norm of WL that it should be basically
square root D out by DN right just
division gives me that okay And this is
basically the same as saying that oh
this is the RMS tors induced norm is
basically order one right this is the
same thing and that's exactly what we
started with right we started with
saying that oh we want to have the RMS
to RMS induced norm of this uh weight
matrix to be uh order one
that's what we talked about when we
derived when we did that whole
derivation of mu last time so this is
justifying basically one other way of
thinking about where that uh condition
is coming from and why that's a
reasonable thing to think about why
that's a good thing to think about.
Okay, good. Then the other thing we want
to talk about or the other thing we want
to look at at in this desired properties
is we also said we care about the size
of the update. We don't
so you want to make sure that the
updates are not too small or too big.
Let's actually look at this here.
So here what I have
is again I have HL is equal to WL * HL
minus one. And therefore I can write the
update also as a linear function given
this. So I can write the update of HL is
the update in W * HL minus one plus W *
the update in HL minus one. Yeah,
everyone with me till there.
Now, I'll give you a minute to say,
okay, can you inductively argue what
other condition you might need to be
able to make sure that your
delta HL update is also RMS order one.
Okay, so remember what you have is that
you already have some condition on WL
which you've have here. You're
inductively assuming a condition here
and now you want to get
this desired property. Okay. So using
this, can you try to work this out for
on your own just for one minute? Try to
take a minute to to see what this might
be
and talk to each other.
Also a good way to check that you're
following along and that you're on
track. If you're confused about
something, ask me a question.
I'm trying to see
Okay, there's my timer. Does anybody
have any questions? I feel like people
are a little bit lost.
>> Yes.
>> So, I know you made the assumption that
But I'm a little confused why we're able
to make that equality for the norm if it
doesn't like where does that come from?
>> Okay, so where did this come from? It's
a great question. I'm not proving this
to you. This requires proof.
>> No, I just mean the equation like
if we assume
>> Yes.
>> Oh, why is this? This is just the
definition of the spectral norm. So
basically what is the spectral norm? The
spectral norm is the value the magnitude
of the largest singular value.
>> Right? And so if I have a vector that is
perfectly aligned to the top singular
vector,
what is it's it's going to be orthogonal
to all the other singular directions. So
the only singular value it's going to be
multiplied by is the largest singular
value.
So if hl minus one is only in the
direction of the largest singular
vector, it will have zero components
everywhere else. And so the only thing
it'll be scaled by is sigma one which is
the largest singular value.
>> Yes.
>> Here we're taking for granted that h is
will be aligned.
>> Yes, we're taking for granted. This
requires proof. They prove it. It's not
that hard to do but it's not worth all
of us spending u it would take a quite a
bit of the lecture and I'm not sure it's
worth going into uh the arguments.
Basically, it's a it's a concentration
argument.
Yes.
And that's
>> this equation.
>> Yeah.
>> This is just how you differentiate,
right? It's just the same uh it's the
same rule.
>> Yeah. So basically like when we are
training our network both W and HL are
changing
>> when you're training your network both
like yes your layers are changing and
your uh
>> uh and your features are changing
because they're getting updated right?
So whenever I want to see what is the
update here, I have to consider the
updates here and the updates here
>> because delta HL minus one comes from
the change in the weights from the
previous layer.
>> Yes.
>> Yeah.
Other questions?
Okay, good. So once you have this, what
can you say
here? I can just write this out again if
that will maybe be helpful.
So I have this, right?
Okay,
if I have this now and I want to look at
how
the norm of this evolves,
well, I want to basically look at it in
terms of
the norm of this, right? The two norm of
this. So, what are the properties of?
So, this is now a norm. So I want to
look at So is everyone does everyone
believe me here that
this I can write clearly the two things
are equal. I can just take norms on both
sides. Okay. Well, now I can apply a the
triangle inequality.
Okay.
And b I can then use basically the sub
additivity or the sub multiplicative
property of the spectral norm and spect
separate these out individually. So I'm
going to get
this to be
Okay. So here I'm applying triangle
inequality
plus basically
um
so I'm bounding this by sub
multiplicative all I mean is that this
norm I'm replacing with this.
Okay.
So here I want to ignore I want to I'm
I'm I'm going to handwave a little bit
to say that I want to say that these are
approximately going to be the same in
terms of order. Okay, these are not
going to be much bigger or much smaller.
I'm only making arguments at the order
level. And so here this inequality I'm
basically I want to ignore this. Yes,
the triangle inequality gives us an
inequality. Yes, we're making this
assumption that we're aligned in the
direction of the top singular vector to
be able to replace this with this.
And I want to hand like openly handwave
that away. I'm not doing that proof.
It's not worth to spend the time in
class to do that.
But what I want you to see is that this
is basically approximately what I get.
And now I can think about the size of
this update in terms of each of these
individual things.
>> Yes. Question.
>> Is it a given that the norm of delta
will be the same as?
>> It is not a given. That's exactly what I
want to derive.
That's exactly what I want to get to. So
maybe I should write this as here
question mark.
So if I want to be able to say that
this has a particular order, I want to
be able to give conditions. I want to I
want to say things about all of these.
And basically if I can assume certain
conditions then I can infer what the RMS
norm or the spectral norm of uh not the
spectral norm but the true norm of delta
HL will be.
Does that make sense?
Okay. I feel like you're still not with
me. So ask me questions. I don't quite
understand what the confusion is. So if
you ask me questions I can try to
resolve it.
>> Yes.
Okay, that's totally fair. Um, I'm
trying to make a rough argument for how
the orders of magnitudes of these things
are going to evolve. So, I want to say
look, I know that this vector delta HL
is the sum of these two vectors. And so
I'm going to say that approximately
I can replace them with these other two
this this sum the norm of these sums.
It's not the same. If you read the paper
there's a rigorous proof of both the
upper bound and the lower there's a
there's a proof of both the upper bound
and the lower bound. We're not going
into it. I'm
>> this is in the paper. Yes. But we're not
we're not we're not going into this.
Okay.
So I can inductively say if this is RMS
norm one then this is order square root
dn.
This is also order square root dn. this
I've derived a condition earlier and I
want this to be order square root d out
over dn. So that leaves this question
mark box over here for this to be RMS
norm one. I want the two norm of it to
be square root dout. So what should this
box be?
I basically want it to be the same as
this, right?
So that's where I get these two
conditions that I want the RMS norm to
be order one uh and the RMS norm of the
update also to be order one. So we
cannot assume this. What I'm trying to
get at is that these two conditions are
what we need to be able to guarantee
these two desired properties.
Everyone with me? This? Yes. Question.
>> Um order means that I'm looking at how
this is scaling with the width. So it's
scaling as for example um
it's the RMS norm is scaling with the
width is what this is saying basically
>> like
yes So that becomes square.
>> Yes.
>> Uh no it's it's scaling as square root d
out with the width.
>> Yes. I was connect.
>> Yes.
>> Yes. Question.
>> Yes, you also have to lower bound it.
And I'm not doing that.
>> Yes. Yes.
>> Yes.
We're saying we're all I'm okay I'm
making a huristic argument here. I'm not
proving anything. Okay, I'm making a
rough argument here. What I'm trying to
say is that if I want to make some
guarantees on how the update of the elf
layer behaves, I will have to make
assumptions or I will have to have
conditions on both how the weight matrix
itself behaves
as well as how the update to the weight
matrix behaves. Okay.
So I'm saying that
I've already kind of said that I want to
get I want this condition. I've already
claimed that I want this condition.
These two I'm assuming inductively
follow. And so I'm saying what condition
do I need here to be able to get that
this will be RMS norm one.
Does that make sense?
That's all I'm saying. And there is I'm
making a rough rough sketch for why this
is true. Why why something like this
could be true. This is not a rigorous
proof.
>> Yes.
Does that mean
nothing here is
>> I mean if you look at the RMS norm it is
order one if you're looking at the two
norm or the spectral norm it is not
order one
>> yes
>> um so uh is the norm of the
Hus.
We're assuming inductively, right? So,
we're saying that if inductively I have
both of these things to be true, then
can I conclude something for the next
layer?
Okay.
So what I want to just point out is that
is that gives us basically conditions
about the RMS norm of the uh
of the weight matrices both the weight
matrix itself as well as the update in
the weight matrix. Okay.
And these are conditions basically that
are that we've we've come to and seen
before. This is just yet another way of
looking at them and coming to them. Do
you want to add something?
>> RMS norm. I'm sorry, this is a typo.
Yes.
>> Thank you.
Thank you.
So from this now remember MUP was
talking about scaling of the learning
rates, right?
What I'm not going to go into here but
again you can look at this in in the
paper and we gave a sketch of this
essentially earlier is from this we can
derive how the uh learning rate should
scale as a factor a as a function of
these din and douts. And if you recall
last time we had this we came to kind of
uh this conclusion. This argument uh
will lead you to a very similar
conclusion. We're not doing it here. We
already did like kind of the the rough
argument earlier last time in lecture.
Okay.
What I wanted to just point out is these
this desired property of what this is
why this is a reasonable thing. what it
means to have feature learning uh is
defined by these two is is defined by
the size of the hidden layers being
something and the size of the update
being appropriately the same u RMS norm
one both of these things and to achieve
this we want to have conditions on the
weight matrix itself as well as the
update to the weight matrix okay
and then with this we can use this to
basically derive scaling laws because
for our hyperparameters that are
identical to what the mu scaling laws
are. Okay,
question at the back.
>> Yeah, I was just following correctly. So
when you write
>> dimension,
>> correct?
Yes.
>> Correct.
>> Yes.
>> Does this idea apply to other parameters
besides learning rate?
besides learning rate? Uh no. This is
focused largely on the on the learning
rate. And furthermore, this is focused
on uh layers that are basically defined
by a matrix multiplication. So there are
other considerations that sometimes have
to be made for other structures of
layers that we're not going to be really
talking about.
>> Yeah.
Sorry, I'm not sure I'm understanding
your question.
>> So like with these conditions we just
got that the change in the weights is
order. So like is like what specifically
the order number is that's like hyperar.
>> Yes. Yes. Yes. Yes.
Okay. Good. So now that we have this I
want to move to what I want to talk
about today
which is muon.
So, Muan is a
new optimizer
and the kind of claim to flame of muon.
Let me see actually maybe I should show
this slide just while I'm talking about
it again.
I think comes from when uh from this
experiment or called the nano GPT
speedrun right which is a a small
network and it's a kind of open
competition where people are challenged
to say how fast can you get this
particular network to have this
particular validation loss and it
started out at a baseline in 2024 of
about 45 minutes and as you can see over
time there's been significant updates to
get it to do better what that I want to
draw your attention to
is this point here which is where when
the muon optimizer was introduced
suddenly that led to kind of a paradigm
change in how people were were thinking
about things and led to massive massive
improvements in the time required to
train this particular network. Okay. So
that's kind of our motivation for trying
to bring muon into the curriculum to
make sure you guys are kind of up to
date with what is happening uh in the
field. And the other thing is that this
was a nano GPT right this is a tiny
model but follow-up work has shown that
actually the ideas from muan can be
scaled up to be able to be used in much
much larger uh models. in particular is
Kimmy model is a tr trillion parameter
model which use muon and there's
evidence that um you know uh at least
the muup style ideas have made it they
made their way into training for uh
other standard other big frontier models
as well okay so let's now talk about
muon
so remember from last time we had this
optimizer recipe which is that okay I
want to choose a norm and within that
norm ball I want to basically be aligned
to the direction of the gradient. So I
want to find the best
uh step that I can take.
And we talked when we talked about
shampoo, we talked about saying well
what if we chose the spectral norm here
and we did this calculation I think two
lectures ago where we found that the
argument for this was ADA time um
u vranspose right here. Actually I
should write here maybe UR
VR transpose.
So what is this doing? This is basically
a
semi orthogonal update. What I mean by a
semi-orththogonal update is basically
this UR VR is something that you know if
if I take a matrix A and A a transposes
identity or A transpose A's identity at
least one of the ways that's what's
called a semi-orththogonal
semi-orththogonal matrix an orthogonal
matrix is one that has both of those
being true right it's only true on one
side it's called a semi-orththogonal
matrix
so what this gives us as the update
equation is the following which is that
WT +1 is wt minus ADA time this update
and this is the key update behind the
shampoo uh shampoo algorithm without
accumulation and what I mean by without
accumulation is that basically I'm not
doing a momentum like aggregation or
averaging of the gradients
um I'm ignoring that even though shampoo
in in reality will actually do an
aggregation and a uh and a a moment a
momentum averaging there. Okay, so we're
we're ignoring that. But if you turn
that accumulation off, this is exactly
the update that you get.
So if you look at the shampoo algorithm,
right? If you go open the shampoo paper,
this is not what it looks like. The
shampoo paper looks quite a bit more
complicated.
Even here, what I have is a slightly
simplified version, but it looks more
like this. So, I have what is called a
left preconditioner and a right
preconditioner, which I had said, by the
way, I'd gave you the reason for why
shampoo is called shampoo. It's because
you use conditioners.
Um,
and you have left ones and you have
right ones. So LT is the left
preconditioning matrix which is
basically an averaging of G gRpose where
G is your gradient
and the right preconditioning matrix
comes from G-rpose G
and these are basically one way to think
about it very very roughly um is to
think of you're basically
rotating your matrix to be
in a particular
space though that intuition is not as
clean. I think the cleanest, nicest way
of thinking about it is really this um
kind of Frank Wolf style perspective
that we've um that we've talked about
here.
Okay, so this is what the shampoo update
actually like.
Um
and if you take shampoo without
accumulation so basically I don't do
this averaging and so I just set my left
preconditioner to be ggrpose and my
right preconditioner to be ganspose g
then what I get as my uh
update equation is given by this
equation
okay
so I have these inverse fourth roots
Why is shampoo why was shampoo why did
shampoo come up with this? Right. Well,
there was this intuition from that we
know from uh Adagrad and from all
everything we've been talking about on
on gradient descent that you want to
sometimes it's there's value in
equalizing which directions you're
you're going you're you're going in.
And so there was this was an attempt at
trying to get more, you know, uniform in
all of the directions that you're going
in. But as you know, computing the SVD
is hard. And that's where these fourth
roots kind of come in.
So it turns out that these inverse
fourth roots you can compute
somewhat efficiently. Champoo is still
an expensive algorithm compared to
something like Adam, but you can compute
them more efficiently than by doing the
SVD through a variation on basically the
Newton root finding algorithm. Okay, so
there's a Newton iterative Newton style
iterative algorithm that you can use to
compute these fourth roots which is why
kind of shampoo
ended up in being being what is it what
it is with these particular fourth
roots. Um this understanding of shampoo
without accumulation as being this uh UV
transpose came later kind of after
shampoo had been developed. Yes.
Question at the back.
>> So I've turned the question was where
did these LTUS1 and RTUS1 terms go? I've
turned out turned off accumulation.
So I'm just instead of averaging over
time I'm just using the current update
the current uh gradient as the to to to
understand my preconditioner. Yes.
for SVD. No, but we will do a little bit
of a calculation that will I think
resolve your confusion in one minute.
>> Yes.
>> What is the initial condition of LT and
RT? Um I think they're just initialized
at zero.
>> But we're I I don't like we're not going
to go into all of the intricacies of
shampoo right now. the real shampoo
deals with momentum and many of the
theoretical analysis are very hard to do
when you have that momentum style term
in there. So right now we're thinking of
no accumulation, right? So we're just
trying to understand what the uh just
with the current gradient update.
>> Yes, question.
>> Um because you can do them you can
compute them in an iterative style of
root finding. So like there's a there's
a variant of Newton's algorithm that can
be used to uh to compute these
efficiently.
Okay.
So to see what the connection of this
fourth root is and why it's connected to
the SCD, I want I just wanted to show
you this little calculation.
So if I think about my GT as having uh
the SVD
u sigma vranspose okay
then I can think of gtranspose
here
as u sigma banspose v sigma transpose
urpose my vransposes cancel and what I
get is just this u sigma sigma transpose
urpose everyone see
And then similarly I can compute the the
other side of that
in the exact same way. Right? This is
one the left preconditioner and the
right preconditioner. Okay. So what is
happening here when I take these uh
fourth roots
well let's just consider one case and
you can work this out case by case but
we don't really know what the shape of
GT is. Let's say it was a a matrix like
this. It's a wide matrix.
And so that means that my sigma is also
going to be a wide matrix. And the way
it's going to look is I'm going to have
a part here that has singular values
along the diagonal. And then there's
going to be a bunch of zeros over here.
Right? That's what my uh SVD is going to
look like or that's my what my singular
value matrix is going to look like. And
let's just say for now I assume that
this is full row rank. So there's no
zeros here at all. It's possible that
you could actually have a subp part here
depending on the rank of your matrix.
But let's just assume for now that this
is full row rank.
Then what I'm going to do is I'm I want
to basically say well how do I compute
the fourth roots of these guys? Right?
That's like a complicated thing in when
you're implementing shampoo. You would
not do something like this. You would
not compute the SVD. You could and that
would still that would be a valid way of
computing this but that's not how
shampoo does it
but now when I think about this sigma
sigma transpose this basically just
gives me a square matrix with singular
value squares along the diagonal right
because I have these these zeros
basically hit each other and so I have
this now square matrix with singular
values along the diagonal over here.
Okay. And now I can take fourth roots
basically
by taking the fourth the inverse fourth
root of this. Well I have a sigma 1
squared here. Sigma 2 * -1 over4 gives
me -1 /2.
So I have the fourth root of g gt
gtrpose is given by u. Then a square
matrix with sigma i to the minus1 /2 on
that diagonal. and then uranspose.
Similarly, when I do um I can look at
the right preconditioner and then I have
gt trpose gt again if I take this uh
inverse fourth root the inverse fourth
root of sigma n^ squ is just sigma 1 to
the uh is just one over sigma square
root sigma 1. So I have this here and
now this is a bigger matrix right. So
here I will have some zeros.
But now when I look at basically this
particular quantity this gt gtranspose
minus to the minus 1/4 this whole thing
I get that all of my u's and v's cancel
and I just basically get out that I have
the uvranspose that I started with right
or that I wanted to get and that I got
in some sense very naturally
from looking at this uh optimization
ccentric perspective.
Okay.
So, if you look at the shampoo paper, I
just wanted to put this out there
because, you know, we've talked about
shampoo. You might go and look at the
paper and like this is nothing like what
we talked about in lecture. It's totally
different. But it's actually the same
thing. Again, uh the SVD kind of shows
you uh how these two things are
connected.
Okay.
So, this is great. And so, any questions
about this?
>> Yes. using this
>> is I didn't hear the question
>> is it because
>> the the fourth roots are the exactly the
fourth roots are more take are more
computationally efficient to do than
computing a full SVD and that is why uh
this this is done but it's still not
super efficient and so that's what muon
solves that problem by coming up with an
even more efficient method.
Okay. Yes.
>> Why exactly are we going forus rather
than
>> the question is why are we going for
minus one over four rather than four? Um
that's a I mean you can come up with any
optimizer you want that does anything
you want but here what you're trying to
do is you're trying to cancel out the
effect of the singular values right. So
there's going to be singular values in
your gradient and if you want to
minimize their impact then you want to
divide by those singular values.
One thing to note actually this is
interesting that there's some papers
that are reported that in practice
people like to implement shampoo with a
minus one/2 here instead of a minus 1/4
and if you do this calculation that
doesn't get to this semi-orththogonal
update right these things will not
cancel out but some some papers report
that minus one over2 performs better in
practice than minus one over4
>> yes question.
>> Yes.
>> Um, we can talk about it in office
hours.
>> Yes.
>> Oh, what can I explain what accumulation
means again?
Accumulation is this idea of like
momentum is accumulation. So, so what
what is momentum doing? Momentum is
saying let me take the average of the
gradients to get kind of a smoother
version of the gradient. Right? If you
remember we looked at those plots where
like the momentum trajectories look
smooth just the stoastic gradient
descent sometimes looks kind of jagged.
So accumulation is saying here in this
case I'm averaging whatever this gt
gtrpose quantity is over time. That's
what this is doing here.
So this is this this is accumulation.
>> Oh.
>> So the accum there's this this the LT is
the left preconditioner. RT is the right
preconditioner and I'm doing
accumulation to compute the left
preconditioner and the right
preconditioner.
Does that make sense?
>> Okay.
We're good.
>> Yes.
>> The minus 104 I mean it happens to but
what I mean by a semi orthogonal matrix
is this.
So this UVRpose is a semi-orththogonal
matrix.
>> Yes.
without accumulation.
So why do you need?
>> The question is why do you need left and
right? Um
this is again uh I believe for
computational efficiency you can there's
many different so this quantity there's
many different ways to write this
um and
we are picking one way and shampoo
picked one way which was good good for
implementation.
Um but if you dig into the literature
here there's many many many variations
and people have explored different
variations to see which is the kind of
best one for implementation. Shampoo was
the first first one and it had some u
success which is why we're talking about
shampoo but there are variations on
shampoo that compute similar things in
slightly different ways.
>> Yes.
>> And so we say conditioners we're talking
about the L&R. L and R are what are
called the preconditioners. Yes.
>> Yes.
Okay. Good.
Okay. So we have these semi-orththogonal
updates and semi-orththogonal updates in
a sense are doing something that is
similar to what we had talked about back
when we were talking about Adam right we
were saying that we want to be you know
not too motiv not not too moved by
particular singular values and so here
the semi-orththogonal update is kind of
like the sign of the
uh sign of the matrix right it's just
saying what are the dominant directions
without particularly scaling them and so
unv
u or uvranspose is capturing those
important directions of the matrix
without the singular values that are
associated with them. It's right saying
that all the singular values have now
been set to one. Right? So that's why
this is um this is in that in that same
spirit. It's it's it's coming all coming
from this the fact that the singular
values change how much you move in every
direction. Okay,
so now
let's come back to the RMS to RMS norm.
We talked about this uh last time a
little bit, but instead of looking at
the two norm here, right? If instead I
looked at the RMS to RMS norm update,
well,
the calculation will be exactly the same
except I'm going to get this scaling
factor here, right? If I look at the RMS
to RMS induced norm instead of the true
norm because these are just related by
this constant scaling. And so if I do
the same optimization that I did for
shampoo, what I'm going to get is I'm
going to get this scaling factor out
here. Okay, everyone with me?
And this is basically the essence of
muon that you're getting at. Okay.
Instead of that spectral norm, we're
looking at the uh RMS norm.
This is idea one that I want to
communicate. This is key idea one of of
muan.
It's the same idea as shampoo
except they didn't come at it happens to
be the same idea as shampoo.
Um, but what they're saying now here is
you want this scaling factor here as
well to make sure that your updates are
of the same order and you're not uh that
you're that when you're moving through
your network things are not blowing up
or getting too small and that's where
this factor comes in.
Okay. So it's focusing on this RMS norm
perspective is key idea one that we want
to have. Uh
okay.
Okay. So now what's muon key idea 2?
Key idea too comes from the fact that
well you know we've talked about UVRpose
and we keep coming back to the same
problem computing UVRpose is expensive
right because basically what we're
trying to do is we're trying to say well
well I have some matrix which is U sigma
vranspose and I want to just remove this
and I want to replace it with ones right
but to do that I need to compute what
that sigma is and that requires an SVD
computation which is expensive I don't
want to be doing an SVD all the time
so what can I do to
get around this and that is the other
key innovation in muon. Okay.
And how muon does this is it does it
through two observations. Observation
one is that
semi-orththogonal updates are great but
if you're like almost semi-orththogonal
and you're just a little bit off
that still does pretty well.
And the second idea is through this uh
iterative update called Newton Schulz
iterations that I'm going to now talk
about.
Okay, this Newton shells iteration is a
way of going from
U sigma vranspose to UVRpose in a
computationally efficient way.
So let's now talk about this. Okay.
Actually, does anyone have any ideas on
how they might want to do this? What
might be a strategy? Do you want a
minute to just think before I tell you
the answer? Take a minute.
Okay, that's one minute. Anyone have any
ideas they want to share
or anything worth?
>> Okay. Well, okay. Let's just do it
together. This is hard.
But the the key observation is the idea
that
wouldn't it be great if I had some
function
if I had f of u
uh that looks like a v
u sigma vranspose and I could take this
function and outward pop uvranspose.
That would be great if I could find such
a function, right?
Okay. Well, in absence of finding such a
function, maybe I'd be happy with
something that's kind of approximately
equal, right?
Or maybe I'd be happy with something
that I could have it's not exactly equal
to uvranspose, but if I keep iterating,
it will eventually converge to UVRpose,
right? So can I can I do something that
will that can I find something that that
I can eventually get there? And so the
key observation in getting to this is
this idea that odd polomials commute
with the SVD. So what do I mean by an
odd polomial? I mean polomials that have
only odd uh exponents. So you know x x
cubed x 5th x7th so on and so forth. So
for example if I wanted to think about
an odd matrix polomial I would think of
something like this a kn * x1 plus a1 *
xxrpose x plus a2 * xxrpose 2 x so on
and so forth. This is making sure that I
only have odd degrees in my um
exponents.
Okay? because here like this is one,
this is three, this is five, so on and
so forth.
Okay, this is 2 n plus one. Good. So
what's one example of this? Well, let's
look at this particular example because
we're going to use it later.
Okay, so I have p of x is 3 over2x - 12
xrpose x. And now what I can do is I can
just substitute the svd in here. And as
always when you have these xxrposes all
of the u's and v's like nicely cancel
out
and what I get here is now u * the same
polomial of sigma time vranspose
right and so
p of x is like you know it's it's like
the polomial is only operating on the
singular values
okay and this is true for all polomials.
So wouldn't it be great if I could find
some polomial that kind of over time if
I could keep applying that polomial
and it would over time converge to one.
So for example if I have some
uh p of x it's like u p of sigma
vranspose then I apply p of p of x and
it'll be u p of p of
sigma vranspose so on and so forth right
because this commutes with the svd this
is what's happening so can I find a
polomial that has these nice properties.
Well, finding this everywhere is going
to be hard. But it turns out that this
polomial that we talked about over there
uh up up over here is exactly the is
does exactly that, right? And because
now that we've observed that
this polomial p of x essentially works
directly on the singular values, it's
enough for me to I don't need to think
about a matrix valued polinomial
anymore. I can just think about how the
singular values themselves evolve when
the when I take when I when the polomial
acts on them essentially or when the
function acts on them, right? Because
now I have whatever it is I have sigma 1
sigma 2 sigma 3. I take the pol. just
taking the polomial of sigma 1, sigma 2,
sigma n, whatever it is. Okay.
So if I plot this function here now I've
plotted this here.
What do I have? Well,
what I have drawn here is this is the x=
to y line
and this is this cubic polomial.
Okay, it looks like a cubic. It has the
characteristic up down shape.
So what happens here now? Let's say I
start somewhere. Let me pick yellow is
actually a good color. So let's say I'm
somewhere here.
I start here. What happens to my
function value
at point 2? My function my polomial
value is this point. Okay. So now what
happens when I take this is the let's
call this 0.1 point 2.3.
Okay. I started at 0 2. I ended up at 3.
Now, what happens when I take P of 3.
Where am I going to end up? Well, I can
do what is called a cobweb diagram. And
so, I go here. So, this is now 3. I'm
looking at 3 here. And what is the
function value here? Right now, this is
like 045.
Does everyone see how I'm like,
well, now if I wanted to see what was
the value at 045, well, I just go to the
x equal to y line. And now this is my
function value at 045.
Now I apply P again, I'm going to end up
here.
I apply P again, I'm going to end up
here. I apply P again, I'm going to end
up here.
Converge to exactly
one.
actually here.
Okay. So if I repeatedly apply
my polomial to any value between zero
and one, I'm converging to one. Does
everyone see that? Just visually looking
at this.
What if I started here?
Where would I converge to the same exact
argument?
I'm going to converge here to negative
one. Right? Does this matter for us?
Does this part of the curve matter for
us
when we're thinking about singular
values? No. Our singular values are
always positive, right? So what we care
about really is what happens basically
in the positive part. Okay.
What happens if we start out somewhere
over here? Maybe here.
Let's say my initial my value was over
here.
Then what happens is I get bumped to
this line here and then I go up and then
I kind of convergent. So basically
there's a regime in which I get bumped
back in. You know even though I'm not
between 0 to one I'm being pulled back
in. So if I started say here somewhere
at even if I started at 1.5
go here
and I kind of converge in the same exact
pathway.
Everyone with me here that like it seems
that for a lot of places whatever my
singular value is I keep iterating the
polomial and I'm going nicely to one or
minus one but I'm not too worried about
I'm I'm never going to be starting on
the negative side right because my
singular values are always positive
question
>> what does applying over and over again
>> I couldn't hear your question
>> what does like applying the polomial
over and over again
>> what does the applying the polomial over
and over again mean in this setting. So
I have let's say I start at some P of
sigma
then I take P of P of sigma then I take
P of P of P of sigma then I take P of P
of P of sigma and so as this converges
as my so if I use the notation P N of
sigma meaning that I've applied the
polomial n times
>> yes question
coming there. Yeah.
>> Um so this means as n goes to infinity
then I'm going to get to one for some
cases of sigma. Right? So now the
question was well what happens if we
start at two. So now this is just a
zoomed out version of the same polomial.
this side zoomed in. But if I now zoom
out, well, clearly some places this
polomial is running away from me, right?
So if I had to start out somewhere here,
for example,
if I start at two, well, my function
value is here. Now I bump to the x equal
to y line. Maybe two is actually let me
start even further out. Let's start at
three
or maybe just slightly past two to make
this easier for me to draw.
Then I'm going to bump here.
And I'm going to bump here.
Um, then I'm going to bump here.
then I'm going to bump here, here, here.
So I might still converge in this
particular case, but if I start for
example at four,
I'm going to go down. I'm going to go
out. I'm going to go out. I'm going to
out. This picture isn't showing it, but
I will eventually there like there's a
limit far enough where I will actually
diverge and and and flow out. Okay. So,
I'm going to show you this in another
way.
Um, let's see.
So, okay. Here I have this. And let me
actually
I thought I'd save this, but okay. I
don't have it saved anyway. That's fine.
I'm going to define maybe it's easier
for me to type.
I have f of
f of x
=
3 / 2
x
-
1 divided by 2
x cubed. Okay. So this is my the same
thing that we plotted. Yes. Everyone
with me here? Okay. So now what happens
when I take f of
f of
x? Uh
okay
so my this is this is what happens when
this is now the polomial applied twice
everyone see that okay now let me take f
of f
of f of x
okay you're kind of
getting uh closer and closer to being
flat at one right you basically are
trying to in some sense approximate the
sign function.
How many times should I go f of f of f f
of f f of f f of f f f f f f f f f f f f
f f f f f f f f of f f f f f f f f f f f
f f f f f f f f f f f
off these other ones
is now really like it's basically
becoming like the sign function, right?
And so everything here is being mapped
up here
and everything here is being mapped down
here. And now there's a there's a regime
in which like if you're around two,
you're going to go to minus one, which
is you're converging to the wrong spot.
This is bad. And then there's a regime
here after which you're just blowing up
completely even if you're iteratively
applying it. But if you're within these
bounds
and turns out that this is minus
roo3 to plus roo3, you're
always converging to exactly one when
you start with a positive value. Okay,
great. Everyone sold on this?
Okay.
So what this means
is that by repeatedly applying this
polomial to our matrix what we can do is
we can approximate UV transpose because
it's as though the singular values are
just all becoming one.
Everyone see that?
So now we need to of course to have this
work we need to make sure that you
initially start out in the right place
right if you start out if your singular
values are really large that's not going
to work you're going to blow up. So the
trick that is applied in muon to make
sure that everything is actually
initialized properly is that you take
your gradient and you normalize it by
your frobinius norm.
Okay remember the frobinius norm is
always bigger than your uh spectral
norm. So it's always going to be larger
than your largest singular value. So
it's making sure that all of your
singular values are always smaller than
one.
Okay.
And this gives us basically what is muon
which is momentum orthogonalized by
Newton Schultz. That's where the mu
o n comes from.
And what you have is you have basically
a momentum style uh accumulation of the
gradient. So I do exactly this momentum
like uh
calculation
and then I take it and I compute the
orth semi-orgthogonalization of it by
using Newton Schultz. So I iterate
Newton Schultz. Typically there's a
parameter in uh I think five is what is
used in the first implementation of muon
and there's been going much beyond five
doesn't seem to help for the particular
polomials they have chosen um
and then what you get oops this is a
typo here this should be
uh
and then what you get is
that is the update you apply
Okay,
everyone with me, this is muan. Okay. So
now of course there's a lot of questions
about how do you choose this PFX and the
other key idea that the authors of Muan
or the inventors of Muan brought about
is that you can actually you know I did
this for one particular PFX but you can
choose a polomial that gives you
particular performance characteristics.
Maybe you compare about compare care
more about one thing or another. So for
example one observation is that if you
have a higher order polomial it might
converge faster but that means that you
have to do more matrix multiplications
to compute that polomial right so
there's a trade-off like faster
convergence versus more computation
depending on which you care about you
can choose different things and there's
been multiple explorations that people
have done to kind of figure out what the
appropriate or or that people are doing
it's not even have done people are
currently exploring how to figure out
what the right polomial is and in
particular in the uh nano GPT speedrun
the record that muan initially set this
is the polomial that they used okay so
it's a quintic polomial
and you might notice something
interesting about this so here I plotted
basically uh this red line is what that
uh quintic polomial looks like and this
is the quintic polomial applied to
itself I don't know five or eight times
I forget exactly how many I did.
But this is not converging, right?
This does not look like a nice straight
line. It's looking like it's kind of
jagged all over.
But turns out that okay, so if you apply
this, this polomial is not really
converging to one. So all it's doing is
it's doing an approximate
semi-orgthogonalization.
If it turns out that this is the right
this works really well even though
you're not exactly setting all the
singular values to one. They're kind of
in the neighborhood of one.
The reason that they chose this that was
that they found that this converged
faster. And one of the key things that
they observed was uh for faster
convergence was basically you want this
first coefficient the coefficient of x
to be as large as possible because that
is what sets the slope at zero to be
large. And the most important thing what
they found was that it's really
important to get these small singular
values to scale up fast because those
are what are bottlenecking performance
was just the empirical observation and
so this empirically was found to do
well. If you observe if you just compute
f of one here
which is just the sum of the
coefficients this is not equal to one.
So that means that this is not going to
converge to one right there's no way for
it because f of one is not one.
So what they did was they sacrificed
convergence for speed and it still
works. Okay. So you don't necessarily
have to have the uh theoretically
guaranteed. You know this theoretical
guarantee is great to start thinking
about things but this was not what was
actually used in the in the
implementation. Since then there have
been better polomials that have that
have been developed. This is not the
best one out there. Uh some of which
actually do have convergence guarantees.
Okay, question at the back.
>> Yes.
>> Otherwise,
>> well, the thing is that we can we can
satisfy them for free by doing this
normalization because this normalization
will automatically map all of the
singular rel to be smaller than one and
by div I'm not actually changing the
semi-arthogonalization because this is
just a scaling
So it won't actually matter. So I'll
answer the question just could be one
thing. So this is basically the last
lecture that we're doing in this series
of optimizers for deep learning. Um what
we've tried to do is give you a sense
and a flavor of how these new optimizers
that are going beyond Adam and ADUW are
really working so that you can basically
be upto-date and current with the field.
This is all active research. You know,
one of the things for example that is
really important about muon is that the
batch size of muon really matters and
bigger batch sizes are better for muan
empirically observed. There's no proofs
of any of these things because basically
it leads to more stable gradients. Uh so
that's one observation for muan. There's
other papers out there that are showing
that in certain regimes certain other
variations on muon. Uh so there's like
scion and prawn and I don't know there's
there's there's many many other
variations that uh outperform in certain
regimes versus others. There's critiques
of those papers that say that well
actually the batch sizes were not
optimized or the hyperparameters were
not optimized the right way. So it's
important to note that identifying the
best optimizer is a pretty tricky thing
because it all depends on the tuning of
the hyperparameters, right? And so
saying that this optimizer is better
than that requires you to do a full
hyperparameter sweep sweep for this
optimizer, full hyperparameter sweep for
that optimizer and identify the best
hyperpar parameters for each. There was
like kind of this kind understanding
that said that oh just use the
hyperparameters for one optimizer for
the other optimizer. They're probably
all the same. That's not that's not
true. You have to optimize them
individually. So
there's a ton of work out there. This is
a very active research area. We will
probably be having some projects that
you can do to build on this. Um, but
because this is so current, uh, we're we
we will have these projects. That's also
the reason that we have these, uh,
extra, uh, what are we calling them?
Participation credit, uh, opportunities
that require you to kind of go in and
and play with some of these optimizers.
Okay, I know there's a bunch of
questions, so I'll hang out here and we
can walk to office hours, but we're at
time. Thank you very much.
Yes, I will post.