recovering material more or less in a
style similar to what's going on in
prints. And uh another reminder for
people is that we have TA office hours
today. Uh so the TAs told us that uh
last week the attendance at the office
hours was extremely sparse to the point
of some of them having zero. So if we're
not going to you know if people want TA
office hours, you know, you should go to
TA office hours. If we think see things
being attended at level zero, then we'll
like divert those resources elsewhere.
Um, so we we've heard people's requests
of uh possibly trying to have uh an
office hour on Friday. We're looking
into it. We're seeing if we can possibly
do it, but you should come to office
hours today if you have uh questions.
Remember the solutions are in scope from
last week. The homework that is
currently happening this week is in
scope. So you know take advantage of it
to understand.
Also want to remind people about
discussion. Discussion tomorrow will go
through and work you through lots of the
basics of uh CNN's. It's good to
solidify your information. There's also
be also going to be a component that'll
be a notebook. So bring your computers.
Uh that should hopefully also make
things a lot lot clearer for you. Okay.
So that's it for announcements. I'm
going to start uh into the material. So
we talked about CNN's, we talked about
how they apply to vision problems, we
applied how we talked about how we have
certain key ideas we want to build. So
what I want to do now is to talk a
little bit more about conlares in light
of some of the questions that we were
getting. So uh recall the basic picture
of what's happening in a con. You saw
that before. We think about the input.
This is a 1D case. you have a sliding
window across the inputs and very
important in convolutions is that the
topology of the input matters. The fact
that you have an image or a line
matters. You have local neighborhoods.
The local neighborhoods for example are
three things. So that's this guy and
immediate neighbor on one side and
immediate neighbor on the other. And
each of them gets multiplied by a
particular weight added up a bias is
added and that generates the output. So
that's we talked about this before
things again recap of before in 2D the
neighborhoods just become a 2D
neighborhoods. So if you ever have any
confusion in uh continents about what's
going on I strongly recommend always go
back to the 1D case because you can draw
the 1D case a lot more easily and then
think about the 2D case because
everything typically just the 1D case
directly extends the 2D case.
Uh so this is the case where you just
have a single channel at the input, a
single channel at the output. And last
time we showed this picture which was
about if you have many channels at the
input,
what happens in a con? So you basically
have weights in your convolutional
filter. Um which again want to make a
note here. uh they're sometimes called
kernels in the context of the
convolutional neural net literature. I
know this can be confusing to many
students because this meaning of kernel
is different from the meaning of kernel
that you learned in your uh machine
learning class where you might have
learned about kernel style methods for
example doing SVMs and other uh
classifiers. This is different but it's
also the same word kernel. Uh
so in that case the kernel is defined by
uh in this case a 3x3 tensor of weights
where these weights over here correspond
to the blue channel. These weights
correspond to the green channel and
these weights correspond to the red
channel and you simply apply the same
thing you apply in sort of the
one-dimensional case and you add
everything up to get a single output.
And last time there was a question about
what happens if there's many outputs. So
I decided that it's maybe it's really
good for everyone to really understand
this. So I'm going to spend a little bit
more time on this topic. Okay. So let's
let's do this together.
So what are we going to do? We're going
to say
let's look at the most basic case first
which is there's a one by one conf.
There's one channel at the input and one
channel at the output. So what does that
mean? That means for every pixel one by
one means you just look at it itself
neighborhood the one by one neighborhood
centered on that pixel which is just
itself
for every pixel a convolutional filter
is a linear fine if you have the bias
operation. So what can you do to a
single input you can scale it by a
constant and add a bias
and both the constant you scale by and
the bias are learnable weights.
So let's start with the
simple case here.
How many weights are there and how many
biases? Okay, one and one. Right,
everyone should be with me here. Now
let's do the 3x3 case. 3x3 case with one
channel input and one channel output. So
again, what does it mean 3x3? 3x3 means
look at the 3x3 neighborhood centered on
this pixel. So 3x3
neighborhood centered on the pixel. You
can think of it this way. The weight
associated with me, the weight
associated my north neighbor, the weight
associated with my south neighbor, my
east neighbor, my west neighbor, my
northwest neighbor, and so on. Okay,
that's if you want to think of it as
what these weights are. This kind of
local perspective helps many people as
opposed to simply having the numbers
because it tells you that it's always
ref centered somewhere
and it's local around there.
So what do you do? You scale the values
at this pixel
and its immediate neighbors by
individual widths. Meaning every single
neighborhood gets its own individualized
width. The northwest neighbor is
different than the northeast neighbor is
different than the south neighbor. and
you can tell them apart because you also
you know how to look in different
directions.
You add them up and add a bias. Okay. So
now everyone take five seconds or 10
seconds to think how many weights are
there and how many biases are there in
this case. Okay. So let's count.
Okay. So
anyone raise your hand or shout out how
many weights?
>> Nine.
>> Nine. Okay. How many biases?
>> One.
>> One. Okay. Very good. So the basic story
should be clear. So now let's change it
to the picture we had before.
We have a 3x3 con with C in channels
as the input and one output.
So what does this mean?
This means that we repeat the process we
did here for each channel. So each
channel has its own mi weight, northwest
weight, northwe and so on. And then you
add them up. You fold all those things
together by adding them up. And then you
add a bias.
Okay. So now
everyone take 30 seconds to tell me to
sit maybe talk to your neighbor, make
sure you understand it. How many weights
and how many biases are there?
>> Okay, so just watch the time.
Okay, 30 seconds are done.
>> Okay, so now
anyone want to tell me how many weights
are there? First, I'll ask a question.
Does anyone How many people have the
answer? Raise your hand if you have the
answer. Okay. How many people are
uncertain what the answer is? A couple
of people are uncertain. U anyone who's
uncertain feel brave enough to express
their uncertainty.
>> 27.
>> Okay. So, uh here's the thing, right? In
this particular case, I've changed one
of the things into a symbolic thing CN
because in the in the context of a
connet, as you you might start off with
a color image that has three channels,
but as you go deeper and deeper into the
network, you'll change as part of your
design how many channels there are. Like
I said before, you know, you think about
intuitively you have a hand detector, a
foot detector, a parrot detector, you
know, and this is going to change at
different levels. So, we have to think
about it in terms of CN. The answer
should involve CN. Okay. So now someone
raise your hand to tell me the answer
who feels confident the answer. Yeah.
>> 9 * CN weights.
>> Okay. Great.
Nine CN weights. And how many biases?
>> One.
>> One. Excellent. So this nine
is the same as that nine.
Right. This is the idea that you repeat
for every input channel.
Okay. So now let's generalize it one
step further.
We were talking about 3x3 before. Let's
think about K by K. Yeah.
>> Should be CN.
>> Okay, that's an excellent question. Let
me uh repeat it for the recording and
then uh make sure that I answer it. So
the question was why isn't the number of
biases C in as opposed to one? Okay, so
the reason the number of biases we think
of as being one is that suppose we had C
in individual biases, we're going to add
everything up together anyway to get a
single output. So when you add a bunch
of scalers together, you'll just get
another scaler. So in terms of
expressive power, we get the same
expressive power by having one bias as
we would by having C in different
biases. That's the side of expressive
power. The second part of it you could
think about in terms of
what happens with the gradients that are
back propped backwards in the neural
net. So when the gradients go back, are
the gradients going to be different on
the different biases that you're hypo
hypo hypothesizing? And the answer is
no, they won't because they're just
being added in. Right? So that if you if
the forward layer, the layer at the
other side says I would like this input
to be a little bigger
on all those biases will say make them
all a little bit bigger by the same
amount. the weights have different
gradients because they are also
modulated by the specific inputs at that
channel. So that's for both of these
reasons we go for a single bias as
opposed to having uh CN biases. Yeah,
>> if you have multiple outputs,
>> I will I will come to the multiple
outputs uh in in a moment. But yes,
we'll talk about the multiple outputs
case.
But before we go to multiple outputs, I
just want to make sure that everyone
says now I've talked about a 3x3 con
here where you had this number nine.
So now let's think about a k by k con a
5 by five a seven by seven a 9 by 9 any
such number. So, how many weights are
there now? Here I think does everyone
can everyone just answer the question
right now? Do you have the idea? I don't
want to go too slowly, but uh if you
need time to think, tell me if you need
time to think. Okay, so what's the
answer? Just shout it out everybody.
>> Okay, excellent. K2 CN,
how many biases?
>> One.
>> One. Great. So now you understand the
general pattern. Now if you think about
the weights here and on discussion we'll
have you talk about it a number like k^
squ cn also s s s s s s s s s s s s s s
s s s s s s s s s s s s s s s s s s s s
s s s s s suggest and the pictures we
had before that you can store these
different weights in an interesting
structure, right? So this structure is
naturally a CN by K by K tensor, right?
K by K for the filter to apply at a
particular channel and another K another
another another CN sorry for how many of
them there are okay
so now
let's have the case of multiple outputs
so we talked about this before so I just
copied it over exactly from what I wrote
before if you have a one by one con with
C in channel inputs and C outputs what
does that look like so we talked about
this before and we said that now that
you have all of these different outputs,
we can take all of these outputs and in
this picture stack them up as a vector.
We can take the vector all the CN inputs
and stack them up as a vector. So at
every pixel now the information that's
carried is a vector of size CN and at
the output at every pixel you're going
to have a vector that's y and it's going
to be of size c out.
So a linear operation an aphine
operation that acts on a vector and
returns a vector looks like this.
So now we can ask the question how many
weights and how many biases
>> is it? So first how many people know the
answer?
How many people are unsure?
Okay. Um some of you are not answering
the question of whether you know the
answer or unsure. Uh so let's uh
everyone take uh 20 seconds and talk
amongst yourselves to make sure you can
answer this question or at least express
your confusion to your neighbor. It's
important everyone gets this. So that's
why I'm doing this. So start.
>> Okay. So again, interest of time, I'm
going to keep uh
So who can answer the question? How many
weights are there? The weights are the
entries inside this matrix. The biases
are the entries inside this matrix. So
how many weights are there?
>> C in time C out.
And how many biases?
>> C out.
Okay. So everyone hopefully this is
making it clear what's going on here for
the one by one case. So now
let's everyone take a minute and do this
case a K by K con with C in channel
inputs and C outputs.
Just putting the pieces together of all
the pieces we've built.
So start talk to each other. Make sure
you can
If you feel like you're done at some
point, you can like raise your hand and
say that. Okay, we can move on. But it's
fine if people I'll give everyone a
minute.
Okay, that's a minute. So, uh, someone
want to raise your hand to give the
answer
>> or does everyone shout it out? What's
the answer?
Yep. K^ squ C in
C out. How many biases?
>> C.
>> C out.
Okay. So again when you see a number
like K^ squ C and C out you should think
of this as a fourdimension as how you
represent it on disk or in memory as a
separate issue right than how many
parameters there are. But how would you
represent it? Well the natural structure
is there's a k by k matrix. There's one
of them for every channel that's at the
input and one of those for every channel
at the output. So see out C in K K is a
way to think about it.
Okay. So now we've talked about the uh
filters and the next question is we have
back prop. How does backrop work? So on
the homework we have you grind it out
because you have to at some one time in
your life you have to just grind out
what the equations are on the homework
uh to make sure you understand it. We'll
but I want to talk about it conceptually
here and then you can work out the
details. So what's the question? So if
you go back to the first uh picture I
showed you
know how backrop works for these things.
So now if you have back prop for
something that looks like this,
you can think of it intuitively as
there's two different conceptual
questions you have to answer.
First conceptual question. So here you
know how to compute gradients for every
single one of these entries. Is that
everyone with me on that? So you look
over here. What's different between here
and here?
So there's two qualitative differences.
One qualitative differences is that
there are a bunch of zeros here.
Everyone with me
and the other qualitative difference is
that you have the same thing in
different places.
Got it? Okay. So let's tackle these one
at a time.
So
first question is what do you do with
back prop on the zeros.
These are places where there's a a
structural constraint. We've induced we
said that you will always have a zero
there. So if you just think about it as
though it were a a layer like this and
you would execute back prop if you
pretend it's this you would get a
gradient that would show up here that
would say I really wish this zero were
something different. Does everyone see
that part in conceptually not in terms
of the implementation but conceptually?
Okay but what do we do with that?
Everyone have a anyone want to volunteer
a guess?
>> Yeah.
>> Do you just ignore the gradient there
and don't do any updates with it?
>> Excellent. The comment was we want the
structural constraint that this is
always zero. So we're not interested in
knowing whether it wants to move up or
down because we've already decided it's
always going to be zero. So we basically
ignore that gradient. This is a
conceptual point of view. If you think
about this as the your reference point,
practically speaking, we never compute
it.
Okay, you could compute it, but we just
don't compute it ever.
Okay, so that's the easy one. The next
one is what do you do with the things
that are shared? The weights that are
shared. So that's what I want to talk
about.
Okay,
so the question is we want to comput a
gradient. So if there's a particular
weight, some weight,
how can we compute the derivative of the
loss with respect to that weight when
the same parameter w appears in
different places in the computational
graph.
Okay, so what does that mean in the
context of a connet? It's that the
reason this is happening is the same
filter is being applied at different
places. So the computation graph
involves some computations that are
happening at this part of the image. It
also involves some computations
happening at this part of the image.
Both of those involve that same
parameter.
So in the computation graph the same
parameter appears multiple places. So
what do you do?
Now you can think about it in terms of
the chain rule which is what you know
this is uh but it's also nice to
understand at a very basic level and so
you have to always also keep in mind the
easy answer which is don't worry
pietorch will handle it which is true
which is why these um these packages
like jacks and pietorch and tensorflow
are so popular and so important is that
they will go through and do the
automatic differentiation on the graph
for
But it is good to know what's going on
behind the scenes because sometimes um
later in the class we'll talk about when
you want to stop it from doing things.
So what's the underlying answer? Okay,
so there's two parts to them
conceptually.
You can pretend that single weight w
that is shared across different places
in the computational graph was actually
different weights. You can think of them
as weld 1, weld 2 and so on. lots of
different everywhere it appeared it's a
different weight they just happen to be
the same value.
So you will compute a bunch of gradients
of the loss with respect to all of those
different positions in the computational
graph
and then you have to combine them in
some way and the way you combine them is
you add them up.
Okay, this is you can think of this
either from the chain rule or uh this
way get the same answer.
Okay. So
between now on the homework we'll ask
you to like work this out uh and to see
you know how it connects the inputs and
so on uh in the case of a conair.
Okay I'll pause here. Any questions on
the on how back prop works conceptually
when you have shared weights?
Yeah.
>> Why are you adding as opposed to
averaging?
>> Great question. Why are we adding as
opposed to averaging?
So, uh
how can I explain why are we adding
instead of averaging? So, first answer
is that's how the math works out just
directly. If you do the chain rule math,
it it works out to adding. Um you might
ask so I will come back to your
intuition about this averaging. It's a
very good intuition of like why am I not
averaging? But the reason is that
actually in your computational graph if
you were to change hypothetically
one of those positions by a little bit,
right? It would change the loss by
this t term times that little bit of
change. You with me? If you were to
change another position by the same
amount,
how much would it change the loss?
the same amount. So if you change both
of them, how much would it change the
loss?
>> The two quantities combined.
>> Two quantities added. That tells you why
you added. Okay? Because the actual
gradient is the sum.
>> Okay. Now,
so go ahead. I'll take another question.
I'll come back to your
>> average.
It's almost like in physics you're
imaginear
combination of each one sort of p
pulling and pushing until you get like
the the net I guess movement.
>> Excellent. So you brought up the word of
superposition which is the way that we
talk about the physics intuition of
linearity right the most basic thing
about linearity is that linearity allows
for superposition and the most basic
conceptual thing that happens with the
chain rule is that the derivatives
kind of are linear local linear
operators because they're local linear
operators they obey superposition so yes
this is indeed a direct consequence of
the idea of superposition
okay so Any more questions before I come
back to the another deeper level
question on the averaging?
Okay. So now let's just think about this
uh averaging
question. So
do you want to comment about why you
thought why your intuition was saying
that averaging might be something useful
or important or or do you just simply
think why there's summing there's
averaging why is it one or the other? W
told those are all equal to each other.
>> Okay. So that because they're equal to
each other, you're thinking ah so you're
thinking of averaging in the sense of uh
I have many things that are equal to
each other. Uh they should be equal to
each other. I'm getting something which
is different. The way I combine
different estimates for something that
should be the same is averaging. Okay,
that's a a good intuition. Um turns out
not to be the right mathematical one in
this case as we talked about. But
there's another reason why you might be
thinking about averaging. Um, and this
is relevant. So in the context of
a neural net implemented on
finite precision arithmetic,
there's a question when you start
averaging when you start adding things
up, right? Even if these are all
different from each other. So suppose
all of these were actually behaving in
an uncorrelated manner, right? They're
just happen to be as though they're
random.
What is this? How does the scale of this
grow with the number of terms in this
sum?
Do you understand the question? Maybe
take a minute to talk to your neighbors
about if if these were uncorrelated or
pointing in the same direction, both
separate cases, how does the scale of
this change with the number of terms in
this sum?
So,
take a little time to think.
Hi.
Okay.
So, spent a minute. So, does anyone want
to volunteer an answer? If I'm if I'm
averaging things like this, I'm sort of
adding up things like this. How does the
scale typically if it was random, how
would the scale change?
Suppose there's 100 things in this sum.
>> Yeah.
>> Well, we're assuming that they're
roughly uncorrelated, then you could
describe them as having a variance that
grows at an order of like I guess and it
grows linearly with the number of
samples at least the standard deviation
so variance grow
>> yeah so variance will grow if they were
uncorrelated the variance would grow
with the number of terms of sum which
means the standard deviation which is
the scale that you expect to see grows
like square root so if there's a 100
things in this sum you expect the scale
of things to grow by 10
as an example if they were all pointing
in the same direction correlated then
you would expect the scale to grow as by
a factor of 100
the real life will be something in
between uh these cases. So what does
that mean practically? It means that in
connets because what does the sum look
like in connets? This is sharing over
all the places that filter is applying
which for an image is roughly if it's a
250 x 250 image that's basically 250*
So the scale can grow by a factor of
250.
Does everyone see that? Okay. This is an
important thing when it comes to
thinking about the gradients in a
convent. And from this point of view,
your averaging question can also be
interpreted as coming from an intuition
of being wary of sums that might make
things grow and thinking maybe an
average would be better because then it
would keep the scale uh at the same
scale.
So typically when we're working with uh
floatingoint numbers and we're doing
FP32 computations in floatingoint
standard float, this turns out not to be
that big of a deal. You have enough
dynamic range uh to worry about this.
But when one starts doing computations
in increasingly smaller precisions. So
the homework this time you see there's a
homework problem that asks you to engage
with how MUP scaling works when you
might be thinking about MUP scaling with
FP8
right which is eight 8bit uh floats. So
in once you're getting 8 bit floats
especially and a little bit in 16 too
then you do have to worry about this and
think about how to structure this
computation in such a way that you don't
get uh things to happen. One of the
approaches that people do is something
called mixed precision training which
they will keep the middle intermediate
results in a another precision a higher
precision to keep track of the results.
Okay. So just wanted to acknowledge this
uh because certainly in modern
approaches are trying to push
performance because you can get a lot
more performance out of the modern GPUs
if you run them in FP16 or FP8 as
opposed to running them in FP32. almost
like four times faster in FP8 than if
you run it in FP32. You will want it's
worth keeping track of these things uh
sometimes.
Okay, so any other comments on backrop
here? Questions people have? Okay, so
now we're going to move on and talk
about pooling.
So we talked about uh
so far we talked about downsampling
using stride. So stride is pretty
simple. Remember stride said we're going
to down sample to move to a lower
resolution by keeping only one out of
four and we'll keep one out of four by
always keeping this one.
Okay. So you could conceptually you
could compute the whole thing and then
just keep one out of four or you could
say I'm not even going to bother
computing the things that I'm never
going to keep and use the idea of
stride. Move your filter by two in this
case. So this should be clear everyone
and for this case again there's no real
issue with thinking about back prop.
It's pretty straightforward.
But there's other ways of downsampling.
Two of them are max pooling and mean
pooling. So mean pooling means just take
the local averages. So take whatever is
in here and average them together to get
a single number. Whatever is here,
average together, get a single number
and so on. Again, should be pretty
conceptually straightforward what's
happening here.
Uh terms of equations, you take the
output, it's whatever your pooling
domain is. So in this case it's a 2x two
little pooling domain
average over it. Everyone clear with
mean pooling?
>> Yeah.
>> Is just equivalent to having your
convolution be a flat one size?
>> Excellent question. Is mean pooling the
same as having a convolution that's a
flat one over size with a stride that
matches here?
>> Yeah.
>> Right. Adding another convolutional
layer that does that. And the answer is
yes. It's exactly the same.
So you can think about this as being
this plus another conler with with
non-learnable parameters.
So everyone's good. So again back prop
for this pretty straightforward.
Effectively what happens is whatever
gradient was hitting this
one quarter of that will hit each of
these positions because of this
one quarter.
Okay. Now that leaves the
other case is called max pooling.
So max pooling says that
I'm going to combine these four numbers
not by averaging but by taking a max
whichever is the biggest one I'll pass
that forward. So intuition behind max
pooling is again thinking about the idea
of a dog detector, a cat detector or a
hand detector or a you know finger
detector. And the idea is that I want to
know if there was a finger in this
place. So when I move my filter at
different places, this one said okay
yeah there was really a lot of finger
here. Not very much finger maybe a
little bit something. So the idea is
that how should you represent the entire
domain from a finger detector point of
view and Max says well if there's a
finger anywhere in there's a finger here
everyone see that kind of intuition
that's the intuition behind max pooling
you just take the max
okay again operation is very clear
output is max over the pooling domain of
hi
now the question is just back prop for
that
Back up here was straightforward. Back
up here is straightforward. Back prop
here has a couple worth a little
comment. So what's the comment? The
comment is you have a max operation
and the max operation behaves an
interesting way which is that
this six is the same as this six. Does
everyone see that? So here's the
question. If this one were to change a
little bit,
what would happen here?
Everyone understand the question? That's
what gradients are doing, right? If this
were to change a little bit, what
happens? So, if this one were to change
a little bit, what happens here?
>> Nothing.
>> Nothing. Because it wasn't the max. If
the six changed a little bit, then
something would happen. But if anything
else changed, nothing happens.
Everyone with me? The only case that's
different is a tie. And basically,
there'll never be ties.
So
you can think of it this way that the
max pool operation when viewed forward
is taking maxes
on the back prop side. When things are
coming back, it's routing the gradients.
So it's taking whatever gradient was
here and it's sending all of it to this
position. It's sending none of it to
these other positions.
So it follows the arg max,
right? The index that the arg max is,
that's where the gradient goes.
So this is max pool.
>> Okay
everyone question there any questions on
this? Yes.
>> What if like the one has changed so
much?
>> Excellent question. Question was what if
the one changes so much that it's bigger
than six. So this is the whole idea of
derivatives. They take a local
perspective. They assume that things are
only going to change a little bit. Why
would they only change a little bit?
Because after I do a gradient update,
I'm just going to update the weights a
little bit. And so the one won't change
by a lot. So I'll just route the
gradient only here.
So this is max pooling.
Okay. Now what I want to do before I
move on to other topics just talk a
little bit about like the historical
like how this stuff was put together
because now you have all the ingredients
of a basic old school connet.
And so this is Alex a picture of Alexet
which is from 2012 really kicked off the
modern golden age of neural nets.
you have an image and you see that the
first thing you do is you have filters
that make it smaller,
you know. So in this case, uh it's a big
filter 55 uh by 55 and you have 96
channels of outputs. So you go from
original three channels to 96.
Then you move you do a max pool
and the max pool turns these uh 55 x 55s
into 27 by 27. Then you do 5x5 cons and
the 5x5 cons gets you to 256 channels
then another pooling and then 384
channels a couple of convolutional
layers. So now there's a comment I want
to make here is in this implementation.
So we've talked about convolution just
focusing on the linear part in the early
neural nets what you would do is after
you do the con and the bias you treat it
like you treat an MLP. So in the MLP
what do you do? You do a linear a bias
and then a nonlinearity component-wise.
So early connets follow the same recipe.
So every time you see uh a conve that
means a conve
nonlinearity.
So a nonlinearity happened here, nine
happened here, a nonlinearity here, nine
linearity here. And so what happens
after all of this is that
move this up a bit so you can see it
better.
Here you get a 13 by13
image from the original 224 x 224 and
this 13 by13 image has 256 channels in
it.
What you do is a little bit of max
pooling and then you turn this into two
4,96 numbers. At this point you no
longer using con layers. You're going to
use fully connected layers. So this is
the style of old school um condents.
They would do some computation on the
image, make it smaller and smaller, make
a bunch of uh channels, then they'd
unroll the entire thing and do a little
uh MLP at the end with a soft max that
had a thousand categories that you're
classifying into.
Okay.
And yeah,
it
just filters together and apply that one
filter.
>> Excellent question. So the question was,
why would I ever do cons of the same
size over and over again? There's no
downsampling happening um one after the
other instead of just using a slightly
larger filter and doing it once. The
reason is that uh remember there's the
nonlinearity here. So it's for the
nonlinearity because you want to have
the expressive power of doing a linear
operation followed by a nonlinearity
followed by a linear operation followed
by nonlinearity and so on. That's why
it's happening.
And so what people did was they said
okay great um
this uh we can keep going. So a very
famous another very famous network from
2014 is VGG
and VGG has a structure that looks like
this
you know uh the details you can look in
prints for what's happening here but
it's the same kind of objects in the
same style just bigger
right there's more more layers
uh there's now this here you saw the
3x3s were like a few times Here you see
larger things are also a couple times
and then a few times repeated
and so this had better performance and
actually very interestingly there's even
some modern applications today where
this this is archaic network from the
perspective of use for most
classification type applications but
there's certain applications which these
things are still um used
but we'll talk about those later
Okay, so this is this is the way these
networks are put together. Any questions
on this kind of putting it together? I
want to make sure we actually put things
together for a bit before moving on to
another topic.
Okay. And the homework will make you uh
do this.
So now I want to talk about data
augmentations. So changing topics.
So we talked about how the convolutional
architecture built in the idea of
translational invariance.
But there's also the question of how to
get other symmetries that you care
about.
And the most natural one to think about
uh in the context of vision is little
rotations.
Did everyone see little rotations? You
want to make sure things are invariant
to little rotations.
So there's a problem. We don't have any
natural architecture by which weight
sharing alone will give us any kind of
invariance or type behavior to little
rotations. We just don't know how to do
that. So what do we do? One is you
expect that given enough data you expect
the data it should learn it itself.
But the other is the idea of data
augmentations.
The data augmentations say that when I'm
training on data, I don't train just on
the data I'm given. I train on
modifications of the data I'm given that
I believe should behave similarly. So I
add more diversity to my data by
injecting it myself.
And current best practice in vision
context especially is that for every
batch that you're using for training you
will actually apply an augmentation with
some probability.
And typically that means that during
training even if you're doing many epics
of training
you will never the network will never
actually see the same input twice. It'll
always see a different augmentation of
it.
So
this is uh code I've p pulled out of the
git repo for uh a particular very nice
paper called pixm mix.
Um HRIS the first author of this was
actually a grad student here. Um he now
uh leads major efforts on AI safety u
and the like and again the time is not
that long ago for this paper.
So there's uh a set of augmentations.
Can everyone see what's written here in
the back? Can you read the text? If not,
I'll zoom it up a bit. Okay. You can
kind of see what these are by their
names.
There's like changing the contrast and
brightness of things. There's making
things look like a poster. Uh there's
little translations in X and Y. You
might think, wait, doesn't the con
already give us that? But the philosophy
here is like add them in, see if they
help. They help. Okay, keep them.
um rotate, solarize, another kind of
contrast thing, shear like you know push
things over a little bit. Um
so these kind of uh augmentations one
can uh uh can use and there's like a
larger list of uh other other
augmentations. And so this list is the
one that this paper thought worked
better than having to use all of these.
Like the additional gain wasn't that
much. It was better to use more of these
more often.
So these kind of augmentations are the
augmentations that are you can think of
as building in
the invariances that you think should
should exist in the patterns you're
trying to learn. Does everyone
understand this? So basically have two
ideas two two things you can do. Augment
your data or build it into weight
sharing in the architecture to get the
inductive bias of your entire training.
So inductive bias is the word we use to
mean what is it the kinds of patterns
that the neural net likes to learn given
the way that it's built and the way
you're training it. That is called
inductive bias. So you want to shape the
inductive bias towards the patterns you
want. You do some of it with
architecture, some with optimizers and
some of it with augmentations.
Okay. So these are easy to understand
but I could stop here but you should
acknowledge reality which is reality is
more complicated than just this basic
story. And so you have more aggressive
augmentations that are applied that
people find practically give robustness.
So here are
uh some of these u more
robustnessoriented augmentations. So
I'll just show them to you visually.
Here's the baseline a picture this bird.
So there's the cutout augmentation which
just takes a block of the image and just
cuts it out.
Did everyone see that? So this is
another augmentation uh that is uh find
found useful to make your learn
classifiers more robust.
There's mixup. So I don't know if people
can see there's a picture of a bird and
a picture of a sea turtle. They've been
alpha channel blended together and the
class for this is no longer so if you go
back to what you saw in your machine
learning class for training classifiers
you can think about the label as being a
one hot encoding that says it's this
class and not any of the other classes.
Everyone remember this from your
multiclass classification from your
machine learning class. So when you do
mix up what you do is you say this thing
isn't just that bird it's a bird and
it's a sea turtle little bit little bit
sea turtle lot bit bird
okay so this is kind of alpha channel
blending then you have cut mix
which is like cutout plus mixup
in which you take a cutout and you put
the other image inside the cutout.
So this is a little bit of a sea turtle
and a bird but mixed together this way.
And then there's this pix which is the
one this paper is doing which I'll
explain more which is a much weirder
one. Um so the first thing that I want
to point out here again is a little bit
of deep learning philosophy and also
what's happening
all of these simple augmentations can be
thought of as trying to make sure that
your training data with the
augmentations looks more like the
natural distribution that you expect to
see. You expect to see rotations in
nature. You happen to have this
particular picture. So to make yourself
cover the distribution better, you add
little local rotations. Everyone see
that? So this kind of stuff can be
understood with the philosophy of I want
to make my training distribution look
like my test distribution.
This is different.
Does everyone see that? You don't expect
to see this during testing.
You don't expect to see this during
testing.
But these are more aggressive
augmentations that are done during
training that make your training
distribution in a sense sense harder
than what you expect to see at testing
to get better performance at testing.
So this doesn't fit in the make the
distributions match
point of view.
Okay. So just as an example, I'll show
you this psychedelic um pixm mix uh
augmentation what that looks like.
So this particular just as an example of
how people creep people get creative.
Take an image they pick from a
particular set of what can only be
described as psychedelic images like
fractals and like weird curvy shapes and
stuff like that. They take one of those
and they add it in. Then they do an
augmentation of the original image and
multiply that in. And then they take
that same mixing image and they multiply
that in. And what you get is kind of a
somewhat dreamlike
weird image of,
you know, the original image with this
kind of strange
hallucinatory
like backdrop mixed in.
And this was found to increase the
robustness of the resulting classifier.
Okay. So people do things like this.
Yeah.
>> Is this so that like edge detectors
aren't as good of an indicator of what
the image is. So is it like reducing the
impact of the individual edge detectors
on the final result?
>> Yeah, it's a great great question. So I
I'll repeat it. The intuition behind
this is indeed that you want to make it
so that you really have to look at the
picture as a whole and not get caught by
little edge detectors and things like
this. So the fact that these are
hallucin what makes people think of
these as psychedelic images that they're
pleasing to the eye. You know your eye
is drawn to them. And so the idea is
that you want to add these distractors
into the image and these distractors are
used uh to help with the training. So
this philosophy of training in a way
that is not necessarily what you're
going to see at test time to increase
the robustness is something which occurs
definitely in images but also in other
domains. You might have heard the recent
um anthropic uh you might have heard
this anthropic was doing this. they
talked about in a a public post where
they would take
their
large language model and they'd like
tune up some directions associated with
being bad um during its training
to sort of try to tempt it into being
bad but then force it to be good with
the idea that this is meant to help
defend against uh it breaking its
behavior in real life uh when people
might you know engaging be engaging with
it. So this you can think of as in the
spirit of augmentations.
Okay. So this is like a larger spirit
that goes beyond the specifics of the
details here.
Okay. Any questions on augmentation?
I don't want to spend too long on it. I
just want to make sure everyone
understands the idea.
>> Yeah.
are someies of this kind of practical
stream.
>> Yeah. So they they in the paper which I
encourage you to look at it's well
written um they talk about how this
particular augmentation gains in
robustness against people trying to
especially adversarial attacks a little
few adversarial attacks but also just
generalization generally.
Um yeah, especially generalization when
the distributions shift more. So when
people talk about robustness, that's
usually what they mean that you are
looking at either people trying to
attack the model, which we'll talk about
later, but uh just working in more
general settings to learn the right
patterns and not overfit to a particular
domain.
Okay.
So now I want to uh come back to
training.
So remember at the beginning of this uh
module I started talking about you know
there's what you need for expressiveness
and there's what you need for training
and these are different. So I want to
shift into the training side now.
So for training what you want is it
should be effective which means you
should learn something that generalizes
well and one of the prerequisite the
most basic prerequisite for
effectiveness is stability. The training
has to actually work. So what do we mean
by instability in training? The most
dramatic kind of instability in training
is you sit there, you start running the
training loop and then you look later,
it's not training at all. And you look
at what's going on and you see nan
nan, right? You're like, okay, something
bad happened. This is, you know, bad
things have happened. This is training
instability. Usually what happens is
some gradients become too large. They
then overflow. You get nans.
So
how do you make this not happen? Okay,
this is the the topic that we're moving
to now.
Okay, so
if you look at these pictures here of
these networks,
they're very straightforward. Everything
is here is expressive.
But what people found is that, and I'm
lying a little, even when they were
training these, there were other
normalizations they were doing to make
even these train. um I think they're
called like local response normalization
and things like that. We're not even
going to talk about them because they're
they're outdated. U
but the big problem is you have many
things stacked on top of each other and
kind of a deep network. And so the
problem is we already told you that
there is this issue with conf is that
the gradients can get big.
Okay. And so just because you're adding
a bunch of numbers up together, but now
you think about what happens as you go
back through a network.
One time things getting a little big is
one thing. But if it happens over and
over again and it happens in a way that
is uh blowing up that can be bad. So
even with FB32
you can tolerate arithmetic growth
but you can't tolerate geometric growth
because geometric growth you know making
something doubling every time you can
think of as consuming one bit of
exponent every single time you'll run
out. Did everyone see that? So you're
really worried about when things
multiply together of bad things
happening.
So
this is the problem that is solved by
normalization layers.
Okay. So
one way intuitively to think about what
a normalization layer is doing from the
perspective of training is you want to
think of it as saying I want to insert
use this here. I want to insert in
between things
between layers of my network
additional layers whose function is to
act as speed bumps for the gradients
going backward so they don't blow up and
also by the same token
speed bumps for the activations going
forward so those don't blow up. Does
everyone see this? This is like the
idea. It's like just a high level
picture of what the normalization layers
are trying to do.
So now the question becomes you know how
do you do it? So here I want to call out
something that you've seen before input
standardization. So you see in your
machine learning class has already been
talked about that you have sometimes you
have inputs and you would like to
standardize them. So you would like to
say whatever your inputs were natively
whatever their native units were convert
them in such a way that they either live
within a finite
box
minus one one or alternatively they have
mean zero and variance one of these two
things. Okay this is input
standardization.
So another perspective of thinking about
what normalization layers are doing is
the following. It says look
you can take your inputs whatever they
are and you can standardize them. Okay
that's now done. So now you have a a
standardized set of inputs that come in.
But remember in your network the output
of this layer is the input to this
layer.
And so input standardization was a good
idea at the beginning.
Maybe it's also a good idea here.
So does everyone see that at a high
level as a how you would approach it?
Practical problem you're trying to solve
is you would like to have your network
not result in nans and to make sure that
it can train effectively. That's your
practical problem. Now your question is
what do you do? You think, okay,
maybe I can do some kind of thing
counterpart to input standardization to
sort of make sure that everything gets
recentered and brought into a right in
the right place
at least recentered rescaled things like
this.
Okay. So
now
uh fortunately from the perspective of
things that you've um already seen in
this class we already have one idea that
we can suggest
right so
okay so just keep this in the background
one idea is we saw in the discussions of
uh maximal update parameterization
that we made these assumptions about RMS
norms. Remember everyone, we said that
we're talking about maximum update
parameterizations. We're making
assumptions. We said the input has RMS
norm one on average. And so we want the
update to the matrix to be such that the
induced norm is correct in RMS to RMS
norm. Remember that. And then we argued
that initialization if we did the Xavier
or HU initialization depending on the
situation that initialization the RMS
norms would be good and then we said the
updates would be at the right scale but
we couldn't make a guarantee at what
happens after you do update after update
after update after update. So you start
out okay you do some updates and now
after the first set of updates the RMS
norm somewhere might start getting big.
Everyone see this as a challenge and
just because you're allowed to move it
right a little bit and keeps moving now
it's big.
So
one idea is to simply force the RMS norm
to be one.
Does everyone see that as a kind of
idea? It's like I would like I made all
my training assumptions assuming the RMS
norm would be around one but I couldn't
guarantee it except that initialization.
So I'll force it.
So what would an RMS norm layer look
like? Does everyone understand what
we're trying to do? I would like to say
that I have a network.
I have some hidden activations. H L
I would like to add something here.
an RMS normalizing layer such that
what comes out let's call it H
twiddle L
has
H H twiddle L
RMS equal to
Yeah.
>> Yeah. I thought you were talking about
that automatically if you're
initialization is right that the updates
and stuff will stay order. So
>> excellent question. So the question was
we in Mup we argued that our updates
would be order one in the context of uh
the MUP initialization. By order one we
meant that if we may change the scale in
the sense we change this right we change
the appropriate thing we're scaling here
is dimension we made the dimensions much
larger it would continue to be order one
not changing with the dimensions we're
compensating for the effect of the
dimensions so order one you saw in the
homework is like tied to a learning rate
say 01
is the scale of the update what is 01
0001 is one in a thousand
Okay. How many iterations are we going
to run?
So if you're allowed to move things by
1,000th, but you do it a million times,
you could find yourself out much bigger.
But the problem hits you much before
that, right? So as soon as you're out to
you started off at order one, and now
you've moved little by little by little
during training. Okay? And now my RMS
norm is typically seven.
Okay, it's gotten bigger.
I'm like in potential trouble because my
assumption for the MUP update was I'm
making the weight matrix update so that
scale the next thing is order one if the
input was order one in RMS norm. Does
everyone see that? But now it's seven.
So this st size of update is actually
moving the up the next thing up by more.
So this can be bad. Does everyone see
that?
>> I thought we said that our updates are
also ordering order to order one.
>> So the problem is order one to order one
is order one. Not the order is not how
many times we're doing this. So there's
different things we're scaling.
We made sure the order was controlled
with respect to the underlying
dimensions
not how many times we do it.
Because if we keep adding over and over
again order one quantities we will get
bigger quantities. So if we add order
one quantities 500 times or let's use
order notation. If we add order one
quantities k times we get something
that's order k if you start tracking
order with respect to k. But we don't
want that. Okay. So one thing we can do
is just explicitly enforce it. Say let's
just put something down such that no
matter what comes in the output is
always going to have RMS norm one. Does
everyone see this as an idea? It's like
you want some property to hold. You have
two choices. You either set up a very
delicate situation where you can prove
this property holds or use duct tape and
you force that property to hold.
Okay. Engineering we often like to do
both. Have some
You might I should find that meme.
There's like a wonderful meme about
this. Um, but you often want things to
just work robustly and so adding
something in that forces it is one thing
you always want to have in your
repertoire. Know what conditions you
want and if nec if they're breaking
force them. Yeah.
>> And that is what
the like horizon and that is what
>> yes so you can think of it that way the
RMS norm layers one way of thinking
about they're doing is trying to just
enforce the make sure the conditions
that things like muon and so on depended
on actually hold no matter how many
iterations have happened they have a
second property which is very nice is
that they also will act as speed bumps
of gradients for gradients so we'll
we'll we'll show that in a moment you'll
see it in a moment
If we have normal layers to like do
everything that we want, do we care
about the initialization at all? Like we
still need to do in
>> uh that's a great question. So the
question was uh if we have if once we're
forcing things to have the right norm
with respect to RMS norms, do we need to
still enforce the conditions on
initialization? And the answer in
practice is a little bit yes, you do
need to but you can be it is more
relaxed
because you did you did want the
remember the actual condition we wanted
on initialization was we wanted the
spectral norm of this thing to be in the
right place.
Xavier was a way of getting it. But that
the spirit of was that we wanted the
updates to be the same order as the
matrix.
right in terms of it spectral norm. So
we do have that still holds right
because that gives the right scaling. So
we do still need to make that sure that
happens.
So even if you put the RMS layer norm
layers in the same one we have to make
sure the matrix is still compatible with
what it would have been with RMS1's.
Okay. So okay everyone understands what
this thing is now trying to do. Now
let's just see how could we do it. Okay.
So the task assigned to you for one
minute is to say give me an operation on
a vector such that if I apply that
operation to the vector no matter what
it starts off with assume it's not zero
u I will get something that has RMS norm
one everyone with me do this one minute
Okay,
let's everyone come back. So you have a
d-dimensional vector.
You would like to do something to it
such that the RMS norm is always one.
What can we do? Someone want to raise
your hand and volunteer?
>> Yeah.
>> Subtract the mean.
>> Okay. Interesting question. So subtract
the mean and divide by the standard
deviation. So I only want this
condition.
Okay. So, where I could subtract the
mean and then divide by the standard
deviation which would give me this. Do I
have to do that?
Right. Arms norm just means that we just
want to make sure the average of the
squares of all the entries is one.
Okay, this is subtle. It's like an
important thing to keep in mind. We are
used to subtracting means and we'll talk
about subtracting means in a bit but in
this case there's no need to subtract
means. You could do it by subtracting
mean but when we talk when we say an RMS
norm layer in practice in the deep
learning community we actually don't
mean we mean don't bother subtracting
the mean. So you're basically in the
same spirit. So all I need to do is
scale it. I need to scale it by
something. So this should be a scaling
Oops. Let me
use the
color. So this should be proportional
to HL. But I want to normalize it the
right way.
And you are right in what you can
normalize it by is something you can
think of as being
s some normalizer where s
is
1 over
d times the sum over j.
Oops.
HLJ squared.
So it's average. Don't worry about
subtracting the mean. Just compute the
second moment empirical second moment
and take the
square root of that.
Okay. And if you want to to make sure
that things are robust, you add another
epsilon to make sure you don't
accidentally divide by zero.
Okay. Any questions on this?
>> Yeah.
>> I just was following the way it was
described. Yeah. Another way of doing it
alternatively
and then you scale that by the norm
which you need squared d
>> sorry
>> s I'm dividing I'm scaling by S where S
is this inside is the average second
moment of the entries. Do you see that
second moment? So I'm taking the squares
of everything adding them up dividing by
D square root of D. Yeah, this this
should be correct.
>> Yeah.
>> Okay. Excellent point. So I wanted to
introduce something that is intuitively
close to what you've already seen. Right
now this thing has no learnable
parameters.
Okay, it's just I want to make sure the
RMS norm is one. I will do this. This
story becomes intricate but let's let's
talk about it uh in steps by steps. It
turns out that when one is using
optimizers like muon in many practical
settings, one actually does want to use
just straight up RMS norm layers with no
learnable parameters
in practice.
Okay. However, in other settings, one
wants normalization layers that have
some learnable parameters. So I'll talk
about those next.
But I do want to acknowledge this. Right
now I've shown something that has no
learnable parameters. And this is
actually also useful in practice with
modern optimizers like mu1.
Okay. So
now
here we did something that was sort of
uh individual
uh vector by vector. Does everyone see
that? It's like vector by vector.
Very important. And this kind of vector
by vector operation is particularly
going to be important when we talk about
transformers and state space models and
things like that later. Um but in the
context of images one often wants to do
a little bit more averaging.
So
here's a picture that is people find
useful when thinking about what uh kind
of normalizations one can do.
What do you have to work with during
training?
What you have to work with is of course
an image. And the image has
some height and width. So I'm going to
fold them together because it's very
hard to draw four dimensions. So we can
only draw three. So height and width
I'll fold together as being spatial
extent. This is like space.
So in addition to space you have
channels
the number of different channels. So one
of these things
is for one input image to your connet
what is going on at this particular
layer. Everyone with me? But
you want to during training have batches
that you use. Why do you want batches?
Often practically speaking, you want a
batch because your GPU cannot will not
be saturated by just using one image at
a time. You have more parallelism in
your GPU. So you're not going to let it
sit idle, let those tensor cores sit
idle. You want to use them. How do you
use them? You put more images in as your
batch.
Okay? So you have a batch.
So you have lots of things that one can
average over.
So one of the first kinds of
normalization layers in the modern era
of normalization layers was a
normalization layer called batchnorm.
What happened here?
So what was batchorm? Bashnorm said
we're going to do the same thing that we
do for input standardization
except we're going to do it at an
intermediate layer. So for input
standardization what do you do? You take
all of your inputs and for every
particular position in your input for a
vector input you take the mean subtract
it off and you set set it so that across
all your inputs the standard deviation
is one.
Okay. So what you do is you do averaging
this way
across the batch.
But to get more averaging and to respect
the idea of what what your spatial
filters are like, you also average
across space
in a convent.
Okay, so bashnorm does that.
So this averages
over space
and batch
not over channels. The logic behind
averaging over space is to say that you
know you might have a cat somewhere in
the image.
You want to make sure that different
positions of the image are all
represented. Okay, so you average over
all the entire image.
So this is uh what batch norm does and
let me just write out
uh the expressions. So
let
curly be you know
the
what is
averaged over. Okay. So for the
different norms it'll be different. For
bashn norm it's batch and space.
You first compute a mean
of whatever the input is
then you compute
a scaling factor. So again it as before
one over Sorry. The size of
Okay, that's very messy.
Sum over everything being averaged
hi minus the mean squared.
>> So this is the standard deviation and
this is the mean. Yeah.
using all the locality information.
>> Okay, hold on a minute. All I'm trying
to do is to understand how to scale. I
will keep all the locality information.
I'm just going to rescale everything.
So, I'll just write the next thing out.
What I could do is to say h out,
okay, as a vector is going to be.
So let's look at H out in the in a
particular position I comma J H out in
the I comma J position to keep the
locality clear. One thing you could do
is just to take H
input.
So okay sorry I'll write input in okay H
in the I comma J position except I'm
going to subtract the mean
and I will divide by this standard
deviation regularized by an epsilon.
Okay, this would standardize it to have
average zero over the averaging domain
and variance one. Everyone with me with
this? But in practice, we also add
learnable parameters. So, sorry, I'm out
of time.
Okay. So, I'll pick up here next time
and continue with the other other
normalization layers next time.
Did you think of batch norm as kind of
like getting rid of an implicit bias
across batches because then like batches
in one channel where like maybe the
values are higher those would have minor
gradients of the loss. So you're kind of
like
>> I mean it's easier to think of batch
norm as just being you are doing input
standardization for an intermediate
layer
>> and you're doing it on the entire size
of input you have which just happens to
be the back
>> that's easier to think about.
>> Yeah that makes sense but like what if
your network wants to learn that like
okay like we don't want like the inputs
to all be like for Xavier in it was like