But again, I'm really sorry that people
you you might get very well kicked out.
So, be be careful about this.
Um,
>> the class is going to be recorded and on
YouTube and it's going to be playing on
the screen right outside
like right like you can just sit right
outside and walk inside if you have a
question
but um I'm somehow not able to get my
slides to show
[Applause]
AB,
>> I can't get the Excuse me. Hey, sorry. I
need to access this
on on
>> Sorry.
Why am I not able to get this to?
Usually this just works.
>> So you have to connect the HDMI.
>> Ah, I did not know that. Okay, that's
what
>> I use. I connected the wrong connector.
Okay.
And you're just going to mirror.
>> Uh yeah.
>> Hello.
>> Start mirroring slideshow. Let's see.
Does this work?
Got it.
>> Now you go back into your
volume control.
>> Okay. Thank you.
>> Slide share.
Okay.
>> Okay. Great. Welcome to the very first
lecture for 1822 282A.
As you can see, there are more of you
than there are seats in the class. We
are very very happy to have you here and
we will be talking about enrollment in
just a minute. Before I officially start
lecture, I want to just announce that
the fire marshall requires us to not
have anyone sitting in a non seat. So,
please do your best to keep the aisles
clear. The lecture will be live
streaming on the screen that is right
outside this room. So, you can go, you
know, easily watch it out there and if
you want, walk in if you have a question
as an option to you. Okay, with that out
of the way, uh let us start. Today's
agenda is pretty simple. We're going to
start with some introductions. Then
we're going to talk about some
administrative details that I'm sure
many of you have questions about. And
then we will start doing some deep
learning.
So this class has two professors. My
name is Giri Jaran. I've been teaching
in this department for a while. Before I
started on the faculty at Berkeley, I
was a researcher at Microsoft research
up in Seattle. So if you ever want to go
hiking, it's a amazing place to be. Uh
before that, I got my PhD actually right
here at Berkeley and I was an
undergraduate at MIT. Uh I was lucky
enough to take the introductory AI class
there with Patrick Winston who is you
know one of my research and teaching
idols and has been a foundational figure
in the field of AI for a um I mean since
its since its beginning. One of the
great things that he used to do when he
started lecture was he would always
start lecture by playing rock and roll.
And the beautiful thing that he told me
that has stuck with me to this day is
that all great ideas are simple. Good
ideas are complicated.
So what we are going to try and do in
this class is going to try and take
these you know ideas that have
complications that have lots and lots of
nuances and try to present to you the
simplest cleanest most aesthetically
pleasing version that you can use to
solidify your understanding that will
then help you actually you know get
further in the field. So this is going
to be a class that is going to have a a
mix of uh a lot of mathematics as well
as a lot of uh programming and to be
able to see the simplicity and the
beauty in many of these ideas. We are
going to be relying on the fact that you
have taken and have a good handle and
understanding of elegant and powerful
mathematical tools because things are
simple when they're looked at in the
right language and with the light right
perspective right we know this from the
SVD when you project into the right
coordinates things become simple and
clear so that's the aesthetic that we
will be taking and so uh we'll talk more
about the prerequisites but that's
something that I would like you to uh
like you to keep in mind.
>> Hi, I'm Professor Sahai. Um I've also
been teaching here um but for longer. Um
but I I've taught this class a few times
uh in the past. Uh so um we've learned a
lot and hopefully you will get be the
beneficiaries of that learning.
>> Yeah, it's my first time teaching the
class. I should should announce that.
Um, we will have office hours uh right
after class in 400 Corey. So, we can
kind of all walk over together to that
room uh when you have extra questions.
In terms of resources, there's a website
for the class, ex182.org.
All of our policies are documented on
that website, so please feel free to uh
look at them. There will be an ed for
the class, which will be the primary
mode of communication with you. All
posts that are put onto ED are required
reading and uh please use ED as your
forum for asking any kinds of questions
including administrative questions that
you might need. Both the faculty members
will be checking ED and we'll be
responding to ED. It's the fastest way
to get a response to your question.
Finally, we will be uh using we will not
really be using this textbook per se,
but if you want a textbook, this is the
textbook that we recommend. It's a very
recent textbook uh by Simon Prince.
There's are many many things that are
very elegantly done in this textbook.
So, um I I recommend you look at it.
There's also many things that we will be
doing that are not addressed in this
textbook. We're going to try to bring to
you some of the you know most recent
advances in the field um and digest
papers uh and share them with you. So
there will be things that are covered in
the class that are not in this textbook.
So it's not that um it's not a onetoone
mapping but this is a good reference.
Okay. Now about the elephant in the room
enrollment.
So, the class might expand, but we do
not know and we do not have control over
it as instructors. Uh, we've been asking
the department to expand the class since
April.
Um, but this is not in our control. If
you would like to make your voices
heard, the department would be the um
place to make your concerns heard. Uh,
we have a possible expansion approved.
So, we are doing our best to make those
accommodations, but we cannot guarantee
that we will be able to do this because
we were only given this information a
week ago. So, we're we're trying our
very very best.
Because of this, we are going to
prioritize having people in the class
who want to be engaged and are committed
to doing the work. This means that we
will have a homework zero that will be
due next week. And those students who do
not submit homework zero will be
automatically dropped from the class so
that other students can be let in. If
you are on the wait list for this class
and you would like to get in the class,
please make sure that you do the
homework as though you are enrolled in
the class. Keep up with the material.
Only those students on the wait list who
have completed and submitted homework
zero will be let into the class. Okay.
um we simply have no other choices given
the you know extreme restriction on the
number of seats that came to us from the
department. Again I emphasize this was
not our choice. We tried really hard.
>> Uh is Sultan here?
>> Sultan.
>> Sultan are you here?
>> No.
>> Okay. Well maybe wait uh just a minute.
>> Okay. So there will be weekly discussion
sections that will be staffed. Um we
will have at this moment only one gsi
for the course and two uh UCS1's. So we
will uh introduce them in just a minute.
These sections are going to be
Wednesdays 3 to 4 and 4 to 5. These
sections are required. This material
will help you in understanding the
material. Discussion sections will start
on Wednesday September 3rd. You can
choose any one section to attend. Both
sections will cover the same material.
Discussions will be crowded for the
first few weeks. So bear with us. We
will be posting discussion uh sheets so
you will be able to get access to the
material.
In terms of getting help, there will be
instructor office hours right after the
class. There will also be gsi office
hours at a time that is yet to be
determined. We will have discussion
sections. We will have the ed forum. And
the most important resource that you
have in this class is each other. What
you have to be able to do is be able to
uh talk to each other, form study
groups, have accountability mechanisms,
and uh be able to uh work with each
other. I want to talk about this one
more minute, but I know you have a
commitment to get to, right?
>> Yeah.
>> So, why don't we do introductions for
the two staff members that uh that are
here?
Do you want to start? Why don't you come
up here and uh use the mic?
>> Okay. Yeah.
>> Hi everyone. Uh, I'm Patrick. I am a
fourth year studying geeks and applied
math. This is my first time on staff and
I'm very excited to work with all you
all this semester.
>> Hi, my name's Alex. I'm a I'm a third
year. I'm studying EEKES and math. And
like Patrick said, I'm really excited to
uh work with all you guys and to uh help
you guys learn machine learning. Help
you guys learn deep learning. Sorry, fun
class. Um yeah, this is my favorite
class and also it's my first time in
course stuff. So yeah, I'm excited to
see you guys.
[Applause]
>> Okay. Um, we have another gsi sultan
Daniels who, uh, is not here yet, but
will be an excellent gsi. I have
absolutely no doubt about that.
Okay, so uh, back to how to get help.
Basically, we are your resources. As you
can see, there are more of you than
there are of us. It is actually a
particularly low staffed semester, so we
will do our best to try and help you. Um
but realize that there's just a limit to
what we can do with the with the volume
in this class. So that what that means
is that it is really really important
that you form study groups and work
together with each other to hold each
other accountable to doing things like
coming to lecture. I know for those of
you sitting in in the um not on inse
it's not a particularly great
environment to start. You're like well
maybe I want to sit in a chair. maybe I
don't want to really be here in lecture.
Odds are that in a week or two this is
going to thin out and there's going to
be plenty of room in the class. So
please try to show up make
accountability buddies so that you have
reason to show up to class and even if
the first lecture like you know this is
you don't get a seat odds are you're
going to get a seat in the in the coming
uh coming days. So, you know, really
make sure that that you make it a
priority to be here. This is a great way
to get to know people. What I also
recommend is making a group of three to
five to eight people, however many you
want, and setting a time where you will
work together on your homework. Put it
on your schedules like a class and come
at that time and meet and do the
homework. This is going to be a very
fastmoving class just given the sheer
volume of material that we have to
cover.
And if you are not kept up with the
homework, it's going to be really hard
to uh digest all the material. So use
each other to do that. Ah, wonderful.
Sultan is here.
>> Do you want to introduce yourself?
>> Yes. Hi, my name is Sultan. I'm a
thirdyear PhD student working on
research on deep learning and I took
this class last semester and I had a
great time and I'm really excited to
teach everyone.
>> Great.
Okay.
If you have private questions that are
not suitable for ed, you may email the
uh faculty to be able to get a response,
but know that ED is probably the fastest
way to get a response. Our emails are
often flooded, but we make time to go to
Ed to respond to questions. Um, and if
you make a private post there, we will
do our best to respond uh very, very
quickly. I will apologize in advance
that we might write to you very very
short three-word emails. That is not
because we are trying to be rude. It is
simply because we are trying to reply to
all of the questions we have received. I
would rather reply to everyone shortly
than write a long paragraph to one
person and not reply to the other 10.
Okay? So, we are really not trying to be
curt or rude when we write short emails
to you. Okay. Great. Accommodations. Um,
we're happy to work with the DSP office
uh to make sure that all of you have the
appropriate accommodations for you to
succeed in this class. Please reach out
to us as as you uh as needed. Homework
extensions in this class will
essentially be automatic if you need
them. Um, project extensions which we
will talk about we will not be able to
offer simply because the project will be
due at the end of the semester and then
we have to submit uh final grades. So,
uh, there'll be a long period of time
for you to do the project. So, we will
not be really offering extensions on the
project.
Now, on to the grading details, the
nitty-gritty.
There are two big components in this
class. It is the final exam and the
project. The homework will nominally be
worth 0% in the class, which means that
the actual submissions are not going to
be graded. We have only one gsi.
So it's simply not reason uh not
feasible. We have we we don't have the
bandwidth. And in the era of LLMs, what
we want to do is we want to really
encourage you to focus on learning the
material. I think an put it really well
that you know using an LLM to do your
homework is the equivalent of instead of
going for a run around the block, you
drive around the block. The point is the
workout. The point is not the
destination. Okay? So doing the work is
what is going to help you learn, not
writing the answer in a box. And so the
whole point is to encourage you to do
the work. So we are not going to be
really checking if you do the work. We
will in the event that there's a you
know boundary case on your grade. You're
extremely near some boundary. we may we
may choose to go back and look at the
homework and see if you know this is
some this is a case where we want to
make some kind of exception. Um however
in general the homework will uh not be
looked at. So
um 60% of the class will be the uh final
exam 25% is the project and 15% is
participation which we will talk about
in a minute. Both the final exam and the
project have a gating effect. What does
that mean? It means that if you fail the
final, you fail the class. You can't
have an outstanding project but fail the
final and pass the class. Similarly, if
you fail the project, even if you have a
perfect score on the final, you will um
fail the class. The key reason for doing
this is to prevent free writing on the
project because we do not want to have
situations where we have groups of four
students and only one of them or two of
them are doing the work and the other
people are not doing the work. So it is
essential that you keep up with the
class and do the work because the way to
do well on the project and be able to
participate fully is to make sure that
you know the material doing the
homeworks doing the the you know
>> discussion
>> the doing the discussion sections. So
this is all uh critical. There will be
no curve in the class. You are not
competing with each other. We have
already published the bins to the
website. These will be the bins that
will be used for grading the exam.
>> The whole class.
>> Uh the exam and the whole class. Yes.
Okay. So, homework policies. There's a
grade scope code. You might want to
write this down. It's on the website,
too. Even if you don't write it out, um,
please join Grade Scope. You have to
submit homework zero there. Remember,
there will be weekly homeworks. They
will do will be due every Friday night.
The grade scope deadline will be set to
the end of the semester. So, the last
week of semester will be what the grade
scope deadline will be will be set to.
So you can technically submit the the
the homework after but the deadline is
Friday night. Okay, does that make
sense? So that means that if you have a
need for an extension, take the
extension, but know that you are taking
an extension and know that that means
that you are accepting the
responsibilities that come with that
extension.
So we strongly recommend keeping up. I
already talked about creating
accountability through a study group.
Um, we already talked about the homework
being 0% and we may look at a random
subset of your homework if you're close
to a grade boundary.
Finally, doing the homework is really
the best way to learn the material. Um,
historically, if you look at the exams,
there have often been questions on the
exams that are very, very similar to
homework questions or build on the
concepts that have been talked about in
the homework questions.
Okay, let me pass to Anand.
>> Great. Um so let's just talk a little
bit about the um background we expect.
So this is 2025. Um it's not uh 2015 or
2013 or sometime in the past. We
understand a lot and to give you the
best deep learning class we are going to
try to use and get you to the edge of
understanding that we that we have. So
we expect uh a mastery of machine
learning at the level of 189 and or and
or stat 154.
We will not be reviewing we'll set
notation but we're not going to retach
you basic machine learning. We're going
to need it um to to build on. We expect
a mastery of linear algebra and
optimization at the level of x127 to27a.
Um we are absolutely going to be needing
optimization is the workhorse uh for
doing modern deep learning. So we're
going to need you to know that and have
facility with doing the manipulations.
um we'll need probability um at the
level of 126 or data 140 or stat 134. Um
probability is the language we use to
talk about things like generalization
and a lot of intuition and principles
behind which the algorithms and the
approaches are designed come from
probabistic reasoning. If you don't have
a deep familiarity with that, you won't
understand it. So we require it. We're
not going to teach you probability.
Um what does this mean? Uh it means that
when you say we're not going to teach
it, we're not going to teach it to you
in lecture and we're not going to
support it in office hours. Um we're not
supporting it in any way. Uh so we'll
point you to stuff that you can read.
You can uh but you have to know it. You
saw the level of staffing we have. It's
not feasible for us to teach you
background material.
Um yeah and to get him if you just
wanted to learn about deep learning in a
cookbook manner um we strongly recommend
you go and take advantage of the vast
number of YouTube um resources and other
free resources out there that will give
you lots and lots of recipes and stuff
you can use uh to do deep learning.
That's not this class. It's not the
point of a Berkeley class. So we expect
you here if you actually want to
understand and learn the material and to
the best of our ability. Okay.
So now you have a sense of um the
background we expect and we'll be
counting on let's talk about uh we've
seen about the homework. The homework
you know will have written questions
involving proofs and derivations and
things like this. We expect you to do
them by hand. the exam you know will be
remember handwritten three hours
in-person exam with nothing else except
you and the exam um but the project is
different so a lot more details will be
announced on ed uh including all the
logistics and sub deadlines and things
like that but key points are the project
is a group project again given the
number of staffing we cannot support a
whole bunch of individual projects um
just don't have the resources uh groups
of four groups of four can mix and match
between undergrads and grad students. Um
for the project itself, there will be a
few options. Uh each of the options will
be open-ended in that it will allow you
to get however far you want to get close
to the research frontier. Um and we'll
build on as well as build on published
papers to allow you to demonstrate your
understanding of deep learning. The
project will require you to learn things
on your own that will not have been
covered in lecture because that's the
reality of the subject. Um however for
undergraduates taking the course as well
as graduate students from EEKES uh you
will have to choose between the project
options we give you that will support um
there'll be room within them but they'll
be bounded graduate students from
outside of EEKES will be permitted to
lead projects outside of our specified
topics um based on aligning with their
research and and the like. We will
publish more details about that on ed
later so you can understand what what
what what's in scope on those teams of
led by a graduate student or two
graduate students or three graduate
students u from another department
undergraduates are permitted to join
those teams as well.
Um the reality of deep learning is that
you have to have uh use computers. Um so
uh we are trying to secure some compute
resources for you and we have made some
partial progress in this direction.
However the compute resources we are
able to secure uh from wonderful
national level programs are are not
sufficient to actually enable all of you
to do the best projects that you might
want to do. Let's just be clear about
that. So uh you might need to bring your
own compute for your projects. uh to go
beyond. We'll try to make sure the
homeworks and all will can run within uh
collab uh free tier and what you can do
on your um modern laptops, but uh you
know even there there might be
explorations you want to do yourself
that go beyond. Um so we're going to
we'll try to get you resources but you
might need more.
>> And and in keeping with the Berkeley
ethos, you know, if if you have
resources that you can use, please So
that the resource that we will obtain
are available to those who do not have
those other resources. Right? So uh just
be
uh we have we we we're doing our best to
get as much as we can but it's still
finite whatever we're going to get. So
>> yeah for that
>> and we'll have to share it
>> for that. The right again if you have
any complaints about that don't talk to
us. Talk to um the higher level people
in the campus administration the
governor and your senator and
representative. um
um for uh understanding what it takes to
compete in the modern world. Um so the
project will involve um lots of work on
your part of course but you'll have to
submit proposals multiple levels. You'll
have meetings with uh us you'll have to
submit drafts. There will also be an
individual component of the project
that's not group which is you'll
individually have to participate in peer
review um of other people's submissions
and give detailed comments and feedback
so that everyone can do the best
projects by the end. It's also just a
part of life uh in this area. So your
actual grade on the project the entire
group will get one grade for the
technical material that they have done
and that will be modulated by your
individual performance as a peer
reviewer to get your grade. So if you do
a really bad job as a peer reviewer for
example not doing your reviews then you
will get a zero on the project because
the zero will multiply even your
spectacular the project. Okay. So, you
have to do all the work. Basic
philosophy in this class is
you have to do all the work. There's no
escapes. So, if you want to do that, be
here. If you don't, there's 400 people
approximately want to take the class.
100 seats, you know, make room for
somebody who does.
Uh the final component of the
uh of the of the of the course is
participation in citizenship. So what
does that mean? It means that we expect
you all as a member of the community and
this class do your job in making the
class better for everyone involved.
Everyone starts off with zero in
participation which is a failing grade.
Um so what what do you need to do to
participate in this class? There are two
components.
One component is ordinary participation.
The things that one expects people to do
in classes. What does that mean? It
means attend and actively participate in
all the weekly discussions. Which means
every week go to discussion and
participate. The way that discussions
are structured, if you are there and
participating,
the course staff will know that you are
there and participating. There'll be
small groups. You'll be working on
problems, things like this.
um some people that may not work uh for
you or you might not be able to do it
every week. Um we're aware of that and
so you can also be actively helpful in
the online forum. This will also get you
ordinary participation.
So
this is expected from you. Of course, if
you don't want to do this, why are you
taking the class? Um,
and on top of that, we are going to
expect four at least special
contributions. We'll put more details
about this on the in the ed forum, but
these are things that you can do that
involve a little bit more work that make
the class better for everyone. Um, that
also actively engage your learning in a
more detailed way. So, one of one of
them, one option is going to be
take one of the modern LLMs. you will
have a we'll have a sign up way for you
to sign up so you don't hit lots of
overlapping things. So for example go to
Gemini and say okay Gemini I'm going to
use Gemini to solve the homework
and we'll record a trace we'll put put
details about this record a trace of you
interacting with Gemini as watching how
Gemini solves the homework problems okay
we will expect you to then annotate that
trace with your own comments critique it
um sometimes Gemini will oneshot the
problem for example but sometimes it
won't um so engage see what's going on
and give us a report on what happens.
You must do this at at most once. So you
can't do all four of this. There are
going to be three other choices. One of
which is uh so I I didn't finish making
the slide. Uh so
uh one will be to do the same thing for
a code. So we'll have homework
assignments that involve code. So then
see using co-pilots, cursor,
winds surf any of these different tools
that you have incl or just the straight
LMS directly and see how do they do on
that coding problem and interact with
them as well. We expect why do we do
this? We expect students in a course
like this to walk away not just with an
understanding of deep learning from a
theoretical and a
let's say a 2019 level way of engaging
with a computer. but also the modern
way. So we want you everyone to have at
least some practice doing this. Okay.
>> No, it's not worth it. Um
>> so this is the uh second thing. Third
thing is also related to code. It's to
the code. So we built these homeworks
over many semesters and they were built
trying to get them out the door so they
can teach the right thing for students.
They're not the best written code.
They're not actually code that we would
be proud to have as our demonstrations
of code. Another thing you can do as a
special contribution is to consult,
critique, look at online descriptions of
what is good coding style, both Pythonic
coding style or also a machine
specifically machine learning oriented
and take one of the problems and clean
it up. Okay? To reflect that style. This
is good for you and it's good for
everyone else. Okay, these are three
examples of special contributions.
There's one more very important one that
I cannot explain to you in a way that
you will understand yet. However, it has
to do with the following. The field is
moving and keeps moving. Some of the
homework was built, oh my goodness, as
far back as 2022.
And uh so
there have been advances.
We do not have the staff bandwidth to
actually take all of the problems and
make them aligned to our current best
understanding. There will be another
option a view for you to do that to add
parts to problems that reflect things
we're going to teach you that were not
understood in 2022. Okay, as an example,
we expect everyone to do this uh because
this is how you will really learn and
master the material and you'll help
everyone else as well. Okay, so
I will pause here now for questions
because we're going to then switch into
talking about deep learning. We talked
about a bunch of administrative stuff.
Remember the short version is go to the
website, read, go to Ed and find out.
But anyone have any questions? This is
the time we can take uh these kind of
any questions right now.
>> Yes.
>> Regarding homework, so actually special
contributions. So to get full credit, we
need to at least four of them. But
detailed LLM has to be used like can be
used on
>> the three from the others as well. And
the others also have caps.
>> The three others can be just mixed and
match.
>> Yes, mix and match. I mean,
>> you can't just do the coding one also.
We'll cap that one. But you you don't
have to do all of them. We encourage
everyone to do all one of each.
>> It's good for you to try one of these.
That's why it's four categories and four
things so you can try them. But if you
really like doing one kind of thing,
we're not going to make it super strict.
We'll we'll write up guidelines. I mean,
the objective is of this is not and
dying. It's to try and make the
incentives for you to do work aligned
with the incentives for your learning.
Right? So that's really So why do we say
that detail reports are only allowed
once? Because let's admit it's easier to
copy paste a problem into Gemini and see
what it turns out. And yes, there's some
value for your learning, but writing
code has a different value for your
learning. And so if you diversify the
things you do, you will learn more.
That's basically where this is coming
from.
>> Notice that basically the way these are
structured, you cannot cheat
except by outsourcing to another person,
right?
>> Yeah.
>> Uh great question. So at the end of the
semester, we will give you a self-grade
form that you will use to document have
a picture of yourself so we can match
you against people's memories of who is
in section. Um as well as document what
are your key contributions with posts
and then we can just check. Yeah, we're
not going to go through like remember a
few of us but we are structuring things
in such a way that the incentives on you
are just to do the right thing and learn
the material.
graduate students that are waiter
or
>> we actually don't even have control over
it. The instructors don't have control
over it. The department autoprocesses
it. So
>> yeah, basically we don't know
>> emails that I have saying I I have
emails from colleagues saying can you
please help so and so get in the class
and we just don't have the
>> but you have to do homework zero.
>> Yes. If you don't do homework zero,
>> you have a negative.
>> We'll block you from um getting into
class.
>> Yes.
>> And I wonder
>> we don't know.
>> Yeah. Basically, we don't know. That's a
key answer to most enrollment questions.
But you better do homework zero. If you
if you don't do homework zero, you're
not getting it.
>> Yes.
scope.
>> We will not be using B courses.
>> So
>> yes.
>> Yeah.
>> No, the point
That's the whole point. So we are doing
our very best to read papers that have
been published in the last
>> month and
get the material updated. Of course
there going to be some material that is
canonical historical material like the
definition of a is still the same 2022
and 2025 right SVD even more fundamental
also is required we won't be teaching it
but so there's stuff that's fundamental
and that's going to be the same but
there's stuff that's new and what we're
trying to do is you know trying to
digest this material that's not even in
the textbooks yet and present it to
So for example right um just some some
of the things that make us tip into this
vast literature that make us tip what is
relevant to teach you is a kind of sense
of stability like is this understanding
that's actually having impact and so
recently um the release of the of
certain Chinese open source models right
uh I think Kim too
>> right in particular made it very clear
that there were things as well as llama
for that made it very clear that things
that we were kind maybe sitting back on
that is this really something that
everyone needs to know or you know is it
still you know too far on the frontier
do you guys need to know it okay so that
kind of stuff is being is going to be
worked into the class so the material in
the class is different you um the
material
the LLMs without reading papers cannot
do well in everything in this class
because there'll be information beyond
their training cutoff date okay So yeah,
the material in the class will keep
evolving and changing. Just to give you
a sense of this, when I first taught the
class in fall 2022,
um just before the beginning of the
class, stable diffusion had come out.
Just before
by the end of the class, there was the
release of chat GPT. During the majority
of the class, chat GPT did not exist.
Okay. And like this there have been
advances sort of in the different terms
and we try to you know kind of make
adjustments as we can to make sure you
are uh at the right place. Not just our
goal isn't just that you understand what
is understood now but that you are in
the right position to be able to
understand the new stuff that will come
out later this year, next year, the year
after and ideally four or five years
after that.
Okay.
>> Yeah.
>> Is hope for zero release on the scope on
the gray scope. I just chat and he said
all assignments.
>> So I'll explain this. So great scope is
the place where you will submit your
homework. Your handwritten homework will
be scanned in concatenated with the PDF
of your code uh your notebook together
into one PDF and you will upload it.
will not put outlines up there. You're
just going to submit there. Think of it
as a place to place a file. That's what
we're going to do. We don't have time to
build outlines. Okay? The homework is on
the website. So, if you go to x22.org,
you can click and there'll be homework
zero. You can see it. Okay? Don't
recommend doing it now, but you will
have to go through and do it by we have
an extended time period, not one week.
We have until Friday of next week for
you to do it.
>> Yeah.
I have a last question. So for the final
for the final project like when
we
think about our ideas for
>> so the final project will be due at the
end of the semester and we will expect
that you will need to use a bunch of the
techniques that you are learning in the
class to do the project. So we're not in
a position to announce the final
projects yet because you don't have the
material to even you know be able to
conceptualize what it is. So we're
expecting to release the final project
somewhere around mid semester mid to
late semester and then you will have the
second half of the semester roughly to
work on them.
>> Yeah, we'll have lots of detailed sub
deadlines and so on but right now it
would just be gobbledygook.
>> Yes. Can I check if the lecture like
slides are recording be uploaded or if
>> we uh the lectures will be recorded?
>> Yeah, the lectures will be recorded and
posted after the lecture is done.
>> However, we strongly recommend that
students take handwritten notes for
everything. Okay? Whether you watch a
video lecture or you're sitting here,
not for administrative stuff, but when
we start talking about material, take
notes. Okay? This is not this is not a
sit back and like casually watch kind of
class. It's not a double speed watch
lecture and like checks their phone
while talking to chat GPT. This is just
not that class. If you ask what you want
like don't take the class.
Full engagement is what we ask for.
>> Okay. Any last questions?
>> There's absolutely no slip days for
homework zero. Um, and like I said, the
you can submit your homework to grade
scope later. The point of homework is
for your learning, but homework zero is
a hard cutoff. Um, and you have more
than a week's notice to finish the
homework.
>> And everything in homework zero you
already know how to do if you know the
prerequisite material. Like nothing
nothing we're going to talk about today
or other days is going to be required to
do homework zero. You can do it now.
>> Okay.
>> So,
>> great. Let's move on.
Okay.
>> Okay. So now we have to confront
something about deep learning itself as
a subject which is
deep learning is a subject where our
understanding of it is
way way way way better than it was in
2015 in the sense that a one-year-old is
way o more capable than a newborn. Okay?
But we are still babies
overall as a species in terms of
actually understanding this material. So
um this is what we expect your
experience and our experience many times
to be like in the class.
[Music]
That's a feeling you'll be familiar
with.
Bye-bye, book. Bye-bye.
Bye-bye.
Okay. So,
we'll do our best to teach you what's
going on, but the there's lots of times
where you will experience a lot of
internal feeling of uh I'm not sure I'm
comfortable with what's happening here
in terms of understanding because you'll
be there's a style in which you have
learned u your foundations, your
mathematics, your probability, your um
principles of how we think about
algorithms and code and linear algebra
and optimization and physics which is
very very stable and well understood and
systematic. There is a rigor um and a
connection between the rigorous
understanding and experiments and the
gaps between what people understand and
what you are taught. I mean they are
some of them are being masked. Um but
some there some of them are more subtle.
In deep learning it's much more in your
face that we don't understand things. So
we will keep pointing this out um as we
as we go uh in the class for at
different places but you just have to
I have to we have to acknowledge it. So
let me see what I Okay. So we talk about
deep learning like what are we actually
talking about here? What is this class
about? So
fundamentally deep learning involves is
a class a class about neural net. So
what is a neural net? A neural net is
fundamentally a simulated typically
analog circuit. So first thing is this
is not a very
the values we're interested in are
continuous values that we're working
with. We'll represent them with floating
point, but they're continuous values.
And these circuits are largely parallel
in what they do and they're doing
information processing.
But to set the very very very many
parameters associated with this circuit,
we have to use an optimization algorithm
to set these parameters. We don't
handcraft them. At times in the
homework, we will ask you to handcraft
parameters to help you understand the
relationship between the parameters and
trying to achieve a certain objective.
But in practice, we're using an
optimization algorithm driven by data.
And so that's what this class is about.
What makes it deep learning, why we call
it deep learning is that the circuits
that we're talking about in practice are
deep and they have many many layers uh
many many circuit elements have to pass
through before you get to the end. Okay,
that's what we mean.
So we do this with a goal. We would have
like like the learn circuit the result
of the optimization driven by data to
appropriately approximately capture
relevant patterns underlying the data.
This is what it shares with machine
learning. It's a subcategory of machine
learning
um where those patterns are present in
the data that's used to train it. And we
want to do this so we can use the
resulting circuit to solve problems
involving new data.
Okay, what problems? Problems for which
whatever patterns we've learned are
relevant. Okay, that's that's the kind
of connection to regular machine
learning.
So
this
sounds great. Okay, fine. We want to do
this.
But the reality of the subject is we
barely know how to do this.
We build things. We try them out. They
work. We have reason and and intuitions
for building it. But these don't often
match the level of rigor you might
expect. For example, if you were
constructing a bridge,
you know, so how to get how to wrap your
head around it. In this class, we'll
basically have two approaches. We will
help you to help you wrap your head
around it. The first is a joke. Okay?
So, I will tell you this joke. I will
this joke will be told over and over
again in this class um to help explain
why things happen the way they do. The
joke goes like this. You might have
heard this joke. So,
a person is walking and they see it's a
night and they see a drunk man um kind
of searching on the ground, you know,
near a street lamp. So, they walk up to
this drunk man and they say, "Hey, what
are you doing? What's wrong?" Goes,
"Well, I lost my keys and I'm looking
for them." And so, the person asks the
follow-up question, "Did you lose your
keys right here?" And the person says,
"No, I lost my keys over there." And the
person asks, "Why are you looking over
here?" He goes, "Because here's where
the light is."
Okay, so this joke is actually
the essence of what we do in deep
learning throughout. Many times you'll
have a very natural question which will
be well you said we wanted to do X. Why
are we doing Y? And the answer will be
because we understand how to think about
Y. We do not understand how to think
about X. So we're going to do Y.
Okay. Now
the pragmatic sense of this is actually
very reflective of what's in engineering
generally which is
it's better to do something that has
some chance of succeeding
than to do nothing which has a 100%
chance of not of not succeeding.
Okay. Now ordinarily in your classes
this is not although it's a very
fundamental principle it's not in the
foreground in this class it will often
be at the foreground
so
what are the things that we understand
this XKCD is a very relevant one so take
a chance to look at it many of you might
have seen this already
um so in case people in the back can't
read it there's a stick figure person
standing on a big mess having matrices
and lambdas and stuff in it. And the
person there says, "This is your machine
learning system." He goes, "Yep." You
pour the data in this big pile of linear
algebra, then collect the answers on the
other side. What if the answers are
wrong? Just stir the pile until they
start looking right.
Okay? So,
you will find in this class that we will
lean often on linear algebra. So it's
good to acknowledge the many reasons
why.
One reason is linear algebra is
something that we understand
and it's something that we have
intuition about that we can connect to
geometry.
So if you're thinking about something,
it's easier to think about things in the
context of something you understand.
Second, linear algebra is something that
we have made computers very good at
doing.
they match naturally to parallel
processing that happens on uh SIMD
processors and other proc GPU like
machines and so if you want to do
something you might as well do it using
something you know how to do fast on a
computer
so we use this as a building block but
don't forget the it's what we understand
so many times we'll be building you
intuition using simple linear algebraic
formulations and you'll say how do I
know this applies to my deep learning
And the answer is well we understand it
here and it seems to have intuitions
that carry over and so we will use it.
>> And if I may add a comment is my mic on
yes. Okay. So the I I just want to admit
that when I started learning deep
learning this was one of the things that
made me most uncomfortable about I'm
used to doing things where I can prove a
theorem and I know for 100% that like I
have optimized the parameters. I know
exactly that I'm doing always the
perfectly right thing.
And for someone who is trained to do
that and has come through taking classes
where you're always used to doing that,
this like look at it this way
perspective is it's a it's a perspective
shift. Um, but one that I found is is is
very useful and very mind expanding in
in really nice ways. It's interesting to
see how your minds have gotten trained
into having a particular way of doing
things. Um, and
having this new perspective is actually
actually really valuable. On the flip
side, um, what I also see often is that
there's a lot of because kind of no one
understands anything anywhere here.
There's a lot of what I what people call
or what I call like ML broism
where you just like shoot off a bunch of
like oh then you take the like some big
term and then some other jargon and then
some other jargony jargon jargon and you
don't really understand what it means
but you hope that the other person also
doesn't understand what it means
and you know you just talk in these like
big big big words and that is also not
an ideal situation. And that is not
where we want you to be. What we want to
develop is a sense of groundedness in
fundamentals that comes from the
training that you have developed through
taking hard classes like 126, like 127
where you've ground out these large
proofs. And so you have that aesthetic
and elegance of mathematical beauty and
bring that to the linear algebra soup,
right? So that we can try to see the
elegance and the beauty in that soup. So
these are two different ways of
thinking, but they're both really
important. Um is what I wanted to add.
>> Yeah. And uh so uh again uh another
joke. Uh so there's a
An engineer, a mathematician and a
physicist are all drunk and they're have
decided that uh all the odd numbers are
prime and so they proceed to talk about
it. And the mathematician says, "Well,
three is prime, five is prime, seven is
prime. It follows by induction. They're
all prime."
And the physicist says, "Three is prime,
five is prime, seven is prime, nine is
experimental error, 11 is prime, they're
all prime."
And the engineer says, "Three is prime,
five is prime, seven is prime, nine is
prime, 11 is prime, 10 is prime.
Okay. So
this joke you will often feel. So what
we're hoping is that you will maintain a
little bit of your sense of groundedness
to know when we are pushing things
beyond and to feel a little bit like
sometimes the physicist in that joke who
says okay this isn't quite right right
but okay this isn't quite but at times
for practicing in deep learning you will
have to take that engineer's point of
view and says yeah I know this is not
right this doesn't follow the theorem
But I'll do it anyway.
Okay. Um, but again, this is part of the
aesthetic. You just have to learn how to
do this. So, now
I want to talk about um, you know, what
this feels like to maybe ground people a
little bit more in
your education has come at a very
special time for human civilization in
that we actually understand a lot of
stuff. But understand that for a very
very very very long time all of the
sciences grew up as alchemy
where people were trying to turn
different metals into gold, give develop
potions of immortality, cure various
diseases, forecast when appropriate heir
would be born and so on and do various
tasks that would allow them to get money
from people who have lots of money and
power. So they could go on and continue
to fiddle with various chem chemicals
and put stuff together. Okay, I mean to
an extent if you watch what's happening
in the venture world and so on, this has
not changed. Um but the important thing
is all of that progress that happened by
alchemists gave us modern science and
chemistry. They built the experimental
equipment. They figured out how to do
all this stuff. And remember, human
beings have had amazing ceramics
for thousands of years before they
understood even the most basic thing
about how ceramics actually work.
People built cathedrals before they
understood F equals MA.
Okay. So
the fact that we don't understand many
things in deep learning, you can think
about as a little glimpse that you get
to experience today of connecting to the
worlds that your ancestors lived in
forever. They worked hard. They made
progress. They made amazing things
despite not understanding them at the
time. And then understanding sometimes
came 10 years, a hundred years, a
thousand years, 10,000 years later. So
we don't know where we are in this
process. So
it's okay.
Okay. Um you'll have to remind yourself
of this. This is this is okay. Um
so now I want to talk a little bit about
some of the history. Um we're not going
to be taking a a histo a largely
historical perspective. Occasionally
we'll mention history. Um but neural
nets are actually uh something that has
been around for a while and uh neural
nets have gone through various phases of
excitement. And so back in you know the
60s
uh 50s actually you know between the 50s
and 60s you had the idea of the
perceptron you had the idea of doing uh
pattern recognition using these things
having having datadriven methods of LMS
which is basically gradient descent. Um
then you had in 1969 this uh book which
described the fundamental limitations of
a one layer uh neural net and that
resulted in part among other things in a
crash, right? And so neural nets were
like super exciting and hot and then
went through a period of oh they're
totally useless and they can't work.
Historically, this has also been
connected to when you outstrip the
available compute. Okay, the actual
compute you can do, the things you have
to work with are no longer capable to go
any further and there's a crash of
disappointment. So, it's like a neural
net winter that happens. So, first
golden age of neural nets ended. Then in
the 80s, compute got better. Other
advances happened, fuzzy logic, other
things were brought up. back propagation
was moved from control theory where it
was developed into uh training neural
nets and you had the second uh golden
age of neural nets that basically ended
at the end of the 80s the beginning of
the 90s. Okay, again a crash from the
neural net point of view. Although
people kept working, smaller groups of
people kept working in the area and
people realized they could do a lot of
this stuff much better using stuff that
had math that we understood better.
So you had a second golden age of neural
nets that again went away for some time.
Then you had the 2000s.
What happened next is
parallel developments, right? You had
computer graphics, you had video games
which led to GPUs. So GPU's main market
was video games. And so lots of people
wanted to play video games. So GPUs got
better and better and better. And then
in the 2010 20098 time frame, people
realized, oh, you can use GPUs to train
neural nets and they're faster. You can
make bigger nets. And then in 2020 2012
begins the modern current the phase we
live in today um golden age of neural
nets where suddenly the
the paper AlexNet beat all previous
methods for doing uh image
classification
and made it that neural nets weren't
neurons before that point were viewed as
an interesting niche tool. So they were
really good at doing things like
handwritten digit recognition, other
little tasks. Um they were bigger in
Japan where they were used in lot uh
consumer uh things as a small thing. But
at this point they were like wait a
minute let's just revisit this. And from
there you had the building forward um of
the wave that we live in today, right?
Which is this new golden age uh for
neural nets. So it's good to acknowledge
this um history a little bit.
Um we could keep going and talk about
the different developments for this in
this age and we will do that uh in the
in the course at different points when
we introduce certain uh key building
blocks but I wanted to give you the kind
of prehistory back. Now our perspective
that we'll use in this class is all
going to be post 2012.
Okay, we're not going to talk that much
about uh details of things that were
understood back then. Fortunately,
you've taken a machine learning class,
you've already seen back prop, you know
how it works. We don't have to review
that. So, we'll largely focus stuff on
stuff afterwards. Okay. So, any
questions on this history? And then I'll
switch to the board and start
introducing some material for the you
know for the for the course now. Any
questions on prehistory or
>> other issues?
Okay, great. So, let's switch to the
board.
So let's just think about uh something
now. I expect most people um everyone
has seen a multi-layer perceptron before
in your previous machine learning class.
What I'm going to try to do here is to
approach the question from a different
point of view to connect uh some ideas.
So
we're going to use a neural net to
approximate functions. So how do we
think about this? The easiest way to
start thinking about it is to think
about approximating a function f that
goes
from the reals to the reals. a
univariate function. Okay, so the input
is x
which is a scalar
and the output
is y which is also a scaler.
And so in discussion next week we'll
also engage with what I'm talking about
right now. Um
so how do we think about functions from
scalers to scalers? You've been doing
this for a long time, right? You can
just plot them
XY. And so when we talk about function
approximation, we would like to think
about approximating an actual underlying
function. And now in the context of
machine learning and neural nets, we
want to approximate a function and we
want to approximate learn that
approximation using data samples. So we
can visualize all that. So we have some
function
So here's the function our desired
and we would like to have a neural net.
So we have a neural net
n and n is going to be defined by some
parameters
theta. These are parameters
and the neural net matches input output
what you want. So n is going to take
a single scalar input and will output a
real. Okay. Okay, so we got a neural net
that takes a scalar input, outputs are
real, defined by some parameters such
that we can approximate functions.
Everyone with me? Great. So now we think
about how do you want to approximate a
function?
So you probably first saw approximating
functions with other things back when
you learned calculus, when you learned
things like reman integration, right?
Right? So when you learned new on
integration, what you did was you took a
function and you approximated by a
peace-wise constant function and you
said hey if I take this function let me
use another color
Lots of different ways to do it.
You get the idea, right? So, this is a
peacewise linear approximation.
Not peacewise linear peace wise
constant. Peacewise constant.
So when we think about neural nets, we
have to think about how we do the
approximation and our goal in doing the
approximation
is
there's many fold. We would like to do
the approximation in a way that has good
approximation properties. We'd like to
be able to approximate the function.
Well, we would also like to be able to
do the computations involved in doing
the approximation efficiently using
linear algebraic uh tools together with
other other tools.
And we would also like it to be possible
to train this neural net to follow
approaches like gradient descent to
actually move the parameters. Okay, so
peacewise constant is one approximation.
But
we can also have a different
approximation, right? We can do
peacewise linear.
So a peacewise linear approximation
would look like this.
Okay, this is piece wise linear.
So again, you saw peacewise linear
approximations probably when you also in
your calculus class where you learned
something like trapezoid rule for
integration, right? These might be
bringing back memories for what you
learned a long time ago. And so you can
see at first glance you can see okay
peacewise linear is a better
approximation than peacewise constant.
Um it's what does that mean? It means it
for the same number of kinks
it is closer to the function.
right in places between the kinks.
So that's one aspect of thinking about
approximation is approximation quality.
How good of an approximation it is? But
the other thing you care about in uh
from the neural net perspective is how
do you represent it? Is it possible to
represent peacewise linear approximation
using parameters that are friendly for
optimization and for computation?
Okay.
So
the question becomes
how
to represent
slashparameterize
a peace-wise linear approximation.
So what do we need to know? So when you
think about parameterization, it's like
I need to describe this peace-wise
linear approximation using a set of
numbers such that I given the set of
numbers, I know how to evaluate the
function. Everyone with me? Okay, great.
So you can immediately see that in these
cases there's lots of choices to how to
do this, right? There's lots of
different choices by which you can think
about this peacewise linear
approximation. So the first thing you
need to look at in this I may zoom in on
this piewise linear approximation thing
a little bit zoom in because I want to
talk about it.
So I'll just zoom in
to some piece of it to some little
section. Okay.
So if I think about a peace-wise linear
approximation,
think of this part. What information
qualitatively do I need to convey about
this purple thing so that you can know
it exactly?
What do I need to know?
>> Yeah.
size.
>> So I need to know how what do you mean
by step size?
>> Okay, so I need to know the lengths,
right? So I need to know al so one way
of thinking about it is I need to know
where these
kinks are, right? What's the spacing
between them? So uh is this
>> Yeah, I don't know what I can
so locations of these kinks.
Okay, what else do I need to know? So
now I know where on the x- axis. So
these locations are here,
here,
here, and here. Okay, what else we need
to know? Yeah.
>> The slopes.
Okay. So, slopes.
Okay. Good. I know where the kinks are.
I need to know where the slopes are.
What more do I need to know?
>> Is that enough?
I need to know how high this thing is.
Okay, so now this is the first place
where you should start feeling okay wait
how much do I need to know? Okay, if I
told you the location of the kinks and I
told you all the slopes and I told you
it was a peace-wise linear
approximation, meaning it's a continuous
function,
how many y's do I need to know to know
which function it is?
One. I need the height somewhere,
right?
Okay, so you can kind of see there's
some kind of information I need to know
to understand this uh peacewise linear
function. Okay, now comes the next
question.
How can I represent this information
in a different way? in a way that's
convenient for me to apply parallel
matrix type of computations to do the
computation.
Okay.
So I can just describe this this
information theoretically I've given if
I tell you all this information you can
replicate this but that might not be the
most efficient way to do it.
So one of the useful ways to think about
it is
so now we need to think about
implementation a little bit.
So we know the kinds of operations that
we know we like to make computers do uh
is things like multiply adds right
multiplies adds stuff like this.
So we would like to implement this kind
of function so let's call it neural net
theta of x
in ways that involve multiplication and
addition. So one way to think about it
is to think about it as some kind of a
sum over little little pieces, little
things.
So I want to sum with weights of some
kind.
Maybe I won't use this. I'll use W.
And I'm going to sum up some other
functions.
G
theta tilda I
>> write a little bigger.
>> Yeah, I should write a little bigger
>> or even on this
So I think I'd like to be able to
represent a peace-wise linear function
as a sum, a weighted sum. Now why do I
like this? Because I know in principle
that
this kind of sum type representation is
going to have natural parallelism that I
can exploit because I could presumably
compute all of these things in parallel,
multiply them in parallel with their
individual weights and then add them up.
Okay, so this is like friendly for
computers.
So you think okay if I wanted to have
this kind of information so all this
information that I needed this height
these slopes
these locations all have to be somehow
embedded in the learnable parameters
like these weights and whatever these
theta tildas are okay so it turns out
that there's a way of thinking about
this that's natural and the natural
thing is to think about
what this little function in here should
be like. So you think, hey, wouldn't it
be nice if I could instead of thinking
about a function that has arbitrarily
um
positionable kinks and slopes and so on
as instead being something that's
defined this way,
okay? where I have an arbitrarily
positionable kink
elbow
and a slope.
So if you think about it, if I add
together a bunch of functions that are
all sort of flat and have a some slope
that I can modulate, then I could
certainly start at zero, go up, and then
change my slope later by adding a
different function that moves the slope
down.
You see how I could construct things
this way? Okay, so this is nice. This
gives us a a way to do that. Now the
great thing is that these kind of
functions
can be put together out of even simpler
things. So this kind of function what is
this? This kind of function is a
a max
of zero
and
some
wx
plus b. There's a straight line
somewhere. So it's defined by wx plus b.
This is a max in this. So this kind of
operation max zero something is what the
relu is
rectified linear units.
And next time we uh you'll you'll see
how to connect this kind of thing to
more linear algebra and set everything
up so you can see the approximation of
this. Okay, because we're out of time.
Um, we have office hours in 400 Corey.
Um, there's another class immediately
after us, so we can't really answer too
many questions here. Maybe a couple one
minute, but then we have to move up.