Okay, tell everyone who was watches the
recording what I just said. [snorts]
>> So, sign up for postp proposal meetings
with uh staff members. Again, there's
signup slots. So, uh make sure you all
sign up. Only one slot per group is
sufficient. And uh you know don't
necessarily take up multiple slots for
your group because that's not really
fair to everyone else around. So one
slot per group is kind of the budgeting
that we have. Okay. I know that the last
time around there were a couple of
straggler groups who struggled to find
uh meeting slots. So make sure that that
is not your group. Good. Any burning
questions about projects before I start?
Wonderful. Okay. So what we're going to
do in today's lecture is pick up where
we left off last time with positioning
and coding. And my agenda is a little
ambitious. What I want to try and do is
if you recall we at the very beginning
of
this uh kind of module on attention and
transformers. We showed this quen next
architecture and there's a collective
who came from the class when uh this was
shown. My goal is by the end of the
lecture you should have some
understanding of every component of
this. Nothing should be mystery
mysterious. Okay? So you will be able to
understand kind of at some level
everything that is going on here as well
as in some of the most recent 2025
uh architectures. Okay. So we're going
to try and take you to the absolute uh
latest models and give you some idea of
what is going on there. But we still
have some buildup to do. We still have
some history to cover before we get to
that. And we started out last time
talking about rope and I ran out of
time. So if you remember, we had this
idea of position encoding. And why was
position encoding important for
attentionbased transformers? Well,
attention has a symmetry to it. And so
the thought was originally that we need
to somehow be able to give the model
information about which tomogen came
first, which token came second, which
token came third, uh so on and so forth.
And so there was this idea of absolute
position encoding where you add an
absolute position encoding vector to um
your attention matrix and therefore you
will uh sorry to your embeddings and
that will allow you to get um this
position encoding.
turned out that that was not such a
great idea. And then subsequently came
this idea of nope, which is no position
encoding. And so there was just, you
know, adding nothing in actually
outperformed these absolute position
encodings.
The next idea was to say, well, can we
do learned relative position encoding?
And we said, well, what we want to do is
we care about not the I don't care if
you're the fifth symbol or the 25th
symbol or the 23rd symbol. What I care
about is where are you relative to the
other people other other s other tokens
in the in the mix. And so I care about
the differences between the different
tokens. And so he said, well, let's
learn something that actually modifies
the attention value itself based on the
relative position between the query and
the key. Does everyone remember that?
And we learned this particular parameter
that that depended on the relative
positions and used that as a relative
position encoding and that beat nope and
absolute position encoding in multiple
cases. However, that also turned out not
to be that great and so the
state-of-the-art and what almost
everything now uses is rope or some
variation of rope. and we kind of
started talking about it last time but
didn't have enough time to go through
it. So I'm going to pick up and talk
about rope now. Okay. So the key idea
behind rope is that we want to basically
um modify
the key
and the query
based on
their
absolute position.
So that the score that they generate
depends
on the
relative
position, right?
And how are we going to do that? Well,
our score we're basically computing as
this inner product between the key and
the query, right?
And what do we know? We know about inner
products. Well, we know that inner
products are basically a function of two
things, right? If I think about the
inner product between this K and this Q,
I can write this as
the magnitude of K. Let's say it two
magnitude of Q
times the cosine of the angle between
these two, right? And so the inner
product is maximized when your vectors
are aligned to each other and it is
minimized when they're orthogonal to
each other. Right? If the angle between
them is 90°, then you're going to have a
uh cosine 90 is going to be zero and
therefore your inner product is zero.
Orthogonal is the worst. Okay.
So what if we can modulate where these
key and query vectors are with respect
to each other based on their
position.
Okay, so every key is coming from a
token at a certain position. Every query
is coming from a token at a certain
position. If we can modulate the angle
between these vectors,
then maybe we can use that to somehow
capture
this relative position. Okay, that's the
key idea behind rope. We're not going to
use exactly that idea, but in two
dimensions that kind of maybe makes
sense to you, right? So for example, if
I have a rotation matrix,
so
those of you who took 16A or 16B with me
might have seen me talk about this. Uh
do people still Yeah. Yeah. Yeah. So
anyways
um
RT let's call this let me call this um
cosine
let's see um
omega t
maybe I should
actually I'll substitute that in later
let me Just call this omega t
minus sin omega t
sin omega t
cosine omega t.
Okay. And what does this rotation matrix
do? Well, when I multiply a vector by
this rotation matrix, we rotate by um
omega t, right? That's what this
rotation matrix does. Okay. So, RQ
basically rotates
Q by
omega T.
So now we want to use this idea to
basically influence the inner product.
So instead of considering the inner
product between K and Q, what if I
instead instead considered
the inner product
let's say RT
qt
[snorts]
and r i ki. Okay. So my query is coming
at time t and I'm considering the inner
product with the key that was generated
at time i or position i. This gives me
qt
transpose
rtpose
r i
ki. Okay.
And so now this thing is a rotation
by negative omega t and this is a
rotation
by
omega i. Right?
So [snorts] now when I put these two
matrices here,
what have I done to my inner product?
Right? I've basically changed the angle
between the two vectors and this change
is now a function of basically t and I
the relative position between these two
things.
Make sense?
Questions?
Okay.
So this is great for two-dimensional
things, but you know if deep learning
worked with two-dimensional embedding
vectors, then things would be very
different. Our embedding dimensions are
never two dimensions, right? What we
have like a thousand dimensions, 2,000
dimensions. This is the kind of
embedding dimension we have. So how do
we extend this idea to work for larger
and larger vectors?
Let me add a page here. That is the key
innovation or one of the key innovations
of rope.
And so now suppose you have some
very long vector.
Okay. And I have here
multiple entries of this vector.
What I'm going to do is I'm going to
group
the country the entries of my vector. So
I'm going to put these two into one
group. these two into one group, these
two into one group, so on and so forth.
And I'm going to treat these essentially
as two-dimensional vectors or complex
numbers,
right? So there's a real part and an
imaginary part. Okay?
And I have now these a stack basically
of complex numbers. If I have a
d-dimensional vector, I have dx
two-dimensional
chunks in there. And I'm going to apply
this exact same rotation trick to each
of these two-dimensional chunks. Okay.
So, what I'm going to do is I'm going to
take this vector
and I'm going to multiply it by
an M which looks something like this.
This is m1,
m2,
m d /2.
And this is a block matrix where each mj
is basically
cossine
2 pi t
fj. So here I talked about I used omega
here but I really want to call out this
frequency in a bit. So I'm replacing
these omegas with uh the corresponding
frequencies.
Maybe it is better to write this in the
other order
and then times t
This is all inside the
Okay.
So now if I have this for every single
kind of pair,
each of these is being rotated
by
the appropriate angle given by this
matrix, right? And so now when I look at
my all of my different channels, it's
like I'm looking at these groups of
channels.
And these fs, I'm going to choose a
different f for each different pair of
channels. So these fi
these fi depend on whether I'm thinking
about the first two channels or the
second two channels or so on and so
forth, right? And I'm not learning these
fs. These fs are fixed. I pick them in
advance and they just are what they are.
I'm not doing any learning here. But now
if I pick an F that is a very low
frequency, what is that going to mean?
That means there's going to be very
little variation over time. And so even
if I have a lot of like if if the t
minus i is very large and I'm I'm
looking at the low frequency channel
corresponding to those those keys and
queries then I'm going to get a high
coherence. These are going to look very
similar to each that the inner product
is going to be high. Whereas if I'm
looking at a high frequency channel then
I'm going to have a lot of
non-coherence. A lot of these times
these inner products are going to end up
being zeros and things are going to be
out of phase and therefore I'm not going
not going to get high inner products or
high scores. Okay. So on a channel by
channel basis I can modulate when I care
about the long time range dependency and
when I care about only local information
or short uh short time scale
information. Okay, here I'm using time
and position interchangeably. Okay. When
I say time, I really mean position in
the sequence because these are
sequential tokens that are coming in one
after the other.
Okay.
So, questions here.
Yes.
>> Could you repeat that part of the
frequency?
>> Okay. I will repeat that part. Do you
have a different question?
>> Uh, yeah. I was wondering about whether
this is applied after the learned K and
Q. Is this separate or
>> this is applied every time while you're
learning K and Q. So like you it's not
like you learn K and Q and then you
apply this. This is
>> in the mix.
>> So
mediates the inner product, right?
>> I'm sorry.
>> Is that what this is saying? Like you're
using it to mediate your So instead of
using J, you're using this as your inner
product.
>> Yes. Exactly.
>> Exactly.
So it's still
>> so K and Q are still learned in the
exact same way as they always are.
>> Okay. So let's let's let's do this one
more time.
Um
okay is the two-dimensional picture
clear? Everyone any questions about the
two dimensional picture? Okay. So when
I'm thinking about this vector here,
okay,
I want to be able to say so, so why do I
care about doing these rotations? I want
to somehow be able to encode the
relative position. And I'm choosing to
use
these frequencies to encode this
positional information in some sense.
What do I mean by that? I'm saying that
if I choose for example
um
I don't want to say the same thing
again. So I'm trying to figure out a new
way of saying the uh the same same thing
but okay does everyone see that here
there's two things that this this ro how
much you rotate depends on two things.
One, it depends on t, which is your
position in the sequence.
And B, different channels get different
frequencies.
Okay,
that's one thing that's clear. Okay,
two, it's clear that to everyone that
low frequencies change less and high
frequencies will change more. Okay. So
therefore is it clear to everyone that
different channels will behave
differently.
So for example for if I have a very low
frequency here then as t changes cosine
t will change very little. Whereas if uh
I have a very uh high frequency here
then as t changes cosine t will change
rapidly. Therefore I will move I will
rotate my vector a lot.
Okay.
So if I have if I'm if I'm rotating my
vector a lot, let's say I have these
high frequency things, basically I'm
making big jumps. Therefore, I'm two
vectors that might be initially close to
each other. much I'm going to move them
into orthogonal positions relative to
each other much more quickly and much
more often than if I had a channel that
was associated with a low frequency
where you know like I'm it's been a lot
of time but I've only changed my inner
product by very small amounts because
the angle has changed between the
vectors has only changed by very small
amounts.
Okay. So therefore I can specialize and
I will have some groups of channels that
will be very sensitive to the T minus I
because of the uh high frequency
component and I will have other groups
of channels that will be much less
sensitive and even if you're quite far
away you it will be almost as though you
haven't changed.
Okay. Does that does that help in that
make things clearer? Yes.
>> So then the scale of the FJS is has to
cover like a long range of
>> Yes. So you're you're choosing a you're
choosing a many different frequencies
and you're pre-choosing them. You're not
learning them.
>> And in the literature it seems like they
use a log scale. Is there or like yeah
it's like they cover many orders of
magnitude. Is there a rationale behind
like what that scale you said it's
chosen a priori like how do they know
how much of a scale to use like between
how many orders of magnitude are you
choosing here and what is the rationale
for that
>> um I think this is one of those things
that's you you try things and you and
you figure out what what happens but
you're also you're you're trying to make
sure that you can capture
different
uh time scales of information
>> right
>> right so if you uh you basically and you
want to be able to so so if you chose
things on the linear scale you might not
be able to do that as easily.
>> Yes.
>> How do you know like whether you should
choose a high frequency for a specific
channel or do you kind of assume that
you just fix these FJs and then the
model will somehow learn?
>> Exactly. You fix these FJs and then the
model will learn because the model is
learning the queries and the keys and
the values. Right. So by fixing these
you're saying well these channels are
going to capture the low frequency
information these channels are going to
capture the high frequency information.
That part is being fixed by your choice
of FJ and then the model is learning
where to put what information.
>> Got it.
>> Yes.
>> Is there a specific like computational
benefit to breaking these up into real
and imaginary components instead of just
taking them as complex numbers and
applying a complex exponential to them?
Um the advantage is simply that then you
can just do all of the algebra with real
numbers because neural networks are not
that good at dealing with complex
numbers though I think that there is
some work in getting this to work with
complex numbers but I think it's just a
mechanistic like matrix multiplies are
easy so just do matrix multiplies kind
of
>> I know we talked about complex numbers
earlier yes that architecture involved
that dependency so I wasn't sure if
there was already
>> uh I know that there is work in terms of
getting complex numbers to work nicely
with neural networks but I don't know
that any of it is so sophisticated that
it has become part of the mainstream
uh yeah
>> just to confirm are you saying that FJ
is a hyperparameter
>> fj is not a hyperparameter
um it is
okay I see what you're asking Um,
one could think of FJ the this the
choice of FJS as a hyperparameter in the
sense that you can try out different FJs
and uh or different groups of FJS. Maybe
I wouldn't say FJ is a hyperparameter,
but the
set of FJS
is maybe a hyperparameter in the sense
that you're you're going to see which
ones work well for you.
And there are there are common
conventions of what works well and
that's what is ends up being used.
But you're just to be very clear it is
not learned when you are training the
model. It is chosen beforehand and so in
that sense it is like a hyperparameter.
>> Yes.
>> Um can you explain again why we're
splitting them into real and complex
part? We're splitting into real and
complex part because simply it's
conceptually easy to think about complex
numbers and we know how they behave when
they're hit with a complex exponential
or with a rotation matrix.
>> And how are we representing them using
the M matrix?
>> So the M matrix is just a rotation
matrix. One could alternatively talk
think about it as multiplying a complex
number by a complex exponential.
They're equivalent ways of thinking
about it. It makes no difference.
This is just the way that makes it easy
to implement everything with real
numbers.
Okay.
Any questions about this? This part is
clear.
Good. Okay. So, this is rope. Basically,
this is uh rotary position position
encoding. I guess I should write that
FJS
are fixed
not learned.
Um and
different
channels
will
have
Different
[snorts]
time scales can be captured
by
Okay,
so that's what I want to say about
position and coding.
Assuming no more questions, I want to
now come back to thinking about
architectures. Okay, and the first
architecture that I want to talk about
is the GPT3 architecture. GPT stands for
generative pre-trained transformer.
There was GPT1, GPT2, GPT3. Now we're on
there was GPT4. GPT5
is the I guess most recent version of
this. We're going to talk about GPT3.
Okay.
So the key heart of these GP of this GPT
style architecture is basically this
transformer block with masked attention.
And if you remember when we started
talking about uh attention and
uh this translation example that we kind
of started this whole uh module with. We
said we had an encoder and then we had a
decoder. Right? If you remember the
attention is all you need paper. They
had this encoder block where you did
only self attention and then they used
that And you had cross attention with a
decoder block, right? Where you kind of
you fed in your English sentence to the
encoder. Then you had a decoder learning
basically your target language. You did
cross attention between the encoder and
the decoder to get the decoder to be
able to predict a correct translation.
Okay? So the encoder was encoding your
inputs in some sense. The decoder was
somehow representing your outputs.
So the question was how do we take this
and make this into a
generative only model in some sense
right if all I want to do if I want to
have a model that can produce strings
and streams of text how do I do that and
the idea was well let's focus just on
the decoder so GPT3 is thought of as a
decoder only model okay and it's kind of
the or one of the first generative style
models that we're going to talk about.
So, GPT3 is again it is an auto
reggressive style model in the sense
that it is it generates a token and that
is fed back into it that then generates
the next token. So, we talked about this
uh a couple of lectures ago, right? So,
you you um uh how these kind of auto
reggressive models work. So, how does
this let's just walk through this
particular architecture, right? So I
have let's say some input sentence. It
always starts with a start token. That's
always the first thing. And so your
sentence is it takes great courage to
let So I take my start token. I compute
the embedding. I compute the embedding
basically of every single word.
Here we're just saying let's assume that
all of the tokens are words. But you
know that might that won't usually be
the case. But this is just for
simplicity. Then you have this attention
layer. That's what this orange layer is
showing.
And this is now masked attention. Right?
So it's important in this auto
reggressive style model that you are not
looking at the future. Otherwise, how
can you possibly learn to predict the
next token if you already have access to
it? You're just going to copy it. Right?
So that's why every token can only look
at the path itself and the past token.
So this token can only look at the token
here. This token only looks at the
previous two. This token only looks at
the previous three. So on and so forth.
That's what these uh this is this is
showing. Then after this
you have this uh you have a
normalization layer here.
And then you have basically a feed
forward MLP.
Then again you have a normalization.
This is a transformer block. You have K
of these blocks. Okay.
Here note that this normalization is
being shown after the residual
connection. Modern architectures which
we're going to talk about later in class
do not no longer use this. And now the
convention is to normalize first then go
through the attention layer or then go
through the feed forward layer. So you
have k of these blocks after which each
of them goes through a linear plus soft
max and then you get basically uh a
probability of the next token for
everything in your vocabulary. Okay
this is the kind of key um
key thing. So for training basically
what you want to do is that you want to
be able to maximize that here you want
to maximize the probability of the word
it because you know that that's what the
next word is here you want to maximize
the probability of the word takes here
you want to maximize the probability of
the word great so on and so forth so
it's basically your input shifted by one
and now you're using that to compute
your losses to then go back uh to pass
gradients through the whole
The other advantage that I wanted to
point out is that basically because of
the uh
the way this is set up and you're
training on next token prediction, every
single token that is going into your
transformer network is contributing a
term to the loss, right? Every
everything is doing a prediction and
everything is being used to compute a
loss. And so you're not wasting any
data. You're basically making use of
every single piece of information and
data that you actually have.
So there's no encoder here. There's no
kind of English to French or Chinese or
whatever. This is just you're training
in a self-supervised way to uh get uh
the next token that you want. This is
the basics of the GPT architecture.
questions about this.
>> Yes.
>> So you just shifting by one to get your
supposed uh values or sort of like the
>> Mhm.
>> Yeah. So basically after start you
expect to see it after it you you you
compute the loss on take so on and so
forth and you're just doing a cross
entropy loss on these.
>> Yes.
>> How do you know which K
How do you know which K to use? So that
is again like a hyperparameter and as we
will see there are so many different
ways to choose. Um what did GPT
um use? GPT used. Let me see.
I thought I wrote this down. They had 96
layers. GPD3 in particular. Uh GP3 I
think this. So these are all parameters
for the GPT3 huge I think it was called
it was their largest one. Uh yes
>> um yes I had a question about the
architecture. So the block is every
block is mass attention. There's no
there's no unmasked attention. there is
no unmasked attention ever because if
you allowed it to have a block of
unmasked attention that particular block
would just you know uh see the next
token and then either it would become
useless or it would learn to cheat.
So it is required to have mass attention
for these decoder only models.
Okay.
So basically for all these decoder only
models, our focus is to generate always
the next token in a sequence. We're
always going to use this master causal
self- attention uh self self attention
training. So you're only looking at
basically yourself and the past.
I already talked about the cross entropy
loss. Um
and then so how does inference work?
Basically at inference time you're going
to sample a token from your output
probabilities, right? Then you're going
to take that sample token, you're going
to stick it back into your input and
then use that to predict the next token.
And you're just going to keep going uh
on and on. One of the advantages of this
is that at inference time, let's say
I've already computed the keys and
values for a bunch of tokens. I can just
cache these, store these, and then when
I'm doing my auto reggressive
generation, I can use them again. I
don't have to compute them again. So
there's a lot of tricks around
efficiently caching these key value
pairs to make uh inference time
efficient in terms of compute when
transformers are being used. That's one
of the big advantages of transformers.
Okay.
So this is important
from a computational perspective.
And then in terms of sampling, how do
you you know at the end all I get out is
a is a is a vector of probabilities,
right? I need to somehow use that vector
of probabilities to generate an actual
token that I'm going to feed back in. So
there are I think a couple of different
strategies that you can use. One is
simply looking at the uh you know
sampling only from the top k
probabilities. And the advantage of
doing this is that, you know, there
might be some really obscure words out
there that yes, technically have some
probability of being generated, but
they're very unlikely. And if you
generate that, then it's kind of really
hard to generate the next
token. Um, or you might have so you
restrict yourself say I'm going to only
sample from the top whatever K uh
probabilities in my uh in my probability
vector. not going to sample actually
from the entire distribution on my
vocabulary because your vocabulary can
be huge 50,000 something uh pretty
large.
The other uh key idea that is used is
called beam search and variations
thereof. So beam search is basically a
variation of best first search. So what
you do is you basically say that look
I'm trying to complete sentences right
and so you know so if I have this
sentence for example it takes great
courage after it there's some
probability the next word is takes
there's some probability that the next
word is it was there's some other
probability that the next word will be
it will there's some other probability
the next word could be it could you know
there's so many different words that
could come after it. So you say, well,
okay, let me look at, you know, some k
different options for what is the word
that could come after it. Then I say,
okay, for each of these words, I'm going
to now kind of grow my tree. Okay, so I
have
a word and then I kind of grow my tree
and then I have these next words and
then I have I can have potentially trees
going um
for for each of these subsequent things.
Does everyone see how I can look look at
this best first search will basically
say okay let me somehow come up with a
heristic some way of saying which of
these do I think is the best one and I
will expand that branch of the tree
first okay but I don't want to be doing
this too far down and so beam search is
basically truncating this to say okay
I'm going to look at some number of top
things so that I can balance my search
in a way that I'm not just looking at
the most likely thing. I'm not randomly
sampling every time and I'm keeping some
running track of what my different
options are. That allows me to, you
know, look at, well, maybe this second
word was really likely, but it led to me
down a really bad path. So, I want to in
some sense backtrack and say, no, I
don't want to choose it will. I would
much rather choose it takes and go down
this other path. And that's what beam
search allows you to do. Basically, just
think of it as a variation on uh best
first search that basically truncates
your search that you're not looking too
far. You're looking in a particular beam
direction. Okay.
So, these are two commonly used sampling
strategies and then there's many
variations thereof that you can possibly
use.
So, just to give you a sense of scale
for GBT there were the question is how
many what is K? There were 96
transformer layers, 96 heads in the self
attention layers. The dimensions of your
key value and value and query were all
128. The embedding dimension was very
large um
close to 12,000
and I believe subsequent models have
since moved to smaller dimensions of
embedding. This is like a little bit of
an outlier in terms of how big that
embedding dimension was.
um it could handle input sequences that
were uh 248 tokens long and in total it
had about 175 billion parameters and it
was trained with 300 billion tokens.
Okay, so
it was big and things only got bigger
from there on.
So this is the thing about GPT. Yes,
question. I might have missed this part
but when we're talking about like
sampling is this like the when we're
picking like what we're trying to input
or in terms of like
>> sorry so when I was talking about
sampling I was talking about how to do
the auto reggressive generation so what
GPT will give me out here
>> it will give me a it will so I have
50,000 things in my vocabulary whoops
so here I have a
50,000 length vector. So I have 50,000
probabilities that are generated and I
have to pick from that one thing to put
back in to generate the next token. So
how do I do that?
And so one way is to say I'm going to
pick from the top K like choose the
things with the largest K. But the other
strategy is to do it not just for one
token but for a few tokens, right? And
how do I choose those? I choose those
based on beam search. So I don't just
pick one immediate next best token. I
say let me pick some things. Let me
explore these trees out a little bit and
then commit to which path I'm going to
go down. So this is about what happens
at uh inference time, not at the input
time. Not Yeah.
>> So if you could construct the beam, you
would actually have to take each of the
the best candidates and then put all of
>> and put them back in. Yes. So you're
doing some generations. You're doing
multiple generations for a small amount
of time
>> and once you've explored the kind of
little range then
>> then you pick one and you commit to it
and you move forward.
>> Yes.
>> Wait, I don't know if I'm messing up my
arithmetic, but there were 98
attention heads and hidden size was 128.
How do they divide?
So I think so this is there were 96
attention heads each of which had a key
value query dimension 128. So this is
not the this is the after division
>> it was 128 not before division.
>> Yes.
>> So at this moment it does not really
answer to any problem. Correct.
>> Uh this is not yes we have not talked
about instruction tuning yet.
We will probably talk a little about it
a little bit about it when we get to the
finetuning part.
>> Yes,
>> it can still answer prompts, right? It
just wasn't super trained.
>> Yes. Okay. It can I mean it can still it
can still answer prompts in the sense
that you can put in whatever input you
want, right? And it'll continue that
input, but it's not trained to
specifically answer questions,
right? It's only trained on next token
prediction. Whereas if you're going to
do some kind of instruction tuning, you
want to mask certain parts of like here,
every token is part of the loss.
Whereas when you're doing instruction
tuning, you will change where what you
care about in your loss.
>> And uh I from the sampling you get the K
of match and how do you is there any
like human supervised learning when you
pick the last one like what is the best
like answer from these collections?
Um so the way this was done was you just
picked then um uh no was there oh I see
was there any human supervision on the
beam search?
>> Yeah yeah
[sighs]
>> I am not sure of the answer to that. Are
you sure of the answer to that?
>> Typically the issues are probabilities.
>> Yeah but I I don't know exactly for GPT3
I think that
>> it's a regeneration. Yeah, just for
generation
model didn't have a committed sampler.
Use whatever you want.
>> Okay.
>> Oh, so I don't think basically the uh my
understanding is that there was no
dedicated like human feedback in uh in
this. You just picked the things with
the with the largest probabilities and
then you could do things on top of that.
But the core GPD3 architecture didn't
use any of that.
>> Yeah.
>> So during the training time you just use
like the sentences like the words um
spoken by human beings and we just feed
it into the marketing models and then
they do guess like tokens by tokens.
>> Sorry I'm I'm not understanding your
question.
>> I'm just curious about like how it is
trained. Um we just feed them with some
sentences.
>> Yeah. So these are these the this was
fed with some like massive internet
crawl. Basically every sentence on the
internet was put into it in some
>> you just like guess token by token to
get the maximum entropy.
>> It it gets token by token to minimize
the cross entropy loss.
>> Oh okay. Thank you.
>> Yes.
>> Just let me try the size. So is that K
the same thing as like the 96 layers or
>> that K is the same as the 96 layers.
Yes. Correct. This is 96.
>> I know of each within each block. You're
saying there's also 96 attention heads.
>> Within each block, there were also 96
attention heads. Yes.
>> Yes. Okay.
Great.
If there's no more questions about GBT,
I'm going to move to now our next I'm
like running out of time. Bad.
Um, okay. I'm going to now move to Bert.
BERT. So we talked about GPT which was
the decoder only model but BERT is the
other side which is the encoder only
model. What if you wanted to train
something to get really good embeddings
so that you could then fine-tune this to
do some many different kinds of language
tasks, right? And that's what led to uh
BERT.
So you want to basically learn this kind
of general information about the
statistics of language and then use
fine-tuning to adapt this to solve a
specific task. And so this is basically
the encoder part of the encoder decoder
architecture that we talked about first.
And so how am I going to uh think about
this? I'm going to think about basically
you you you pre-train this thing and you
do um
masking of the words in your input
sentences for training this. You're not
training this to do next token
prediction. You're training this to
predict masked sentences within
the input itself. So here you're not
going to be using uh causal or mass self
attention. Here you're using full self
attention just like you would in an
encoder in the encoder decoder
architecture. Right
here you're allowed to look at the past
and the future. Okay. So for example
here my input is something like
the and then I mask this pulled into
mask station.
This goes into a transformer layer
and then basically now this token was
the one that was masked
and here I'm going to have a cross
entropy loss that is going to uh on the
value of what this mask token is.
Similarly here
on top of this mask token I'm going to
try and predict what the next what what
the word that should be in uh filling
that blank. Okay.
Typically I think it's like 15% of the
of the tokens in your input are masked
like some something like that. It's a
small it's a small fraction. It's not
very large.
this the important thing is that you
always use this what is the convention
is to call this a CLS
uh and that's kind of that's the token
that's the parallel to the start token
but in BERT
uh the start token is not always just
for a sentence it's kind of it could a
sentence could be a a group of sentences
you could have a CLS and then several
sentences and then a CLS and then
several sentences and in BERT two
different sentences basically anything
that in English we would separate with a
period or a full stop is separated with
this se token. Okay, it's separated to
separate sentences.
And this is important because in
addition to the cross entropy loss on
the masked tokens,
there is a secondary loss that BERT is
trained on. And this B this secondary
loss is called uh is is is about is next
sentence prediction or sentence
adjacency prediction. So what bird does
or what bird did is that you have your
you have your training data and I have
my stacks and stacks of sentences. I
take them and I mask 15% of the words in
this. Then what I do is for some other
small fraction of sentences I swap the
order of the sentences. Okay? Because
what I want Bert to learn is I also want
Bert to learn that there is a natural
order to sentences you know like some
things you know uh some things come
after
other kinds of things you know
so for example
um what what we'll do is that there's
sentence A sep
might be the natural the real order of
how the text is written but Instead,
what we will have is we will swap the
order and then what BERT or what the
model is trained to do is on that
separator token, it predicts if these
sentences are in the correct order or if
they're in the wrong order.
Okay,
it turns out that this that's how BERT
was trained. It turns out that this
sentence order doesn't seem to actually
matter and subsequent versions uh of
these encoder only models don't
necessarily always use this loss but
that is how it was historically trained
because they saw in that model it
actually did make a difference.
>> Yes.
>> Do they predict like all the mass tokens
in one shot or they predict them mass
tokens like token by token?
um you predict them in one shot
essentially you because this is all
happening in parallel.
Yeah. So on the mask tokens basically
everywhere here where there's a mask
you're predicting the probability of the
mask token. But let's say one of these
inputs was a
se right this ended the station. The
mass pulled into the station and then
there was a period. So there was a se
here and then a next new sentence
started here. On top of this separator
you would look at um this sentence and
the next sentence and you would say are
these in the correct order or have these
been swapped?
Make sense?
>> Can we only just understand like as a
data version of GBT?
>> No it is not. It is fundamentally
different in two ways. One is that there
is no auto reggressiveness here. Second,
it is not using causal self attention.
It is using necessarily
like full self attention, right? It's
looking at the past and the future.
>> So yes, there's a transformer
architecture, but
>> yes,
>> uh you say we predict the masks all at
the same time, right? So would it how
different would it be if we predict some
of the mask and use it as input again so
we have a more complete synthesis and
then predict the rest of the mass
>> you could you could do that and that
would be more like a decoder style uh
architecture that is not what BERT did.
>> Yes.
>> So how exactly do you test bird whether
or not the next sentence was the same or
not? Like does it have a token that it
sets to one or zero? So you basically
have you have the ground truth, right? I
have I'm looking at Shakespeare. I know
which sentence came first. Just in my it
uh in my input to the to BERT, I have
switched them. So then I can I can
compute the loss on that token.
>> Does BERT have like a token that it
outputs then that says whether or not it
can switch or what does it output?
>> No, you're just computing a loss on that
SE sept token. So you know you know what
the like you say zero if it's in the
correct order and one if it's flipped
and so you know whether what what it
should be and so you again you can
comput a cross entropy loss on that.
>> Yes. I'm not sure if the question really
makes sense, but like when we have like
with the auto encoder of having both
encoding and decoding, but now we're
kind of like separating it, right? Like
is I was wondering if you could explain
more about the difference of talking
about training loss based on both the
encoding and decoding which is like one
at a time.
>> So these are all different kinds of
tasks, right? The encoder decoder
architecture was for a translation task.
BERT is used for just understanding
something about language so that we can
take language convert it into these
useful vectors and then use these
embeddings for doing some other
downstream task. So for example, so
BERT, what they call it BERT, you don't
say you're training Bert, you're
pre-training BERT and then you fine-tune
BERT to do your particular task. And for
that fine-tuning, you will take
embeddings that BERT has generated. And
you could take the embeddings from the
last layer. Sometimes you take
embeddings from some other layer. But
what you're doing is you're saying like,
okay, now I have let's say I want to do
a sentiment analysis kind of task. Okay.
So here the example, this is all from
Prince. I have the sentence here.
The soup tasted like socks. Okay. And I
want to now understand is this a
positive restaurant review or is this a
negative restaurant review. Okay. So the
way that this will be done is that you
will use this CLS token and on this CLS
token you will predict whether or the
review is positive or you'll predict the
probability of whether this review is a
positive review or a negative review.
And so you will take the embeddings from
BERT and then further you know add a um
maybe it's a feed forward layer forward
layer maybe it's a linear layer whatever
you want and train that to use those
embeddings
and learn whatever task you want to do.
So, another example of uh a task that
you might want to use bird embeddings to
do is something like,
you know, here uh Zara works at uh
Chanel in Victoria.
So, I want to figure out what type of
word this is. I want to understand this
is a proper noun. This is a verb. Um and
I want to understand what entity this
is. I want to understand that this is a
city or this is a place. And so what I
can do is again I can fine-tune this so
that on each of these I learn to predict
the probability of the entity type.
Okay. So these are just two examples of
many different things that you can do
downstream from the BERT encodings.
That's why it's an encoder only. It's
not meant for it's giving you an
encoding that is useful for you to then
do other things.
Does that help?
Whereas GPT kind of will it just
generates stuff for you. There's no
add-on that you're going to add on to
it. It is complete in one in that sense.
Okay.
Other questions?
>> Yes. Uh so the star token is uh I think
it's it's wrong because in the class
token it contains the information.
>> I'm not sure I understand.
>> Oh I mean the last slide you said the
class token is the start token. I mean
it's it's saying that this is the start
of a new like you know if I'm if I'm
somehow chunking my
input into this is one group of things
next group of things next group of
things each of these so for example if
I'm going to do a downstream
classification task um these clss are
telling me what is my sentence
so clss are can can be between things
that are bigger than sentences they may
not be bigger than sentences but they
could be bigger than sentences.
>> Yes,
>> we're talking about CLS is we're not
referring to the input character. We're
referring to like the embedding of the
CLS character.
>> Is that what it's giving us our actual
like classification or decision
information?
>> So we will have the input embedding of
the CLS character which will just be
some learned embedding of that CLS
token.
But then when we are training the loss
we will look at if we're trying to
predict like if we're sorry when we're
fine-tuning if we're trying to predict
whether this is positive or negative we
will compute a loss on the
output corresponding to the CLS token
on whether the probability of the review
or was the review positive or negative
make sense?
Yes.
>> Generally, do we train BERT like one for
the class level prediction, one for the
word level prediction or do we just
train B once and we use it for
>> So, you train BERT once and you don't
use the CLS token when you're training,
right? When you're fine-tuning, you will
then fine-tune it to do
sentiment analysis or to do uh entity
type prediction and so on and so forth.
I guess maybe clarif
do we tend to fine-tune two separate
models or does fine-tuning to make a
good prediction on the sentence level
for a positive review generally also
mean it also does a good job um
producing like word level
>> no you would do separate these are
separate fine tunes you will not do them
together that you yeah
>> yes
>> so the set token isn't actually is it
replacing punctuation or is the
punctuation remain in the tokens
themselves?
>> Punctuation remains in the tokens. This
is in addition.
>> Okay.
>> Yeah. Because punctuation could like
there could be a question mark that
could appear. You can't replace all of
that with
sets.
Okay. Okay. So now
um I want to tell you about one more
thing that's different. Now this is
completely switching gears. not talking
about um
transformers
for a little bit but if you remember
when we talked about mamba right and
state space models I showed this picture
everyone remember that and um I wanted
you to ignore this part of it then and I
still want you to ignore this but now
what I want to focus on is this chunk
>> [snorts]
>> Okay, this block and what is this gated
uh linear unit? Okay, so gated linear
units are things that are often now
being used to replace or instead of the
MLP feed forward layer that comes after
attention. Okay. And it's a simple idea.
It's basically saying
that whatever your input is, put it
through two linear layers. Okay?
Then put one of those through a
nonlinearity.
Take the product of them and then put
that through a linear layer. And because
you're taking the product of two things,
one of which you're putting through a
nonlinearity, it's called a gating
because this is gating. Basically this
might set a bunch of things to zero for
example if it was irrelevant right so
this multiplication is this gating and
so this is called a gated MLP okay so
this is instead of a fully connected
feed forward layer and so in mamba for
example we had this uh linear layer then
there was a small convolution then there
was nonlinearity then you had your uh
state space model and there was this
gating ing essentially where you had
this the same input going through
another linear layer going through a
nonlinearity and then you take the
product of these two things before going
to the output. Okay. So, and you notice
here there's no uh I don't have an MLP
that the output of this SSM is going
into. Instead, I have this connection
here. Okay? And this is what is called a
uh a gating
And so there's many different
nonlinearities that that can be used
here. You can use your favorite
nonlinearity, but there's a couple of
different ones that have kind of
um
become popular or useful. So a gated
linear unit when it was the kind of when
you think of gated linear unit, it's
classically defined as the following. So
I have this linear layer. So x is my
input and so I take a linear layer which
is just wx plus b. And I have this other
linear layer which is just vx plus c.
One of them I pass through a
nonlinearity for a gated linear unit.
That nonlinearity happens to be a
sigmoid. And then I take a product of
these two things. Right? So
this is one path. This is the other path
and then I take this product here. And
that is what a gated linear unit is.
Since then there have been many
evolutions on kind of how to choose
which nonlinearity this is. One
nonlinearity that is popular these days
is what is called the u swish
nonlinearity which leads to the swigloo
unit. Okay. So it's swish plus glu is
swigloo.
Swish is basically saying let me take x
time sigmoid of beta x where this beta
is now a learnable parameter.
Okay. Um,
and one of the nice things about this
swish is that it looks kind of like a
relu, but it doesn't have the sharp
elbow at zero. And so it looks kind of
like
um
and it looks something like this.
My drawing is not so good. Um, sorry, I
forgot to put a picture of this up, but
if we have time at the end, I'll pull
up. There's this really nice blog post
about this that actually I can show if
we if we have time at the end. But so
it's like it's kind of like a relu. Um,
you know, it's it still has the x as x
goes to infinity, this goes to uh
infinity.
And this beta here, this is learnable.
And as beta changes basically if you
choose beta to be equal to u zero you're
just going to get a linear function
right and as beta grows uh you can make
this look like different shapes okay
so this is just a simp this is the idea
of a gated linear unit that I wanted to
bring up why do people well not people
but why do um
why do these work there's this paper uh
on exploring some of these
nonlinearities.
And actually, I think it's worth pulling
up this uh quote. Let me give me just
one minute to do this.
Uh I meant to copy it and I forgot.
Okay, so this is the last this is a
paper by Noam Shazir from Google
and the conclusions of this paper say
we offer no explanation as to why these
architectures seem to work. We attribute
their success as all else to divine
benevolence. [laughter]
Um
so that's just this is it's the last
sentence in the paper. It's a very
short, sweet, four-page paper that kind
of explores many different variations of
the nonlinearities on these and
concludes that the swigloop kind of
works the nicest.
Uh, and this has kind of become it's
become a sort of a meme uh within the
within the community. For example, I
think if you remember Muan
and the blog post of Muan that kind of
launched Muan quotes this article as
saying, you know, hey, I
yes, you came to this blog post to
understand why Muan works. But again,
remember that a sufficient explanation
would also be divine benevolence. Um, if
you if you go look up Keller Jordan's
blog post, he also he also quotes this.
So anyways, I thought that was worth u
worth reading out. So these work,
they're nice. But there is one intuition
for why they work. And a subsequent
paper found that actually instead of
looking at this gated linear unit, if
you look at a squared relu that allowed
you to do a basically peace-wise
quadratic interpolation instead of
peacewise linear interpolation
that can often perform just as well as
uh some of these things. One of the
things that you see with these gated
linear units is that they make doing
things like multiplication much easier
to do than with just simple values. And
so if you look at some of these papers,
there's some nice examples of how uh you
can easily get or more easily get
multiplication out of uh things like the
swigloop than you can with uh just
straight relu based nonlinearity uh
MLPS. Okay. So this peacewise
quadraticness offers some advantages and
that's one intuition for why these seem
to work better.
Okay, the last thing I want to touch
upon before we can get to understanding
this quen is
yet another architecture for what are
called mixture of experts models. Okay,
so the challenge is that you know MLPS
are great but they use a lot of
parameters and compute at inference time
right if I have these wide networks they
often like you go to 512 then you expand
by four then the number of hidden units
then you come back down so there's a
there's a lot of parameters uh a lot of
the parameters in the models are hidden
inside the MLP feed forward layers okay
so can we somehow
you know, do better by specialization is
the key idea of the mixture of experts
type of models. And these ideas have
been around in the community for quite a
while, but only recently have there been
tricks and optimizations for training
these mixture of expert models that make
them competitive with the standard dense
MLP models.
So the key idea of mixture of experts
models is to say that look for every
single token maybe I don't need to go
through activations for every single
uh unit in my MLP right maybe some
tokens can be processed some way and
other tokens can be processed other ways
and I can just keep parts huge parts of
my network quiet when processing certain
tokens right so there's the idea that
there might be some experts that can
deal with some tokens and other experts
that can deal with other tokens so that
I can not have to use all of my network
for processing every single token. Can I
somehow efficiently route my tokens to
the right part of the network? And these
right parts of the network were thought
of as different experts. That's kind of
the key idea.
And so I'll show you pictures from kind
of two key papers in this in this space.
Uh so this is uh from this paper by uh I
think William Fedus and I think Noam
Shazir is also an author. This is also a
paper that came out of Google.
So this is this idea of a switching
transformer, right? Basically you want
to switch where your tokens are being
routed to. So I have a token and you can
tell need to be on who [laughter]
um I have a token and you can tell kind
of you can date this paper
uh in some sense because it's still
using this additive uh positional
encoding
you have a self attention layer you have
this normalization layer and then
instead of having an MLP layer here what
you have is you have many small
smaller MLPS which you call each of
which an expert
And you have a router network here that
decides, oh, should I go here or should
I go here or should I go here or should
I go here? Okay, so every token, so this
token gets a different routing compared
to this token which gets a different
routing. Okay,
so there are two key challenges here.
One is how do you figure out how to
route, right? Like that's the important
thing. Um and so this router is also a
trained layer and it's basically a
linear layer that produces uh
probabilities on which expert a
particular token should be routed to.
Okay. And this is also trained along
with everything else.
One thing that people noticed was
important was at initialization you want
to have the probabilities for each of
the uh experts to be kind of roughly
equal. You want to make sure that no one
expert is being chosen too often at
initialization. Otherwise, you're not
going to you might you might end up with
um bad training.
So there here this switch transformer um
there's a mixture of experts paper that
came before this. I'm skipping that kind
of but that said let me just route to
one expert at a time.
There's another important thing to see
here. So for example, if I generated
that this should go to expert 2 with
probability 65
my output here I'm multiplying by this
65 that allows gradients to come back to
this router network so that this can
actually be trained. Okay, so I'm
choosing one expert. The switch
transformer said choose one expert,
multiply whatever that expert says by
this probability and that's kind of your
your output.
Building on this and kind of there's
been a lot of work uh there's now this
open mixture of experts model that came
out of uh the Allen Institute I think.
Yeah. Almoe E. And so now there let's
look at kind of the uh this is a nice
figure I think. So here this is kind of
a standard dense language model
architecture. So I have an input now you
can see this is a newer paper because
the norm is coming before the multi head
attention whereas here the norm is
coming after the multi head attention.
I have this multi attention and then I
have basically this MLP or this feed
forward network right here. Here we
instead replace this with this mixture
of experts where I have this router.
This router then chooses which experts I
want to go to and then goes forward.
Unlike the switch transformer which
routed to one expert,
here
I'm choosing some top K experts and I'm
routing to all of them and then I'm
combining their inputs in a linear
combination
with the weights given by the
probabilities with which each expert was
chosen. Okay. So if if I think that I
should go to expert one with high
probability, I weight the output of that
expert with that high probability. But I
I also throw in some other experts that
I'm choosing with lower probability with
appropriately lower weights.
Make sense? Yeah.
>> If you choose to give an expert with
let's say probability P, do you always
choose it with probability P or is it
like sampling from a Bernoli with
probability P? Um
there are different options. Um this one
I believe just chooses the top K, but
there are many many many different ways
in which you could do this.
>> Okay.
>> Um I I'm I'm sure that there is a
version that does what you suggested,
but I don't know what it is off the top
of my head.
>> Yes. So is mix mature of experts really
like better than a normal key for
network or is it just to improve like
>> so so the advantage of m mixture of
experts is now there's huge parts of
your network that are not being
activated at inference time right and so
from a compute perspective it is
definitely better the challenge is that
there these things are trickier to train
um and training these routers and
getting all that correct can be can be
hard so there's for example example. I'm
not going to have time to go through
this, but there's kind of many different
options of which you can go through of
how to train this. Yes.
>> Is this like a low direct approximation
for like a very large V4 layer?
>> You could think of it that way. Yeah.
>> Yeah. In some sense. Yes. Are there also
potential benefits? Kind of like the way
we thought of like multi-headed tension
where you're like potentially breaking
it up to try to introduce specialization
or like mixture of experts actually is
better and not just like a cheaper
alternative.
>> I think that is a very possible
thing. I do not know that we as a
community know that yet but uh maybe we
do. I think basically 2025 is the year
that we are seeing mixture of experts
type models incorporated into the kind
of latest releases. Until this year, I
don't think that there were many models
that incorporated these kind of layers.
And so coming back to this for example
Quen picture.
So what you have here
is now a hybrid architecture, right?
So what this is is this gated delta net
which I'm not going to have time to talk
about but you have a homework problem
that talks about uh linear attention.
This is a variation on linear attention.
It's basically a state space style
model. Okay. So think of this as a state
space model with some tweaks on mamba.
It combines ideas from Mamba with ideas
from linear attention. Uh following in
that same philosophy of work that we
talked about before we talked about
transformers. And so there's three of
these. And then the fourth one is a
classic attention type layer. And both
of these instead of having a feed
forward layer here, they're putting a
mixture of experts layer here. Okay. And
so now if I look at this gated delta
like what is inside this gated delta
net? Well, I have I'm computing my keys
and values. I'm doing some small maybe
convolutions here. This is a
normalization layer. Um,
this goes into this. Think of this as a
state space model. And then I'm going
out and here what you see is this is my
here I would expect maybe to have a MLP,
right? If I had an attention layer
followed by an MLP like a a classic
transformer would have an attention
layer followed by an MLP. If I think
about the state space model as replacing
the attention layer I would expect to
have here a MLP but I don't have that.
Instead what I have is I'm going through
this linear layer followed by a
nonlinearity. I have a gated linear unit
here. Okay.
And now if I look at that attention
block up at top again you see I don't I
have my attention
over here
there's no way I can reach up there but
over here you see that
this is again now I'm using a gated
linear unit instead of having an MLP
which would be here in the traditional
transformer architecture. Does everyone
see that?
Okay. And this is just basically scaled
dotproduct tension. The other thing I
want to bring to your attention here is
these this is using now a position
embedding called partial rope. What it
is doing is it's saying that of my I
have a query vector of some size
the first 25%
of that vector I'm going to do rope on
and the rest is just nope.
So I'm doing a mix of these things.
Okay. And somehow this is what they see
worked best. So here they're using
partial rope. Okay. So there's it's yet
another variation on um
on this um
I guess I don't have enough time to go
into the delta rule to tell you but
these are this is basically like it's
like a momentum like memory parameter
alpha and beta that's telling you how
much I want to care about the past.
Think about it as a recurrent network
that's or a state that's being updated
constantly.
And then I definitely don't have time to
go through these but
these are basically the a series of
recent models that are coming out this
year. So we can just pick a couple. So
for example, if you look at llama 3.2 uh
1 billion parameters again you're seeing
rope, you're seeing the RMS norm. So
this is kind of a little bit uh standard
here though. You're seeing that in this
feed forward layer again you're seeing
this silo activation which is again a um
variation on the swigloo where you're
pegging beta to be exactly equal to one.
Uh what's another example to show you?
Here you're using rope. Here you're
using
you're using a combination of nope and
rope. Some layers you're using nope.
Some layers you're using rope.
This one is so this quen architecture uh
these larger trillion parameter models
or multi-billion parameter models. I
don't know why this isn't moving but
yeah
okay here I don't know if you can read
this but here now these this is now a
mixture of experts layer in both of
these the Kimmy and the Quen models.
So here you have a router. In both of
these cases, this is using multi head
latent attention which we haven't talked
about but maybe we will talk about. It's
another modification on uh multi head
attention where you're doing some smart
caching and you're not uh to make things
more efficient. But as you can see
there's no like specific there's no one
right way, right? There's so many
different choices and this parade or
frontier of what the models are is still
being investigated, understood, but at
least now when you look at this picture,
what I'm hoping is that you can figure
out what each of these particular things
is or if you if it's not something that
you've already seen, it's a variation on
something you have seen and it is not
impenetrable. Right? That's the goal of
what we're trying to do is like whatever
is the most recent stuff. I don't want
anyone snowing you with jargon, right?
Like this is all stuff that is
understandable.
Okay, so I'll stop there. Sorry, I'm a
few minutes over.
>> Just want to double check the experts
are they are they trained individually
for the downstream task and then we just
choose some of these.
Are the experts trained individually for
the downstream task? Um, no. They're
just trained.