finish up uh graph neural nets and move
into RNN's. Just a comment on where we
are relative to the reading. If you
think about the Prince uh textbook,
uh chapters through chapter 11 is all
the connet stuff. Chapter 13 is the GNN
stuff. Nothing in this lecture is in the
prince textbook um at all. The older RNN
material that I will be hope getting to
at the end is you can find it in this uh
textbook the deep learningbook.org.
This is an older textbook but the
coverage of the classical RNN material
is quite good.
Uh so but the perspectives we'll be
giving here are definitely different
than the classical perspectives. So
the project information I know I said
that I'd announced we'd have the
information up on Friday. There was a
little bit of delay. We'll it'll go up
today but a couple of key points that we
wanted to just make sure everyone is
aware of by announcing them in lecture.
The project has many many different
stages uh for of things you have to do.
The
proposals from you uh and teaming in
groups of four will be due on November
3rd. So we'll give you details of what
you're supposed to write in that
proposal. Um you'll have to do work to
to make that proposal. Ahead of that
November 3rd due date, the week before
we have required meetings for all of
you. So every project group has to sign
up for a meeting slot. come to office
hours or sign up for a slot that will
make available have signups available
for you to talk ahead of your proposal
and then you will have submit your
proposal and then there'll be another
meeting with the TAS the following week
the week immediately after the proposal
submission for you to get some feedback
and to discuss because the process of
writing the proposal and thinking it
through helps you understand what needs
to happen. There will be other
deadlines. In particular, a draft
report, final report for your project
will be due the week right before
Thanksgiving. You will ask be expected
to do peer review and then you'll have
time between that and the last day of
class to actually finalize your project
report.
There will then be a a poster
presentation you can do in RR week in
this slot. Okay. Okay, so this is like
all this will be outlined in the post,
but I want to make you aware of what
things are coming on the project.
Okay, so you know we're going to be
transitioning from graph neural nets to
RNN. So just we just uh continue with
the RNN GNN discussion. So everyone
remembers we want to generalize
convolutional net ideas to graphs. We
figured out how to generalize many
ideas. Um we saw that if you had
directed graphs with edge labels, we
were good. you could just use everything
you learned for a CNN. U
but there was one exception which was
you didn't know what to do about pooling
and downsampling that we said there
seemed to be no uh general solution that
wasn't problem specific.
So then we said look we talked about
this case directed graphs with finite
set of edge labels for which CNN ideas
would just generalize directly and but
the hard thing was this corner which was
undirected graphs with no labels and
that's what we said okay you have to
somehow use the information in the
vectors uh and the neighborhood
structure to make your decisions. So we
followed that and we said look you know
just thinking through different things
you could do making certain choices of
how things are allowed we got to some
architecture like this that is one thing
you could do there's many things you
could do but wanted to help you think
through how the constraints of what
you're allowed to do force you to think
about the actual range of possibilities
okay and then using analogies to things
you see in machine learning
okay So now we want to talk about the
thing that did not generalize which is
pooling and downsampling which is a key
challenge.
So as we talk about this the first thing
I want to do is to ask this question why
do we pull anyway? What was the point of
pooling? So this is like a
okay someone we talked about having
downsampling and pooling. What was the
motivation we had for introducing
downsampling and pooling?
>> Yeah.
>> So lowering the resolution is what
downsampling and pooling does. But why
did we want to lower the resolution
while we were doing processing? What was
the point of doing that? Yeah, in the
back.
>> So one possible solution is that this
would make let us use fewer parameters
to process a down sampled image.
However, what we saw that we did was
whenever we would down sample, we would
add more channels. So the actual
parameter count needed to process all
that stuff was not really going down
because we had already had weight
sharing across space. In fact, it seemed
to be going up.
Okay, so the it wasn't a parameter count
motivation for for doing this. So who
who remembers why do we do down? Yeah.
>> Okay, great. So this was the idea that
we wanted to capture attributes of the
image that existed at a larger spatial
scale. And to have larger spatial scale,
we had to have receptive fields that
were large enough to capture that scale.
And if we did that using only small
cons, we would need lots of layers to
get receptive fields that big and it
wouldn't really be capturing the
inductive bias we wanted, which is to
actually capture a bunch of stuff in a
larger way. Downsampling allowed us to
do that. Okay, so if you think about it,
let's say
use a different color.
We want to grow the receptive fields.
faster
with layers.
So what that means you want so we
translate this idea into a graph. Okay,
let's translate this idea into a graph.
In a graph the same principle might be
useful. It is the idea that on a graph
when you're passing messages, right,
which is what we said you're going to be
doing. Everyone looks at their
neighbors. Uh
it takes you a while to get any
information from far away in the graph.
It has to go through many many many
steps of processing before it gets to
you. Same as in a connet having 3x3 cons
only grows the field by one every time.
So if you wanted to get information from
a distant part of the graph to make it
available, you want to do something. Did
everyone see that? So that's that that
motivation doesn't go away just because
we're in a graph neural network. And
that motivation remains one that we're
generically interested in. Lots of
different problems might want to have
this kind of global structure available
to us.
Okay. So if you think about it, uh
there is one solution to this problem
that I want to mention before we talk
about it's very natural in the graph
neural net uh that's different than what
we would do in a connet.
Okay. So if you wanted to have
information come from far away in the
network and be visible to you,
we can do something different because
the graph we we did a graph neural net.
We chose to do the processing in a way
that respected the graph topology
because we thought the graph topology
was useful. Same as in a content
but we get to choose what the topology
is for processing.
So unhack.
So let's describe it as a hack
hack
for GNN's.
If it's taking a long time for
information to come from distant parts
of the graph, we can add a node that's
connected to the entire graph.
Okay.
Add a fake node.
So, does everyone see the idea here? You
want information to flow from far away
to you. So you say everything
there's a fake global node that has been
added. It wasn't in the original graph.
It's added. It's connected to
everything. And so in one step of
processing one layer all the information
will flow to the global node. Then in
the next phase all information processed
aggregated in some way at the global
node will then flow back to everybody.
Everyone see this at at the level of
receptive fields just thinking about
where the information comes from. This
solves the problem because now the
receptive field is everything at after
layer two.
Okay. Any questions on this as a hack
idea?
Yeah.
>> So, great question. Okay, so you a
couple of different questions here. So,
things I'll parse them out. First
comment was, do you really want it to
suddenly have it be everything in the
graph? This is like at a generic graph,
there's two things that you have access
to. local structure because that's
visible in your graph and everything
right there's nothing intermediate
whereas in images you have a natural
sense of okay like down sample it by a
factor of four this is you know like
local structure but not very far does
everyone see that so this is a very
coarse instrument
that it just says okay we can just get
to global which might not be what we
want if we wanted to have intermediate
level things be uh discovered that are
useful for processing for generality on
this graph. That was point one. Point
two that was made was that
if you introduced this global node and
you had embeddings let's say that were
threedimensional
at some point what is this global node
going to do with information that's
coming from a thousand different nodes
in the graph?
It has to squash all of that information
down into a three-dimensional embedding
that will then go out to everybody else.
Does everyone see this second point?
Okay, this second point is actually a
generic problem in graph neural networks
and it's called oversquashing.
Okay, literally that's the term it's
called overs squashing.
So aside talk about overs squashing.
So overquashing refers to the problem of
lots of information that you want to
collect into one place getting squashed
into a smaller dimensional embedding and
therefore lost. So you can't you in
principle can see everything far away
but all the details are gone that you
need because everything has been forced
to go through a small dimensional
embedding. Does everyone here understand
the kind of vague idea of it?
So in graph neural nets there's two
problems. One is the overs squashing
problem which is that too much
information flowing through a bottleneck
gets squished down and details get lost.
And another problem is called over
smoothing which we talked about before
which is that because of the limits on
what you can do you end up just doing
averaging averaging averaging and
smoothing things out. Okay for example
we talked about if you don't have the
ability to know which is your right edge
versus your left edge you can't detect
an edge in an image in a because you
can't tell. All you can do is average
and smooth things out.
So these are two uh sort of general
challenges with the
the GNN.
>> Yes.
>> So
seems like sort of implicit in what you
just said there was enough.
>> So that's a great question. The question
is I I kept saying because of small
embeddings and there's this challenge of
the idea that maybe you can solve this
by making the embeddings larger. In
fact, in graph neural nets, people do
try to make the embeddings larger.
Embeddings larger come with the standard
cost and constraint that one has in
neural nets is that you're adding a lot
of channels. Because you're adding
channels, you're then going to add lots
of parameters associated with those
channels. And sometimes what this can
result in is overfitting type problems
where your data you have too many
parameters too your embeddings are too
large and you end up not learning the
pattern you want and instead memorizing
your training data. Okay. So that that
concern remains although we've told you
there's lots of things about the way
that gradient descent works that
automatically tries to seems to mitigate
that a little bit more than you would
learned about in your standard uh ML
class but it's still a concern. Uh there
is a very interesting area of thought of
how can you modulate the size of the
state with the size of the graph to try
to control this problem. This remains an
active area of research. How do you
combat the overs squashing problem and
how does that couple together? In fact,
remember we said before, we're going to
talk about transformers later, but one
way of thinking about transformers is
transformers are just graph neural nets
on a complete graph. So all these ideas
that we're talking about also have
counterparts in transformers because
transformers really are just graph
neural nets on a complete graph.
Okay, so this is one idea. Yeah, go
ahead. Question.
Ah, great. So, when we do pooling, we
downsample the image. And so, suddenly a
3x3 conveled
has an effect as though it was actually
a 7 by7 con on the original image. Of
course, it's a very structured 7 by7 con
because it only can do one thing on the
neighbors, but it's it's like a bigger
con. So, does you understand that part?
Because you're you're working on the
image smaller. So, 3x3 is actually
reaches out further than the original
image.
So, that's what I meant by it grows the
receptive fields faster.
So for GNN's you can grow the receptive
fields instantly to everything by adding
a global node and
but that doesn't give you the
intermediate thing. So a brief aside
before I continue on this is that this
idea of having global nodes turns out to
be so useful that even learned systems
sometimes end up doing this. So we'll
talk about it later but uh in
transformer type networks sometimes
people have found that the models learn
like you don't they don't have any
global nodes but they learn to use other
things that are present in the training
data as though they were global nodes
for collecting information.
So sometimes transformer networks
trained on text will use things like
start of not can't use start a sentence
because of certain other reasons but
they'll use like punctuation
and they'll say ah here's some
punctuation great I can collect a bunch
of stuff here and then come back and
look at this information on this
collected global node and sometimes in
vision problems they'll find boring
scenes of images like plain sky and they
say oh good this is a good place to
stick uh a bunch of like scratch work uh
you know like collect collect global
information into one place. So people in
when studying interpretation have found
these kind of behaviors from learn
systems in graph neural nets the idea of
adding uh fake global nodes is done
explicitly by adding explicit global
node.
Okay, so now we find ourselves in the
situation that
okay, we can get information to
everybody, but is there a way of getting
information to kind of pull to something
natural to the topology of the graph?
Okay, that's the problem. So you step
back and you say, what do we need to do?
We need to go from many nodes
to few nodes based on what? Based on
vector contents inside the nodes. That's
all you have generically. You have
connectivity information as well. Okay,
but you have to do it somehow based on
this uh uh vector contents.
So now
let's just think about it from
your machine learning class.
Have you seen any problem in your
regular machine learning class that seem
to be about going from many to few
where the
so in in multiclass classification
the few are already determined at the
beginning. There's cats, there's dogs
and so on. So this is not like that.
This is I have many things. I want to
group them in some way so that things
are fewer.
Okay. So who's seen this? Shout it out.
>> Clustering. Yes.
Okay. So this is like clustering.
which is an unsupervised learning
technique you learned.
So let's recall a classical
uh clustering approach Kines also called
Lloyd's algorithm for vector
quantization
which you've presumably everyone has
seen. How does it work?
It says you do this procedure.
You have a hyperparameter choice which
is how many clusters you want. Okay, K.
Then you start at random in some way.
There's different ways of doing this
starting at random. And then you say for
each of the clusters that you've got
right now randomly initialized,
calculate centers for those clusters.
Then you take the points and you map
them to the center to get new clusters.
Then you go to the calculating center
part and repeat. Everyone remember this?
Okay, great.
So we have a generic approach to doing
clustering from K means and other
related algorithms.
So now the question is if you want to do
this as a replacement for pooling,
you have to make sure that the step
you're doing is differentiable.
Does everyone see that? So it's kind of
it's a subtle thing because in
max pooling there's you have to make
sure gradients flow back through the
pooling operation for subsampling. The
gradients flow back through it. But you
also there's not really a concern that
the operation itself should be
differentiable in what it does.
It should route gradients through it.
But here presumably we don't know the
right way to do clustering for our
problem. If we knew for this particular
graph or this particular problem domain
in advance we can construct the right
down sampled clusters then of course we
can just do that insert that for our
graph specific problem. We want a more
generic approach. So we want to care
about the differentiability.
So you ask the question is this
differentiable?
So let's just think through this.
Starting at random we don't worry about
being differentiable
for k means this look at k means itself
calculating the centers
we that's fine that's a completely
differentiable operation to calculate
the centers
what about mapping points to centers
is that differentiable
does everyone see what we're trying to
We're asking the question if I the
output of this is a map that says for
every point which one it belongs to.
Okay, so you can think of that as a one
hot vector that has zeros in a bunch of
places and ones in some in one place and
zeros everywhere else is the operation
that goes from wherever the centers are,
whatever information is inside the
vector to mapping points to the center
uh to specific centers. Is that
differentable?
So let's take votes maybe. Yeah, sake of
vote. Who votes that yes, it's
differentable?
Okay, couple of votes. Who votes? No,
it's not differentiable.
Okay, so can I hear have a volunteer in
the not differentiable category to argue
why you think it's not differentable?
So, a lot of people raised their hands.
You know, you're not alone. Yeah.
>> Yes.
>> Does everyone see that? That's a very
good intuition. It's like it's like a
step function in some way in that the
only permissible outputs are all zeros
or ones. So how do you go softly?
Okay, a little bit of change will not
result either results in no change or a
dramatic change. So this can't have a
derivative. Very good intuition. Okay.
Yeah.
>> Ah great great question. So by itself
this is not differentiable. Okay. So,
but maybe we can use softmax ideas to
make it differentiable.
Okay. So, the barrier is this hard
assignments of points to clusters.
So, if we can get around this barrier,
we're good. Okay. So, can we use a
softmax?
Okay, so that's the idea. So now there's
a couple of different ways one could
proceed. One way is to say let's look at
clustering algorithms that you or
clustering like algorithms you've seen
that already have this softer assignment
property and see if we can adapt them.
So for example, if any of you have seen
uh Gaussian density estimation, right,
where you try to estimate some density
uh some distribution of points, an
empirical distribution of points and say
let me assume this was drawn from some
Gaussian density and the Gaussian
density was a mixture of K Gaussians
that usually those algorithms usually
involve EM and they involve soft
assignments of points to particular
Gaussians.
So you could do we could go down that
that that path. We're not going to but
that's a totally valid thing to study
and people study uh clustering
algorithms like that in the context of
graphs.
Instead
we're going to follow an idea that's
called diff pool.
Okay,
which is if you want to you can look at
the documentation in PyTorch Geometric
and the paper itself is called
hierarchical graph representation
learning with differentiable pooling.
Okay, if you want to read the paper.
Um, and it's going to say when we down
sample a graph
because we're going to have to do this
soft assignment,
every point,
every node is going to belong to
everything. Does everyone see that? If I
if I soft assignment, then nothing will
be pure.
So every point will belong to every
cluster a little bit and as a result
every cluster will be connected to every
other cluster a little bit because there
were edges presumably in the original
graph. If the graph had no edges it's a
boring problem. Okay everyone see that?
So we're when we do the downsampling in
diff we're going to get a smaller graph
but it's going to be fully connected and
there going to be probabilities on the
edges some kind of weights on the edges.
Okay
so
the idea is again following the softmax
idea we're going to make every point
belong to every cluster just with some
probability.
Okay, does everyone see the objective
we're trying to do? We're trying to make
a differentiable pooling operation
because this hard assignment is a
barrier to differentiability. We're
going to have to do something soft. Once
we're going to do something soft, we're
going to end up with things being fully
connected. We just live with that. So,
we do a we go down, we'll have things
fully connected, but with some
probabilities.
Okay. So this problem is has fall this
this this this is a really interesting
algorithm to study because it ex it
shows us some design principles that's
why I'm want to cover it.
So the idea is we want to do this.
Okay, we want to do this. However, we
don't know how to do this,
right? We want to do this. We don't know
how to do this. We don't know the right
way to do this for the kind of graphs
for our application.
Everyone see that? So now what was the
meta trick that we talked about in this
class for what do you do in deep
learning when you don't know how to do
something?
>> Make it learnable. Okay. So we're going
to say I don't know how to do this. I
will make it learnable.
Okay. So how do we make it learnable?
We're going to gray box the problem.
Right? there's a problem which is
figuring out how to do the downsampling.
We're going to say, okay, this is going
to be a box. How to do the downsampling?
I'll call it a gray box because we're
going to look inside it a little bit,
but we're going to be kind of treat it
like something that should be learnable.
So, we have to understand what are its
inputs and what are its outputs. So,
think of a specific module like think
about CNN, you have a downsampling
layer, okay, pooling, we're talking
about that. What does this look like?
Well, it's going to have to have inputs
which are the graph with some embedding
vectors inside every node.
Okay, that's what it has to start with.
And its outputs has to be a klength
vector for every node with probabilities
in it.
Like for this particular node, which of
the k different clusters does it belong
to? which is not going to be a hard
decision, but it's going to be will I
belong 90% to this, 10% to this, or 9%
of this, and tiny amounts to everything
else.
Okay,
does everyone see the input output we
need from this gray box? If we choose to
decide that we're going to do something
like clustering in a differentiable way,
we want something like this.
Okay,
questions?
So we'll give it a name.
For node I we'll have an SI which I'll
think of as a row because it's
probabilities P1 through PK.
Okay.
So I need some differentiable operation
that does this
that goes from a graph with embeddings
to vectors like this.
Does everyone see that? Okay.
Now
the key thing is to say
what are my ingredients that I'm going
to use.
I know how to get to probabilities. I
have a standard way to get to
probabilities which I compute linear
scores of some kind and I softmax them.
Okay. So I'm building this gray what
what I put inside this gray box. So
it'll end with some kind of scores that
go through a softmax that give me this.
Okay.
So now what do I know? I have a graph.
That's my input. It has embeddings in
it.
I will want to have k scores for every
node
that I'm going to then run through a
softmax.
So
stepping back, this looks like what kind
of a problem? This looks like a node
level classification problem on a graph.
Everyone see that
I have an inter. So I start off my big
problem remember is I have a graph
neural net for some problem. I want to
tell if chemicals are smelly or
different tasks, right? Could be graph
level, could be node level, whatever.
In between I want to do pooling. Looking
at this in between problem, I have a
graph
problem that's node level
classification.
So I ask myself, how do I do problems on
graphs?
Given a graph, I need a different set of
steps to give me scores. But I go, oh, I
know how to do this. I have to make it
learnable. So what's a generic way to
have a learnable algorithm on a graph?
Anyone?
What are we talking about right now?
We're talking about graph neural nets.
If you want an alertable algorithm on a
graph, you make a graph neural net. So
we reduced the problem of doing the
pooling part to saying I want a graph
neural net.
So inside my big graph neural net, I'll
have a little graph neural net whose job
is to do pooling.
Okay, questions.
He said like look when we have the graph
we have the connectivity of the graph is
used to pass messages the information is
inside the embeddings but presumably to
do the clustering the positions meaning
the connectivity matters if you want to
do clustering well how do we know that
the information we need to do the
clustering is actually present inside
the embeddings everyone get that really
good question. We're going to end up
solving this problem in two ways. Um,
what we're going to do is we're going to
a hope the information exists.
Okay? And B, we're going to set up some
auxiliary losses during training that
will encourage the network to make sure
that information exists.
Two different things. Okay. But the hope
is very important in terms of how we do
it. We're not going to engineer the
information into the graph embedding.
There are ways to do that to try to
engineer the information into the
embedding. Um we'll talk more about that
when we talk about transformers. But
here we're going to use this hope and
then uh encourage method.
Okay. So the answer is
use a GNN.
Okay.
So now what we're going to do is we're
gonna make this a design choice. Come up
with a GNN. So what's what does it mean
to come with a GNN? It means come up
with some kind of information
aggregation algorithm with learnable
weights have some number of layers pass
messages and do that. We're going to let
that be a black a box right now a design
choice
like how you do it. So practical answer
go look at other people did copy their
poolings and use them right but they're
going to be learnable parameters inside
this GNN
and the end of that GNN will be a linear
thing that generates scores based on the
embeddings followed by a softmax to
generate the probabilities we want
then we'll drop that in. Yeah.
Yes.
>> Excellent. So that now comes the
question, how do I actually use this
information? So I'll talk about that
next. Like how do I how do I given that
I have probabilities? How do I get
information into a node?
Okay, so that's what we'll do next.
So we have these soft assignments into
clusters,
right? We need new vector embeddings for
the S for the clusters, whatever the
clusters are. I think I used K here. So,
let me fix this.
So, the answer is pretty
straightforward.
The natural choice is if I have
probability of membership.
So every node has a probability of of
being in different uh clusters. It can
just take its embedding and split it ac
across the probabilities into the
different clusters and sum things up.
Everyone see the natural choice. You
think of it as like you take the
embedding and you pour it into the
different clusters you belong to
according to your probabilities.
So the hidden for J is ranging from one
to K over the clusters at the next layer
layer plus one is whatever it was before
at the previous layer times the
probability that node I belongs to
cluster J
from the softmax.
Okay, so this is the
formula you'd use.
So now all of the embedding information
that was in the original graph has been
poured into these K clusters.
So I have new embeddings for this K
cluster, these K clusters.
Any
questions on this? It's like a natural
choice to do. Clearly nicely
differentiable
as an operation. Just you're keeping
track of operations. As an operation,
this is a mild nonlinearity. It's a
product,
right? So, it's going to send a gradient
back to this and to this
Next thing you'll notice, let me see. I
don't know if I
Yeah.
Notice that as a operation, remember the
entire gray box has this behavior.
So this gray box when it has gradients
on this, those gradients will go back to
the node.
Right? Did you see that? According to
this probabilities,
so it's like it has the same routing
property of gradients that max pool does
except it's soft.
Okay.
So in particular, one doesn't have to
worry about having a residual skip
connection over this. This is already
giving you something that routes
gradients nicely. Yeah. Question.
Ah, great question. The question is, is
the clustering GNN, the GNN we're just
talking about, is it frozen during
training of the main GNN? No, it trains
with the main GNN.
You you choose its architecture and you
might initialize it based on information
from other related graphs. That's all
fine. But you let it tune for this
family of problems during training.
So that's the So remember this is
sending gradients nicely onto this, but
it's also sending gradients into these
S's. And these S's are the outputs of
the little GNN inside. So it's sending
gradients gradients are going to get
routed into that uh little GNN and that
little GNN is going to have updatable
weights and so on.
>> Yeah.
>> So are these new clusters the new
the connection.
>> Yes, the the the clusters are the new
nodes.
We're down sampling. We started with a
big graph that had n and now we have a
little graph that has k. The original
graph had some connectivity structure
with some adjacy matrix and this one has
a new connectivity structure with a new
adjacy matrix. Except even if the
original adjacy matrix was filled with
zeros and ones, this one is going to
have adjacency matrices that has
fractional values in it.
Okay? Okay. So, it's a soft adjacency
matrix.
Yeah.
skips.
>> Yeah, great question. So, when we talked
about the skips for when you do the
downsampling, we said that was important
to do when you had a bunch of operations
together in a block that were doing the
downsampling like for example a strided
con.
But we made the there's a little
exception which is if your down sampling
is just a clean subsample or a clean max
pool nothing else entire block just
consists of a subsample a max pool or an
average pool then that little tiny block
that only does not require a skip
because it by itself routes gradients
nicely.
So that's the special case from before.
And so this entire diff pool block
behaves like an like a max pool visav
routing of gradients and does not
require a skip across it.
>> Yeah, just this connection. So here you
have the small graph with K nodes and
here you have the big graph with nodes.
Just this does not require a skip.
Okay, so let's think about this. Our
original adjacency matrix at layer L is
N byN.
I need to have something which is K by
K.
So in interest of time I can just show
you the answer, right? Basically I have
something that's n byn. I need to get it
to k by k. I have to ask myself what k
byn thing do I have?
Does everyone see that? Like I only I
have limited choices in what I have to
work with. The only k byn thing I have
is this s. So what is the s
It's all those probabilities.
I have n different nodes in my original
graph. I have probability assignments
for them. I call them little srposes,
stack them up, and I get an S matrix.
So then if I want to get something using
this matrix
that has k by k size starting with
something that's n byn this is the
natural operation just on getting the
sizes to work.
Okay this is just getting the sizes to
work.
So inside this matrix aig
represents how strong we want an edge
between cluster i and cluster j.
Once we went to soft assignments to
uh clusters, we're going to get soft
edges.
That just happens. Fortunately, having
soft edges is not a big deal for us
because we know how to adapt our
algorithms to having real number, single
real scalar numbers for the edge. We
just multiply the message on the edge by
that number. So you look at the
embedding across the edge. You just
scale it by the strength of the edge.
Okay. So
now we have a way to get a new adjacency
matrix for our graph. So
we have a GNN. To summarize, we have our
differentiable pooling operation has
going to have soft assignments. So it's
going to have the output of the GNN
inside of it is going to give
probability assignments for every node.
From that we will get soft edges for
between our K by K graph. Everything
will be connected to everything else
just with different weights and we'll
get new embeddings for everything. So we
can continue doing GNN processing after
this point.
Okay, so you get something that looks
like this.
Here's our graph neural net. We have
some graph processing layers with skips
on them.
Then we have a diff pool.
So we have a I'll label the size of the
graph.
So this is nodes.
This still has nodes.
Here we have k nodes.
This continues on.
Then there'll be some output layer and a
final loss.
So for GNN training, what happens is the
loss will send a gradient back. It'll go
back back.
It will then go inside the diff pool for
the little GNN sitting inside here and
it'll also go out back here.
This path through that routing will also
send gradients back but also through
this will send route gradients back.
Okay, so this is the strategy. So first
practically speaking when diff was
introduced it was the first really
practical
uh pooling mechanism that moved the
needle quite substantially on many graph
problems since then there have been
other and modifications of this but I
think from a design point of view I want
to present this idea
so we can just train this end to end but
remember this thing you the question
that was asked is this thing really
needs to have
information about the graph structure
and right now the information about the
graph structure isn't really present in
this end training. So you think about it
random initialization this is doing
potentially a really bad job of pooling
the network into clusters
and so everything from here is like not
very good gradients.
So just end to end training might not be
giving the gradients you need to get
this thing to learn how to do its job
which is presumably to reflect something
about the graph structure. So we're
going to use a trick which is going to
we're going to use the trick of adding
auxiliary losses. So, so far when you
think about auxiliary losses,
these are loss functions you add during
training that are not the thing you're
actually interested in, but are there to
help training. So, you've seen these
things so far as regularizers,
right? You add some penalty, an L2
penalty or something to regularize
training. But that's only one sense. You
could do other things too. And this is
an example where doing something is
useful.
So what does this represent? The idea is
we know something about what this thing
is supposed to be doing. We have some
idea for what are desirable properties
of this.
We can add losses
to training that encourage this thing to
do the right thing, what we think think
is the right thing. And that will
combine with whatever end to end losses
and gradients are coming through to
hopefully encourage the right behavior.
So
what are some of the properties we want?
One property is we want to have the
clustering respect the graph topology.
That's the big idea. Clustering should
like have something to do with the graph
topology.
So
let me just uh use an example here.
Okay. To say how how to do that. Okay.
So let me I guess I'll this is the kind
of loss one can use but this is by
itself is a bit hard to understand. So
let me just walk through it and I'll
give do an example.
Okay
if you want clustering to respect the
graph topology presumably the A matrix
has to figure into the loss. Does
everyone see that A is the graph
topology the adjacency matrix.
Okay, so I have the A matrix,
but the other thing I'm going to need is
something that the A matrix
something that should be like the A
matrix, right? If I want a loss, I have
this thing I want to aim for respecting
the graph topology A, I should have
something that's like it that has to
depend on the output of diff.
The output of diff is basically this S
matrix.
it gets used in some way but it's
basically the s matrix is the thing that
the graph pool the graph neural inside
is outputting.
So then I have a and I have to do some
loss on a that's related to s.
So one way of getting guessing this kind
of loss is just do the same kind of type
adjustments. A is n byn
right? S is has K and N in it. So I
can't subtract S. That would be like
type mismatch.
So I think of what operation can I do to
get something that's actually N byN? And
S SRRPOS is N byN.
This might not satisfy you as a
justification, but you should understand
that this is actually also a
justification.
I need something. I have this. I need
something of this size. Let's start with
what I have. I have S. Does that work?
No. What's wrong with it? Wrong shape.
What can I do with the shape to make it
the right shape? This.
Okay. Does this make any sense? Maybe it
does, maybe it doesn't. But at this
point, I can try running code
as a phil. It's important to internalize
the deep learning ethos. Okay.
So, while I'm sitting down trying to
think about it, I shouldn't let my GPU
be idle. I paid a lot of money for that
thing, right? Go try this.
Did it help? It helped.
That's good enough. Right? Even if it
doesn't make any sense. Very important.
Okay? But let's also try to understand
why this might make sense.
So, Here's
a little contrived example
of a graph
for which we know we have an idea of
what the right idea of cluster should
be.
Okay, does everyone see this little
graph? I just made this to illustrate
what's happening. You should always do
these kind of examples. So here I have
three nodes connected to each other.
Three nodes connect to each other and
these two groupings of nodes are
connected with a single edge. So
intuitively if I tell you please cluster
this into two clusters, these should be
a cluster and these should be a cluster
from the topology point of view. Does
everyone see that? Okay. So now let's
see how does this manifest in the
adjacency matrix. And as soon as you see
how it manifests in the adjacency
matrix, you'll then believe why this is
a good idea.
So what is the adjacency matrix for
this?
So one, two, and three are all connected
to each other, right?
Four, five, and six are all connected to
each other.
Does everyone see that? And now four,
three and four are connected to each
other specifically.
Okay. Everything else is zeros.
Everyone see this is the adjacency
matrix. Now when you look at this
adjacency matrix, what adjacy matrix is
this almost like?
Right? This adjacy matrix is almost like
an adjacy matrix that doesn't have these
yellow ones in it.
This has a block of ones, a block of
ones, zeros and zeros.
But that matrix is visibly low rank.
Do you see that? Like very very visibly
low a low rank matrix.
So that suggests ah wait a minute. If I
want to approximate A with something
that's kind of low ranky, that might be
a good idea. Once you start getting to
low ranky, you look here and you go, ah,
SSRpose, this is low rank because it has
a bottleneck of K, right? What is
SSRpose?
Show here. Remember this is S. So
this is
like that.
So this is a K little bottleneck of K.
So this is going to be a low rank
matrix.
So this example tells you, okay, this
makes sense.
So if this is going to have assignments
across clusters
that are probabilistic, you're going to
get most of this most of this and you'll
get some stuff here, you know, in these
spots in SSRpose
for a good basically matches this to one
and this to
>> Yes.
Yes.
share roughly the same
high.
So the SST
>> um so we can talk more later. I'm not
100% following your question
specifically, but
what this is saying is that what this
example is trying to illustrate is that
if if all of these vectors had S's, if
all these nodes had S's that basically
assigned them to one cluster and these
assigned to the different cluster, then
what you would get is just these ones
and just these ones. you wouldn't get
you'd get all these zeros and you
wouldn't get these things would also be
zero in that case.
So in that sense the rightish answer is
close. Okay. Now you're asking the
question if these were probabilities
generic probabilities why would you get
things close to one? Is that your
question?
Oh, no you don't. Okay, so that's a good
question. You don't, right? Because um
if you have two entries that are similar
to each other, right? That doesn't mean
you're going to have to get a
a one
in that position because probabilities,
if you take the even if you were doing
an inner product of probabilities. So
first let's look at it. You get inner
you're saying this thing is like
pairwise inner products of the
probabilities. So two probabilities that
are the same are going to be behave the
same way. But probabilities inner
products aren't necessarily going to go
to one.
Right?
Good question. It'll go to one if it's
one zero but not otherwise. But you
Yeah.
>> Okay. Yes.
In this matrix, we're saying that every
>> Yes, every node is connected to self. We
just make that assumption. Every
>> Yes.
>> So, just to follow up on the previous
point. So, we're just is the reason why
that's okay that they're not it's not
actually one. It's just that we're
trying to get as close to one as
possible.
>> We're having a loss that encourages it
to be close to one. So we say if we can
encourage this to be close to this
that's is doing the right kind of thing
in this example things that are natural
clusters
will emerge
will get rewarded by this kind of loss
that's all we're doing this is a
heristic loss that we're making okay so
the second property we want is we would
like the cluster assignments to be as
close to hard assignments ments as we
can make them.
So we don't just want to we want to
respect the graph topology and we would
like to make nodes mostly assigned to a
a single cluster.
So we need something that will make have
that property and here's a way to do it.
We just take a sum over all the nodes of
some on a probability vector that
rewards
hard decisions.
Okay. And entropy has that property
as an example. Entropy is maximized when
sorry is minimized whenever all the
probability is in one place and there
are zero probabilities elsewhere. That's
the entropy minimizer.
So if we put entropy penalties on these
vectors that will encourage them to go
closer to one somewhere and zeros
elsewhere.
So this is like another matter of saying
well I have this property I get because
remember I I started off wanting to do
clustering and I found just for
differentiability I couldn't do hard but
I still would like to do it as close to
hard as possible. So this property
emerges naturally. Then I look in my bag
of ingredients and I say is there
something that likes hard decisions or
you know happiest and hard decisions
maximized minimized. Yes I have entropy
just use it.
So I think people saw entropy when you
saw decision tree uh generation probably
in your um for doing the splits where
you wanted purity of splits you were
using entropy to kind of reward purity
class purity uh in a in a split.
So same kind of logic applied here.
Okay. So to summarize what happened. So
now I have these two auxiliary losses. I
add them during training. And now I have
a different pooling method that is
learnable called diffpool.
Um and to summarize the story we started
off over here. We knew how to do that.
We said okay we can talk about this if
we don't have pooling. But once we have
pooling, we move into this infinite edge
labels that are scalar case
but just fine.
We know how to deal with that.
Okay. Any questions on diff. Yeah.
>> So in particular weights on edges. So
let me mark make a note of this.
scalers,
the scaler weights. Why? Because our
adjacency matrix isn't 01. Our adjacency
matrix has fractional or other numbers
in it. So how do we use how do we take
advantage of that? The easiest way is
any embedding that goes across the edge
just multiply it by the weight inside
the edge. This is not a learnable
weight. This is like a a label, right?
Just it's just a fixed aspect of this
topology.
That's a way of taking information
across the edge naturally.
>> Yeah.
>> Yeah. So, it's a great question. There
there are approaches to doing pooling
that
are not learned that are tied to a
specific application. So it says that
I'm just going to execute the following
uh algorithmic clustering and
downsampling of the graph. That's
application specific. So you can think
about CNN's as having done that. So CNN
say look I know images every other pixel
is a good way of downsampling.
So it just you just do it. Same thing
for any graph. If you have a knowledge
of this family of graphs and you have an
algorithmic thing that you believe is a
good way of downsampling the graph, you
can just drop that into your network.
You just do that. Um, and then you still
what that does is basically instead of
having a graph. So this remember what
does this graph gen what does this thing
do? This thing generates
S.
The operation of the graph neural net
inside here just generates S. So if you
have another way of getting S which is
assignments like how do I assign this
node to a cluster
then go ahead and use that. You can
still do these operations to get new
embeddings and new adjacency matrices
for the new graph
except the inside of that operation will
not be differentiable or not something
you want to learn. That's also fine. I'm
talking about the a gener uh something
you can use if you don't know what to do
uh specific for your application.
So this is useful also to help think as
an example of how does one think about
these kinds of problems. How to follow
the example of I don't know what to do.
Make it learnable.
I I have an obstacle. This is not
differentiable. How to break that
obstacle? Make it soft. I get a method.
I can train it end to end. It might not
do exactly what I want. Well, I can add
auxiliary losses to get what I want.
These are generic ways of thinking. This
approach helps you see that.
>> Yeah.
>> Excellent question. So remember all
losses are used when one is doing back
prop
right. So
they are they're done that way. When in
forward operation of the network they
don't do anything in the in back prop
they exist as losses. Now
you can say am I adding them to the
final loss? In a way yes I'm adding them
to the final loss and so there's some
hyperparameter of how much I weight
these different auxiliary losses which
has to be tuned for the problem. Um
however these losses look inside the
diff pool and they look at the A and the
S
right so they are looking at things that
are different than just the output of
the network so in that sense they're
attached to the diff pool itself
>> um okay it's a great question how do we
illustrate this idea a of putting a loss
here. Okay, great question. So let's
think about it from the so use this red,
right?
So this is the loss. What we do is we
say
just attach the auxiliary loss here from
a picture point of view. It's not going
ahead to the end loss. This is the loss
on the output. So we call this is the
output loss, the normal loss.
We just have another loss. Stick it on
here. When you do gradients, all losses
will push flow gradients back. So this
flows a gradient back and this will also
flow a gradient back. So this thing's
gradient will flow back into here to do
two things. It's going to say to the
learnable weights inside of here, do the
right thing. But it's also going to flow
back over here to say hey put the right
kind of information in the embedding so
that this thing can do the right thing.
>> Yes, excellent point. So everyone heard
that the key word is important linear
combination. Remember the whole point of
backrop and the chain rule is that from
the derivative point of view everything
is linear. All the backrop operations
are linear. There's no nonlinearity in
backdrop. So because all of the backdrop
is linear, superposition of losses
works,
right? So you get this linear
combination of the the gradients seen
here are superposition of the gradients
coming from this auxiliary loss and the
gradients coming back from that loss.
Great question.
Okay,
so I got through this more slowly than I
thought. So I'll finally want to come do
a couple more little points from GNN's
before we finish off GNN's.
So
there's
one final challenge in GNN's which is
how to think about held out data. So
I'll go through this pretty fast. So
held out data is absolutely required to
do machine learning, right? You have to
have held out data. You need held out
data to do validation. You need held out
to do testing. You need always have held
out data.
So in images, how do you do held out
data? You do held out data by holding
entire images out.
Everyone with me?
Okay. in graphs because we have the idea
of node level problems we have other
things we can also hold out and this is
particularly important when you're
studying a given graph so if you're
studying the Facebook's graph which is
Facebook's network it's not like
Facebook can hold back a separate
Facebook graph
it just has the real Facebook graph
so you have to figure out how to hold
out data on a single graph so the First
approach is during training you excise
entire nodes from the graph.
Just remove them from the graph.
They're held out. You bring them back to
see what does the learned algorithm say
predict for those nodes. But it wasn't
trained on them. They're gone.
Everyone understand this as a highle
approach. Just like if you want to hold
something out, just remove it.
Okay. The challenge with this is this
impacts connectivity
because remember the gra the nodes in
the graph are doing double duty. They
have information in them but they also
have connections and those connections
are used for information processing.
The example that makes it more easy to
see is if you're doing held out nodes in
a chemical graph, if you just removed
atoms,
right, completely
that's like very bad, right? You really
are like changing the structure of this
thing quite substantially. So you can't
you're messing up the graph topology.
So what else can you do? What you want
to do is you want to remove the content
from the node
like get rid of the content
but I want to leave the node in
okay so I want a node that's emptied of
its content.
So
you had
a node connected to various things
and had some vector in it.
I want to replace this with
the same connections
but with nothing inside
spiritually. Everyone see that
problem is we what's nothing
right how do I put nothing inside the
node because the operations so I can say
I simply have nothing there to which
point I'll get a null pointer right and
I'll try to reference information for
doing a matrix multiply and there'll be
nothing there and fault
I can't do nothing there's no such thing
says nothing. Does everyone see this?
It's like a might be annoying, but it's
a real problem.
So, what do I put here?
Okay, did everyone understand the
problem? So, there's a couple of
choices. One is to do the kinds of
things that you might have seen. I don't
know if you've seen it in your machine
learning class. The idea of like imputed
values. Do you see imputed values? Who's
who's seen imputed values for where
you're missing data?
A few people. Who has not never heard of
imputed values? It's totally fine if you
haven't. Okay, great. So there's a set
of methods that people have for when you
have missing data, which is to say,
well, if I'm missing data, replace it
with an average. Um, replace it with
things like that. Those kinds of
approaches are possible. But in the
context of graph neural nets and the
context of machine learning, we have
another choice that we all we often try
to prefer especially when you have lots
of data
and that is
what should go in here. I don't know.
Make it learnable. So make this a set of
learnable parameters called mask.
Okay.
This is like mask from masking tape
where you put like for painting
something you put masking tape down so
the paint doesn't go there like remove
something like it's that that's that's
the sense of mask not wearing a mask on
your face mask although I guess that
would work too. Okay, but
this is just a value that says nothing
here.
and it's a learn value. So during
training, you make sure that you mask
out lots of values during training so
you can learn what mask is and then you
have other held out data that's always
masked and you you let it figure out
where it is. Yeah.
>> Ah great question. So this is a
learnable vector which means it's a set
of parameters. What's the loss? Whatever
loss you have during training.
So if it's a node level problem,
right? If it's a node level problem, you
might have a node level prediction
problem.
Okay? So in a a a node that has been
masked
on purpose during training will still
have its loss
during training.
Okay, so everyone see the value like
this is telling it look when you see
mask figure out what should go here.
Okay, now a node that is actually being
held out is going to be masked but will
have no associated loss during training.
it will just be masked
but there'll be no node level
supervision telling it for an output.
the way you held out data. Way you hold
out data. You don't have any training
loss associated with held out data.
But additional things that we mask so
that we can learn what masks should mean
during training is an augmentation of
adding of masking data that is done that
has a loss.
Okay, great. Okay, so that's all I
wanted to do about uh
uh GNN's. I have five minutes. I will
introduce some RNN's stuff and then I
will continue this uh the next lecture
but okay so RNN's are a very interesting
story so you might ask why is there no
section in prince about RNN's like I we
we chose the prince book after looking
at all the deep learning books we could
see and we thought that was the best one
to recommend to you guys to read except
it has one shortcoming it doesn't have
RNN's so for this a little bit of
history is useful
So before 2018 there was a consensus
view in the community that there's two
big successes in deep neural networks.
Images in vision using CNN's and
language and speech using RNNs. RNNs are
recurrent neural nets.
In 2017
the attention is all you need paper came
out and transformers were introduced.
And what happened was that transformer
architectures introduced originally in
the context of language and then moving
into speech uh slowly consumed
all of the success stories that used to
be success stories of R&M. And so there
was a time let's say
the year before last okay
at which point many people thought that
okay this was these are just uh
consigned to the dust bin of history
right they exist for maybe historical
purposes but no one needs to know them.
A small group of people kept working on
this direction and now if you look as I
mentioned before the latest Quen and the
IBM uh foundation model both are open
source and visibly have evidence of
ideas growing out of here in the new
models. So
you we can't count them out. But the
Prince book was written with the idea
that okay we're just going to count this
out. We have to make choices that's out.
That's why. Okay. So, what's the big
picture here?
The big picture is we've generalized
CNN's to graph neural nets to any graph
topology.
But that doesn't mean that you just
treat all images as though they're
graphs,
right? You taking advantage of images is
still useful. So the key issue in
language and speech along with control
and time series data is that they're
sequential.
You can there's like a one-dimensional
topology associated with it that has
ordering
and also has a natural causal dimension.
Stuff language kind of is a little weak
on the causality but still kind is still
definitely there. But stuff in the past
has a different relationship to the
present than the future.
Okay? Because we're embedded in time.
Time is very special.
So RNN's were saying R CNN's are like
fundamentally about space
and RNN's are fundamentally about time
is a way of thinking about it. So from a
signal processing perspective
you can think of it like this
in signal processing there's two major
families of filters that one can use
there's fir filters finite impulse
response filters to which the neural net
counterpart is CNN
and this has corresponds to weight
sharing across space
and There are also infinite impulse
response filters
in signal processing which despite the
word infinity still have a finite
characterization except that finite
characterization is in terms of a finite
dimensional hidden state.
Okay.
And these filters their counterpart in
neural nets are RNNs and the weight
sharing is done across time. So that's
the big picture of what's going on and
the approach that we follow in thinking
about RNN's is we follow all the design
ideas and principles we have from CNN's
to the extent we can and we just replace
space with time and enforce causality.
So it's really RNN's are about causal
through time which means you're allowed
to depend on the past you shouldn't
depend on the future.
Okay. And so next time we'll go into
this in more detail and work it out. The
discussion will have you think as a kind
of a exercise of thinking about backrop
uh when you backrop across time. So
there'll be a little bit of a review but
it's just basically backrop on in the
discussion for you tomorrow to get you
ready for this. Okay. So uh I have
office hours now. My office hours are
just going to be till 1 because I have a
oneoff meeting at 1 that will force me
to end office hours early.
How