Okay.
>> Okay. Let's start.
So,
we we're going to change gears now. uh
the optimization now you know a lot of
the core uh optimization ideas modern
perspectives um I wanted to acknowledge
one thing which is I think we we
mentioned this in the post now you
understand a bit about what we were
saying in the first lecture that we're
going to be introducing material to you
that's pretty uh up to date um as a
result of this as we mentioned many of
the homework problems we have from now
onward that have coding components
don't necessarily acknowledge either the
MUP perspective or the muon perspective
on how to do optimization. Um it's too
much for us in our limited staff to
actually update everything. So that's
why that we have that other
participation option for you to you know
take it on yourself to say okay how
would you add a muup or a muon engaging
part to this uh coding problem and
that's one of the reasons we're doing
that so you can share with your
classmates hopefully after the last
couple of lectures this that makes more
sense to you than it probably did at the
beginning of the uh of the class that
we're going to have this partic
particular way of participation. Um
before we move into the topic I wanted
to also acknowledge uh the you know the
text we recommend and we often like
we'll show figures from it which is
Prince's understanding deep learning
book. So in case we haven't been
mentioning it but in case you want to
know what you should have read up to um
it's basically you should have read up
through chapter nine uh of that textbook
in terms of what we've covered uh so
far. Of course it doesn't have coverage
of uh mup and muadan and all of that
that perspective is not in the textbooks
yet. uh we're going to be engaging with
connets uh now and that's chapters uh 10
and 11. Now for the connet engagement
this is more stable uh material uh
that's well understood. So the textbook
is is is quite good in terms of engaging
with it. There'll be some added details
we'll talk about in class but mostly the
textbook is quite good.
Okay. So uh now many of you when you
walked into a deep learning class maybe
were expecting to learn about lots of
different deep learning architectures
and we did say we were going to do that
but we wanted to make sure you had the
foundations first of being able to
actually engage with what's going on in
the optimizations and so on so you can
appreciate a little bit more what's
happening with the architectures.
Uh so the architecture order we're going
to be taking in this class is you've
already seen multi-layer perceptrons you
know fully connected things that things
we've been talking about uh in class as
well as in in a previous class
now we're going to talk about CNN's
convolutional neural nets now and CNN's
are uh going to be used to both
introduce CNN's but also to talk about
many of the architectural building
blocks which will be important kind of
throughout uh all the other
architectures we'll talk about But in
case you want to know where we're going
to be going, I mean, I think it's on the
on the website, but you know, we're
going to go from CNN's to graph neural
nets and from there to uh RNN's
and we'll include a treatment of uh
state space models, which again at the
graph neural net and is partially
present I think in Prince's book. The
RNN's are not and state space models are
certainly not. Those are again something
that's more recent in their development.
But in case again for a preview of
things in case people are following
what's going on with current
developments the state space ideas are
now becoming integrated in some of the
uh leading edge models. I believe one of
the latest Quen models has a a hybrid
between transformers and state space
models as part of its structure. So
after we talk about uh state space
modeling we'll move into talking about
transformers. That's the kind of order
of architectures we're going to be
talking about uh in this class.
Okay. So it's good to you know sort of
keep in mind very high level you know
what is the difference you know between
uh multi-layer perceptrons and CNN. So
before I maybe talk about this figure a
little bit I I did want to just ask a
question. Uh how many people raise your
hands if you have seen a convolutional
neural net before in a class?
Okay, so a lot of people have uh of the
people who did not raise their hands,
how many people have seen a
convolutional neural net in the sense of
having worked with it like you played
with it in some way uh in research or
some other some other way work or
something like that. Okay. So between
those two, it's almost everybody uh in
the in the class. So,
uh, I hope for those of you who've seen
this stuff before, you will still get a
bunch out of the lectures. Uh, but we
have to make sure everyone's on the same
page. So, some of it might be a little
bit of review, but try to, you know, use
the fact that you know something to ask
good questions. Okay.
So uh if you think about a multi-layer
perceptron the kind of what's happening
in a layer one hidden layer let's say is
you have you know for example the inputs
the layer you have the outputs and you
have a fully connected graph between
them of weights and you have a giant
weight matrix that looks like this. It's
like illustrated by colors you know
darker colors are uh larger weights and
lighter colors are are smaller weights
and white is zero. Okay. And what a
convolutional neural net is at some
level is it says we're going to
specialize that weight matrix. So it's
not a generic matrix that you can fill
with anything you want, but it respects
a very nice graph. So it's the
interactions are only local. So h1 only
depends in this case on uh x x1 and x2.
H2 depends on X1, X2, X3 and so on to
three three neighboring things.
So that gives you a structure if you
want to think about it to the weight
matrix that looks like this that there's
a whole bunch a sparse structure there's
a whole bunch of zeros where there's no
edge in the graph. Okay, everyone get
that part?
And furthermore, there's one more thing
that happens in the CNN's that we work
with is
Some of the entries of the matrix are
the same. So in this particular case,
all the diagonals are the same. All the
one-off diagonals are the same. All the
one-off diagonals in the other one side
are also the same. They must have the
same weights in them.
So the number of distinct weights in the
distinct real number parameters in this
is much much smaller than this. So
that's another aspect of CNN if you want
to think about it at a high very high
level.
But
you know let's let's try to understand
this more
so CNN's to understand CNN's is to
understand both architectural principles
for neural nets but also ways of
thinking that get gives rise to
architectures and the historical
perspective CNN's can be helpful in
understanding uh how how that happens
how people thought about something asked
how can I use a neural net to do this
and came up with architectures
So CNN's definitely grew out of one
particular uh domain which is computer
vision uh computer vision problems and
computer vision problems are problems in
which you have images or video and you
want to do something with them. Okay,
that's computer vision.
So the classic computer vision problem
that we're going to also kind of focus
in on when we uh talk about CNN's in
terms of motivation is you know
classification.
So you're given a picture and you have
to tell whether it's the digit zero the
digit one the digit two the digit three
four five six seven eight or nine. Okay,
that's like for example, if you ever
used saw the emnest data set which we
have uh had you play with a little bit.
Uh you know that's what that data set
is. So that's a kind example of vision
problem. You have a picture in the case
of emnest a grayscale picture and you
have to give a class classification for
it. CR10 is another uh data set that
we've had you play with and that's a
data set in which you have again a small
image uh and it's in one of 10 classes.
Okay, that's the classification problem.
Uh
there's more kinds of problems in
computer vision than just
classification. And the other one we're
going to be using later to kind of talk
about architectural principles that we
don't we can't get at just using
classification is the problem of
semantic segmentation. So this is a
picture out of prints
uh for semantic segmentation where you
can see here hopefully everyone can see
I'll zoom in right you can see a scene
and the scene has been with given
stylized colors. So the fact that
there's a a blue couch doesn't mean that
in this scene the couch is supposed to
be blue. It's just that the everything
that is couch has been colored blue and
everything that is table is this
particular shade of green. And so
different kinds of things are have
different colors as a way of
representing what the computer vision
task here is which is to label not the
entire image but to label every pixel of
the image to say what kind of thing is
this pixel a part of. Does everyone see
how that's another interesting uh
computer vision problem?
So we'll use this later to talk about
architectural principles we don't get
from just uh thinking about
classification problems. But computer
vision is a broad area. There's an
entire class on computer vision that
many of you are taking which has an
unfortunate time conflict with our
office hours. We know this. Um and you
know so this is not a computer vision
class. However, you will have to learn
some computer vision kind of along the
way.
So here it's important for a little side
digression is useful
which is there's a few problems in the
world that or families of problems that
tend to drive at least currently a lot
of progress in the deep neural nets
area. Computer vision is one of them.
Another is natural language processing
and to those are the two big ones and to
a lesser extent you have a lot of
progress uh being driven uh through
thinking about control and robotics but
this distant third uh to these two uh
big ones. So as a result if you want so
suppose you yourself say I don't care
about any of those completely reasonable
to not care about any of those however
you still have to know a little bit
about them. Why? Because many new
advances will come out in papers that
are rooted in one of those uh domains
and you have to be able to understand
enough about the domain to be able to
get at the idea you want. So suppose
you're interested in know certain kinds
of you know problems about molecules.
Great. You have to be able to read read
a paper uh about natural language
processing enough to see okay here's the
technique. Can you adapt this to your
molecular problem? Okay. So that is the
limit of our goal in telling in teaching
you anything about vision or about
natural language processing is to
hopefully get you enough so that you can
then read a paper with the assistance of
chat GPT or something else to get the
rest of the context to be able to digest
what you need to get. Okay, that's
that's our goal. This is not a vision
class. It's not an NLP class.
There are other classes that are fully
dedicated to those topics. Okay. So now
the other key thing I want to talk about
uh that drove the development of CNN's
is the nature of the inputs we have. So
we have images. So what's an image? So a
grayscale image is a grid of pixels
filled with you know particular values
for the pixel how bright or dark it is.
A color image looks like this. It has a
height. It has a width. And it has three
distinct channels. The red channel, the
green channel, and the blue channel. For
example, there's also other color spaces
which are also useful and interesting.
And computer vision classes will might
talk about how do you exploit those
appropriately.
But the kind of object it is is like
this.
It's a array
presented to us that has a height, a
width, and a number of channels.
And what we're going to do in CNN's is
we will build neural nets that take
these kinds of things as their basic
objects and we'll try as much as
possible to stay within this kind of uh
domain for as long as possible before
they have to go to some other domain. So
a classification problem cannot be
expressed this way. Right? Right? If you
want to give an output of this is a dog,
this is a cat, this is a banana, this is
a horse, that's not naturally, you know,
an array, it's like a a vector of scores
associated with each class. So we'll
convert to that at some point, but CNN's
as long as possible stay in this kind of
zone. Okay, so that's a bit about CNN's.
Okay, now I want to talk about at a high
level certain key ideas and I'm going to
divide them into two categories. So here
I'm just going to
the first category is expressivity. I'll
call it expressivity which is what are
the kinds of things that we want to be
able to express with our CNN that we
believe are relevant for vision
problems. So the architectures every
architecture can express certain things
and it can express certain things easier
and other things potentially harder. So
the idea the thinking here is whatever
the kinds of
things that are that we would like we
believe are relevant for understanding
the patterns associated with images we
would like to make those easy for this
CNN to express and therefore learn.
That's the thinking. So the first idea
I'll use a different color.
I don't know if that's a different
color. Um the first idea
is locality
and the idea here is that the order of
the pixels matters. If you take an image
and you shuffle the pixels, so take all
the pixels and put them into a different
place. You've all played that little
game with puzzles, right? You take a
there's a picture, there's a bunch of
squares, you like move the squares
around, you you quickly get something
that doesn't look like anything. So a
random permutation of pixels doesn't
look like an image. That means there's
something about the spatial arrangement
that matters. And in particular, the
view is that the very local arrangement
of p of what's going on in a in an image
matters. So people who' worked on
computer vision for a long time thought
that there are things like edges and the
edges in an image are very local.
They're having with contrast between
pixels right next to each other. So this
idea of respecting locality was a design
principle that they wanted. And what
does this end up having as a consequence
of thinking about this is the goal? We
end up
have having a convolutional structure
with small filters.
So again the history of this is that
people when they were doing image
processing
before CNN's would use convolutions as
tools for doing image processing.
Why did they use convolutions? Because
convolutions arise naturally in signal
processing and they're local. So they
would use them and they were useful. So
they were like okay let's have a neural
net that also has convolutions in it.
Now another principle
that they that people want is that
if you have an image and you do small
certain kinds of local transformations
to them it's the same image or almost
the same image. So if you take a cat in
an image and you move it five pixels to
the right, it's still a picture of a
cat. In fact, the same cat.
So this is an idea that said, look, we
would like to respect
certain
invariances.
And other terms used are Equivariances
slightly technically different and
generally the idea of symmetries
in our problem domain.
Like for example, if you translate
something an edge or a circle in an
image to another place in the image,
it's still the same circle.
Okay. So what is the consequence in
terms of the engineering or the
architecture of doing something like
this is
there's actually two different ideas
that come out of this.
The first idea is weight sharing.
Okay. So what's weight sharing? Weight
sharing is what's expressed in this
pattern here by the idea that the same
exact numbers
show up at different places
in this matrix, this larger matrix.
What does that mean? It means
practically if you've made a good weight
a set of weights that's a good edge
detector for example and it's a good
edge detector at this place in the image
it's probably also a good edge detector
over here in the image. So why should
you have to learn a fresh edge detector
over here from scratch when you know
that you just want to have a good edge
detector that works across the entire
image. So how do you translate that into
something you can do in architecture is
you say we'll just share the same
weights across the entire image and
that's what turns this uh that's one of
the core principles behind a CNN and it
says we're not only going to have a
convolutional structure with small
filters but they will be you know kind
of spatially invariant filters which is
the counterpart of like time invariance
in LTI for those who've seen it
But
it turns out that there's many other
symmetries that are present in images
that aren't easy to translate into
weight sharing schemes. So for example,
in a an image, you might say, well, it's
not only that if you translate a circle,
it's the same circle. Circle is a bad
example. Okay, let's look at a a a kind
of squiggly shape of a star. Okay, like
a a star shape. If I take a star shape
and I take the star shape and I move it
around, it's still a star shape. But if
I take the star shape and I rotate it a
little bit, it's still also a star
shape. In fact, the entire image, a
picture of a cat and a picture of a cat
taken with a camera that's slightly a
skew is still a picture of a cat. So you
might think there's other symmetries
that are present like small
that has weight sharing taking care of
the idea of small rotations.
So you need some other standard trick
that you can use when dealing with a
neural net to say I I actually believe
in some other symmetries that might
exist. And that other trick which we
will talk about today hopefully
that also comes out of uh thinking about
what you want is data augmentations.
So this is different. We all like make
it with a mark it with a a color.
This is really about training.
So this is about how can I get it to
learn a certain symmetry if I can't
build it in. So one is there's two
approaches. One approach says uh
hopefully the data will speak for itself
and will reflect that symmetry and it'll
pick it up by itself. and the other says
I'm not sure the data will let me
actually make sure that the data the
model sees during training makes it
forces it to learn this symmetry that's
data augmentation
okay
so another large idea that drives the uh
building of connets
is the idea that in vision problems you
have hierarchical structure
which is basically
parts
make holes.
So edges compose together and can form a
finger. So a finger is a whole compared
to edges. But fingers can come together
with palms to make a hand. And a hand is
a whole compared to a finger. And a hand
can come together with a forearm and so
on to come up with an entire arm. You
see what I'm saying? And lots of objects
in the real world are composed in this
hierarchical way that we can break it
down to subp parts, subpart parts, subp
parts, subp parts. Everyone with me?
This is something that exists uh in in
computer vision. and because it's
believed to exist in reality. Uh so
the question is how can we have an
architecture that
uh reflects this
and this is what leads to two things.
One is depth.
You make your model deep with many
layers. Now this grew out of what people
were already doing before in computer
vision pipelines. They would before when
everything was handcrafted, they would
say, "Well, I'll make a good edge
detector. Now, I'm going to make the
take the results of the edge detector
and collect it together to make a
subpart detector. Then I will take the
subpart detectors and I'll make compose
them together to get a larger part
detector and so on until I finally get a
hole.
So, they were already doing this
multi-stage kind of processing. So that
in neural nets became okay I will have
many different layers they'll feed one
into the other. So that's one thing that
you get from this kind of idea.
But there's another that comes along
with it
and this is the idea of
multi-resolution.
and filter banks.
So again, what does this meaning? This
says that
when you're looking at a scene and
you're looking at it at the level, so
let me I'll use the example here. Okay,
so let's me zoom in.
Oh, okay. Unfortunately, there's a limit
to how much I can zoom. Uh uh so I
didn't think this through. Uh if you if
you were to z keep zooming in, right,
and look at this little little tiny
space here,
you can't really make out at that zoomed
in scale. You're not really seeing the
hole. You see the hole when you like
zoom out a bit. Then you can see the
hole. And if you the intuition here is
that if you wanted to capture a sense of
what this image is at a lower
resolution,
this actually makes sense, you can do
that. You can have a picture and you can
have that same picture at a lower
resolution and you expect a picture at a
lower resolution will still have the big
things the same, but it might not have
all the small things.
Okay, this is the idea that you can
understand these things at different
resolutions.
So this is the multi-resolution idea
and the filterbank idea is sort of goes
along with it which says
at a very small scale. So this is maybe
coming out of even science. uh at a very
small scale the number of different
things is small
but as you get to larger and larger
scales the number of different things is
larger.
So at a small scale you might have you
know certain kind of edges certain kind
of gradients things like this but at a
slightly bigger scale you have like
little like pieces components of things
and an even larger scale you have even a
larger set of possible things you might
be interested in. So
this is the idea related to the idea
from signal processing of filter banks
that you might have a bank of filters
and the number of filters might be
different at different resolutions
because the number of things you're
looking for is different at different
resolutions.
Okay, so this is all be beame another
very key uh
way of actually doing the design of a
convolutional neural network.
So hopefully I will be able to talk
about all of these things uh today to
you know kind of flesh them all out but
I wanted to acknowledge something from a
deep learning perspective which was
that
in the early days of neural nets people
would try to apply so the all these
ideas are pretty old
right and people knew about this way of
thinking back in the 1980s
uh and they would try to make a deep
neural net and to have you know weight
sharing and I think even convolutional
structures were in the early 90s um to
try them out in neural nets but it was
very hard to get them to train so simply
having the right expressive expressivity
isn't enough you have to also have get
them to work
so there's other key ideas
which is I'll call them in the getting
it to work
and here I will list them
uh and
some of the key highlights that are
common u one of them is the idea of
normalization
So what normalization layers do is they
don't have any expressive uh capacity.
They don't they're not trying to express
anything. What they're trying to do is
to make sure that the activations and
the gradients in during training of a
neural net stay in the right place.
So you've already seen this in the
discussions when we're talking about
like MUP and muon where we said look
this RMS norm is very important and
interesting and so uh we'll see that
even if in principle at initialization
you could have a property that all the
RMS norms are nicely controlled in
expectation
uh and you could have the property that
at the first step of training all of the
updates you do will not mess that up.
uh in practice it can be the case that
as you keep training those RMS norms
will start moving and changing and at
some point bad things will happen
because if you were thinking because you
set the learning rate assuming that the
input layer input to a certain layer had
RMS norm one and you want to make sure
the update was the right size and now
suddenly the RMS norm of the input to
that layer is 100 the update is going to
be a 100 times bigger
which could then put you in the wrong
place. So in practice, getting things to
train and to train stably involves the
introduction of normalization layers.
And there's a whole story of how
normalization layers have changed. Even
the first papers in the modern current
era of neural nets had kinds of
normalization layers put in. They're not
the kinds of normalizations we're going
to teach now, but they are like the
precursors to those because of this
issue that you had to get things to
work. And this was a very very key thing
that you needed.
Okay. So we'll talk about those.
Another trick that is uh useful to get
things to work uh and to train well is
the idea of uh dropout
which is very interesting because
dropout actually neither originated
uh nor is primarily continentbased.
However, early connet implementations
and the getting Cognist to work uh
really swore by dropout that there was a
whole period in which people were
wondering do you need to use dropout or
not and then people settled on the idea
that even in contemporary networks you
use dropout in the right places uh
because it helps training a little bit.
Okay, so but that's another kind of
trick that we will talk about.
And the third very uh key idea in
getting large deep networks to work is
called
residual
or sometimes called skip connections.
So I'm not sure I'll be able to get to
these today. Um but
they are very important. They persist
not only in uh connets but in all modern
architectures.
uh and they have an interesting story
which I'll preview for you a tiny bit
here which is that you already know the
answer to this question but I will make
sure you can see it again which is
sometimes there's a tension between what
makes sense and what works
and deep learning always makes one
choice which is you do the thing that
works even if it doesn't make any sense
Okay. And so you most of the time you
can not feel this, but residual and skip
connections should definitely make you
feel, wait, this does not make sense.
This seems to violate what we talked
about up here. And the answer is yes. At
a philosophical intuitive level, it
does, but it works. So
that's more important.
Um, okay.
So this is like kind of a high level
picture again because most of you have
seen it. I wanted to organize that
different things you've seen into a kind
of framework of like what's the
difference between these these things.
Some are there for expressivity and some
are for getting things to work. Okay. So
now let's uh you know get into the uh
mechanics here a little bit.
So think about uh you know convolution.
So first thing I want to recognize is
we call them con convolutional neural
nets and they're named after
convolution. But if you go and look up
con the standard definition of
convolution, it might not agree with
what you see in a connet. So we have to
like let's deal with that squarely now.
And then from now on after this one
mention I will talk about convolution in
the neural net style as opposed to the
standard style.
So you might have seen convolution in uh
a class on where we talked about linear
time invariant systems. You might have
seen this idea in a physics class. You
might have seen it in the context of
Green's functions and solving
differential equations and stuff. Lots
of places you might have seen it. But
what how is it defined? It's typically
defined in continuous time first for
one-dimensional uh signal. And it says
you want the convolution of some x of t
and some h of t. And how do you do it?
You take the integral from minus
infinity to infinity. You have a dummy
variable of integration which takes x of
toao and then you multiply that by h of
t minus toao. Very important thing is
this minus toao.
So in LTI class you might have heard
this talk about flip and drag. one of
the signals is flipped and then dragged
across the other to do an averaging.
Okay? And
there's a nice property of convolution
that you can choose which one you flip.
It's fine. You get the same answer. So
uh you know you see things like this.
Now you can also do this in discrete uh
time which is of course relevant for the
case of neural nets. So for a
one-dimensional input, you can think of
x now at index t. So y at index t
defined as a sum instead of an integral.
And you literally just replace the
integrals with sums.
But and again the same flipping can
happen. You can choose either one to to
flip. You get the same answer.
But the case of uh discrete val time uh
is very important because it also
introduces the idea of a finite impulse
response uh case. So finite impulse
response case is the case fir in which
the filter h is only non zero at a
finite number of places. So it's only
non zero from minus k to plus k. So
suddenly this infinite sum becomes a
finite sum and you have this structure
here
where you say each of the different hes
that you have multiplies a sliding
window of x's.
Okay. So if you want to know what y is
at t, you look at the corresponding
neighborhood of x in the neighborhood of
t. K steps in one direction and k steps
in the other direction.
everyone just brings back memories if
you've seen it before. If you haven't,
it's fine. But I want to acknowledge
this. So very important point.
I will use a different color.
Pink
in deep learning.
We don't flip.
Okay, we don't worry about flipping the
filter. We say because there's a clear
distinction. The flipping is very
important because mathematically when
thinking about convolution in many
settings, you want to take this idea
that well, it's kind of symmetric and
it's two arguments and use that uh for
proofs and for other things. So, it's
very important to understand how to use
one or the other. But in deep learning
context, we always know this is the
input and this is the filter. We never
view them in the other other way. At
least most of the time we don't. So in
that case, we're not worried about kind
of thinking about the symmetry between
these two objects. So we just take the
filter and flip it and we just call that
the filter.
Okay? So we don't have any of the
flipping.
So if you look uh here at uh
this particular
this I'll make again here no flipping
prints a very nice figure where you can
think of it as you have three weights
for an FIR filter of length three. So
that would correspond to K of one one
before and one after. So if I want to
know the output
uh Z2, I take all of these X's, I
multiply them by their corresponding
weights.
And again, the weights are not labeled
the same way that you would label them
typically in uh a filtering case. In a
filtering case, you call this W0, this W
minus one or plus one, and this w + one
or minus one, depending on how you think
about it, which is natural because the
zero tells you the center. But in deep
learning, we often don't put zero at the
center. That doesn't mean the center
isn't important. It just means the
notation doesn't make it clear where the
center is.
Okay, you should still think about where
the center is. It's still very useful.
Okay, so in this picture, you have these
multiplications explicit and following
the same we think about linear layers.
Generally, we often have a plus where
you add these things together. When you
add them together, you can also add a
bias.
Okay. So
I want to make another note not note
here
can also
have a bias
which just joins in the plus same way
you think about a linear layer.
Now when you want to compute Z3
you just shift everything down.
The same W1, W2 and W3 act and the same
bias gets added.
Okay. So
any questions on this? Is this clear to
everybody what's going on? Okay.
Hopefully everyone's seen this, but even
if you haven't, this should make it uh
clear what's happening.
Okay, so there's now going to be some
details that we have to go through.
So first, is the story different in two
dimensions? The answer is yes and no.
Right? Yes, it's different because now
you're in 2D. No, in that it's the same
exact ideas. The only difference is
instead of translating in one dimension,
you're translating in two dimensions,
but you still have the idea of local
neighborhoods. And so this is a nice
picture illustrating it. So now you have
weights, but the weights aren't arranged
as three numbers in a row. You have a
grid
where there's a center weight and corner
weights, and they're all different.
Okay? So again, you multiply the
corresponding x's in the input by these
weights, add them all up, including
adding in a bias, and that gives you
your output.
Okay. So now you everyone has seen and
should understand the basic uh operation
of a convolution in a connet.
There's isn't much more to say about
this but there are some sort of little
details. Okay. So next level of detail.
What if you have more channels? We said
images tend to have for example they
come in with three channels red, green
and blue. So now what happens?
So now your input image has a red layer
uh sorry a red channel a green channel
and a blue channel. And if you want to
do the same 3x3 idea
you have nine weights associated with
it.
Because you have you do the same op you
do you do a convolution operation for
the green channel. You do a convolution
operation for the blue channel. You do a
convolutional operation for the red
channel. And then you add them all up
and that gives you one channel of the
output.
Okay, everyone clear with this?
Okay. So
what's the next case? Okay,
the next case that you can think about
and let me just watch the time. So
if
we want
more channels at the output
of the
can repeat
with
fresh
weights
and biases
for each output channel.
Okay, so the input comes in in color
with three channels. There's a design
choice of how many channels do you want
at the output of the first hidden layer.
This is a design parameter.
If you want one, that's fine. You have
the convolution. If you want decide to
go for a 3x3 convolution, then there's
nine weights and a bias associated with
it. But if you wanted there to be two,
there'd be nine weights and a bias for
one of those channels and another nine
weights and another bias for the second
channel. And if you wanted 10, there
would be 90 weights and 10 biases.
Everyone get it? Again, not complicated,
but it's important to uh keep in mind
and and understand.
>> Yeah.
>> So, you mentioned language. Are we
sharing the between
>> Great question. So I'll make I'll make a
note here. Note
weights
not
shared
across channels.
The only sharing that occurs is
across space.
Weights are shared across space because
the same filter is applied at different
spatial positions. They are not shared
across channels nor are they shared
across depth in the network.
Why are they not shared across channel?
Because the idea is that different
channels are intuitively capturing
different dimensions of information.
And so if you think for example that RGB
is has a lot of redundant information
across the red, the green and the blue
then you might want to change to a
different color space which has less
redundancy or you say fine I'll live
with the redundancy I'll the filters
will sort it out but I want to let them
sort it out
but yeah you do not weight share across
channels you only weight share across
space because spatial uh translation
invariance is the thing you believe
exists in the
Great question. Any other questions
about this basic picture? Yeah,
>> you're saying we don't change across
channels and we also so we change across
channels. We don't change across layers.
>> Yes. So if you if this is I'm talking
about one layer, we're talking about
depth. So we'll have many layers of
this. So the second layer, so if you
think of it this way, if the first layer
is computing edges, the second layer is
trying to put together, you know,
subfingers. The third layer is trying to
put together fingers. The fourth layer
is trying to put together, you know,
hands. And the fifth layer is supposed
to put together like larger limbs. And
the sixth layer is supposed to put
together people. And the seventh layer
is supposed to put together, you know,
small groupings of people. And the
eighth layer is supposed to put together
formations of people, right? And so on,
right? Something like this. So each of
them has their own at that scale object
that they are kind of capturing. And if
you want to think about the channels
intuitively, now this will break, but
one intuitive way to think about the
channels is to think about the channels
as being uh detectors for different
kinds of things.
This isn't what actually happens, but
it'll help you think. So think about a
channel and deeper in the network as
being a finger detector, a thumb
detector,
other things like this or fingers in
certain orientations detectors. Lots of
channels you can think of as having some
intuitive meaning like this. That's not
what actually happens. But it helps you
think about the idea of why there are
many of them. That's all that matters.
Why there are many of them, not what
they are. Yeah. channel or layer.
>> So this is uh the channels at a given
layer. So
can think
incorrectly
or inaccurately
about channels
at layer L, output channels.
as being
X detectors
for
that spatial position
and
different X X's.
example,
fingers,
toes.
What's another finger size object?
Flies,
you know, things like that.
>> Yeah.
>> You just said that
for
everything. So why would we think of the
color in the same
Great question. So the question is why
are we think about the colors the same
way you think about fingers versus flies
versus toes? And the answer is that the
what sits inside of a channel is a real
number
and it's a so it's like a continuous
object. So the only things that exist at
the pixel level raw is how much red is
there, how much green is there and how
much blue is there. That's it. That's
all the meaning that exists at the basic
lowest level. When you get at higher
layers of the network as you kind of
have propagated out, have looked at
neighborhoods and gone out. Now the
kinds of semantic meaning that might be
able to be captured there is different.
So here it's you can again think
inaccurately as how much fingeriness is
here, how much towiness is here, how
much flyiness is here, things like this.
Again, this isn't quite right. Um in
fact getting something like this to
actually although this is not what
actually happens, building things that
behave more like that is a major thing
that happens in interpretability
research. people make things like what
are called sparse autoenccoders and the
like which are trying to pull out things
that are more likely to be interpretable
in this way because the actual um
channels are not okay but that's
something that happens but this is still
a way of thinking about why you need
many of them that's all we're trying to
get why you need many yeah
>> so for example in our
channel for our comfort layer we have
another
Yes. So the answer question is if you
want this is this is one channel of the
output of the hidden layer. If you
wanted a second you'd have another copy
of of of this we still use the same
pixels but have different weights
associated with that second channel with
its own bias also.
>> Yeah.
>> Sorry.
Like fingers.
>> Oh, X is like fingers.
>> Yeah.
Examples for X's. Yeah. So, examples
for X,
fingers, toes, flies, stuff, any object
that makes sense at that scale or
attributes that make sense at that
scale. Yeah.
>> When you have a bunch of these like
different weights, they do they sort of
automatically differentiate themselves
from each other like how do you know
you're not just going to get like 20
horizontal?
>> That's a great question. Um the answer
is uh so the question is how do you know
that the different channels during
training will actually specialize in
doing different things
actually have different things. So
there's a couple of things that are the
ways that happens. First is you
initialize randomly so they're not all
initialized to the same thing. That
gives you a chance of learning something
different. The second is you hope that
it is useful to learn different things.
There's gradient descent that's trying
to make the loss go down and so it'll
try to do useful things but there's a
leap of faith there. And the third thing
is that
in reality they do learn redundant
things and then the question becomes is
that a feature or a bug to which the
answer is much more nuanced which we'll
come to uh later.
If they were to initialize the same,
would you expect them to still I guess
we might see like leap of faith that
still sort of separates out.
>> No, they won't. If you initialize them
the same, unless there's something
different later that will break the
symmetry. If there if you initialize
everything at every layer the same,
nothing they would do nothing to break
that symmetry.
>> Um so you have to break the symmetry
somehow.
Um and random initialization is one way
that we break the symmetry in training.
Um, yeah.
>> Would you ever want to have weights that
only act on like certain input channels?
Like so instead of going like if you
have like you know 32 input channels
like oh I only want this image to act on
like 10 of them or something.
>> Yeah. So the question was do you ever
have weight matrices that only look at a
subset of channels? The answer is yes.
We'll talk about that later.
>> Yeah.
Oh, sure. Sure. What is this picture
illustrating? This uh let me just use
this.
This block of nine weights is supposed
to be nine distinct weights.
They have colors chosen randomly for
visual aesthetics. They don't mean
anything. This mean they're nine
different things.
>> The nine different things multiplied the
corresponding nine different things here
and then it's like a inner product.
>> Okay. Yeah, I thought
>> yeah has no meaning. Just a straight uh
inner product. Um and the colors here
just reflect what channel they came
from.
That's all I'm trying to be illustrated
here. Um yeah, last question. Yeah.
>> So you said that um
You're talking about
layer you can have multiple channels.
>> Yes.
>> But I'm seeing this picture that you've
taken all three channels
and you're getting
>> sure let me just do it. Okay. Um let's
see if we can do this on the fly.
Okay, let me see if this works.
Come on. Ah, didn't work. Okay, I don't
know how to do this. How to select a
particular piece of this. Uh, I'll just
draw it. Okay.
Free form select might work.
>> H, too much trouble.
>> Okay, I'll just draw it.
>> Thank you.
>> Okay,
here's my bad version of
this box. Okay, another one.
Okay.
And here's
Okay. That's another one of these
outputs. Another channel.
>> Each of these cubes have different
weights.
>> Yes.
So if you want more channels, you just
repeat. You do this again with different
weights and different biases and you get
different outputs from the same input.
So you just keep stacking up. That's
actually a point that I wanted to what
makes it clearest. We can just do it
again to
special case that's useful.
Okay.
Is a one by one convolution.
Okay. So, what's a one by one conve? A
one by one convey
this pixel. I'm not going to look at
neighboring pixels. I'm just look at
this pixel. So, if you think of it from
the perspective of just straight
convolution,
you might think, well, that's silly.
That's just multiplying by a constant,
right? But when you think about many
channels, it's not silly because a one
by one con, what what's a one by one con
do? a one by one conf
with
C in input channels. C input
channels
and C output
channels.
So everyone understand what I mean? It's
a conveyor. It's not going to look at
neighbors, but it's going to have the
input to it has C in channels and the
output has C out channels.
So, what does that look like? So, the
input
from one pixel
is a vector.
Call it X.
The output. What is the size of X?
CN.
The output
for
this pixel.
Remember the output for a conair is
always for this pixel. The next pixel
you have to shift everything. So the
output is always for this pixel. The
input depending on the size could be
many pixels.
The output for this pixel is also a
vector
and they are related linearly.
Okay. So what is the rule?
Y
is a weight matrix acting on X.
What is the shape of this weight matrix?
C in
C out
plus biases. Well, how many biases? C
out.
So a one by one con is another word for
a pixel specific linear layer. Dense
linear layer. Does everyone see that?
That's what dense linear layer did.
And so
a one by one conf is a good way to help
if you can understand a one by one con
and you can understand the rest and then
you can understand that these have to be
compatible that will give you the
general story in your mind. So it's
useful to think about the special case
of one by one con. They're also useful
in practice.
Okay. So if you think about the uh one
by one case we can remember
we can also
have a nonlinearity.
We don't have to have one. We can also
have a linear conveys have a nonlinear
conlair. So would a nonlinear conve
again for our one by one example
the output could be for example
relu
where the nonlinearity unless we specify
otherwise acts uh component by
component.
So this is a one by one con with a
nonlinearity. But if you didn't want a
one by one con and you wanted a 3x3 conf
for example, what happens from math
point of view? What happens from a math
point of view for a 3x3 conf is you will
still have biases that are the same size
as the output channels.
Your W will just, if you want to think
about it, get a whole bunch more columns
in it because your X will have the
values for this pixel, but also the
values for all the neighboring pixels
that are relevant all stacked up if you
want to think of it as unrolling it into
a 2x2 a standard matrix.
Okay.
Okay. So, this is where I want to make a
comment.
This perspective of thinking about a one
by one con and then thinking about non
one by one cons as though they were in
the same shape is what helps you in many
implementations
take ideas like mup and the like and
apply them to the context of convents
because we've learned everything there
in the context of matrices. So if you
think about RMS norms for example, you
can think about the RMS norms at every
pixel because the image is filled with
pixels.
And then you can say one approach is to
say if I want to maintain constant RMS
norms then I want to make sure this
weight matrix is the right way and this
biases are the right way all that kind
of stuff.
Okay. So this if I if I make my con
bigger my D in from the perspective of
MUP or muon changes for this weights.
Okay, so that's another reason to think
about one by one cons. And in fact, um I
believe many of the practical
implementations of muon for connets do
exactly this. They will take the weight
the weights for a con layer and
effectively
map them into a regular size matrix with
the input being
uh all the different channels at all the
pixels that are relevant and the output
being the all of the channels at this
particular layer. Okay, so this is the
correction for how to connect the ideas
together. Any
questions on the one by one case and how
to think about now you have to work it
out yourself you know on paper and
there's like we'll give you homework
that has you count things and stuff like
that you just get used to it
the actual shape of these objects is
important and the weight matrices aren't
matrices actually in terms of how
they're stored in con layers they're
stored as tensors with different sizes
associated with them
but that's for implementation reasons
Okay.
So, good. Everyone is clear on this. So,
now we can come back up here
to this picture here.
So, this picture brings up a a very
interesting question is that this
picture started with Z2
purposefully. It didn't start with Z1.
Okay. So can anyone tell me right now
why do you think this picture started
with Z2 and not Z1 when you talked about
the basics of a cond?
>> Um yeah
>> you need to pat it to use Z1.
>> So you said you need to pat it which is
a word right? Um that's true. Um
but at a picture level can you just tell
me at a picture level what happens? You
need the three input values to get a Z
value and there's no corresponding X for
Z1.
>> Yeah, you kind of float off, right? So
if you think about it as you just run
the code, it tries to index this array
at a place the there's nothing valid.
You invalid memory access error, right?
Like what are you going to look at? Does
everyone see that? There's like a
question of what do you do on the
boundaries? So this is the question of
padding. So we need to talk about
padding.
So let's move down.
Okay.
So this is a picture again just taking
it from you can understand the idea of
padding easier in the case of 1D because
it's easier to think but the same thing
applies in 2D.
There's a problem of what to do at the
boundaries. So if your filter wants
three inputs at the very beginning it
doesn't have three.
It only has two. What are you going to
do for the third is the question. And
one choice, the choice illustrated in
this picture is called zero padding,
which is that when you don't have an
input, but you want one, you just say
it's zero. Everyone see? Okay. So you
can think of it as you literally take
the input, you expand it by adding zeros
to the boundaries and then you only do
the filter in the places where it fits.
Okay, that's another way of thinking
about it.
And if you chose not to pad, then what
happens is you simply do not calculate
for any of those inputs that are
invalid.
So you start here with no padding.
Does everyone see that? So that's also a
choice. Just only do the ones that fit.
So there's another name for the special
case of when you pad such that the
output is the same size as the input.
So there's always a choice of padding
that'll let you do that. That's called
same padding
because this
just you know you want the same size
output image as the input image.
Okay.
So this is the basics of uh padding. But
I wanted to take this uh moment and
maybe give everyone uh
this is set the timer if Okay, I'm going
to give everyone one minute.
Talk with your neighbors and see if you
can come up with any other ways to pad
than this.
Okay, this way of padding is you put
zeros. Are there any other choices?
So go ahead and thick talk.
But if it works,
>> I don't know about
Okay.
>> Timer ran out.
>> Um, anyone want to raise your hand and
suggest uh something that you came up
with that wasn't zero?
>> Yeah.
>> Wrap around. Maybe
>> wrap around. Yeah, you can wrap around
pad
just video game style.
You know, you go off the screen here,
you come up here, right?
Something that's called circular
padding.
Okay. So uh in the context of images for
example uh can anyone say what might be
a problem with doing zero padding or
wraparound padding from the perspective
of what a small filter might experience.
Yeah.
Go ahead. Yeah. Back there. Yeah. Yeah.
>> So idea is like let's say you have a
horizontal edge detector. Now you're
patting a bunch of zeros around like wow
there's a really sharp
I guess I'll detect that as an edge
just like a big shiny.
>> Yes, everyone see that? So zero padding
and wraparound padding will generally
introduce a sharp discontinuity
um at the boundary and the sharp
discontinuity any kind of detector that
picks up sharp discontinuities will say
hey something's happening here at this
discontinuity. Um, the flip side is you
might want to have detectors that pick
up sharp discontinuities and feedback
signals that say there's nothing
interesting there will suppress the
development of sharp discontinuity
picking up things if there's a whole
bunch of sharp discontinuities that are
semantically semantically meaningless.
So either way there's an issue with
sharp discontinuities that may or may
not come up. Great. Um, so wraparound
padding and zero padding both suffer
from sharp discontinuities. Can anyone
give me another padding? Can it come
with that padding that doesn't have the
sharp discontinuities? Yeah.
>> Okay. So, you could copy,
>> right? So, there's copy padding.
But the question is how exactly do you
copy? So, you have choices. You can copy
X1 over which in one dimensions is
clear. in two dimensions like which and
you have 3x3 filter which one do you
copy right so but that there's different
kinds of copying um another version of
copying for a larger for a 7 by seven
filter let's say you have to copy out
significantly past the boundary so what
do you copy there
you can keep copying but again you'll
have the same discontinuity issue so
what's another kind of generic approach
one could do
>> yeah the average of all neighbors
around.
>> Yeah, you could put average. You could
put averages there. So that a kind of
Yeah, you could do averages.
>> But there's another one that's uh if if
anyone has seen how JPEG works, you
might have seen this other approach that
is also possible. Yeah,
>> you do reflection.
>> Reflection. You could do mirror padding.
It's called mirror padding.
So if you do a mirror padding then what
happens is you sometimes get less of
this discontinuity effect just just
mirrors over so at least it's smooth
right you still have might have a
discontinuity at the derivative but not
at the level itself and so these are all
different choices however practically
speaking it's important to recognize
that the one that most people do because
of the ease of implementation and the
fact that it tends to just work is just
zero
But you should know these others exist.
Okay.
So this is padding. Uh this lets you
deal with different uh shapes. So now
there's
that's all I want to say about padding.
There's another term that we should
learn. It's just called receptive
fields. As we make a network deeper,
what happens? So what is this? This is
again a figure from Prince.
So you can always ask the question
depending on which layer you are in the
network
how many things does this depend on.
Okay so this comes out this is a term
that came out of biology originally and
so it says at hidden layer 1 if I'm
doing a 3x3 conveime
you have these channels here as the
output of the hidden layer. What do they
depend on? Well, they depend on these
three pixels in the input.
Okay. Now, suppose there was another
filter afterward that looked at three of
these
at the at the second hidden layer. Does
everyone understand the picture? This is
hidden layer one, hidden layer two. Now,
I point to one of these and I say, how
much of the input does this depend on?
Well, these all depend on these guys and
these depend on this. So, it just grows
up out by one for threes. Does everyone
see that?
Okay.
So, now
the question I want to ask is suppose
all of the filters in your connet are
3x3. This is your 3x3 case. So I have
layers upon layers of con filters and I
go to layer L.
How big in order sense is the receptive
field going to be?
How many pixels at the input will depend
will will this depend on this single
pixel at layer L. Do you understand the
question? question.
Suppose
all cons
are 3x3 or just 1D
or in 1D
at
layer L.
How big
is
receptive field?
Okay, does everyone understand the
question first?
Okay, we're kind of what this question
is getting at is how fast is information
being collected from the entire image as
we're going doing the processing.
That's the question we want to
understand.
So, anyone want to tell me the answer?
Just look at this picture. What if I did
this again? One more time. How big would
the thing get?
>> Right. Just shout it out someone.
>> So you're looking at 2 L + one.
>> Yeah.
Okay.
Right? You're growing by one. The
important thing here is that this is
linear growth.
So sometimes what you want to have in a
continent is you would like to have
information from further away get here
faster.
You want to have more information come
together. Does everyone see why that
might be desirable? Um,
it's when you want to have when you
think that the you're using a small
conf, but you think the objects you're
interested are actually getting bigger
at this layer. There aren't really
objects with very intermediate sizes.
So, how can you how can you get uh the
receptive field to grow faster?
And this is again a an old idea from
signal processing which is that if you
would like to have the receptive field
get faster larger you can say is you
could down sample the image.
So because a 3x3 con on an image that's
half by half size actually goes out much
further in terms of the actual spatial
extent of the original image. Does
everyone see the intuition behind that?
A small box on a smaller image is a
bigger box when you scale it up.
So this is the idea of downsampling.
It's a very important part of
continents.
And so
one way you can do down sampling is
what's called stride.
So you can think of stride as actually
being the composition of two things
which is why I really like this figure
in Prince
because it shows you downsampling in
this way. It says
you could imagine something that
actually had a circle here, a circle
here, a circle here, and a circle here.
All these other circles, but you throw
half the circles away. Easiest way to
down sample is just throw half the
things away or to subsample at a certain
rate. Everyone see that? Like if you
want to take a high-res picture and make
it a low res picture, the simplest thing
you can do is literally throw away a
whole bunch of pixels.
So computationally, you might think
computing a bunch of things that you're
going to throw away is not a smart idea.
Everyone with me?
Okay. So
the combination
of the two steps of doing a filter and
throwing stuff away in an efficient
manner is called stride.
It just says take this thing but instead
of moving it by one, move it by two.
That's stride too. Okay, moving it by
two means throwing every other thing
away. Moving it by three means throwing
every
two out of three away.
Okay, everyone see the picture? Okay,
that's called uh stride.
Again, basic stuff, but everyone has to
know it. And going back to the original
picture, this is a fully connected
network. And here's a con uh with size
three as a bunch of weights. If I have a
con of size three with a stride,
it looks like this. So instead of having
six outputs, I only have three outputs.
And they look like this.
Okay, good.
So you can see that if you have uh
stride you get this growth faster
of receptive field. Okay, I think I am
out of time now. I went slower than I
wanted. It's fine. I have another
lecture before the discussion. So it's
good. Um so I have office hours now. Uh
we will we hope to in the next two
lectures we want to finish up connetss
uh the connet story get the basics then
we'll move on to uh graph neural nets.
Okay.