we can get started. Okay. So, I'm going
to continue where uh we left off last
class about state space models. And we
started talking with about this with the
two key problems that we were trying to
address with RNN's, right? We liked
RNN's because they had this concept of
state and therefore were good at
capturing long range dependencies. Um
but we had the problem that you know
when you had uh lots of sequential
multipliers and you would actually have
these decaying weights on the past and
you would start forgetting the past. So
you had the idea that maybe the state
could capture the past but it would be
hard to actually do this. And the other
challenge with RNN's was that they were
uh hard to train parallelly. And so what
we did was we said okay well let's get
rid of this horizontal nonlinearity that
was blocking us. And what we did was we
said okay let's just think of this as a
linear system. Think of it as a state
space model. And we can then use
this equation essentially.
And given the weights A, B, and C, we
can just use a convolution to actually
get our um training to work, right? And
the fact that it's a convolution and
that h of t does not have to wait for
the computation of h of t minus one to
be able to compute it. I can directly
parallelly compute it given all of my
inputs. Therefore, I can speed up
training. Everyone remember this? And we
said that if you did it straight using
the convolution way, we would have a
total of uh order t^2 compute. But if we
use the nice fft trick, then we can get
to order t log t. And we had this idea
of how to do this using order t log t.
But we had the issue with well we
actually have vectors here. The fft is
set up for scalar uh inputs. Everyone
remember this context from last time?
We're good.
And then the one other thing we talked
about was that hey it's not just about
computing this long convolution. But we
also have to compute the coefficients of
the long convolution. And these
coefficients are also well they're big
matrices right? You have this c * a to
the k * b. Computing these powers of a
can also be quite expensive. So what was
the trick that we came up with to handle
the fact that computing large powers of
a is a problem?
>> Make a diagonal. just make a diagonal,
right? And so we can say that once we
have set up a as diagonal, we can
represent the entire family of systems
that can be represented by
diagonalizable A's because again we're
learning these these weights anyway. So
we can essentially learn the basis and
therefore there's a huge family of
things that can be represented. the
things that cannot be represented are
such things that um have some repeated
values.
Uh but you know we we give that up
basically. Okay
great. So we had this diagonal A and
then we said that okay you granted me
that we are going to say that we can use
the FFT trick even though our inputs
were not actually um
scalar inputs. We had vectors going in
this everything U's and X or the X's and
H's were all vectors. And so what we
wanted to start off with today was
saying, well, how can we handle the FFT
given that all of our inputs are
actually vectors?
Everyone caught up to speed and remember
what we talked about last time in that
quick recap? Okay, great.
Okay, so now let's start thinking about
this.
So we're going to consider our state
space model or our system as h of t is a
h of t minus 1 plus bx of t and then y
of t is c h of t plus dx of t. y of t is
our output x of t is our input. Right?
And here we're uh thinking about this in
some sense as this input output view. So
let's say y of t has dy dimensions,
x of t has dx dimensions
and h of t has dh dimensions. Right? And
remember this dh is the thing that is
capturing all of the past. that is the
that is the uh our our memory or ability
to capture the history or the context of
our sequence is in in is is
related to how big this DH is. Okay, so
this is going to come up later when we
uh talk about a few things. So I just
want to highlight that.
So what are we going to do here? we have
this y of t
and I want to think about y of t on a
component by component basis right so
this is every dimension of my embedding
and so I'm going to write y of t as y of
t of1 y of t of two y of t of dy right y
of t is a vector
everyone with me there nothing nothing
has happened right
but what I want to do is now I want to
think about
Y as a
stack of sequences that are changing in
time. So I can think of Y as well. I
have the first component of Y and that
is a sequence that is evolving in time.
So I have the first component at time
one, the first component at time two,
the first component at time three and so
on and so forth. And then I can think of
the second component at time one and
time two and time three and time four
and so on. So instead of thinking of a
sequence of vectors, I can think of a
stack of sequences of scalers,
right? The kind of straightforward way
that I might want to break these things
up. So this I'm going to think of as a
sequence. Okay? And so for every
component of my input, I have a sequence
that is evolving.
For the kith component,
this is the sequence that I have. Any
questions about this?
Good.
Okay.
And how many sequences such sequences do
I have? I have dy such sequences.
Okay.
And similarly, I can think of the same
thing for my input X, right? And for the
input X, how many sequences am I going
to have?
DX such sequences. Okay.
So if I think about this y
tk. Okay,
how do I compute this ytk? Well, ytk
is going to depend on basically
everything that has happened in the
past, right? So it depends on x11. It
depends on x21 depends on xt1 depends of
first component all times of the first
component all times of the second
component and all times of the last
component up until time t. Right? We
have a causality restriction. So it can
never depend on t + one. But we have no
restriction that says that it can't
depend on other components.
Okay.
So now I'm going to think of each of
these as these sequences
and my claim is
that I can actually write
this sequence yk. Okay. So which is the
sequence of the kith component.
So when I say sequence y k I mean that
sequence up there.
And I'm thinking of each of these as
sequence
sequences of X.
And by having an appropriate filter
here, I can write this as a sum of
different convolutions. So I'm going to
take DX different convolutions
and I'm going to add them up to get my
sequence YK.
Okay. So this is not obvious how this is
happening, right? This is like a little
bit of like okay take this on a leap of
faith. So okay, first any questions
about this setup before I go forward?
There's a lot of indices moving here and
there. So yes, question.
ah that is going to come through the
design of this filter. Yes.
So we know basically we want to we want
to make sure through we know from our
linear system that we've set it up to be
causal, right?
So we're going to choose this filter to
be such that we'll just follow the
properties and I'm not even going to
actually derive exactly what this filter
is for you but you will see why what I'm
saying is true.
So to understand this a little bit
better um I thought it would be very
good to go through an example
because what I want you to get is the
spirit of what is going on. So let's
consider this following system. Okay. So
I have h of t + 1 is
just this very simple diagonal matrix
time h of t plus
um just 1 1 0 1 * xt + 1. Let's say that
the initial state is zero. And let's say
your observations are being controlled
by this matrix or your outputs in this
case. Okay.
So
take a minute look at this and write out
component by component how h is
evolving.
Okay, how is the first component
evolving? How is the second component
evolving?
And use this to see if you can
come to a conclusion like this. You can
see what these convolutions might end up
being.
The best way to try to see this is to
just actually work out some algebra
yourself. So, take a minute and uh just
just play with the math for a few
minutes. If you have a question, feel
free to ask me. I'll give you some time.
Is the question is what I'm asking you
to do clear to everyone or is there a
confusion?
everyone. I can't I can't I can't read
the room. Okay, I see a thumbs down.
Okay, someone want to ask me a question
or someone?
>> Sure. So, what I want you to see what
Okay, so here let's just step back.
Okay, what we want to do is we're
dealing with the fact that these things
are vectors.
We want to be able to use the fft tricks
to be able to
uh get to order t log t instead of order
t^2.
To do that, we have to somehow be able
to break our sequences of vectors into
sequences of scalers and convolutions of
sequences of scalers so that we can use
the FFT tricks.
And so what we're doing is I'm trying to
justify to you that this that this can
be done. Does that make sense? And so
for that what I'm asking you to do is
I'm saying it is really hard to see this
in like some symbolic notation with T's
and K's and L's and notation and indices
floating around. So I want you to try to
work this out for this example which is
you know engineered to be just simple
enough that the calculations aren't hard
but it'll illustrate what I'm trying to
say.
Everyone with me? Okay, great.
Um, you can set it up many different
ways. Here we're setting it up so that
>> it it really it doesn't matter. It's
just a convention issue.
>> Oh, is there a bad handwriting issue?
>> Okay, tell me where. You're fine.
Okay, that's my timer. But I feel like
everyone's still working. Do you want
another minute? Okay.
[Music]
Okay.
So, let's let's try to go through this
together. It's nothing complicated,
right? What I'm going to do is just
write this out step by step.
And so, if I look at the first component
of H now,
well, what is this? It's
just ht of one. I'm taking one times the
first come on here.
Um,
wait, did I mess something up? Uh, no,
sorry. Uh,
yeah. No, sorry. This is correct. Uh,
yeah. Plus 0 times the second component,
right? So, one times the first component
plus 0 times the second component. So I
just have this here and then I look at
the input and so I have one times the
first component and then one times the
second component right that gives me
this equation here and so now if my
initial state is just zeros what I can
immediately see is what is this first
component doing it's just accumulating
all of the input right both the
components of the input it's taking the
two states um I shouldn't use the word
state it's taking the two components of
the input and summing them together and
accumulating this over time.
Yeah, everyone see this?
It's this running sum. Okay,
now let's look at the second component.
Well, the second component here is alpha
times
ht of two. And now here there's a zero
one here. So this guy only really cares
about the second component of x, right?
So this is just This is like an
exponentially weighted average. Now
you've seen this kind of thing before.
So this is just this exponentially
weighted average of the second component
of the input. Okay.
And now adding this together, what do I
get on the output y? Well, the output is
half of the first state plus half of the
second state. That's the first
component. So I have half ht of one plus
half ht of two. And so I get you know a
half times the first component in input
plus this kind of
one plus this exponential uh averaging
of the second component of the input.
Right? This is just algebra for what
these things turn out to be.
And then you know yt of two is much
simpler. There's no averaging here. I'm
just taking the second component of my
hidden state. And I know that that is
just the running sum of the second
component of my input.
Okay, everyone with me? So my point here
is not to illustrate the algebra. My
point is to illustrate why are these now
interpretable as convolutions. Right?
What I want to say is now I can think of
see this is now what I have here is this
is some function of a time sequence of x
for a particular component. So this is
the sequence of x at the second
component of x. Right?
This is the sequence of x at the first
component of x.
So let's look at yt of two just because
that's easier. So yt of 2 is now just
this sum.
But instead of thinking of it as a sum,
I can think of it as one times
x i2.
Right? I can x i2 is just 1 * x i of2
and let's say x was some some sequence.
Let's say I just drew this out as some
example. So at zero it has this value
one it has this value so on and so
forth. What is the filter that I do the
convolution with to recover this running
sum?
Well, I'm going to have a filter that
basically only uses the past plus where
I currently am plus the present. So, it
has a tap at zero and then it has taps
at everywhere in the past.
And this filter when convolved with this
signal is going to give me exactly this
yt of two.
This I'm just going to I can just
straight multiply this on. So then to
get yt of zero
I get only zero. Then I have two
overlapping and it's just the sum of
these two. Then I have three overlapping
it's the sum of these three. So on and
so forth.
Everyone with me?
I feel like you're not with me. Lost.
Are you with me? Thumbs up. Thumbs down.
Okay, good. You're with me. Good.
So this is just just to see very
explicitly now that I have taken a the
you know component by component of y and
now it is a sum of convolutions with
the input sequence x. I can do the exact
same thing for the other component,
right? Yt of one. I can again separate
it out into
a convolution with the first component
sequence of X and a convolution with the
second component sequence of X.
Here I will just have now some
exponentially weighted taps for my
filter, but it's the same exact
principle. It's just a convolution.
Okay. And so for whatever I have, I can
always separate these out into
everything depends on the first
component, second component, third
component. It's always going to be
linear combinations. Therefore, I can
always make a filter that will be given
that will give me the appropriate
convolution which gives me this setup
here.
Does everyone see that? I'm not worried
too much about exactly what these FKL
are,
just the fact that I can compute them.
You had a question.
>> Yes.
>> There is.
>> Yeah.
Uh, did I miss a factor of alpha
somewhere?
here. There's Am I missing a factor of
alpha here?
>> You just copied the
>> I copied something wrong.
>> Yeah, forgot the t.
>> Oh,
where did I forget an alpha t minus one?
>> Here I forgot an alpha somewhere.
HT2 times alpha here.
>> No,
>> I copied over HT2 wrong somehow.
>> Ah, yeah. Okay, got it. Sorry.
Um,
so here I should have an alpha
>> and here I should have an alpha.
>> Okay, I must have made an algebra error.
Okay. Well, I'll figure this out. Sorry
if I if I lost your exponential. But
even if let's say I had an exponential
factor here, right? Let's say this was
not a one here. Let's say this was an
alpha t minus i. I'm not entirely sure
where I made the algebra error. I will
fix this, but it's just algebra. If this
was alpha t minus i, what would this
filter look like instead? This filter
would look like this. Like it would be a
decaying exponential of this form right
the the values of the filter I I'm sorry
I must have just lost a factor but uh is
not the point I'm trying to make right
what I'm trying to say is that the fact
that it can be written as a colum
doesn't depend on what the exact inputs
are
right yes that's that's the key thing
that I want to communicate I will fix
this and put this up um with the
appropriate alpha in the appropriate
Please. Sorry about that. Okay. Yes.
Question.
>> Why did you call it approximate filter?
>> Oh, I
appropriate filter.
>> Not approximate appropriate filter. Yes.
Yes.
>> So, okay. So, so there is there is a
pro. So, okay. So what you're bringing
out is that okay you're like okay you're
saying you can do this FFT trick. So
just to preface your question just a
minute just a bit for everyone. So now I
have broken this up into many many many
convolutions right and each of these is
capital T long and so I can have each of
these happen in order T log T time but I
have a ton of them right. In fact how
many do I have? Well, I have k times l
of them. Um, or I have dx times dy of
them, right? So, I have dimension of x
times dimension of y. So, if each is 100
dimensions, that's 10 to the four.
That's a lot of convolutions.
Okay. So, this is this is exactly the
issue that we're basically going to try
and um handle next. Is is that exactly
what you're thinking about? Yeah. Okay.
So, good. So this is this is exactly
where I want to go. So we've solved a
part of it, but this is still a lot of
computation to do. Okay, 10,000
callutions is no joke.
Okay, so how are we going to Okay, I
actually wrote this here. Great. How do
we want to deal with this further? Okay,
well in connets, how did we how did we
solve this problem? How did we think
about this problem? We said in a connet
we were we were we were having these
filters that were basically uh these
convolutions that were looking across
channels and across all of the
neighboring pixels and so on and so
forth. And we said well that's a lot of
work and what did we do to make it
easier on us. We said well let's not
combine across channels right and then
we did this depthwise convolution idea
or channel wise convolution. Well why
don't we just take the same idea? It
worked there. Let's see if we can make
it uh make it work here.
So if we wanted to make this work here,
what do we need to do? Remember, we've
already kind of committed to a being
diagonal.
Okay,
so what does it mean to now have the
different channels not really interact
with each other? what we want to have in
but the parallel to a depthwise or
channel-wise convolution is to say that
every channel of the input just stays
like it doesn't mix with the other
channels in the SSM layer. It might mix
in the MLP layer that comes after it but
in the state space model we're going to
have each of the channels just do their
own thing. They're not going to mix with
each other.
Everyone understand the philosophy or
the spirit in that we're trying to
proceed with?
So where are the places that these
different channels can mix with each
other? Well, the A is already diagonal.
So now what about the B matrix, right?
That's the kind of big thing. So if I if
I can write out our equation here, we
have h of t + 1
is equal to a h of t
plus b
x of t.
And if I can think of x as this,
it has these different components.
And if I want to make sure that these
don't mix with each other, what is the
structure that this is going to impose
on B?
It's going to be basically like
almost block diagonal in the sense that
it's going to have you know just I can
have this fan out to multiple hidden
states but I don't want these two things
to mix right so I'm going to have these
like columns so these going to be block
diagonal with these columns
so that I can have one state or one
component of the input fan out to
multiple hidden states but none of them
are ever going to mix with each other.
Okay, that gives a and the same
structure is going to have to hold for C
if I want to have this this property
hold through all the way to the output.
Okay, so this gives us basically a uh
block diagonal type structure for B
and that basically helps us
uh reduce some further computation. Yes,
question
>> just explain one more time why we're
doing this.
Why are we doing this depthwise con
convolution? Okay, great question. So
again, the name of the game is compute,
right? The if you can do it with less
compute, you're saving money, you're
doing better.
So if I split my my system, my big
convolution up into these many many
convolutions so that they can they're
all convolutions of scalar sequences.
That's great. But the I'm concerned also
not just about the length of the
sequences, right? I I can go from order
t^ squ to order t log t by splitting it
up into many convolutions.
But now the fact that I have many
convolutions, well, if I'm just doing
millions of convolutions,
even if every convolution is relatively
short, I'm still going to blow up in
time. So it would be nice to reduce the
total number of convolutions that I have
to do.
And so instead of having 10,000
convolutions, which is what I would have
if I had to do
um dx * dy, if I had full generality on
this filter here,
how can I reduce the number of
convolutions?
And so to do that, I want to set a bunch
of these filters just to be zero.
And one way to do that is to say that
I'm going to set a bunch of the
coefficients B to zero.
One structured way to do that is to
follow exactly the path that we followed
for depthwise convolution where we had
that exact same problem and we reduce
the computation by saying we're not
going to mix across channels. Does that
make sense? Okay. Yes.
>> Is it a design restriction that we
cannot have hidden dimensions?
cannot have the hidden state be uh lower
dimensional? Yes. So here basically we
will we will maintain that the input and
output will be the same dimensions and
the hidden state can expand but it will
not reduce exactly and this is kind of
what we want right because we want we
want to actually and that's what we're
going to talk about next is we want to
make the dimension of h to be as large
as possible because that's where we're
holding all of our past. We want to be
able to use this recurrence to capture
the context or the or the history of our
sequence.
Uh so we're we're not opposed to making
it large.
Yes,
>> I'm a little confused like how do you
how do you like and
>> so uh A and B are learn matrices but you
can always force some parameters to be
something and just set them to zero.
Don't pass any gradient through them.
Don't learn those parameters, right? You
can learn certain parameters and not
other parameters.
So for example, when a is diagonal,
we're just going to force a bunch of
things to be zeros. We're only going to
learn the diagonal elements.
Great questions. Okay, good.
Okay, so these are all the different
things that we are are putting together
and we're building towards basically
this S4 model. Um so now I want to move
any questions on this part before I move
to like the next section. Okay.
Okay.
So now this question was perfect because
we talked about well h the dimension of
h we always want to be larger than the
dimension of x and in some sense that's
a design decision
but the dimension of h is in some sense
one of the critical parameters for our
whole setup because that captures what
we can we can u handle but there's a
fundamental trade-off here right if we
make h bigger and bigger and bigger
That means more and more compute, but it
also means we can store more and more
stuff about our past. So there's an
efficiency versus efficacy trade-off,
right? To be efficient, I want age to be
small, but to be effective, I want to
remember as much of the history and as
much of the past as I can.
So what I want is actually want to like
I want to have a sweet spot somehow
where H is as large as it can possibly
be. But you know I want to make sure
that my compute is still while still
minimizing my compute.
Okay.
So now
this is the key thing that kind of the
family of state space models are are are
working towards. And this first model
that I'm currently talking about that we
talked about last time and I'm going to
talk about for the first part of this
lecture is the S4 model. Okay.
I think it's for
structured
state space. That's three of the S's and
there's another S. Do you remember what
the other S is? No, but there's four
S's.
Um, and then the one that comes after
that is
S6 because it's
structured selective
state space. Okay, there's more S's, but
you can you can remember what the SS
are, but there's four S's and then
there's six S's. um we're talking about
the one with the four S's and I know one
of them is structured state space I'm
just forgetting what the fourth one is
so now can we think about the other part
that we're so for this S4 model can we
think about the long range dependency
that we want to engineer right we've
talked about the parallelization we've
talked about getting this to train
efficiently right that part we've kind
of we've wrapped up a little bit that
part what I want to move to next is the
other thing that we talked talked about
which is
how do we make sure that we can remember
our history and we don't run into the
RNN problem of just the past dying away
too quickly.
Everyone with me on what we're trying to
do? Okay.
So our A is this diagonal thing
and we have these igen values. We're a
discrete time system at the moment.
So what can we say about these igen
values in terms of what we want and what
we don't want? Right? We're going to
learn them. But are there desirable
properties and undesirable properties
just for a system? Let's say I take a we
take a dynamical system. What kind of
A's are good for system stability and
what kind of A's are bad for system
stability?
>> Yeah. absolute value.
So if I have absolute value, so the
absolute value of the igen value is what
matters. And so if the absolute value of
the igen value, if it was bigger than
one,
what would this mean for the
corresponding state? Right? We do we
want this to happen? This is really bad,
right? Because if you if you have a
system and your igen values are bigger
than one, then you're just blowing up
blowing up. You're going to run out of
floating point very fast, right? So this
is bad. You do not want to end up in
this regime. So here your system
explodes
and this is bad.
Okay.
So the other side is that when all of
your igen values are less than one and
what happens when your igen values are
less than one?
You're going to slowly decay away to
zero. You're not going to explode. So
that's very good. But this is kind of
the same issue that we had with RNNS,
right? That you have this decaying
weight on the history.
And so
yeah, it's there, but it might just die
away very fast. You're doing all of
this, you know, state computation blah
blah blah, but you're just setting
everything in the past to zero very
quickly. So this is also not that great,
right? You know, the history might die
out fast.
So what's the sweet spot?
What if lambda is exactly equal to one?
What is the the what if the absolute
value of lambda is exactly equal to one?
This in control systems is basically
critical damping. Right? So you have you
have the system state is maintained
but it's not exploding and it's not
dying out but it's somehow just moving
around without changes in magnitude
right it could have changes in direction
but it doesn't have changes in magnitude
so are you happy about this or sad about
this
pros and cons to this Right?
Let's say our igen values were all real
valued. What are the choices that we
have in this case? If we wanted to just
set our system to be
we have two choices, right? We have
lambda is plus one and we have lambda is
minus one. That's not a lot of choices.
It's pretty there's there's only these
two choices.
And the other thing about these is that
they're not really friendly for gradient
descent. They're far apart from each
other, right? So if you initialized at
the wrong one, like gradient descent
might not even take you to the other
one.
So what what do you do? What can you do
here? What is the next thing that you
try?
go to complex, right? You say, well,
I might not like complex numbers, but
you're going to bite the bullet and
you're going to go to complex values.
So, how do you let's maybe let's yeah,
what might be a way in which we can
think about initializing complex values
here? What's a what's a good way to
think about how to how to have complex
values?
Let me see. Maybe uh
I might want the time at the end. So I
will give this part away. But
so what I'm going to think about is I'm
going to think about these lambdas as
having a real part and an imaginary
part. And I want to now make sure
what do I want to make sure what what do
I want to have be true about the real
part of my igen values? what is good and
what is bad.
If it's I want it to be negative, right?
I don't want it to be positive,
otherwise things are going to blow up on
me. So, what's a way that I have of kind
of making sure that things are negative
or positive or checking the sign? Well,
I have a nonlinear in my linearity in my
pocket that basically does this for me,
right? So I can basically put
a relu on this here and put a minus sign
and that ensures that this is always a
uh always negative and then I can have
my igen values be captured by this.
Okay. And this will give me something
that that kind of works pretty well
here. I'm thinking of uh J as the uh
negative root of uh uh as the root of
minus one. Okay. And so this is the
parameterization that I will use to
actually learn the igen values for a. It
turns out that it's pretty sensitive to
figure this to this parameterization and
exactly the initialization that you will
use to learn these parameters.
So you have to kind of set up your
system so that your igen values are
largely very close to the unit circle
and other ones are inside. Like if you
have some IGEN values in your
initialization that end up outside the
unit circle, you're prone to instability
and that's not very good. So uh there's
basically tricks that you can do to get
this initialization. I'm not going to go
into those uh right now, but I talked
about this hippo paper last time that
talked about that that that was the
um one of the key generating ideas for
even starting out this line of state
space models and it was talking about
the expressivity of linear functions
themselves. But you can actually get
initializations for this that are based
on some of the calculations uh analytic
perspective from the hippo paper and you
can use those and those are actually end
up being very good initializations.
And what the paper authors found is that
if you actually find these good in
initializations and you freeze the A to
have those initializations and then you
just don't train on A at all. You just
train the parameters in B and C. Turns
out you can actually do pretty well as
well. um it's not you can do better if
you also train a but even just these
good initializations initial
initializations uh can get you a lot.
So that's what I want to say about
initialization. Uh and that kind of
comes to the question that was asked
about I think someone asked this
question uh last time which is well how
do we deal with the initializations? How
do we make sure that things aren't
blowing up? And so it it is quite
complicated but we will basically the
bottom line is that you want to use
complex values. You want to make sure
that they're close to the unit circle
and then things work out. Okay. Yes.
Question.
Yes. Um so here you're going to think
about this as
uh this is going to make sure that
you're going to have this is going to be
negative.
So this thing is going to be small.
Basically it's going to be e to the
something negative plus a complex part.
The complex part is going to rotate you
and this part is going to make sure that
you're smaller than one.
>> Yes.
>> So what if the represent
>> you're saying that can I just default
set my real part to be uh zero all the
time?
>> Yeah.
>> Right. So,
um I guess there's nothing preventing
you from setting your real part to be
zero all the time, but you're losing
expressive power. And in particular, if
all of your data is actually real
valued, uh one of the things that you
can do is you can say, well, how do I
deal with the fact that there are now
complex numbers showing up? Is you can
say, well, I'm going to have complex
numbers in the mix so that I can have
these properties that I want, but then
I'm actually just going to throw out all
the complex parts. and you know just use
my real uh the real parts. And so you
don't probably want to be setting your
the real parts of your system to be
zero.
>> Yes.
>> Yes. So, do we need that?
>> You're saying that? So, so you you you
would want it. So, because there's a
couple of things, right? You're you're
you might want to say that there are
some things that I do want to forget.
There are some things that I want to
learn. There are some things that I want
to forget. Having that flexibility
allows you to learn that. But if you
always set it to zero, then you're
you're giving away that
uh degree of freedom.
Other questions? Okay. Yeah.
So you want you want to have your IGEN
values to be around the unit circle
mostly. Yes. On the unit circle and
maybe a few inside. That's what you're
you're hoping to get.
close to zero. So,
>> yes.
No, you don't. No, no, no. You don't
want the real part to be mostly close to
zero. You want it to be you want the
magnitude of the thing to be one. And
you can have whatever distribution
between the real and the complex part of
that you want.
Okay. Good. So what this does is that it
allows you to have this kind of long
range dependency that uh transformer
models were historically not as good at.
So this is a table from this uh S4 paper
and these are a bunch of standard
benchmarks and this in particular is a
particular uh
uh benchmark that required looking at
lots of historical context. This is part
of the long range arena benchmark. And
what you can see is that a bunch of
these transformer models could not even
complete this task, but the S4 model
um
made a bunch of progress. Okay, so
we're not going to go into the details
of of of any of these things and we
haven't even talked about transformers
yet. That's what we're going to talk
about next week. But the point is to
highlight that thinking specifically
about this long range dependency
actually allowed the S4 model to
outperform many other state-of-the-art
art models particularly on these long
range benchmarks. However, what we have
the problem is that these were not
necessarily as good as transformers on
other kinds of tasks that did not have
this long range dependency. They were
not bad, but they weren't as good as
attention-based mechanisms. Okay. And
we'll talk about the comparison to
attention based mechanisms maybe next
week after we actually talked about
attention. We haven't really gotten
there yet. Yes. Question.
>> Yeah. I just want to make sure that I'm
understanding why we're taking things to
the complex realm. So, we're saying that
we're trying to learn some matrix A.
Yes. And that matrix A is diagonal of
values.
>> Yes.
>> And so, we need to learn those values.
Yes.
>> And so, we're parameterizing the values.
numbers exponential to the minus
>> correct
>> and that gives us two degrees of freedom
instead of one for every value. So we're
learning two parameters instead of one
for each value.
>> Yes.
>> And so I'm just trying to understand
exactly why that is better because it
seems to me like the ultimately that it
value is just going to be a number,
right? Like at some point
>> it's a number and a direction.
>> Okay. So that second degree of freedom.
>> Okay. I think yeah, if you could just
explain that like again.
>> So what so what is what are these values
doing? Right? These values are talking
about or they're they're affecting how
your history evolves at every time step.
Okay? And so you you're with me that you
don't want them to be big and you don't
want them to be small. Okay? But you
want them to somehow be able to train.
Mhm.
>> So if you want them to be able to train,
you have to give them somewhere to move,
something to do. And you so you want to
be able to adjust your IGEN values to
see how different performance changes.
And so if you want to have a continuous
space where you can have values that all
have magnitude one, but
you're you're kind of your unit circle
is all you got, right? Like you
otherwise if you're restricting to reals
then you have plus one and minus one and
how are you ever going to train that
thing?
>> That makes sense.
>> Does that Yeah.
>> So the degrees of freedom allow for the
optimization.
>> So yeah now you can optimize on on this
unit circle right.
>> Okay sense.
>> Okay good.
Okay.
So this concludes basically what I
wanted to say about S4. Okay.
What did we have? Just to summarize, we
had an linear time invariant system and
the key trick that we used was we used
the fast forier transform to be able to
speed up
uh the convolutions and this allowed us
and the fact that we could write this as
convolutions at all by removing the
horizontal nonlinearity allowed us to
parallelize the FFT further allowed us
to speed that up and then by
appropriately choosing a to be diagonal
signal and choosing the appropriate igen
values and initializations for that we
were able to get the kind of long range
dependencies that we needed. Okay, these
are the two different things that were
important
but this wasn't as good as it could get
and so that's what brings us to now the
latest version or actually there's now a
further evolution on this. There's like
Mamba 2 and then there's Deltanet but
I'm not going to talk about either of
those. um maybe next year you can take
the class and we'll talk about them then
or uh there's actually a really nice
blog post about Deltaet that after this
lecture you will probably be able to
read and understand on your own. So if
you want to you can uh take a pass at
that but I'm going to talk about Mamba
now.
So the S6 version takes yet another lens
on linear systems and uses that to give
one more degree of freedom to the system
that can enhance performance. So we
talked about you know state space
systems and state space models as having
the recurrent hidden state bas
statebased view and that allowed us to
be very fast at at inference time.
There was the input output view which
basically said that look you don't need
to you can express these things as
convolutions you can train using
convolutions therefore you can
parallelize and you can have fast
training. So that was the um input
output view. But when you think about
discrete time systems, there's actually
a third view and that is
the fact that a discrete system can be
thought of as a sampling or a
discretization of an underlying
continuous time process.
Okay.
And taking this viewpoint
a allows us to get an element of
selectivity
into the system which can help
performance. Okay. So the problem with
the S4 style or the LTI style of um
systems was that look in some sense more
history is always better. Okay. So if I
can put more and more and more and more
stuff into my state the more I can do
tasks like associative recall okay
but at some like you know some I don't
have infinite state something has to
give somewhere okay
so what are my choices here right my
choices are to either somehow forget my
fast or somehow choose what is and is
not important
in adding to my state. So if I could
somehow be selective about when I want
to put something into my state and when
I don't want to put something into my
state, this could maybe be helpful.
The problem with LTI systems and
convolutions in general is that if I
want a particular token to look maybe
you know 10 time steps in the past and
it's relevant for particular kinds of
tokens to do that because of the LTI in
this it means every token has to look 10
time steps in the past but maybe there's
some differences here in how I want to
do this and maybe I want to be able to
adjust when I look in the past and when
I don't look in the
So to be able to do this, can I have
some extra degree of freedom? And that's
what we're going to try to talk about
next using this continuous time
viewpoint. Okay, everyone with me?
So for that I want to think about now my
uh discrete time system here.
I want to think about it essentially as
a sampling of a continuous time system.
And one way to think about that is
basically I want to think about um
some continuous time system of this
form. So instead of having an h of t
here, I want an h dot, right? I'm
thinking about the rate of change as
being represented by a linear system.
Okay,
this A and this B is not the same. You
have to basically make sure that you
match these up. But if I want to now
convert from a continuous time system to
a discrete time system, I need to fix
and understand what my sampling interval
is. Right? There's many different ways
you can do this. You can read multiple
Wikipedia articles about many different
ways of sampling. We're going to just
pick one. And what I want to start is
just with the scalar case, right? Let's
understand this. In the scalar simple
case, the exact same thing holds
basically verbatim for the vector case.
The all the key meat is in here.
So let's say I have some continuous time
system. I'm going to call this, you
know, x dot of t is axt plus b t. How do
I convert this now to an underlying
discrete time system? Well, I fix a
sampling time. I call this delta t.
And let's assume that this u of t is
basically has this peacewise constant
nature. So delta t is small enough that
whatever my u of t is I can approximate
it by these peacewise constant uh
uh steps. Okay.
So if I do this
I can basically rewrite
or I can I can say that well if I have x
at time delta t now let's say x0 is
where I started out that was my initial
state then I have x at time delta t is
basically an exponential decay or growth
depending on the value of a times my
initial state xnot plus the impulse
response that comes from the uh input
right these are the two components that
I'm going to get when I try to
discretize this okay
just to remind you all when I have this
kind of system here
which is the case remember for lambda in
discrete time systems lambda outside the
unit circle meant you blew up lambda
inside the unit circle meant you decayed
what is the corresponding thing for
discrete For continuous time systems,
>> positive and negative,
>> positive and negative, right? So if this
is greater than zero, this means you
explode.
This means you
decay to zero. Okay,
so we're here in this case. We don't
want to be in this exploding case. So
we're just basically going to assume
that we have an a that is less than zero
uh for for the purposes of this
conversation.
But I can use this now to basically
sample
my continuous time system. Right? This
is my equation for a continuous time.
And I can correspondingly write a
discrete time equation like this.
Everyone with me?
Okay, good.
So it turns out that basically now I
have essentially this is like the A and
this is like the B.
But I have this additional player here.
I have this delta T. And by changing
delta T, I can change the nature of the
A matrix essentially and the B matrix,
right? Because these things matter. So
what happens if I choose this
delta t being close to zero and what
happens if this delta t is large?
Actually take a minute. Why don't I just
let you guys think through this and work
this out? What happens when delta t is
close to zero? What happens when delta t
is large for both of these two
components here?
Any
questions? Is it clear what I'm asking?
Yes.
>> Yes.
>> Ah, okay. So, why are we going back and
forth from continuous time? Let me
answer this question for everyone.
What I want to be able to do is I want
to be able to use the thinking and
interpretation from continuous time to
understand and make moves in discrete
time. So what I want to first establish
is the correspondence between continuous
time and discrete time. So if I have a
discrete time system and I'm imagining
it as a
as being derived from an underlying
continuous time system,
the only reason I'm doing that is for
conceptual purposes. I'm never going to
be using the continuous time system in
actually implementing any algorithm. I'm
but it's helping me think about things.
So when you're doing this sampling
basically the choice that you have the
choice that you have let me just maybe
draw a picture here that will maybe will
also help right let's say I have some
I have some signal here.
Okay, this is my signal. And by choosing
different sampling intervals, right? So
I can choose a sampling interval like
this.
And then these are my samples. These are
my big delta t's.
And then if I do the sampling, all you
see are these green dots.
This looks like a pretty like constant
signal in some sense, right? But if I
chose a different sampling interval
and I chose
now I can get much more uh I can get a
much higher frequency. This is like
related to the Nyquis theorem for those
of you who have seen signal processing,
right? This is basically the Nyquis rate
of sampling that allows you to capture
the different frequencies that you have.
We're not talking about that here, but
basically the sampling interval that you
uh that you choose
captures different information. So this
you can have a discrete time system that
is a function of a continuous time
system, but by choosing different
sampling intervals, you're essentially
capturing different behaviors.
of the underlying continuous time
system. That's that's what I want you to
see. And I want you to see that
mathematically by trying to plug in some
like plug in some numbers here and play
with this. Is that clear? Yes. Okay. So,
do you want another minute to try and
think through this or you're
no? How many how many people want a
minute or how many people are just want
to or how many people are totally lost?
>> Yes. Could you explain how did you get
the exponential
>> here?
>> Yes.
>> This is basically coming from
uh this part. So it's just the
exponential response x dot equal to uh
ax will give you just an exponential
and then this is giving you an impulse
response which is giving you this part.
Okay, let's go through this together
since I'm not seeing anyone doing any
writing then I'm not sure. No one's ask
any questions either. Okay,
so let's assume that a is less than zero
so that no one's blowing up anywhere.
Now let's look at this right. So if I
have my delta t is very close to zero
then e to the a delta t is basically
like one. And so what does this mean for
my initial state?
If this coefficient is like one
am I keeping my history
or am I losing my history?
>> I'm keeping it right. I'm not really uh
yeah I'm not I'm not forgetting it at
all. So this means that I basically you
know
remember history.
But if delta t was fairly large that
means that this is a decaying
exponential because a is negative and
the larger delta t is the faster I'm
forgetting my past. Right? So this is
saying forget my past.
What about this other term? What about
this impact of the input here?
So here to see what's happening here,
let's use the tailor expansion of this
quantity e to the a delta t minus one.
Let's say delta t is smallish that we
can actually use the tailor expansion.
But then I have e to the x is basically
1 plus x, right? That's my tailor
expansion. So I can rewrite this as 1
plus x - 1. So this is approximately a
delta t
multiply it by the b / a. And then I get
this b delta t.
And now again here if delta t is very
close to zero,
b delta t is
close to zero. So does that mean is the
effect of the input high or the effect
of input low? Like input doesn't matter
much, right?
But if delta t is very large then the
input matters a lot.
So basically
by changing the value of delta t by
dialing this up and down I can decide
whether I care more about the current
state or I care more about the history.
Right? This is a knob that I have
that can allow me to tweak things. Okay.
So what do you do with a knob? You're in
a deep learning class.
You tune it, right? You train the
parameter. So we've seen that basically
by changing this delta t,
we can choose what we want to keep in
memory and what we don't want to keep in
memory in some sense, right?
And remember, we're doing this on a
channelby channel basis. And so we can
have
different channels having this different
different delta t's and therefore you
can remember some channels more you can
remember other channels less and you can
collect information into certain
channels that will have the history and
you can collect information into other
channels that is more based on the
current information or current state or
current input. Right? So because we're
we we you know we're following the S4
architecture of of having these
depthwise convolutions. So we're not
going to be mixing channels and so we
can have different parameters for
different channels and bring the
selectivity that is one of the S6 SS
um
into our system to increase its
performance.
Okay.
So what we're going to do is we're
basically choose delta t based on our
input. We're going to learn it. So how
would we learn it? Well
the natural thing to try is to say well
can we come you know put in a linear
layer and see what you can get. So you
have you want to now depend on the
entire U. You don't want to depend just
on the channel by channel U but you want
to look at your entire input U or X.
let's call it x input x and you want to
say looking at this entire sequence well
how do I want to be thinking about um
thinking about what this delta t should
be so let me try a linear layer and see
what I can do so does a linear layer
work or maybe why don't you think about
this for a minute or just digest this
for a minute talk about something or try
to talk about how could we possibly go
about learning this delta t yeah take a
minute and if you have a question in
that minute also ask me
>> can you scroll up just to show
I'll just pause
if you everything is clear. Spend time
thinking about how could I, you know,
learn what this delta t is based on my
input u uh input. Let me actually call
this input x.
Uh, no, never mind.
>> Yes.
>> Yes. Why would we choose Why would we
choose like delta t to be
>> ah okay so here's a great question that
I should answer to everyone so the
question was why wouldn't we choose
delta t to be the nyquis rate right
because so if we chose delta to be the
what is the nyquis rate saying for those
of you who have signal processing
background it's basically saying that
well if you're faster than the if you're
twice as fast as the largest frequency
then you're going to keep all of your
information but that's the whole point
right you might not want to keep all of
your information. You might want to
forget some of it.
So
big delta t's allow you to forget
information. You can see that
pictorially as well.
Make sense?
Okay. So, let's just think through this
together in the interest of time and
getting through the rest of what I want
to get through.
So if I wanted to learn this, a natural
thing to try might be to say let me do a
linear layer. I can just think of this
linear layer as some inner product of
some vector W
with some U. Right? Can I just try
learning a linear function of U?
What's the problem with this
particular approach? Is there a problem?
Does this work?
What is delta t representing?
It's a time step, right? So it's my
sampling interval. What is a what is a
sampling interval of minus3?
It doesn't really make any sense, right?
Like so if this inner product and what
is the inner product? The inner product
can be any real value. It can be
positive, it can be negative, it can be
whatever. So I don't like it because it
can give me a time step of -3 and then I
don't know what to do with that. Okay.
So I want something I want to learn
something in a way that forces it to be
positive
so that I can basically do something
with it. Um so the norm is one way to do
it. But what's a standard thing that we
always do like we're again like throw
out your control theory hat but put on
your deep learning hat and you want to
force something to be positive in a deep
learning class. What do you do?
you can try to do some kind of
nonlinearity or or or or relu right
so um yeah so the natural next try is to
say well
I can do a relu
of let's say
let me bias or not a vector
okay
The problem with this is that this
works, but the relu is zero very often.
And so that's not something you really
want either. Um, and so what ends up
working really well is this thing called
the soft plus,
which is basically like the relu, but
it's a bit smoother.
Uh, and it has some properties that are
sometimes beneficial. So it's the log of
1 plus e to the x. and this blue curve.
So the red is the relu and this blue
curve is what the the soft plus is. And
so instead of setting hard to zero, it's
kind of slowly going to zero and it's
giving you these really large delta t's
if you want or you can have these really
small delta t's. Okay.
And so basically with this what you can
do
is you know if you if you ignore all of
your learnable parameters for a minute
just uh you know you just think of a
scalar case and you set a and b to one
then you can think of this as well I'm
learning some function
based on my input that is telling me how
much do I want to weight the history
versus how do I want to weight my
current input. Okay, this is something
that I can learn.
Um,
okay.
And this is something I just want to
write this in this form because you've
seen this form before, right? We've seen
this in momentum. We've seen this like
you have an intuition about what happens
when things look like this. But this is
essentially
it's the same kind of thing. It's not
exactly the same thing, but it's the
same kind of thing that's happening
here,
right? There's a trade-off between these
two parameters. They don't necessarily
sum to one, but there is uh you can you
can tw you can tune each of these uh
each of these parameters. It's important
to remember here that these parameters
AB are all learnable, right? So, it's
not exactly the same, but it's just an
intuition that you can build.
Okay.
So
what this does is now we can say that
okay we can now choose this delta t we
can learn this delta t and with by
learning this delta t based on our
different inputs.
We can have
an a k and a bk and maybe even a ck for
each of these. In practice, in the S6
models, they actually don't learn the
CK, which is why I didn't write this
here. But you now see that theoretically
you can learn different
waiting matrices
for different inputs and therefore you
can say that you know for this input I
want to behave this way, for this other
input I want to behave this way, so on
and so forth.
Does everyone see how this selectivity
is being obtained by choosing and
learning this delta t parameter? Okay.
And we're not like using the continuous
time system here per se. We're just
using it as a inspiration and a
motivation to set this up to be able to
learn these things and have this
selectivity that helps us then remember
think about what should be in memory and
what should not be in memory or what
should be in our history in our state
and what should not be in our hidden
state.
But have we lost anything in this
process now? Yes. Question.
>> Yes. Exactly. Right. So suddenly our
system is now time varying and we spend
all this time talking about all this
fast for transform stuff. But that only
works for LTI systems.
So what are we what is the what are we
going to do now? Turns out that you can
still do the unrolling of the system in
the exact same way. So here now instead
of having terms
um
that are like a to the k that's going to
be replaced with something like a the k
* a the k minus one * a1 * a kn because
I'm going to have all these distinct
matrices but I can still do the
unrolling in the exact same way it turns
out. And so I can still have y of t as a
linear function of all of my inputs,
right? And because I've eliminated the
horizontal nonlinearity,
I can still process this fundamentally
in the same parallelizable way. It won't
be the convolution. I won't be uh uh I
won't be able to do the fft trick on it
and it will become an order t operation,
not an a t log t operation. But it is
still parallelizable. Okay.
Uh if you want you can read lots of work
on exactly how this parallelization is
done. But the key thing that you need
that I want to communicate is that it
can be done parallelly and you don't
have the serial bottleneck that the RNN
has. Okay.
So that's really what I wanted to get to
today. There's another small point which
is that um how do you now initialize for
these S6 models and there is a a couple
of initializations that work.
It turns out that the reliance on it's
it's still the complex initialization
still help for this but they're less
critical. Um and you can really stick to
initializing
in real numbers now that you have the
selectivity on which things to remember
and which things to forget.
So that helps you and the initialization
uh you can have a bunch of different
oper options for the initialization.
And so I'm basically out of time but I
will just conclude with this. This is
just the architecture of the sequential
mamba block. So you have a linear layer
here. Then here's a convolution just to
capture maybe some local uh short range
dependencies that maybe these SSMs are
not as great as capturing.
You have a nonlinearity. Then you have
basically these um
linear layers that can help you uh
selectively learn the selective a uh a
b's and c's. It turns out that sometimes
you don't even have to uh be fully
selective. A lot of the heart of this
comes from choosing the appropriate
delta t and learning delta t. But also
learning b and c separately and learning
the b and c parameters separately can
give you some boost if you learn them in
an input dependent way. And then there's
this path over here which is a separate
kind of gating. Um, and when you have
this multiplication here, you're
basically saying, let me take uh my my
input, put it through a linear layer,
then I have this nonlinearity. And if I
didn't have this multiplication here,
this block would essentially be like an
MLP, right? But now I have this
multiplication here. But this block
seems to have has a similar effect as
though you if you had just put an MLP up
top. So the Mamba blocks often uh look
like this.
Um and so this this path is sometimes
called a gating path. So I just wanted
to point that out. Okay, I think that's
it. Uh um I am out of time so I will
answer that in office hours. Okay, see
you next class.