I'm working on homework zero. Uh
the be sure you submit it uh on Friday
by the deadline and uh discussions will
start this week. Uh they start on the
discussions will be on Wednesdays. Uh
this week we will staff just two
discussions because we only have one TA.
Um and this is 3 to 4 on Wednesday and 4
to 5 on Wednesday. On the website you
should see the room. So go to e282.org
you'll see the room. So go come to the
come to the discussion have your laptop
ready. We will post on uh ed before the
sort of computational part code we want
you to install on your machine. We'll
also have a link uh hopefully there that
you can use to download in case you
haven't already. You should have a
functioning uh Anaconda environment on
your laptop so you can do do work on it.
Uh you can also use collab but you have
to figure out um that on your own
possibly. The
important thing is the discussion we'll
build on we talk about in lecture. this
will generally be the case and if there
isn't room in the discussion given the
number of students and approximately 500
students who want to take the class and
the number of seats in those rooms um if
you're there and the room is full you
can't get in you know we're very sorry
sorry uh but we will post the entire
worksheet on ed afterwards so you can
see it as and the code will already have
been posted
so discussions are interactive in this
course. We expect you to go work with
others and be doing that. This is not a
sit back and relax kind of discussion.
If that's your idea of what a good
discussion is, just skip, you know,
don't go. Um, give your seat to someone
else. Uh, important other announcement
is it looks quite likely that we will be
able to expand the class. So, if you
want to get in, remember you have to do
homework zero. And
>> and even if you're already in
>> Yeah. Even if you you're in, you have to
do homework zero or you'll be dropped.
So this is extremely important. But uh
we have uh
keeping our fingers crossed that hey if
we hope to be able to let everyone in
who has does homework zero successfully
who actually feels like you know they
want to be in the class. And for those
of you if you're, you know, if you're
waiting outside the room three to four
and somehow you can't get into the room,
what I highly recommend doing is those
of you who are standing outside the
room, don't just leave. Everyone who's
standing outside the room, get together
and say, "Okay, let's together work on
this discussion worksheet." Uh there,
you know, you you'll have a you'll have
a critical mass of people. Let's say you
can't get into the room. Use the time,
use the time to make connections because
that is what is needed to you know
succeed in this machine learning deep
learning world is that you will have to
be selfarters. So this is in some sense
a simulation of the real world before
you graduate. It's uh so use that. Yes.
>> Will there be extra sheets printed for
people who are going to stand outside or
who may not get in?
>> Yeah,
>> we can try to make that happen. We will
try our best. That's a great idea. And
so yes, we will support that by making
sure that we can try to keep a stack of
sheets outside the room. But even if we
somehow fail at that, it will be posted
on ED so you can just download it and
and do it even if somehow but that's a
great suggestion and we will do our best
to have extra sheets so that you know
you can just work on your own. In
typical week once we're in steady state,
we'll be posting on to ED only after the
discussions have completed uh because we
know how many students have very bad
habits and so it's important for people
to go.
>> But this week we'll because of the
enormous difference between the number
of seats we can put forward and the
number of students who want to take the
class.
>> Yes.
>> Discussions will not be recorded. This
is on the website. So yeah, discussions
will not be recorded.
You're expected to go take notes.
>> Yes.
>> Will solutions be posted?
>> Yes, we will t typically post discussion
solutions uh afterwards.
Okay, good. So let's uh continue with
the material. So last time at the end
we're talking about thinking about you
know building up the idea of neural nets
from the perspective of function
approximation. So this is just a quick
you know recap of where we were. So I
remember I drew a function on the board
saying consider a function easiest one
to visualize our functions of one
variable that have exactly one output.
So R is to R. So you can draw them on
the board. So here we've drawn it. And
now the machine learning problem is that
there's a true function but you don't
know it. What you have is samples. So
here we've just labeled in red.
Oops.
You can see here these little x's. These
are the x's that you have in your
training data. And the corresponding y's
I've just labeled here. So this is a
pair an xy pair.
Uh so you have all of these. And what
you're trying to do is you're trying to
from these samples learn what the
function is. This is like a way of
visualizing what's happening. Discussion
will be going over this with code for
you.
Okay. So now last time we talked about
the idea of you know you can approximate
it with something. So you can
approximate a peiewise linear
approximation.
So you see here in
in this blue there's a particular
peacewise linear uh function
approximation that is drawn. Not a
particularly good one. You see all kinds
of kinks and things that are not
tracking the true function. But notice
that this peacewise linear approximation
that's drawn, the second blue one here,
it does go through all of the training
points. So notice it goes through all of
the red points. Okay, this is a generic
thing that can happen.
Um, there's another one, the
other blue one you can see that also
hits all the training points and somehow
feels a little bit better. So, this is
just meant to remind you of things that
you've already seen. But the focus where
we were going last time was to say that
you have such a peace-wise linear
function. You would like to
learn it from data. An intermediate step
that's very important is you have to
represent that function somehow on the
computer. And so you have to understand
what does it take to represent the
function you want. So in this case we
said that this peacewise linear
functions are specified by these elbow
locations, the slopes and an overall
vertical bias.
So to
parameterize that for the computer we
have to pick some linear algebraic
friendly representation of that. So we
started with this last time and last
time we got to saying that if we write
this as the representation for the
function where the g theta is described
this way
where the g theta individually looks
like this. It's a function that has one
kink in it. Then if you add up a
function shifted with lot with one kink,
you can get a function with as many
kinks as you want wherever you want
them. Okay? As long as you can move the
kinks.
So that's what we did last time.
Everyone cool with with this? So already
you know from your intuition that if I
choose a pie-wise linear approximation
with enough pieces, I can get as close
as I want to the function I want.
Okay. So
now
let's just draw this thing
in block diagram form.
So it's useful to be able to draw
diagrams. So in this case we have to
draw this wx plus b. So that's taking x
multiplying it by a w and then adding a
b to it. And then we have to run it
through this max with zero. So the max
with zero is called a rail loop. Right?
So it's literally the function that's
max of zero and whatever its input is.
It's called rectifying linear unit. It's
one of the most simple simplest
nonlinearities you have. Has lots of
nice interesting features which will be
talk about later. But
now in neural network terminology which
we expect everyone to have seen but
maybe the terminology you saw was
different. So I want to make sure
everyone's aligned to standard some
standard terminology. These are these
nonlinearities are sometimes called
activation functions.
It's just a term. It has no
just a just a word.
So if we put this stuff together this
math here together as math
we can just expand out these g thetas
and you see
an expression like this. So here is
another piece of notation that we want
to make sure everyone is is familiar
with. And the piece of notation here is
that
when we have a nonlinearity, we
sometimes apply the nonlinearity to an
entire vector. So you take x is a scaler
here. So just remember this is a scaler.
But this W, if I group together all of
these, if I take this sum. So notice
what I've done here is we've taken this
sum and we've just turned it into a
matrix
vector multiplication in this case. And
so this thing is a vector. All these
biases, these B prime I those are, you
know, a vector. And
when we have a nonlinearity that acts on
a matrix or a vector, unless we specify
otherwise, what that means is it acts
component-wise.
It's a piece of notation. So it acts on
every component. So notice this is a
compact representation of what you have.
Any questions on this compact
representation?
Okay, good. So now
there's a question of you know how do
you label these things because you have
this B over here right good here you
have this B over here and you have this
B over here so typically we will label
these things with which layer they
correspond to these biases so let me
write that in right now so let's call
this we're using these primes we might
as well interpret them as ones
Okay, so let's just uh call that one.
Make that prime into a one because it
looks like a one. And then
this other bias comes afterwards. So
this is two and this weight matrix is
also two.
Sometimes we'll specify very clearly for
you what the shapes are of things like
how big they are and sometimes you'll be
expected to figure it out from context.
So in this case the context is how big
is this sum.
So we'll just make it up to D.
In which case you can interpret this X
is a scalar
this W as let's say since we're
premultiplying it by oops we're
premultiplying it by a matrix we should
make this into a column. So we can think
of this as a column. It's a column with
D entries in it. This is a matrix that
has to give a scalar output. So we'll
call it'll be a row with D entries. But
in general, keeping track of the shapes
of things is something that's very
important and you should be doing. It's
one of the baines of uh working in
neural networks and just have to do it
also in the code. Um so in the code
often we'll use this package called IGEN
which helps you deal with these kind of
sums and things like this but you still
have to keep track of the shapes of
everything.
Okay. So it's useful to also be able to
think about this thing not as symbolic
math but also as a diagram. So in block
diagram form putting everything together
what we have is we have x coming in
then it meets these uh weights and
biases in parallel. Notice the
parallelism is very visible goes through
relus and then we get these
intermediate activations. So what we do
is we we call this make use dotted lines
here. Maybe I'll use a different color.
It's not visible what you're writing.
>> This is now okay.
>> So we'll call this the input layer.
Then this
is the
first hidden layer. Again, this is just
standard neural network terminology.
and the activations at the end.
These are called the activations.
So this is activation. You hear someone
talk about the activations at a
particular layer. What they mean is what
is the output of that layer.
This can get confusing because sometimes
we'll have layers that are just linear
and don't have any nonlinearities. Okay,
but they still use this term
activations. So all these hes are the
hidden activations and then we have
all these second layer weights and
the second layer bias.
And in this case if it's the last layer
we typically call it the output layer.
Use the same color.
Uh typically output layers we will have
will be something that is linear aphine
and oftentimes we will sometimes have
things that are after the output layer
either in processing that are like we'll
some put the loss we'll call it a loss
layer sometimes we'll convert things
into probabilities like softmax layers
we'll have other things we'll stick on
but typically as you've seen in your uh
previous class you have an input you
have some number of layers in domain
that have involve typically some
nonlinearity and matrix vector
arithmetic and then you have an output
layer just typically alphine that's how
we think about deep neural nets okay
very basic kind of make sure everyone's
on the same page with terminology so I
want to do this right now in lecture to
set up for discussion where you will see
code that walks you through this
specific example and lets you visualize
what's going on in this case seeing
what's happening and you can learn
you'll learn something from uh what
happens in that discussion. Okay, any
questions on this before we move on to
the next topic?
It's all very standard. Just want to
make sure everyone's on the same page.
Okay, great. Let's move on. Okay.
So, is this visible? Yes.
Okay. Is my mic working? Everyone can
hear me. The recording can hear me?
Yes. No.
Okay. Great. Okay. So um what I'm going
to do today is I'm going to talk through
some basically standard terminology. A
lot of this should be familiar to you
folks and then start going into what is
going to be the focus of our attention
for the you know first almost four three
four uh weeks of the class. I'm not sure
uh how many but uh where we're going to
talk about optimization and that's going
to be a a big thing that we're going to
come back to again and again. What I'm
going to be talking about today is stuff
that all of you have probably seen in
some form or another in either your
optimization class or your machine
learning class. And so it should be
quite familiar to you. What might not be
as familiar is the specific
interpretations because that's what
we're going to be uh spending a little
bit more time on in class today. So this
is a good lecture for you to try to get
a sense of what is the kind of work that
we're going to be doing in uh a bunch a
bunch of the class. Before I start, I
want to announce that we will have
office hours right after class in 400
Corey. It's a little bit of a funky room
to find, but what we will do every week
after lectures, we will kind of collect
right outside lecture. So if you want to
hang out for office hours, just like
hang out with us and then we will walk
as a group to office hours. uh strongly
encourage you to come. So um if in case
you can't find it, just wait for us
right outside this room and we will
always walk together to the office hours
room. Okay.
So you've all taken the machine learning
class and within machine learning you've
seen basically two different categories
of problems, right? You've seen the
supervised learning style of stuff and
you've seen unsupervised learning. So in
supervised learning basically you have
this situation where you have these XY
pairs of data. X is whatever
characteristics or features maybe that
the that the data has and you can think
of it as that uh you can call it your
input, you can call it your coariant.
This is just again terminology.
Y on the other hand is your output or
your label. So for example, you have a
bunch of cats and dogs and so you have
labels that say cat or dog. Now when you
think about these labels, the type of
label that you're thinking about leads
to different kinds of supervised
learning problems, right? If you have a
real valued output, often the kind of uh
machine learning model that you're doing
is a regression model where you're
trying to fit uh something in the style
of le squares, not necessarily that. On
the other hand, if you have binary or
discrete labels, then what you're trying
to do is something like classification.
So the cat and dog classification
problem is um is more of that style. And
these are kind of the two classic things
that you look at under supervised uh
learning. And here generally what we're
doing is we're saying look let's take
one specific model and train it to solve
one specific problem using this one
specific training data set that I have.
That's the paradigm that you're
operating in.
On the other hand then you have
unsupervised learning right and on
unsupervised learning the big thing is
that well we don't have the wise right
we don't have any labels. And so what
you're trying to do is you're trying to
uncover
properties that are implicit in the X
data that you have. So for example, the
most standard example that probably
everyone has seen for unsupervised
learning is principal components
analysis, right? I have a bunch of data
and then I'm trying to recover what are
the most important directions or what
are the directions with the most
variation within this data.
The other kind of um unsupervised
learning that you might have is then
clustering. And here probably everyone's
seen K means as well, right? Uh in 189
you've definitely covered this. So there
you're trying to say this is kind of an
unsupervised way of thinking about
clustering, right? That's the kind of
unsupervised parallel. You're trying to
say which of these folks are like the
others and which of these folks are are
different. So you know there's a cluster
here because these are all similar to
each other. There's a cluster here.
these these points are all similar to
each other. This is the second kind of
unsupervised learning problem. And then
maybe the third type that you have is is
looking at really density estimation. So
saying let's say I have a bunch of data.
I have X1, X2, X3, X4, so on and so
forth. And what I'm trying to understand
is what is the underlying
distribution that actually captures all
of this data. And then you use that for
basically all kinds of different
follow-on problems. But this also falls
into a category of unsupervised
learning. And this is all stuff that you
should have seen before, you're familiar
with. We just want to kind of put that
terminology out there, make sure
everyone's on the same page. Do you want
to add anything?
>> Yeah, I just want to add one comment
here. Um, so for those who've taken a
machine learning class, we're we're
extremely confident that everyone has
seen something like PCA and everyone has
seen K means. We know that some of you
may or may not have seen explicit
density estimation. So we we know that.
Um the other minor comment I wanted to
make is that what you probably
experienced in your machine learning
class was that these two categories felt
different to you in how they were taught
in that you saw on this side one style
of how things were done. Just you set
things up into some optimization
framework and you did some kind of
optimization thing with the exception of
one category here. where you learned
about decision trees which felt a little
different and over here what you saw
what might have felt like a whole bunch
of bespoke algorithms that do this
particular thing. So this is just a a
cultural thing you should also be aware
of uh that you might be familiar with.
Um this will be different when we come
to deep learning.
>> Any questions on this? We're good.
Okay. So then now what are we trying to
think about when we think about deep
learning? Well, within deep learning, we
also in some sense have these two
categor categories, right? We have the
supervised and unsupervised categories.
And you can use a deep network to do
regression. You can use a deep network
to do classification, right? We can
solve classical machine learning
problems using deep learning techniques.
So that paradigm extends and
is a standard thing to do.
What is something what is so what is a
supervised learning type of problem that
deep learning kind of unlocks that maybe
wasn't as studied in traditional machine
learning. So one example of that is
something like localized annotation. So
what do I mean by that? Let's say I have
an image and in this image there is a
cat and there's a bicycle and there's a
traffic light and there's a person
walking. Well, I want to basically have
okay, these are all the pixels that what
do these pixels represent? They
represent a the cat. I want to be able
to shade out what the traffic light is.
I want to be able to identify what uh
where the pedestrian is, for example.
And if you think about this for example
in the context of a self-driving car,
it's important to be able to do this
kind of semantic segmentation also with
context, right? It's one thing to say,
okay, here's an image and there's a cat
in it. It's another thing to say that
here's an image and there's a cat in the
middle of the road here. So doing this
kind of semantic segmentation is
something for example is a is a kind of
supervised learning that you can unlock
using uh deep learning type of
techniques.
Again, um there is the unsupervised
flavor of deep learning techniques. And
so here one of the most standard and uh
nice ones is of just learning
embeddings, right? So what does it mean
to learn an embedding? An embedding is
basically taking any kind of data and
turning it into vectors.
um the standard and most famous of this
and kind of this came from u NLP is
taking words and turning them into
vectors and so you have a vector for
every single every single word how do I
learn what vector is for what word well
that's I can think of that as a learning
problem that is my process of learning
embeddings and this is basically you
know in some sense uh similar in spirit
to the idea of principal components
analysis We want to say look we have all
this data. We want to figure out what
are the key dimensions of this problem.
I want to look at only those. I want to
reduce the dimensionality of my data.
Okay. So I take whatever my data set is
all my words or all of my numbers
whatever they are and I want to embed
them into a vector space into vectors so
that I can look at them within that
vector space of those vectors. Okay. So
there's a similarity here to how you've
been thinking about PCA.
And then you know as I'm sure everyone
has heard that the other big thing that
you have is generative models, right? So
you want to be able to generate a
picture of a cat, a picture of a dog,
you want to be able to generate text.
This is the big set of other kinds of uh
deep learning models where you have uh
the ability to basically create uh or or
or generate samples from a particular
from a particular distribution
essentially and from that this has a
parallel to what we think about as
density estimation in classical machine
learning where you're saying well you
know if I want to develop a model a
generative model for a cat what I'm
really doing is I'm saying let me look
at all of my training data and can I
develop a distribution for the pictures
of cats? And then when I want to
generate a picture of a cat, what that
really is is it's I'm trying to sample.
I'm saying take this distribution. Now
draw me a sample from my distribution on
cats. Right? So that's what generative
models um are trying to do. And we'll
we'll talk about this more in the class
as we go on.
And then within deep learning you have
basically the paradigm that we are now
that's becoming more and more important
which is the paradigm of foundation
models. And this idea of a foundation
model is this idea that you have some
data you've trained a model on something
it has learned something and then you
take that foundation model and fine-tune
it to your particular task. And this is
different from let's say how uh machine
learning has been done for a while where
let's say I wanted to develop a model to
predict housing prices um for you know
give me a house and give me the
prediction for the house price well I
train a specific model for that right I
take in the zip code I take in the
neighborhood I take in the school
information I take in you know what the
prices of the neighboring houses so on
and so forth I feed this data in maybe
as some vector I train some model and
then I get an output. And so I'm
specifically training this model to
predict houses uh house prices. Now if I
wanted to use this model to let's say
you know predict uh the weather, that's
probably not going to work. Or even if I
say I trained a model to predict house
prices in the Bay Area and then I wanted
to use this model to predict house
prices in New York. Well, my data is
going to be drawn from completely
distrib different distributions. these
models might not work. But the idea of
foundation models is uh a fundamentally
different perspective where we're saying
look we're just going to train data on a
bunch uh train models on a bunch of
different data without necessarily even
having a particular task in mind and
we'll hope that the models will learn
some underlying representation of the
data and then we can fine-tune it and
use the representations that is somehow
learned in an underlying way to you know
be fine-tuned to our specific specific
task and more and more we're moving into
this foundation model fine-tuning
perspective from the perspective that we
had before of a specific model for a
specific task.
Anything you want to add before I move
on?
>> So uh here there's going to be a
difference I mean this we just described
is the reality. Um, of course in this
class we will still have you train
oftentimes models from scratch for some
things you need to know how to do that.
Just one has to understand that practice
and the real world is shifting and the
engineering considerations are shifting
and we are going to be teaching you
about that shift um in the in the
course. Probably in your machine
learning class you've just never touched
this issue at all. You only train models
from scratch for a specific purpose and
we were kind of told this is a paradigm
and we just want to make you aware
paradigms do shift.
>> Okay. So with this um these are just
some examples of you know supervised
learning tasks. Um these are nice uh
examples from the prince book. Here's an
example of uh generative modeling. So
these are generated
uh models. These are not real cats. So
some examples. Okay.
So with this now I'm going to start
writing. I highly encourage everyone to
take notes and it's I'm really happy to
see that a bunch of people are taking
notes. For those of you who have laptops
open, I assume that you're using this
laptop to do something that is helping
you learn actively right now in this
class. Otherwise, I strongly encourage
you to put those laptops away. Um,
because it's distracting to you and it's
distracting to your neighbors. So, if
it's really essential for you to use
your laptop, go for it. But I encourage
you to take notes especially with now I
haven't really made slides for this
because I want to be able to write and
uh have support you writing as I'm
writing. Okay.
I think I just pulled the cable but
yeah. Okay. Good. Okay. So now we're
going to be talking about
optimization.
So we have in our case some XY pairs.
This is our data. And what we're trying
to do is we want to be able to basically
take in our data and predict a label. So
we have some training data. But what we
want to be able to do is we want to do
something with some new data. Given a
new sample X, I want to be able to
predict what is the label for example Y
on it. And for this we want to have some
model. Let's call that model
F theta of X. And this gives us Y. And
so here again X is my input,
Y is my output.
And here now I've introduced something
new. I've introduced this theta. And
these theta are my parameters.
Okay,
maybe I'll try.
So, how am I going to do this? Well, I
really want what do I want out of my f
theta? I want to be able to do something
that takes in real world data and gives
me an output and gives me a label of
that real thing.
What do I actually have in my hand? In
my hand, I have just samples of training
data. I have x1 y1 x2 y2 x3 y3. Right?
So the best thing I can do is I can say
well let me try to do the best I can
given my training data. Right? So what I
have
And the kind of standard thing that we
always do in machine learning is we do
risk minimization or empirical risk
minimization
on this training data
where let's say I'm taking some I want
to look at the argument
over theta
of now my loss function.
So I'm looking at this loss function.
This L is my loss function.
Y I
F theta
XI.
So let me unpack this a little bit now.
So this L here represents my loss
function. It's telling me how much do I
care and how do I care when what my
model predicts which is this f theta of
xi is different from yi right so this
could be for example squared loss it
could be cross entropy loss whatever
pick your favorite loss function right
this is telling me in what way do I care
when I get it wrong and I'm going to say
look how many data points do I have
let's say I have n training data points.
Well, these are my n samples. I'm going
to look at the loss and the difference
between yi and uh uh I I'm going to look
at the loss for each of these data
points and then average them. And then I
want to find that parameter. I want to
find that theta
that minimizes this average loss. Right?
This is a specific well- definfined
quantity that I can compute using my
training data. So why do I care about
this particular loss? Is there something
special about this?
In some sense, yes, it's the thing I
have. I care about this because the
training data is the data that I have.
Right? So as we talked about in the
first lecture, there's an element of
looking where the light is here. You
know, why are we choosing to fit a model
to our training data? Because we have
that training data. If I had more data,
if I had other data, I would love to fit
a model to that, but I don't have it.
So, what sometimes can happen in, you
know, thinking about uh training these
models is that we get so focused on the
training data that we think that fitting
the model to the data is the point. But
that's actually not the point. The point
is to be able to predict something about
some real world data. That's what we're
trying to do. But we have reduced it to
this problem of fitting a model to this
training data because that is what we
know how to do. It's kind of like you
sometimes think about all right why do I
why do we like linear models? We like
linear models because we understand them
because we can do something with them.
It's the same kind of thing. We like the
training data because we have it in our
pocket.
So how do we then go from this once we
acknowledge this? How do we go from this
to trying to you know approximate how
well we can do in the real world? How do
we actually measure how well we can do?
Right. So for this we have basically
hold out test data. So we say look you
know if I want to be able to approximate
what I can do on a real true new sample
that I have never seen before and I want
to measure if my model is good or not.
The best thing I can do is I look at the
data that I have. I hold out some of it.
I pretend as though I have never seen it
before and I try to fit a model and I
and I measure my performance of my model
that has been trained on this other
training data on this new data that I've
never seen. Right? So that is what we
think about as as hold out test data.
But how do we now even kind of measure
this or how do we get a sense of
how well we're doing? And because we
don't know anything about the real world
data like say let's say you're trying to
you know uh predict uh labels on
different kinds of animals and you have
a label prediction for cats and dogs and
cows and sheep and snakes and you know
so on and so forth
and if I could have a full distribution
on the you know
all the animals in the world I would
love to have that but I don't actually
know what that distribution is. Maybe I
train on a bunch of stuff that is, you
know, animals and then I get a picture
of a bunch of dinosaurs.
You know, clearly my model that has
never seen a picture of a dinosaur
before is not going to do well on this.
So to be able to make some sense of how
we are
um going to be able to do, we have to
make some additional assumptions on our
data. Right? If we can't say anything,
it's going to be really hard to give
guarantees about what we can do because
well, the real world can do lots of
really crazy things. So the key
assumption that we often make in this
setup is we assume
I don't want this color.
So key assumption
is we assume that X and Y are drawn
from a distribution
P XY. So I say that I have a joint
distribution from which these labels and
these uh data points are drawn. And
let's say my training data and my test
data are coming from uh these same same
situations. This might not always be
true but often this is an assumption
that we will make to be able to
understand what our performance is. And
then we can think of our theta star
as the argument
of theta over that expectation. Now now
we can take an expectation over this
distribution. We can think of this as
the loss of yi comma fa
x i
>> what? Oh.
So this is basically the thing that we
can use to try and uh capture the idea
of our uh of generalization right how
well can we train can we predict
something on data that we have not yet
seen okay but even with this we have
some challenges and
it's not like we can completely uh solve
this problem. So what are some of the
key challenges that we that we see in
something like this? Well, the first
challenge for example,
challenge one
is that well, we've assumed that we have
some underlying distribution pxy, but we
actually don't know what this is, right?
So, we don't know this. And so, how do
we handle that?
Well, we handle that essentially through
having our heldout test set, right?
We're having an assumption that all of
our data is coming from this underlying
distribution pxy. And so we say, well,
the best we can do is we have this test
set. Let's pretend that that's the
distribution. Let's assume that that's
the underlying distribution. We will
measure performance on the test set as
an approximation
of this true um underlying expectation
that we actually want to capture. Okay,
does that make sense to everyone?
Everyone with me? Questions? Add
something?
>> Yeah. Just a comment here is it's more
way of thinking, right? Um when you're
getting when given a problem, you often
are told everything the problem states
is just taken as god-given, right? But
real life isn't like that. So, we're
trying to point out to here is that we
make assumptions to help us think, but
then we know those assumptions don't
hold and you have to do something. This
key distinction of what are the
assumptions you're making that are
helping you think and then what are the
things you have to actually do and how
do you bridge that gap is important to
keep in mind
Okay, so the second challenge that you
might have is that well I have this loss
function and that's great but maybe it
doesn't work well with the kinds of
optimizers that I want to use. As we're
going to talk about optimization is kind
of the heart of um a lot of machine
learning.
So you want things that you can actually
run algorithms like gradient descent on,
right? And if you have non-ifferiable
losses, well that's just not going to
really work very well. And so the key
solution here is that well if your loss
doesn't work
find another loss
um you know make it somehow make it
smooth make it continuous lose the non-
differential abilities to be able to
make it work again um as was emphasized
in the earlier lecture it's about what
can you do to make things work right
it's not about what would be perfect in
the ideal world it's um it's a there
there is an element of what is the
engineering problem to solve we to have
a sum loss by on which we can run
gradient descent. So um that's one key
thing and then there's a third challenge
which is
let's say I did the all of this I found
some you know I found I made this
assumption I found a loss that works and
I even found a theta hat right I fit my
model I solved my optimization problem
here. I got a theta hat. Great.
Theta hat works
great
on training data.
But then I actually run it and evaluate
it on my test data,
but fails
on
test data
in the sense that it performs really
poorly. I maybe shouldn't say fails.
performs poorly.
So somehow my theta hat has learned
something very very specific about the
training data and is able to minimize
the loss there. Get that be very low.
But whenever I show it something that is
not from the training data,
it is completely failing. And the common
reason that this happens is essentially
overfitting, right? You've somehow fit
too closely to the exact examples that
you were given in the training data and
you're not able to generalize outside of
that to what might be your test data.
And so the common solution that we use
for this is something that you have seen
before
and that is regularization.
And what regularization does is it gives
you basically some
side information or some other pressure
on the parameters of your model to say
hey we love the training data but just
not that much you know
keep a little bit of distance. So try to
fit to something else. So the common
what's the what's the regularization
that you've all seen before
>> lasso. What else? What's even easier
than lasso? ridge right so what is ridge
reg what is ridge doing if you think
about ridge if I think about my ridge
regularizer
right I have some loss I have let's say
x w minus y whole squ
and if if I feel my w is fitting too
closely to this data
what's something that I want to try and
do I want to say hey maybe think about
putting W somewhere else. What's a way I
can apply pressure on W to go somewhere
else? I can change this term, right? I
can change this optimizer. So here I'm
trying to find an argument
over W.
And if I say lambda
norm w,
what I'm saying is look, I want you to
find a w that fits that makes x w be
equal to y, but I also want to make sure
that you're not doing that while making
w be 10 billion, right? I care about w
being small. And this is a common thing
that you do because you think that well,
you know, parameters are generally
small. And if you don't like this well
there's another you know hundred
different ways of doing regularization
to incorporate whatever side information
that you might have about W. You can do
tikkenov you can do lasso whatever else
you want right
and this you've seen you know in your
classes before that can help this can
help you avoid this problem of
overfitting by saying don't go too close
to that training data but of course with
every solution there comes a new
problem. So now what is the problem that
we have introduced by the solution of
regularization?
Yeah.
>> Bias. Yes. But what's a practical
engineering problem that we need to deal
with? Yeah.
It might be that this optimization
problem is harder to solve. That's
entirely possible. But I'm thinking of
something very boring. I'm like how to
write how to actually solve this thing.
What's lambda right now? There's one
more number that I have to deal with. Is
lambda one? Is it 0.1? Is it 10?
Each of these will give me a widely
different solution. Right? So it's not
like oh you just write ridge you call
ridge and it's solved. But it actually
matters what the parameters are. Now
what I've introduced here is what this
lambda is is now it's a hyperparameter
right
and I want to make sure that well the
hyperparameter might will actually
affect my solution. So if I was the best
student and I wanted to find the best
hyperparameter what would I do?
I would try them all.
Right? And then we could have the entire
class trying all of the hyperparameters
and that that would be it. But it's
clearly in feasible even for this simple
situation, right? To try all of the
hyperparameters. So hyperparameter
search is now
an extremely becomes becomes a problem.
Um and how do we find this? And the
thing is that lambda you know you might
have not have qualitative differences in
the solution for different sorry let me
restate that
lambdas and hyperparameters typically
vary or the order of magnitude of this
hyperparameter is typically what
matters. So when you're doing a
hyperparameter search, often you're not
going to actually look at every single
lambda, but you're going to look at
different orders of magnitude. Um, and
you're going to try to do a sweep over
that. But even that is often, you know,
can be too hard to do. When you're doing
this, typically what you're going to do
is you're going to have a set of
validation data that you're going to
keep separate. So this is your training
data, you have your validation data, and
then you have your test data. This
validation data is what you're going to
use to say well I trained my model on my
training data. Let me now validate my
model by looking at uh how different
hyperparameters are behaving uh on the
validation data. And then I have my test
data which is kind of my what I'm going
to use for my uh generalization
performance. Right?
So this this makes sense. But in reality
when you come to deep learning you don't
have just this one hyperparameter like
you have in ridge and even in ridge
identifying the hyperparameter you
cannot try them all right. So you have
too many hyperparameters when you're
thinking about deep learning problems.
So that's a key problem that again we
don't really know how to solve. So we've
solved you know we solved the
overfitting problems regular
regularization but now we've introduced
this new problem of hyperparameter
search. And so there's a couple of you
know things that we can do here but this
is the new problem
is hyperparameter search.
Okay.
And there's a couple of standard
solutions that you kind of use. The
first is that you use um let's say you
just try to take all of your
hyperparameters and scale them together.
You kind of couple them together so that
you pick what just picking by picking
different scalings you're varying all of
the hyperparameters at the same time.
And so you limit your search pace.
You're not taking every hyperparameter
and doing um a crazy amount of search uh
on it. So how should I write that? I
should say scale
hyper
parameters.
Uh
together,
couple them.
The other option that you have basically
is to say well I think Alan likes to
call it be superstitious.
um which basically says look at what
people have done before and look at the
paper that you're building on. Look at
whatever the default parameter was. Um
what did the people who just did the
work before you do it? Just copy exactly
that it worked for them. Hopefully it'll
work for you. And if you can't find
something that matches exactly what you
were doing, find the closest thing and
then use their hyperparameters. Right?
So basically use
what other people did.
>> Yes. Question.
It seems like we really enjoy
understanding our data and generalizing
and so I'm wondering if a better
machine learning models that optimize
meaning
these like the lambda like alpha beta
values change over time as the model's
learning and the best way to learn needs
to be found through gradient descent.
Does that exist like are there meta
machine learning?
>> Yes, this is Do you want to take that
question?
>> Um, yeah. So, there's a lot of work on
how you set hyper is a big problem. So,
there are learning methods that people
use to try to set them. That's better
than uh so talk about when you can't
search. So, first is
you can search dumbly, you can then
search intelligently. There's a whole
range of how to search intelligently.
It's important to do dumb search well
too. So for doing dumb search, well the
dumbest of dumb search is you drop down
a grid over all your hyperparameters,
scale them on a log scale um for
appropriate appropriate scaling and just
sample in this grid uh on a regular grid
and evaluate everywhere. Cursive
dimensionality kills you there. Then
there's the next dump approach which is
important to recognize is instead of
searching that grid by exhaustive
search, do random sampling.
randomly draw things inside that grid
with an appropriate distribution and
then pick the best one. I can afford to
do this many hyperparameter tests, draw
that many samples. This this is better.
Okay. Then after that comes what you're
talking about is more intelligent ways
of doing the sampling and possibly doing
adaptive sampling there to do search.
All of that is hyperparameter search
when you can afford to do the search.
Then comes the problem of you can't
afford even that much and that's where
what's being talked about here comes in
which is the reality that every one of
you will face and everyone in practice
faces all the time
other questions
okay
so with this now I want to say okay so
clearly we have established that
optimization matters um so let's talk
about optimization and what is the
optimizer that we are going to be using
for most of our time
well it's going to be gradient descent
or some variation on gradient descent
okay so here what are we trying to do
let's say I have my loss function my uh
this is um I have my y
f theta of x
and I'm going to just rewrite this maybe
as the loss and explicitly call out this
parameter theta theta um
x train
y train. Okay,
gradient descent says okay let me try to
now use
a step every single time to get a better
and better estimate of what my parameter
theta is. So I say I start at some theta
kn. This is my initial condition
and then I write theta t + 1 is given by
the gradient descent update
theta times the gradient with respect to
theta
of my loss function.
um
okay so here basically I'm saying that
this is where my next step is this is
where I currently am
here is my learning rate
and this is my gradient so I'm going to
take a step of the size um of given by
my learning rate in the direction of my
negative gradient. Okay.
So now a whole lot of stuff that we do
comes from the possibilities and the
limitations that are introduced by
gradient descent because gradient
descent or stoastic gradient descent or
the variations thereof are our
optimizers of choice. The fact that we
can implement these efficiently and
quickly um the fact that we can do back
propagation is what enables everything
right. So understanding gradient descent
fundamentally helps us understand what
are the possibilities and limitations in
general for training gradient descent.
Right?
So what we're going to do today is we're
going to think about basically gradient
descent and some brothers and sisters of
gradient descent essentially. So I want
to think about this
specifically for the least squares
problem. So I want to consider
now W is my parameter. I'm just taking
the loss of w and that's just x w
minus y. Okay, so there's no regularizer
here. I'm just trying to find a vector w
such that I can have this linear model
be fit as well as possible. Okay,
I know that this is the least squares
problem
and I know my optimal solution for this.
I know that my war star is given by
xrpose x inverse
xtranspose
y. Okay.
And now I can write my gradient descent
update equation. Actually all of you
write the gradient descent update
equation as a good practice. You'll
probably need it in homework zero and
homework one anyway. So why don't you
write the gradient descent update
equation?
So for that you have to take the
gradient of
this loss. So what is the gradient of a
squared norm? Anyone?
What's the gradient of this guy?
[Music]
Okay, compute the gradient. Take one
minute. I'll give you one minute.
I'll set a timer.
Yes. Question
three
well on the test but not
sorry perform well on the train but not
well on the test data. Is there a
possibility that the probability
distribution of your training data is
not
close enough to the past data?
>> Yeah, that's that's entirely possible,
right? And so there's a lot of different
problems that you can that can show up
of this form. One of the key like this
is called basically out of distribution
data when your test data is out of the
distribution of the training data. And
that's kind of like this example where
you train on cats and dogs and then
you're trying to classify dinosaurs.
smart way to tell if these two
distributions are the same or close
enough.
>> So definitely yes. So there is
definitely you can do things that you
will try to estimate the density of what
your your test data is. You will try to
um
uh sometimes you can try to create
samples that are from this from the if
if you have a sense of what the estimate
of your test data is you can try to
create samples generate samples either
come up with labels for those uh or
acquire data uh there's this is a huge
huge area of research is how to handle
this kind of out of distribution area
how to out of distribution data
Okay. So now in that one minute everyone
else
what is the gradient
of this
>> very good right okay so make sure you
know how to do this so with this we can
write this gradient update
Okay.
And I'm just going to So this is a WT
here
and I'm just going to rearrange this to
write this as identity.
Bring the WTS together. 2 ADA
XT X
times WT
U plus now this 2 A XRpose
Y right
so now what I see here is that I have a
recurrence relation
on my WTS right that's the weight and so
what do I know about these kinds of
recurrence relations what matters here
in terms of so what do I want this
gradient descent to do first what what
is the ideal behavior for this gradient
descent for me to be able to
um identify my correct parameter
what's the word
starts with a cge
>> converge good right I want this to
converge to a solution and so I want to
take step by step by step go to wherever
I want to do what matters for the
convergence of this given that I have
this matrix here that is dominating how
my iterates are evolving
this matrix is what is the key thing
right and in fact I can think about this
I can specifically think about this as
let's say I know wt minus one I can look
at it as the distance to my optimal so I
know that my optimal here is given by
this so I can instead of just thinking
about conversion I can think
specifically in the case of le squares I
can say how fast am I conversing to w
and I can subtract war star from both
sides.
This gives me i - 2 x
wt.
Okay.
So I'm not going to you know in the
interest of time and this you've all
seen before.
This I can just write as
okay just grouping some terms
you can rewrite this also in terms of
war star
and I get this evolution.
So this thing here
this is a vector.
What is this?
What kind of object is this? What are
the shapes of this?
Is this a vector? It's a matrix. Right?
So now if I want to try and understand
how
this vector so what I want this thing to
go to zero.
I want to converge to my optimal
solution. What do I need to think about
of this matrix to be able to
say anything about whether this is going
to converge or not converge? What's the
key thing?
Yeah, just start it out. Just
>> it's values, right? So, what do I need
to check for the IGEN values of this
thing?
This everyone should know this. Just
just Yeah, I just want to make sure that
you're all with me. The whole room
should resoundingly
speak up. The more of you speak up, the
less likely your own voice is heard.
>> So there's
>> you know this you know this whatever is
your gut is correct. Just say it.
>> Interesting. They're saying the
continuous case.
>> Ah okay.
Okay. So these are discreet. So yes
there's two cases. So if you
um
so in a discrete setting I want to make
sure that my igen values are all
less than one small what happens if I 2
* 2 * 2 * 2 * 2 goes to infinity half*
half* half* half time half goes to zero
right so which one do I want this to be
like less than one right so I want all
of my igen values to be uh to be bounded
in absolute value. So I want to look at
the igen values
of identity minus.
Okay.
So what does this tell me now about
these values? How can I can I say
anything about these values?
What kind of matrix is this here?
Identity is a special matrix. What kind
of matrix is it?
>> Diagonal. It's also symmetric. What
about 28 is a scalar xrpose x is also
symmetric. Right? So this entire matrix
that I have here
is symmetric. Right? And so I know that
basically the singular values and the
igen values only differ in sign.
So that also tells me like again you
know I can think about this in terms of
igen values but I can also just think
about it in terms of singular values
doesn't matter because it's symmetric we
can just use igen values for now. So I
want to make sure now that
absolute value of 1 - 2a
times this lambda max
is less than one. Right? So now if I'm
looking at the igen values of this and
if I want all of the igen values of this
to be smaller than one, what are the two
candidates that I have for being the
maximum igen value in terms of the igen
values of xrpose x
I can look at remember there's an
absolute value here. So I either have to
look at the largest igen value or I have
to look at the smallest igen value.
Right? The igen values of this are going
to be in between
this and I need 1 - 2 a lambda min to be
also less than one. Does this make
sense?
Right? One of these two is going to be
the maximum value.
And so when I process this through
actually take one minute and come up
with a condition on ADA with this. Do
this. Do this algebra. Do this algebra.
I'm not going to do it out. You do it
because if I write the answer, you won't
remember why it's tricky.
So how do you deal with the absolute
value?
That means the absolute value implies
two inequalities that you have to
satisfy, right? Not just one.
Okay. So if I just look at this uh
lambda max equation, I have minus one
should be less than 1 minus 2 a lambda
max. It should also be less than one.
Which side is trivially satisfied? the
left hand side inequality is trivial or
the right hand side inequality is
trivial.
the right hand side, right? Okay, good.
So, this implies that I what I need to
look at I need to have minus 2 less than
minus
2 ADA lambda max, which implies that I
need to have ADA less than one over
lambda max
for this thing for this thing to be less
than one. Right? So basically if I
choose a learning rate that is smaller
than 1 / lambda max I know that this
quantity
is going to be less than one. Is it
sufficient for me to just look at that
or do I need to check anything else?
How many people think this is
sufficient? How many people think I need
to check anything else?
Okay. Well, you're both correct. Both
answers are technically valid though
this is in some sense sufficient. So
here we can do the same algebra. We will
get ADA less than one over lambda min.
Right? But what do we know about one
over lambda min and one over lambda max?
Which one's the bigger one? Which one's
smaller? One over lambda max is always
the tighter bound. Right? So if I can
check that ada is less than one over
lambda max. This is automatically
satisfied. So the constraint on my
learning rate comes from the largest
value of this matrix because that's
what's trying to blow up your uh your
vector or your error as fast as it can.
Right?
So that's what says this is the maximum
step that you can take. Okay?
So I don't think I'm
going to
do this right now. I'll try to see.
Okay. So I'll
do a small bit. Let's see.
So now just to kind of build this
intuition further,
this is some constraint on my learning
rate. Does this tell me which learning
rate I should choose? You know, I don't
want just sum any learning rate. But
what actually matters is actually
choosing a specific learning rate.
Which learning rate might I want to
choose? Or how do I go about doing that?
Well, one property that I might want to
have when I am choosing my learning rate
is I might want to have that all of my
igen values are as close to each other
as possible. Basically, my two
candidates for my maximum. I want to
make them as close to each other as
possible because then I don't have one
direction that's running off and the
other direction that's very slow. Right?
the more uniform I my my learning rate
ADA hits every single one of my igen
values right so the more evenly
everything is is decaying the faster I'm
going to converge otherwise what's going
to happen is I'm going to move very fast
in some directions and move slowly in
other directions so to deal with that
basically what I want to have for the
fastest convergence is I want to have
something like this
is I want to have my two candidates
be equal.
Okay. And of course you can equalize
this if lambda min is equal to lambda
max. But the other thing that you can do
if you solve this out you will get ADA
is equal to 1 / lambda min plus
lambda max.
Okay.
So what you will see is that the optimal
ADA that you're going to have
is given by this. And then when you plug
this back in to see what is the actual
decay rate that you're getting, you'll
see that the condition number is
actually going to pop out. So this is
going to be the difference between the
uh or the ratio of the largest and the
smallest singular values. And if you
remember from the discussions on ridge
regression and regularization,
remember when do things struggle to uh
converge? When do you have these
overfitting problems or uh in your
training data? Well, it's when your
condition number is bad, right? And so
you see that all of these things are
kind of connecting up and coming back
together.
So I have five minutes and I'm going to
try to get to one more thing in this
time coming back to regularization.
But what I want to try to build up to is
the idea of the implicit regularization
of gradient descent. This is coming to
the what are the possibilities and
limitations that are introduced by
gradient descent. Well, one of the very
cool properties that gradient descent
has is it has this property of implicit
regularization. Have people heard this
term implicit regularization before? No.
There's no expectation that you have. Um
but this is something that people uh or
that you know is a is a nice thing about
gradient descent. And the way that we
can understand this property is through
uh thinking about specifically uh
gradient descent from the perspective of
igen values and singular values. Okay.
So I'm not going to be able to finish
all of it today given the time I have
but I'm going to start building up to
it. And what I would like you to do is I
would like you to go home remember ridge
remember SVD so that we can finish this
next time and you'll be fully on board.
Plus you have to do homework zero which
you have to learn that for. But now let
me take for example the ridge solution.
And my ridge solution looks something
like this. Right? So if now my loss was
the following
xw - y.
And now you should have um this
expression should look familiar,
right? Everyone's seen this expression
before.
This is also by the way equal to the
following. So this is like kind of like
the least squares version of ridge.
There's also the minor version of ridge
or the kernel ridge form
um xxrpose
plus lambda i
inverse
time y.
So this
the kernel
um This has some nice properties that um
I don't think I have the time to talk
about but definitely remind yourself of
why it is nicer to think about in a
sense xxxrpose compared to xrpose x
because xxrpose is just computing the
inner products of your features or inner
products of your data right and so for
functions where you can easily compute
the inner products this kernel form can
be a lot easier and faster to compute.
But now if I think about this X is equal
to U sigma VRpose as my SVD of X.
How can I write W star?
Well, I can write star
and I will just write this out
as
I'll use this form.
I'm going to have this xrpose x. So I'll
I'll I'll I'll
um
yeah.
Um
so let me plug in uh I get v sigma
transpose urpose times
u sigma
pose plus lambda i inverse
time xrpose
times y.
This is my w star.
And I will I'm just out of time. Okay, I
will do this again next time. But this
basically what I want to point out is
that this I can write
as the following.
Okay.
Yeah.
Okay. So what I want to say here uh I'll
do this again next time but what I want
to say here
is look at this particular quantity here
right so these are the singular vectors
here and here the left and the right
singular vectors
if I can basically what this is saying
is like look I'm like if I look at
gradient descent it's going it's
decoupling the movement in the
directions given by each of the singular
vectors right that's what these are
these things are pulling out
and what this quantity is here when
lambda is very very close to zero when
it's very small what I have is that
this thing becomes very small right if
if lambda is very close to zero sigma
square over sigma squar is basically one
over sigma
>> sorry
Yeah,
this sigma over sigma squar uh is
basically like one over sigma. Whereas
when lambda is very large, what we get
is that this thing uh is close to zero
and then you don't see any movement in
any of those directions.
So we will talk about how this is
connected to early stopping of gradient
descent in the in the next lecture. I'm
over time so I'll stop here now.
>> So we have
>> office hours in 400 Cy.
>> Yeah. So, we'll walk over there next.