So, we're going to continue
uh where we left off. We're about a
little bit behind. So, I'm going to try
to finish what I wanted to cover and
then hand it over. So I want to finish
up the states self-s supervision stuff
and we'll switch to going back to the
statesbased model idea of how to make
recurrent things actually work in a
modern context.
So
um recall last time what we did was we
used this example of you know common
filtering where we have a linear system.
We know if we knew everything about it
how we could make the optimal estimator
for it based on the observations for the
estimating the state. But we asked the
question how could we learn that if we
had labels and then we said what could
we do if we didn't have ground truth
labels of the underlying state? Can you
still learn anything? And we said yes,
you could. And now we want to step back
and like learn from that example a more
general idea of self-supervision.
And so recall the basic story in
self-supervision is there's a pattern I
want to learn that I believe exists and
is visible in the data. However,
my training algorithms that I have need
labels to train. I need losses and
labels, things like this. But I don't
have any labels. So what can I do? So
the answer is if I don't have them and I
need them, I'll make them from the data
I have.
And so the lessons we learned was that
you know it is in fact possible to learn
a partial pattern. Uh so in the case
that we did before, we said look if you
ran this with only the um input output
behavior, you could never learn what the
actual underlying state was because
there's you know change of coordinates.
But you can basically learn it up to
change of coordinates.
Um, and we saw that you we need
scaffolding parts of the neural net that
you train, namely that artificial lay
that artificial output layer that we
created um that we needed to basically
be able to run our loss. And we saw in
the context of the sequential uh common
filtering type model that there's this
generic idea of next thing prediction in
causal sequence modeling. So if you're
trying to predict something and you
believe there's a causal pattern, you
can try to predict the next thing and
hope that you can catch something from
that. It's very natural in the common
filtering setting. It comes out of the
ideas of system editification more
generally in control, but it's more
broadly useful.
So what I want to do is I mentioned this
last time is I want to step back and
connect on supervised learning in
classical ML. And recall there's two
things that you learned about. Um
there's dimensionality reduction and
clustering.
Uh you also learned possibly about
density estimation and we also mentioned
before that generative modeling is a
kind of unsupervised learning but we're
not going to engage with that part here.
And so we said look think about PCA
which is the dimensionality reduction
idea you know and we said look you have
an algorithm that you know and the
algorithm that you have is you have x's
you have no labels no y's just have x's
but you believe that there's some
interesting distribution underlying it
and you want to understand it from a
kind of linear or gaussian perspective
and so what you're thinking about is
that even though this is in a high
dimensional space it actually exists in
a lower dimensional space that's what's
interesting about it and the PCA
approach neglecting the main parts is
you construct a matrix X which has your
data points as its rows. You could also
do it with columns. I'm just using rows
to match what we saw in linear
regression. You comput it SVD
and then you take the top K singular
vectors and you use those for
dimensionality reduction. So you say
those top K vectors the V's are the same
size right as the uh X's. Those V
vectors represent the directions of
greatest variability from the PCA
perspective. That's where the
distribution is actually moving around.
And so you can use it for another
problem to do dimensionality reduction
by simply projecting to the lower
dimension using those V's. Okay, so
that's something you've seen and the
you learned this in your machine
learning class. However, this feels very
different than supervised learning when
you look at it because there's no loss,
there's no labels, there's no gradients,
and there's no optimizer. So, literally
every single thing that we've been
studying in deep learning is not present
here seemingly. So, that's where we kind
of ended. We kind of zipped in the last
two minutes. I want to make sure
everyone with me on this. We have to
start here. Okay. So
you think back and ask why was this PCA
approach reasonable
and one way to understand his
reasonability is to think about the
echert young mki theorem for forbinius
norm. So what does that say? What that
theorem says is if you look at a matrix
X and you want to find a rank at most K
approximation of X where the closeness
of the approximation you're going to
measure in a norm which norm provenius
norm so proven norm just says I would
like to match every entry of that matrix
as well as I could and the average mean
squareed error across all the entries of
the matrix.
So if you think about minimizing this
inbinous norm, this theorem tells you
that the way to do it is just to take
the outer product form of the SVD and
just truncate it. Cut it at K. Just keep
the top K singular uh values and their
corresponding singular vectors to
construct your rank K matrix. Okay, so
this is the theorem that uh you've seen
in your optimization class. Um it's a
very interesting theorem, right? Because
rank kess is a very non-convex
condition. The sum of two rank k things
or the average of two ranky things is
definitely not rank k. Um well typically
not rank k. Um so that but you can all
you can solve this this way. So what
this provides us is a a way to think
about what PCA is doing in a different
light because here you have something
that looks like a loss, right? It's
actually good oldfashioned mean square
error,
right? So suddenly you can think about
what it is that PCA is doing as
minimizing a certain loss. But that's
good, right, for us. So now let's like
expand on this.
So we interpret this in neural net
terms. So for neural net terms what we
need so I've written there no loss no
labels no gradients right it also has uh
let me just add to that list
no mini batches
right it has training data x but there's
no no like batches that you're running
so we want to interpret this in neural
net terms and to do that we're going to
say first thing I'm going to try to that
is something that corresponds to a mini
batch size one. Okay, so I want to take
a batch type perspective. So to do that
I'm going to take a rowby row
perspective on x hat. So if you think
about it in Fbinius norm right if this
is X
and
this is X hat
okay let's label these
so I'm just writing these X and X hat
together
because I want to approximate this in
Finius norm. I want X1 hat transpose
this row to be as close as possible to
this row. Does everyone see that there's
an overall constraint that this matrix
should be rank K, but I want to match it
row by row in closeness in mean squed
error. So that's very good, right? from
our point of view because if I want to
say I want to use as my mini batch idea
the rows of X it tells me that there's
something to loss it against namely that
row of X hat yeah
>> is there anything special
>> as I said before we can do this also by
columns
>> I just I'm just using rows because we
did linear regression you put our data
in rows so
>> that's all
nothing is nothing is specific about
rows here. Um, okay. So then we can say
great, let me try to interpret this in
neural net terms fully. So now I can
think of X as a D- dimensional vector.
So now I'm going to flip it to go to
columns. Up here I was thinking about
it, but I can always now think about in
terms of columns. Think about this as a
dimensional vector and I'll have an X
hat, which is it reconstruction, right?
Supposed to be close to it.
And now I want to minimize this regular
squared uklidian norm regular mean
squared error.
The only thing that remains is I have to
enforce the rank k constraint.
So I can encode the rank k constraint
that I want structurally
as
how do I make sure that something's rank
k. I make it the product of two matrices
that are structurally at rank at most k.
then it can't grow. Right? So I say I
make W1 such that it takes a
D-dimensional vector to a K- dimensional
vector and it's a linear linear
transformation and then I take another
linear transformation that takes K
dimensional vectors to Dimensional
vectors. There's no way this product is
going to have rank more than K. Does
everyone see that? So now what I've done
is I've taken the thing that I want and
I've encoded it into a neural net
architecture.
Okay, the regularity I want into an
architecture. And now I can say great,
I'll just train with this loss over the
entire data set using batches.
Everyone with me?
If I get to the optimum, whatever it is,
I know by Eert Young that I'm going to
be here
in terms of the actual reconstructions.
Everyone with me?
Okay, I'll make sure I pause here for a
minute.
Okay, all we're doing is we're saying
because we have this theorem that tells
us another way of understanding what the
solution to PCA is that we can interpret
in terms of loss, we can then turn that
into an actual training recipe for a
neural net. So now I'm free to do all
the things that I'm normally free to do.
I can change my batch size, my mini
batch size. I can choose my optimizer
how I want it. I can do anything I want,
right? I can add weight decay. All kinds
of stuff that I would do to train in a
network I can do here. And I'll still be
approaching in spirit what's happening
there.
Okay.
Very good. So now what have we achieved?
We said that look I can take the
dimensionality reduction technique that
you learned and I can map it into the
idea of self-supervision. So what do we
call what is self-supervision?
X is the input, but X is also the label.
Remember, the label shows up in the
loss. The input shows up at the
beginning of your architecture
somewhere.
Here, they're the same thing. So, I
self-supervise by saying I want to
encode X such that it's as close to X as
possible.
Okay. So, this approach has a name.
Okay. And the default ingredients are
your labels are X's themselves.
The architecture is an encoder followed
by a decoder and there's a bottleneck in
the middle. This is called an
autoenccoder. Autoenccoder. Encode
yourself to yourself
like auto regression.
Everyone happy with this? Okay. Okay, so
this sets up uh one kind of technique
that's used for uh self-s supervision.
And
in the traditional perspective here, you
can sometimes draw it this way with an
encoder followed by a decoder. And we
draw it with these shapes to kind of
emphasize that you start with something
big, you get something small, and you
take something small and you make it big
again.
Okay, these boxes are just drawn to
illustrate that. And if you think about
this the traditional perspective, so
traditional perspective PCA for
dimensionality reduction is the goal of
doing dimensionality reduction is to
have a projection
that you can apply on new data.
Okay? So the only thing we need to do
the projection is the encoder,
right? Because the encoder takes
Dimensional vectors into K dimensional
vectors. The decoder is just scaffolding
for training.
We need to train. So we have to put
something there. We put this there.
>> Okay. Yes.
>> Great question. The question was here I
just have W1 and W2. Are there weights
tied in any way? That's your question,
right? So uh the answer here is you
don't actually have to wait time.
Echert Young guarantees you in this case
that if you're going to train this thing
to convergence and actually the lowest
possible loss, you're guaranteed that
you have to project into this space. Now
you're not actually going to get the V
matrix necessarily because the V matrix
has this additional property of being
orthogonal. There's nothing here
enforcing orthogonality,
right? So you're going to get something
projecting into K dimensions. Um
but you definitely don't need to do any
weight ting to say that this is kind of
the opposite of that. It's just enforced
by itself.
Okay. So what I want to do next is
just show you some pictures of this
idea. So now you have this idea, right,
of doing this kind of thing.
encode, decode, have a bottleneck or
something in between and autoenccoder.
Now, nothing is saying that we have to
make the structure of the encoder just
be one matrix,
right? Nothing is I mean for PCA it's
one matrix. We want a linear projection
because we wanted a linear projection.
We chose to learn a linear projection.
But if you're happy, if you have some
other aspect of what you think, some
other knowledge of what you think the
underlying regularities are, you're
allowed to bring any neural net you want
into the encoder and the decoder. As
long as you have this architecture of
having an input followed by an encoder
that goes into something that's like a
bottleneck and then a decoder and you
and you have the loss be with the label
that's the same as the input, you're in
autoenccoder land.
So now let's just see it with some
pictures. So these are some great
pictures from uh Sergey Livian's
lectures 22 from 2021.
So it says okay let's think about this.
You can do this for images. So for an
image what's going on here is images go
in and the encoder is presumably some
kind of neural net architecture that's
tied to images like a CNN.
So you have an encoder and then you go
to some hidden smaller dimensional thing
for example 128. So this is a 100 by 100
image. So it's if it was black and white
it would be 10,000 uh dimensional. If it
was color like this picture is it would
be 30,000 dimensional.
And then you just map it down to a small
space that's 128. So these kind of small
spaces are sometimes just called latent
spaces from kind of the generative model
uh tradition uh point of view.
So you have this output. Now you want
this to be the desired output. So this
is the label just copied over what was
here.
So you have to use a loss. So you can
use any relevant loss function to train
this.
So for images for example you could say
I just do mean squared error on RGB.
That's totally reasonable. Um, but you
can do other things, right? Any loss
that you think is reasonable for your
application can be used. What happens?
You have a loss. You will then get
gradients. Everything is a neural net
and so is differentable. So the
gradients will back prop through here.
They can train this thing. They will go
here. They will go back here. They will
train this thing and everything will
just keep training.
So historically autoenccoders um
actually came out right they were
they've been known for a very long time
and this style of training was very
popular at the very initial parts of the
current age of deep networks where
people didn't know if they could get
endto-end training with a loss working
and so they would do autoenccoders at
different layers to kind of stage
layerwise build up some initial
condition first that they thought was a
good initial condition and then they
would train end to end from that point.
Um but then that went away once people
figured out how to make endtoend
training work. Um but in an interesting
way as we'll talk about later the modern
perspective of foundation models in is
in a way a return to the idea of
autoenccoding as the right way to set
your initial conditions.
Okay. So
again this is a we call this the classic
vanilla autoenccoder.
But once you have this picture, you're
actually you should think, okay, I can
bring all of the tricks that I know to
bear.
So in this case, what's happening is the
regularity that you want is being
expressed
using
the architecture.
So you say your architecture is a connet
because you think the things you want
are captured by this locality and so on
that we did to derive connets.
But we learned that there's two other
ways that we can think about encoding
the regularities that we want.
Right? So
what what what are some of those ways?
So here's one.
Okay. So this is called a sparse
autoenccoder.
So in a sparse autoenccoder
what we're going to do is we're going to
take the
input same as before it's the label
outside except now instead of saying
that I'm going to go to something which
is much smaller a bottleneck I'll go to
something that's potentially even bigger
however
what I'm going to do is to make this
bottleneck actually be a bottle neck is
I'm going to try to impose an auxiliary
loss. So remember we introduced this
idea of auxiliary losses right as a way
to capture when we're talking about the
diff pool right you can capture
regularity you want using auxiliary
losses also so we can use the auxiliary
loss idea here
so in the auxiliary loss idea what we
can do is we can just take this thing
and we can stick on
an auxiliary loss
that
is sparsity seeking
So you saw in your optimization class
for example that we could use an L1
loss.
So we can say go ahead and encode it
into this large vector except I'm going
to penalize the L1 norm of this vector.
Okay. And what that will do is again
you'll have gradients that are going
from the standard loss back but you'll
also have gradients coming from the L1
loss back.
And if you remember the intuition of L1
loss, the L1 loss says, look,
I penalize everything, every dimension
is penalized by the same negative
weight, right? Like everything I want to
push it down. So it basically says if
this particular entry isn't pulling its
weight relative to the others, it'll
just be driven down to zero.
Okay? And so that's the kind of what's
the intuition for the sparsity seeking
behavior of L1 loss. Whereas L2 loss,
the smaller it is, the less it's
penalized. So there's no reason to drive
it all the way to zero. But in L1 loss,
it's being penalized constantly to the
same amount.
Okay, so this is a way to have a sparse
autoenccoder. Any questions on sparse
autoenccoding?
Okay, so here we use the auxiliary loss
idea to to express the regularity. So
what is the regularity here? By saying
this is sparse, we're saying that look
whatever this is, it's some mixture of a
few small fewer degrees of freedom that
are being adjusted. So in here you think
maybe from an interpretability point of
view that one of the entries here is
like doggginess,
right? And there's like a little
collection, a few of them that kind of
tells you what kind of dog,
right? And you wanted to basically say,
okay, this is like and then something
which kind of centers it and like some
things that are telling you like where
this thing is located. So if you have
described this in natural language,
you'll naturally kind of go for a sparse
type of description. So this is trying
to encourage that and that's why this is
a bottleneck. The sparsity is what's
creating the bottleneck.
>> Yeah. So this is the desired results
of a couple
of zero entries.
>> Oh yeah, great question. The question is
at the end of the day if I have a 128
dimensional vector or I have a 1 million
dimensional vector that only has 128
non-zero entries,
>> are these basically the same thing?
Right? The answer is almost. But there's
a big difference in that if you have a
milliondimensional vector with only 128
things that are non zero, there's
information in two places. What those
128 things actually are, that's the same
as the 128 dimensional vector, but also
which 128 things are on. So this this
information that's in this cominatorial
sense of like which particular ones
you're activating.
you're sort of also ass.
>> So the idea here is uh as typically in
all of deep learning, right? It goes
like this. We think that there's a
pattern. We think the pattern might be
well captured in this by sparse vectors.
We think this is true. To encourage this
thing that we're thinking to actually
happen during training, we add
something. Okay, so in the bottleneck
case, the thing we thought is low
dimensional. The way we did it was we
put an architectural constraint that
forced it to be lowdimensional. Here we
think it's something that's sparse. So
we add an auxiliary loss that encourages
sparsity. And then we just say, okay,
training run.
and you hope that this thing comes out
to be sparse. At random initialization,
this is not sparse.
Okay, at random initialization, this is
a really bad reconstruction. But you
hope as time goes on between the
auxiliary loss and the desire to
reconstruct that this thing ends up
being sparse.
>> What I was asking is more the idea of
like
oh if I give it a dog.
>> Great question. The question is when you
do sparse autoenccoding do you try in
advance to decide the interpretation of
different vector different things in
here and the answer is no. We say we
don't try to say that this is going to
be the doggy neuron and we'll say okay
we have an L1 loss on everything but the
doggy neuron is free for dogs.
>> We don't want
>> it'll different ones based on
>> so the idea yes we're hoping for the
idea that at the after training happens
that these will actually be sparse
during the encoding process but this is
only being encouraged by the auxiliary
loss it is not being forced
of course it could be that you train
this thing and this thing ends up being
not sparse in which case you're like
okay that didn't work right and you'll
go back and fiddle with something will
you fiddle Most likely the first thing
you'll fiddle with is you'll first
you'll check is the reconstruction
decent, right? If the reconstruction is
not decent, you have other problems. The
reconstruction is decent, you're like,
"Okay, maybe I should up the
the multiplier on this L1 penalty to
make it hit harder." Things like this
usual things one will do when you have
different knobs you can tweak.
>> Yes, question. this auxiliary loss. Are
we comparing the hidden vector to
anything or is it purely just like a
regularization?
>> It's like a regularization term. It's
just an auxiliary loss that says, "Hey,
I want this thing to be
small in L1 sense, which I know is going
to be yeah. So you saw in the diff pool
example, we had a auxiliary loss that
was doing a comparison and we had
another auxiliary loss, the entropy
loss, which is like a regularizer.
So all of that we can think of as
auxiliary losses.
So yes you know that there's
architecture
auxiliary losses but there's one more
thing one can do which is data
augmentations.
Okay so you can also do what's called a
dnoising autoenccoder
which is a data augmentation. This says
I can do any kind of autoenccoder I
want. This can be small. This can be
big. This can be whatever. I'm not
that's not really the thing I'm worried
about here. But I can take the dog. I
can do an augmentation. Here is an
adding noise augmentation that I do. And
then I can train it.
So it's interesting that
in all three of these examples right in
the autoenccoder coder style what you're
trying to learn is a way of
approximately representing the inputs in
a way that captures their most important
attributes.
So in this one you're just forcing it to
be small and importance is of course how
well does it reconstruct. In the sparse
autoenccoder again importance is how
well is it useful for doing
reconstruction but you have this
additional jittera that I would like
this thing to be maybe interpretable in
somewhere just by be sparse.
In this one we just say look I just want
to be good at reconstructing
and the reason it's going to capture
what's important is because I'm going to
do augmentations that try to destroy or
change things that are not important and
it has to be robust to that. So the only
way you're going to be able to den
noiseise this thing is because you'll
realize that wait actually every pixel
level detail isn't important. there's a
bigger picture of what's happening that
requires smoothing and looking at what's
going on around around figuring out that
oh okay actually this is a dog and oh
actually its eyes are here so I can like
remove the noise here better than just a
Gaussian like blur will do for removing
the noise and that's what I hope will
work and so that's what you want this
encoder to learn
and you want the decoder to be able to
carry it out so you better capture that
in this hidden hidden thing okay so
that's denoising auto-enccoder idea
but once you think about dnoising
autoenccoders
any augmentation is good.
So another very important kind of uh
autoenccoder family is called masked
autoenccoders which is another kind of
augmentation.
So in this augmentation what you do is
you take parts of the input and you say
I'm going to mask them. So remember we
talked about this in the context of
graph neural nets. We said we want to
take a particular node and remove it. So
we can do the same thing here. And so
for images you could just like paint it
gray gray blobs. That works. Um
if your thing is not an image,
you might involve having a learned mask
question mark vector that you have to
use. Same as we saw in in GNN's. But
again, to be able to recover from this
kind of damage, it has to be the case
that this includes what's actually going
on underneath so that the reconstruction
can just fill everything in.
Okay, so this is the kind of spirit.
Autoenccoders don't take that long to
understand the ideas. You just ask
questions. But what you're basically
trying to do is take the spirit of
dimensionality reduction and say
dimensionality reduction is about
finding a representation that cleanly
captures what's important.
Lowdimensionality is only one thing that
can do that. There's only one
possibility. What you actually want is
it should capture what's essentially
important. And think about the original
input as having lots of different
features associated with it. The
thing that plays the spirit of
dimensionality reduction should have
like purer features in it like better
features
which is a qualitative term better
features better in what sense good
enough to do the reconstruction
so
one comment about this that I want to
make before I move to one tiny bit of
talking about one more topic before I
hand it over is
if you have a bottleneck in your
architecture,
there's you can think of it as there's
no choice. If you want to be able to
have good reconstruction, you have to
distill out what's important.
When you eliminate the bottleneck
entirely, for example, if this was just
the same size as the input, then there
is a hypothetical fear that what the
encoder will learn is just identity.
and the decoder will just be identity.
Adding masking or adding noise blocks
identity from being a valid solution.
So that's the traditional way one
understands the value of doing masking
or uh denoising autoenccoders.
But we'll show you in the homework that
actually remember we said there's many
things that are regularizing and one of
them is actually the actions of the
optimizer itself and gradient descent.
So even the
just the actions of gradient descent
itself in training the autoenccoder will
also bring a regularizing effect
even if you don't have the bottleneck.
Okay. So that you'll see in in the
homework.
Okay,
any questions on autoenccoding? So it's
like a a classic example of self-s
supervision. The same thing masked
autoenccoders will come up when we talk
about uh for example BERT in the
language processing context. It's just
exactly this idea applied in language
settings. Yeah.
>> For mass autoenccoders, your losses over
the regions, right? Or is there where
they were computed over the entire
image.
>> Great question. So here you have a
choice of what you're trying to do,
right? So depending on the architecture,
you could say I want to have the mask
the reconstruction on everything, which
is what I've described here. There's
some cases where you can follow the
spirit of masked autoenccoding and just
say I just want to reconstruct the
masked parts.
>> Yeah.
>> Yes.
So
>> yeah, so again this is an important and
subtle point. When people started doing
uh autoenccoders, they thought you have
to have an actual bottleneck.
That's how people started.
Then people realized that wait, we have
multiple ways of expressing
regularities.
So sparse autoenccoders are the classic
example which says I don't have to make
the bottleneck small in dimension. It
can be large but I'll force sparsity to
make it small. You see this is like
edging out. You start off saying it has
to be small. You're like okay it could
be big but sparse. Okay. And then when
you go to denoising autoenccoders,
you're like, actually,
maybe it doesn't even have to be small.
Okay, so now here it could be, you're
right, a hypothetically it could be that
this thing just learns the identity and
this thing does all the work of
denoising.
That could happen, right? Right? That's
a possible valid solution. But you
expect during training like why would it
put all the work here,
right? Why would gradient descent do
that? Probably won't,
right? Probably split the work.
And if it splits the work of doing some
of the denoising in this part, then this
is still going to be a better
representation quote than the input.
Okay, that's like an intuition. But once
you take that intuition, right, you can
say, okay, the same same exact thing
applies here. You know, this does this
doesn't have to be smaller anymore. It
could be the same size or it could be
bigger.
Gradient descent is also a player.
So that's the kind of evolution of the
spirit of autoenccoding from the initial
it must be a bottleneck to now all
you're trying to do is sort of purify
clean up the representations so they
better capture what's important.
This is vague
okay but hopefully it but it's still the
same spirit as dimensional reduction in
that what makes it better might be
better for a downstream task. you just
take these encodings and you use them
for training another uh downstream task
the same way you use a dimensionality
reduction from PCA
and so the final proof of it being
better is it works better for a
downstream task
okay
so
um I want to kind of stop with like a
little tiny comment on one more thing
I'm not going to spend a lot of time on
this but I want to make sure you're
aware of it We started off by saying
there's two different approaches to
dimensional to uh unsupervised learning
in traditional ML. There's the
dimensionality reduction approach and
then there's the clustering approach.
And what I've just told you is that
dimensionality reduction in spirit
connects this autoenccoder style of
self-s supervision.
So you should just from your love of
symmetry, right? Say, is there a
counterpart of the clustering spirit?
Do you see that? It's just a way of
thinking, right? Can you make clustering
also feel like it's a kind of
self-supervision?
And the answer is you can. And it's
called contrastive self-supervision.
And so the core idea of contrastive
self-supervision
says any example in your data and its
own augmentations.
Okay. So you take an example an image
and do a data augmentation on it.
Whatever cluster the original belongs to
the augmentation should probably belong
to the same cluster.
Does everyone see that as a spirit? The
augmentation is not supposed to change
its character a lot.
So you should probably belong to the
same cluster. Does everyone see that?
It's okay.
That's the idea.
And similarly,
fundamentally different examples in your
training data probably belong to
different clusters. So the spirit here
is your data is quite rich. There's a
thousand different kinds of objects.
So you pick an image at random, its
augmentation is in the same cluster as
this image. If you pick another image at
random, it's not going to be in the same
cluster.
Everyone see that as a kind of guess.
So can you turn make a learning
algorithm based on this? And the answer
is sure you can. Okay.
So I have some papers here that you can
read the references to. Um
you take a you take a data point and you
take another randomly chosen data point.
They probably belong to different
clusters. So you have an encoder for
them that results in some embedding.
These two belong to different clusters.
What does that mean from a clustering
algorithm point of view? It means
they're far away from each other because
clustering algorithms like K means being
things that are close together.
So you say you enforce make these be far
apart. You reward distance.
Whereas an augmentation of this you say
belongs to the same cluster.
So you reward closeness
penalize distance
and you just train. Now to be careful to
choose a distance, right? So this this
works but this is called contrastive
self-s supervision. It's not a there's
no decoder here.
There's only encoders
that are trying to learn the regularity.
So fundamentally this requires the
augmentations.
Okay. Contrast self-servision requires
Okay. So just
because deep learning is interesting and
weird um the fun thing that I'll leave
to you to read about if you want to is
to say can you do contrastive self-s
supervision without the contrast.
Okay, what this is saying is remember I
said you randomly pick another image and
it's probably in a different cluster.
People found that in practice, if it was
actually in the same cluster, bad things
might happen a little bit during
training because you're trying to push
apart things that should be together and
that can sometimes cause trouble. So the
question is, can you get away from
having negative examples at all? And
there are tricks that uh let you let
that work. Yeah,
>> data augmentation means do uh it's
problem specific, right? So an
augmentation for image could be like
adding noise, changing the colors,
contrasting it, rotating a little bit,
translating a little bit, shearing it,
you know, cropping out little sections,
stuff like this,
>> right? All of that stuff that you expect
should be not changing the basic
character of the image.
Okay.
Okay. So I will stop here and hand it
over uh to the and this is the end of
self-supervision by itself. And now
we're going to go back to the question
that was raised earlier of you have
these state space models, you have this
problem with nonlinearity. What can you
do
Okay, good. So, I have about half an
hour.
Okay.
So
coming back to now you we've talked
about RNN's and what I'm going to try to
set up in this lecture and the ne next
lecture is essentially the modern
counterpart to RNN's and talk about how
we get around the key bottleneck that
RNN's have presented to us which is the
fact that when we have these
nonlinearities in RNN's they become
difficult to train right everyone
remember that we're we're with like what
our agenda is is somewhat clear. So what
is the problem with these traditional
RNNs? Well, basically what happened is
that when you're doing back like you're
unrolling this thing and you have this
nonlinearity showing up every time in
your computation graph and so you have
all these sequential paths that you have
to do your forward and backward pass
through and this made things very
difficult to train.
What is the key idea? We see that okay,
we don't like the nonlinearity because
that is creating all of these paths. We
cannot parallelize this, right? What we
want to be able to do is we want to be
able to do something that will allow us
to parallelize.
The kind of brilliant but
uh surprising idea is that well, you
don't like the nonlinearity.
What state space models did was said,
let's just get rid of it, right? We like
linear things. Let's just make things
linear. That's the key highlevel idea
that we are going to explore. Of course,
this idea is, you know, in some sense
simple, but to actually get it to work
involves quite a bit of complexity and
that's what I'm going to try and
disentangle and talk through in the rest
of the lecture and then uh tomorrow's
lecture.
Okay. So this is our picture of an RNN
and here we have these horizontal
nonlinearities right in each of these
blocks there's stuff happening but one
of the key stuff things that's happening
is that there is this uh nonlinearity in
each of these blocks okay
so what these so uh state space models
said was okay in this traditional
uh RNN we have something like this you
have a hidden state
ht +1 one and it is some nonlinear
function of maybe your weights times
your previous state maybe you have some
dependence on input so on and so forth
there's a bias term what we're going to
think about is let's just get rid of
this entirely
and let's think of a model that is of
this form okay
and so for those of you who have taken a
control theory or any kind kind of
systems class, any linear systems class,
you've seen this kind of stuff over and
over and over again, right? Ax plus BU,
if you if you've done it in control,
you're used to seeing this this is X and
you're so used to seeing this is you,
right? Um that's and and so here this
thing is called the state because that
is what is capturing all of your time
dependence all of your history and every
time that is what is being updated that
is where your that is where your memory
is. So in talking about these models I'm
basically going to be following a series
of papers that have come out in the past
couple of years. None of this material
is really in the in the prince textbook.
So take lots of notes.
Um and I will do my best to communicate
it nicely and cleanly. Um the material
is being drawn from a series of papers.
A large number of them are coming out of
uh Chris Ray's lab at Stanford as well
as the Mamba work which is coming out of
I think Princeton or CMU. Um and I think
that the that the the authors of those
used to be at st at at Stanford right so
there's basically this one uh group that
has been doing a lot of work and then
now recently there is a uh new work out
of MIT called Deltanets that is kind of
further building this state space uh
perspective out. So why do we care about
understanding the state space
perspective? Maybe I'll motivate that
just a minute before I even go into um
yeah maybe let me show you this picture
uh before I go into talking more about
it. So this is uh the architecture for
the latest Quen model. So the leading
essentially open- source model and I'm
not going to there's a lot more stuff
here. We're not going to go into all of
this. But what I want to draw your
attention to here is
this
delta net. Okay,
this delta net is basically a so there
was this S4 state space model. Then was
there was S4 diagonal then that led to
Mamba and an evolution of then there was
Mamba 2 and then building on that there
was this Delta which is currently
considered one of the leading state
space models.
This is now incorporated
into this you know leading Quen model.
Okay. So it used to be that transformers
were you know like people thought that
okay it was going to be all attention
but it turns out that the many
advantages of state space models and the
fact that at inference time uh these can
be done quite uh computationally
efficiently makes it very attractive to
have aspects of your model or parts of
your model incorporate state space type
architectures. So I'm showing this just
as an example to say like we're not
teaching you some esoterica uh thing
just because I happen to like control
theory but it actually matters. Um
similarly here is a picture of the the
granite architecture from IBM and again
you see here some of these um
mamba blocks. So you see it's a hybrid
architecture, right? They have attention
blocks but they also have uh the state
space blocks and they're being used for
their differential strengths. So there's
there's important reasons to basically
understand this. We will not I'm not
going to answer all the questions about
all of these things. We will you know by
the end of the class we'll be able to
understand all of the parts of these
pictures.
Okay. So with that let me now come to
what I wanted to talk about. Okay.
So what kind of things basically
the thing the kind of thing that we like
doing and that is nice and efficient for
training and that is nicely
parallelizable.
There's one operation that we know how
to do. And what is that operation
that we've like looked at so far that is
nice for training?
Matrix multiplication. Yeah, matrix
multiplication is nice. Specifically,
convolutions are particularly nice,
right? Convolutional convolutional
neural nets we know how to train. And
the nice thing about convolutions is
they're they're nicely parallelizable.
Okay. So, wouldn't it be great if we
could use the fact that now we have just
reduced this to a linear system in the
sense to be able to
use convolutions. Okay. And if we can do
that then maybe we will be able to
parallelize our training nicely. So,
let's think somehow we have we have
learned our system. We've learned our
our model and we have these learned
weights A, B, C, um, and D.
And let's say we have this
uh this particular system with with
fixed and learned weights. Okay, this is
now an LTI system. So you now know that
I can think of this basically by un
unrolling it, right? So if I look at H
knot, that's just B * X knot.
Then I look at H1 and that's AB X plus B
X1. H2 I have a^2 bx knot plus so on and
so forth. I can just unroll this
recurrence and get this these equations
out. Make sense to everyone?
Any questions about this?
No. Yeah. Okay.
So, I can basically write my hidden
state H just as a function of my
different inputs, right? I'm removing
the dependence on the different hes.
Everyone see that?
So now I can write my output y.
I just have to pull in this c matrix
here, right? Y is essentially c * h k
plus d * xt.
And so I have my output is just c a k *
b * x plus c a k minus 1 b * x1. so on
and so forth.
And the nice thing about this is now
this only depends on my previous inputs.
It doesn't depend at all on my hidden
states.
So to compute my output now, what do I
need to do?
I can do all of these different
operations in parallel, right? I don't
need to wait on the computation. I don't
need to wait to compute ht to then
compute ht plus one. I just have all of
my inputs. And because I know what my a,
b, and c are, I can just
compute the next hidden state. Does that
make sense to everyone? Yes. No
questions. I'll pause here for a minute.
Everyone with me? Thumbs up, thumbs
down.
Okay, good.
So, this is just a convolution. And this
is great, right? So this is basically
giving us a way to parallelize our
computation, right? So at this point
maybe some of you are like
a little bit suspicious or not yet.
You're still you're just very trusting
people. Yes. Question.
Exactly. Okay.
>> This is exactly the question I was
hoping someone would ask. So, thank you.
Okay. Do you have a followup or you want
>> So, um, not quite. So, okay. So, I
showed you these architectures
and these architectures here indeed
mix different kinds of things. Like
there's an attention layer here and
there's nonlinearities there.
But what you will uh see is actually for
example here
uh do I have a picture of this here
somewhere?
Where did it go?
This is an example of the the the
mamba architecture which I'm probably
not going to get enough time to go into
in detail. But the key thing is that
what we're going to do is we're going to
maintain nonlinearities on essentially
what is the vertical path.
The horizontal path is time. And if you
look at if you remember our RNN issue
on this horizontal path we had
nonlinearities and those were causing
problems for us in our back prop and
computation graph. But if we just have
these nonlinearities in the vertical
path,
those allow us to still parallelize
because we can just basically put an MLP
block after our solid state block and
that can do all kinds of nonlinear
things and recover our expressive power.
Okay, so we're going to have this but
we're going to capture the history and
the time dependence of the sequences
in this linear part.
And one of the key insights that came uh
this I'm not going to talk about this
today but there is there was this paper
called u hippo or hungry hungry hippo
which talked about a representation
or how you can basically uh do polomial
approximation
um that will help you c and and how you
can use basically uh differential
equations and discretized versions of
differential equations to represent many
different functions And basically saying
that actually linear functions can have
a lot of expressive power. And one other
way to think about is that well you know
like yes we we're doing neural networks
now and we're doing a lot of nonlinear
things but we have been doing linear
stuff for a long time and you can
actually capture a lot of stuff with
linear functions as well. So there's you
know you can think of it two ways but
this hippo paper um also brought about
this realization that actually looking
at a particular linear perspective can
uh can bring about a lot of expressive
power as well but here we're going to be
combining this with an explicit MLP in
the vertical direction. Does that answer
the question? But this is exactly what I
was thinking that you're probably
thinking. So I'm glad you uh vocalized
this this question. Okay. So, we have
this. So, we're we're focusing on this
linear thing and we're we're hoping that
it's going to give us uh give us what we
want. Any other questions here?
Okay, good.
So, let's um think about this. So, now
at position Yes, question.
still get paral.
>> No. So there they there will still be an
independence. Yes. In the sense that you
will you will you will train it the same
way you would train in an MLP.
>> Yes.
>> Whatever nonlinearity
>> function whatever
was acting as
or
>> okay that's that's an excellent
question. Um so in RNN's yes we choose
to we choose to have an a sigmoid to to
avoid this blowup problem. This blowup
issue is an issue that we we will come
to I will probably not talk about it
today but we will talk about it
tomorrow. Um and we will handle this by
thinking about the en values of the
linear systems that we're thinking
about. And so one way of what the what
in RNN's the sigmoid did was it just
made it squashed all the values and made
them small. But in linear systems we
know what causes blowups and we know
that IEN values are the things that
cause blowups. And we understand
critical damping and uh
exponential stability. And so we're
going to use those ideas to initialize
appropriately and make sure that we can
still get the kind of long range
dependency we want.
but make sure our systems don't explode.
But this is this is again still the
tricky part or a tricky part of state
space models.
Yes.
you so you could write you could write
an unrolled version of this but what I
need to do is I need to compute the
nonlinearity before I can compute the
next hidden state
so I need to operate the here I can do
all of these in one go I don't
like this term depends on this term and
this term depends on this term if I
unroll it with the nonlinear ity but
without the nonlinearity I can just go
and get it all as one convolution or one
matrix multiply
>> yes exactly parallelization that's the
key thing the thing is that you can
parallelize this
okay so this is the really nice thing
this is the like key or one key thing
about state space models
so the other thing that we want to
really uh bring out is that okay you
know but this is still a lot of lot of
compute right to compute these
especially if you're having long context
and your t is getting larger and larger
then you know to compute position t I
still have you know I have I have my
history I have t history now behind me
and the longer my history is
the bigger this power is right so the
more the the longer my convolutions
because this is essentially an infinite
impulse response that I that I have,
right? And so the the way that I'm going
to handle this is that I have a sequence
and it's all going to just I I'll load
the sequence that can fit into my memory
and then I will do the convolution that
I can do. Okay? So the bigger t gets,
the more multiplies I'm going to have to
do.
So
if this if at position t I have you know
let's say I have a maximum sequence
length of capital t okay and I have let
me write this out maybe
so I have um here
uh zero maybe not zero
I have one to t.
Okay, maybe t is the maximum context
length that I can handle. This is the
maximum number of things that I will
have
to compute
every position t.
I basically need order t compute, right?
Because there are t terms here, right?
So how much compute do I need
all the way up to capital T?
Yeah, go ahead. Or
t^ square over two essentially, right?
Um but I need order t^2 compute. And the
basic the the way to see that is if I
need one compute, two compute, three
compute, t compute, I have to add this
all up. And essentially the compute that
I need is a total of t^2 compute. Okay.
So as my context grows this is getting
larger and larger. This is not great.
The question is now and one of the
really nice things about these models is
can we do something better than this
order t^2? And this is the second key
insight or power that state space models
leverage. So I'm going to give you a
minute to think about this and think
about well what could we do to go and
improve beyond beyond this order t^ squ
compute the nice thing is what we have
is we can do this parallelly but tsquare
is still a lot what can we do to do
better so you know take a minute think
talk to your neighbors ask questions so
on and so forth I'll set a
All right.
Yes,
So that's my timer. Okay. So, anyone
have any ideas or suggestions on how
we could go do better than order T
square?
>> Yeah.
For
examp
you've only if you've saved T already
you could only
>> so you can save some of these powers of
A and basically improve how fast you can
compute that you can you can do a little
bit of improvement and we'll talk a
little bit about that, but that's not
going to get you a the big kind of
improvement that we're we're looking
for.
>> Anyone else or Yeah.
Get all these sizing
across the different
>> You could try things like this but um I
want to try and take a a different
different perspective and so maybe this
is um so when I was in undergrad uh
everyone had to take a signal processing
class like we all took signal processing
it was part of our lower division and we
you know this was but these days you
guys you guys don't
and so when you think convolution what
is the so in in signal processing you
think
uh convolutions
in time domain are
what what's the what's the corresponding
there's time domain and there's
>> frequency domain and convolutions in
time are
>> multiplications in frequency right and
to be able to get this duality
what is the transform that you use
>> the fier transform right or the dftt so
what is this algorithm that everyone
who's taken 70 has probably heard of
>> FFT.
>> The FFT, right? The fast fer transform.
So what the fast fer transform says is
that oh I can actually use dynamic
programming or a divide and conquer
style approach to instead of having an
ordered t^2 or n squ computation to
compute the fier transform of a length n
sequence how fast can I do it from you
can do it in n login. Right? So if we
want to try and improve this well the
answer is yes
and we can use the fast
fia transform
okay
and I want to go from order t^2 to
instead or maybe I shouldn't write this
here I should just say
should just say order t
log t right and so this I'm basically
going to do a dynamic programming
style algorithm and the key thing that
one has to notice so how will we do this
we have to do these convolutions well
what we're going to do is we're going to
do an fft of your filter you're going to
do an fft of your sequence you're going
multiply and then you're going to do an
inverse FFT
and you're going to get out essentially
in time the time domain convolution is
going to come out right so everyone any
questions about
how one would do this again let me just
say that slowly I have my filter my
filter is essentially
these matrices
okay my filter is these matrices
and My signal is my inputs x1 x2 x k
and then what I'm going to do is I'm
going to take both of these I'm going to
transfer them to fiery domain which is n
login do a multiply
and then do the transform back again so
I can do this basically in n or t log t
time okay
now there's another okay so when you did
fft what were you used to having all of
your elements of your sequence be like
when I think of a signal I typically
think of a signal with entries where
where every where every entry of my
signal essentially is or every value of
my signal is a scalar right like I have
something like when I think of a signal
I think of something like if I'm
thinking discrete time I'm thinking of
something like this or I'm thinking of
in continuous time
I'm thinking of something that's
you know it's a it's a scalar I can't
but what do we have here what is every
entry that I have
each of these things this is now my I'm
saying my signal my first entry of my
signal is x knot the second entry of my
signal is x1 the third entry of my
signal is x2 but these are all actually
vectors right so I want to use the fft
but is it obvious how to use the FFT I
just kind of said that we can use it but
we have we have a little bit of a issue
here right that you know when we do the
FFT we're used to doing it on scalers
does everyone see the issue but here we
have matrices and vectors instead of uh
scalers multiplying scalers
everyone with me yes
I don't think it would just work like
that. I mean, essentially, we're going
to break it down component by component.
The key idea, I mean, at some level,
it's all linearity and it's all just
change of basis, right? And so, uh, you
can think of it in maybe there's a way
of thinking about it that way. The way
I'm going to talk about thinking about
it is basically breaking it down
component by component uh to to
carefully account for uh each of these.
So we're going to take these vectors and
break them down into a se into a set of
sequences to be able to to to be able to
do this. And this was the one of the key
things that doing this,
you know, being able to use the FFT
trick on these vector valued sequences
was one of the key contributions and
innovations of the first set of um state
space model papers.
Okay. So before we get to that, I'm not
sure I have enough time to fully get
through that. So I will go through that
next time. But I'm going to um talk
about one other little thing which is
that let's say we can somehow get this t
log t. Okay, we still have this vector
issue but you'll grant me that probably
we can do some careful accounting.
Everything is nice and linear and you'll
trust me that I'll teach you how to do
it next time. Okay, but
let's talk about one other issue since I
don't have that much time left.
which is we also have these
things here, right? These c a to the k *
b. Maybe I should just copy this. Uh
oh, wrong thing. I want this.
Did not work out the way I wanted to.
Okay, never mind. Um,
you remember that equation, right?
Okay.
So, what about this term
computing? This is also like these are a
lot of matrices to multiply, right? And
one of the things here is that what we
want to do is we want to be able to have
a lot of hidden state, right? We want to
be able to capture all of the past into
this H.
And so to do that, if we want to capture
more and more history and context, we
want to make H big.
The larger H is, the more stuff it can
it can can it can store. So that means
that these this a matrix and these is
going to be quite big right so this is
quite a bit of uh this is not a small
matrix multiply to handle so yes there's
a dependence on the length of the
context but also there's the per context
compute that you also have to think
about okay
so this a to the k again you can think
of computing a to the k in this you know
in some in a in a memoization or caching
way where I can think of Well, I can
keep doubling it. I don't have to I
don't have to multiply a k times, but I
can kind of do a squaring trick to maybe
reduce that to a log uh level of
computation.
But even then, a to the k is going to
add steps to your computation graph,
right? Because I have to that that this
is a sequential operation. Even if I do
it in log number of steps, log k number
of steps, I'm still going to have to
first square it and then square it again
and then square it again. I cannot
parallelize this, right? My computation
graph uh path becomes longer.
So is there a way that we can speed this
part of the computation off?
>> Yes.
Yeah, that's exactly what we are going
to do is we're going to say that well
what is the nicest matrix that if you
wanted to take powers of what would be
your choice you would choose a diagonal
matrix right and so it turns out that we
can actually just we're just going to
say let a be diagonal we're going to
restrict a to being diagonal
now does this come at a cost or right
because now we're restricting the kind
of interactions that your uh state space
model can capture. There's only certain
things that can that can capture. Well,
it turns out that most matrices or many
matrices are diagonalizable, right? So
up to a change of basis, you're
capturing a very large family of
structures using a diagonalizable
matrix. Which are the matrices that are
not diagonalizable?
Well, those are the ones that have
basically a a Jordan block structure,
right? Or a non-trivial Jordan block
structure for the people have seen
Jordan blocks. Yes. Okay. So, basically
that means that if you have these
repeated values, then you're going to
have issues with uh with
diagonalization.
That's true. What we're going to say is
we're just going to let those go and
we're going to be able to try and
capture we're going to capture as much
as we can in the very large set of
things that can be captured by
diagonalizable matrices. And because
we're learning these parameters, we
basically we'll learn the basis that is
the diagonal basis, right? Um that's
that's basically what's going to happen.
So what we're going to do is we're going
to say
let's just add this structure and let's
restrict
to diagonal A matrices. Okay.
So, I'm not going to start this thing
because I have like three minutes left.
What I'm going to say instead is what
are we going to do next? So, just a key
point that we already talked about, but
we're now going to say that we're going
to try and restrict to um these diagonal
A's. We're going to remove all of the
horizontal nonlinearities. We talked
about expressive power.
And the way we're going to handle this
expressive power issue is we're
basically going to say here you're going
to have your um ignore this for now.
Ignore this part. We'll talk about
gating later. Just focus on
this part.
Um and here what this is this Mamba
architecture is just saying look here
you have
some kind of linear projection. Okay.
Then you have a a small con. Maybe you
want to do some uh you know uh
processing of your data. And then here
you have these two nonlinearities.
Then you have your state space model.
Then this is this is the gating that we
haven't talked about but we will talk
about later. And then again you have a
linear layer. Okay. So you do have these
nonlinearities.
We're going to use the tricks of making
sure A is diagonal and using the FFT.
One thing to question, one question that
you might have is wait,
if doing convolutions using the FFT was
so much better, why don't we talk about
this in the connet part of the class?
And it turns out that the the key reason
is that for this n login game to really
kick in, you want to be thinking about
really long convolutions. when you have
when your convolutions are small, it
doesn't make that much of a difference
to just do it straight as a convolution.
And so the gains weren't enough to
really use this that much in in
convolutional neural nets, but in in
state space land, uh that starts to that
starts to really matter.
So in summary, uh state space models are
nice because you know in train time you
can do all of these things parallelly
and then at inference time this is
really easy to compute the the next
state, right? Because you just have
you've collected all of your history
into this h of t. To compute h of t plus
one, you just do a h of t minus one plus
the input. So uh at inference time these
are these are quick to update as well
right so you you're not even doing
convolutions at inference time
because all of your history is captured
into this one uh one hidden state. So
they can be cheaper than other models to
implement at inference time as well. So
I will stop at that because uh and uh if
there's a last question I can take it.
If not we will continue uh Thursday. Any
questions?
Okay, great. And see you Thursday.
>> Yeah.