We're going to move on today to talk
about uh graph neural nets. And I wanted
to point out right now uh important
resources for you to have u if you want
to learn more. So first is of course
chapter 13 in Prince's book. So Prince
uh covers transformers before he talks
about uh graph neural. the treatment
will be a little different in character,
substantially different in character,
but it's still there's good stuff in
there.
There's a really nice uh blog post from
2021 on graph neural nets. We will
reference this in both the homework um I
think possibly also in the discussion uh
next week.
Uh our treatment in this class is going
to be limited on graph neural nets and
there's it's an incredibly important
topic practically.
So uh if if you want to learn more about
many different things, you should know
about uh the different software packages
uh you know pytor geometric for example
uh this deep graph library um and
spectral for those who like using
tensorflow um
and there's a lot of information in
there that deals with various practical
things that end up happening u I've only
mentioned these extremely briefly and
most I will not meion at all. Uh
Stanford has a really nice course on
graph neural nets. So one of the real
leaders of the field uh is a professor
there and this class has a lot of useful
information if you really want to go
deeper in graph neural nets. Uh so I
want to point these resources out in
case for people who want to want to use
them.
Uh I we mentioned it on the last lecture
but uh in response to student demand we
have moved uh TA office hour from the
last office hour on Tuesday to Friday at
in 5:31 Corey at 2 to 3 p.m. So please
take advantage of that.
Um and with that I'll just uh continue
with the material. So we're moving from
in the class we talked about MLPS first
and you've seen them before in our
earlier classes to CNN's which some of
you may or may not have seen um before.
or in fact many people seem to have seen
them before to but hopefully the
treatment here helped you understand
them better uh to graph neural nets
which many of you have not seen before
but some of you may have
so the pictures that we saw before where
you know an MLP sort of everything is
connected to everything else uh because
you don't know what's going on uh in
terms of any particular information
structure about the inputs anything
could be important for anything else to
CNN's where you had this structure that
said there is a locality to the inputs
nearby pixels have to do with each other
probably and the processing took
advantage of that and so graph neural
nets are about generalizing this so
instead of the kind of things we saw
before where we have images that we want
to do something to we're going to have
graphs okay so very briefly
I wanted to just you know quickly just
put on here so you can go and reference
it when I put these up for everybody
that we've learned many concepts in the
context of CNN. And one of the most
useful things about graph neural net
from a pedagogical point of view is it
helps you see which of these concepts
were actually just tied to CNN's and
which ones are actually more general and
to appreciate them in a little bit more
of their general form. This will help
you when thinking about new
architectures.
Okay, so everything up here you should
you we've talked about. Um there's one
loose end that I realized in uh office
hours someone asked about I realized I
hadn't talked about it. So I wanted to
quickly mention this tie up this one
loose end which is this is a form of
dropout which is called stochastic depth
regularization.
Okay, it's extremely simple as an idea
but I should just make sure you you've
heard about it. And so in dropout
remember we use dropout for MLPS where
we individually remove for a particular
training done run certain inputs to the
MLP we just zero them out. Okay we we
call this a kind of data augmentation
that we do for intermediate layers. Okay
so stochastic depth regularization is
doing the same thing removing something
with some probability except it does it
at the level of an entire block.
So it says with some probability in a
resnet you'll just remove this block
entirely just wipe it up. So instead of
having something with a skip connection
you just have the skip connection.
Okay so in terms of mechanics that is
the full explanation. It takes one
minute. Okay but you should know this
exists and its purpose is light dropout.
This is used to help with overfitting
and for creating a kind of redundancy.
So in dropout we said what it did was it
forced information to be carried not
just in one particular activation but
across many activations added some
redundancy
because after all any one thing can be
dropped out. So the same thing applies
here at the level of blocks. This
creates a kind of functional redundancy
that you can't have this particular
block doing a very special thing that
this particular block hasn't done any
of. They all should be doing some things
kind of a little bit shared.
There are other reasons for doing uh
stocastic depth regularization that you
can read about uh in terms of why people
think it works. uh empirically people
find in many situations it helps
it has another little advantage during
training uh which is different than
dropout in dropout when you zero out
some things it doesn't really help you
computationally because it's an MLP that
you're dropping stuff out from and you
can't really take advantage of this
unstructured sparity that you just
introduced in terms of the computation
but here you can take advantage of it
computationally you don't have to do
anything for the block you dropped out.
So buys you little little bits of
computational savings. Uh if you know
10% of the blocks are being dropped out,
you can run the entire operation, you
know, without doing that 10% of work as
well.
>> Yes. Question.
>> What are like traditionally chosen
values for the dropout percentage?
>> Uh typical probabilities are so in
dropout for MLPS you go like 50 or 10%.
Here it's more like 10. Um there's
different schedules that people use for
dropout uh for stocastic death
regularization. Sometimes they will drop
stuff out earlier more often than
they'll drop stuff out later. Um this
different scalings they use but you can
read about it. So again the rule is
always the same. If you're working on
something and you're experiencing
overfitting you say okay what are my
list of things I could do? Look at other
papers. if they did stocastic death
regularization you'd be like maybe I
should try that okay that's the
practical import but you should know
what it is
okay so now let's start into uh the GNN
topic so the big picture of generalizing
CNN's is to say images have local
structure what is the most general
object class we know about that captures
the idea of local structure and those
are graphs
Okay, so graphs also occur because they
do this. They occur in lots and lots of
uh potential applications. So, you know,
here's a picture from Prince that sort
of shows you a few uh little pictures
of, you know, when things can happen.
You can have graphs connecting papers,
the directed graphs in terms of who
sites who, for example. Um you have
follower networks in the concept of
social networks. um friend connections
also you have who buys what in
commercial settings. Hopefully these
examples will help you understand why
graph neural nets are extremely
practically significant. Um because
people who deal with large social
networks want to suggest something to
you really care about that graph and
really would like to make predictions uh
based on that information.
Um you also have you know so networks
that have lots of labels you also have
in
the context in context of mechanical
systems civil engineering mechanical
engineering anytime you're building even
electrical circuits you have graph
structures so here's an example of a
graph kind of showing the kind of meshes
that happen when you're thinking about
3D modeling
and graphs have also played a role in
computer vision where you want to
express the interreationship of objects
to each other. So graphs are useful
things to have around.
And so the question is
how can we take advantage of the graph
and build a deep neural network that
takes advantage of the graph structure.
Okay, everyone see the kind of big
picture here? So uh in terms of
practical importance, I mentioned some
examples here. The other place where
they're extremely important is
chemistry. and materials because as you
can imagine molecules are naturally
graphs um and so they play a huge role
there and in other domains in physics so
lots of physics inspired neural net
stuff involves graph neural nets
okay so now let's start building some
analogies the basic kind of question
that we started off when we talked about
CNN's was the idea of image
classification right you have an image
and you say is this an image of a dog, a
cat, an airplane and so on. The
counterpart in graph neural nets is
called graph classification. So you're
given a graph and the entire graph has
to be digested and understood and then
you say something about it. I think the
example in that blog post uh is
here's a chemical. Does it smell or not?
Is it a smelly chemical? Right? So you
see that's kind of a property of the
entire graph.
So you know you have some information
that's used it comes in on a graph
like images
every information will be expressed in
vectors in in your input and then you do
some processing in a graph neural net
and then you get a classifier at the
end. Okay that's like a classification
style problem.
But just like we had semantic
segmentation which was a pixel level
problem.
You have a counterpart in graphs which
you can think of as a node level
problem. So you have a graph and you
would like to do some kind of
classification at every node.
Okay, hopefully this is very natural.
And because graphs have nodes and edges,
you can do the same thing for edges.
And for edges you can also have this uh
other might seem as a conceptually
distinct thing is even saying should
this edge exist.
Right now in our treatment here we're
going to focus entirely at the node
level but everything we talk about can
be generalized to thinking about edges
as well. Okay.
So everyone get the kind of big picture
of the mapping. So this is the first
level of mapping. Ask yourself the
question given the things you know how
to do in CNN's what are the counterpart
things you could imagine doing in a
graph are they useful or not and yeah
they're useful so here we talk about in
terms of classification
but you can also think about it in terms
of regression so classic example is
here's a molecule graph tell me the
three-dimensional position of the
individual atoms when this is being
immersed in a solution with a certain pH
Right. Very important practical
question.
Okay. So hopefully everyone's on board
with uh what we're trying to do.
And so now to understand graph neural
nets, we're going to start with the
simplest conceptual step which is we're
going to think about images which we
know how to do as though they are
graphs.
We'll understand what kind of graph they
are most naturally and then what would
we do which is we'll do the same thing
we did before except we're going to
think about it as a graph everyone see
this as a good way if you want to
generalize something you want to say
okay what is it that you know let me
understand what I know with a lens
towards the more general picture I want
to look at so I can see what I might
need to change
okay so here's a very simple picture so
I've dri I've made a little image hair.
Can everyone can see this little image?
And just for reasons of visual uh
depiction, I've used fours for the
smiley and ones for the background. So
you can see the different colors.
And
we're going to think of nodes in the
graph as being pixels in the image.
Okay? So there's this pixel, which is
the top corner of the image. It happens
to have a value in it, namely one.
So I'm going to think of it as a node.
There's a particular node here and it
has a value one
and the local neighborhood structure of
the image which was expressed by the
array in a CNN. I want to make it
explicit as a graph. So
let's look at this little section here
and blow it up. Okay. So let me make
this bigger.
[Applause]
So if I want to express the information
in this little section as a graph in
terms of what the neighborhood
relationships are,
I can say for example this one is the
one I'm calling here the center one. It
has neighbors.
So I can think of it as having neighbors
as having edges to the neighbors.
But you can think of it this way. You
can think of an edge between this one,
which is this one here, and this one
that says this particular node
has information coming from the north
from this guy. You can use like like I
did before, right? North,
south,outheast, west. And this
particular node has information coming
from the south from this one.
So, first thing you notice is there's a
relationship between these two. And for
a connet, the kind of stuff we did in a
convent, it matters,
you know what that ordering is because
there's a difference between the image
and the image upside down.
Does everyone see that? So I have to
have both those edges. So first thing we
notice is what kind of thing is like a
directed graph. It's a directed graph
and it has labels on the edges that tell
what kind of relationship those two
things have.
And similarly you have west and east and
you know then you have southeast
northwest and all these other edges.
So I'll I'll pause here. Any questions
on this sort of bigger the story that
we're doing. So we have an image. We can
view the image as a graph. This is how
we would for example view it as a graph.
And of course the edges continue on out.
I just zoomed in in one little place.
Any questions on this?
>> Yes. The relationship between north and
south for each nodes are the same. I
mean this is north and south the same as
north and south here.
>> Excellent question. So uh let me zoom
out here because I' I've captured this.
Uh is there's a finite set of labels in
this graph?
Right? There's north, south, east, west,
northeast, southeast, northwest,
southwest. And this label is the same.
So this edge south label and this edge
north label is the same label as this
one. So in that sense the labels are
capturing the nature of that
relationship and there's a finite set of
them. So it's the same.
Okay, does that answer your question?
Okay, good. So now you have the idea
that you have uh these neighbors and we
have to make note of something else
which is that you always have a special
relationship to self
right in a con you need to use the
information here but you can just say
graphs have a self they know where they
what they themselves are at a particular
node.
Is that clear?
Okay. So now what we're going to do is
we're going to just look at our picture
from before of
how we do a con a 3x3 con.
So everyone remember this picture from
before for a 3x3 con where we thought
about there being weight matrices
associated with every position in the
3x3 grid and you had a bias and you
computed the output for this particular
position by taking a sum of information
from neighboring pixels as well as this
pixel itself.
Okay. Now we can think of that from a
point of view of where the information
is flowing on a graph. We can think of
it as a particular node receives
messages from its neighbors
each of whom has their own labeled edge
to me. So I'm going to take the
perspective of me being the node the
center.
So I get information from all these
different edges. And so I see this has
come to me on an edge labeled north.
So I'll multiply it by the matrix W N.
This information has come for me from an
an edge labeled south. So I'm going to
multiply that information by a weight
south.
Everyone see this? And I do this and I
add them all up and I take my own
information that I have from the last
layer and I multiply it by something
specific. the weight for me. Add that up
and then I add a bias.
Okay, so I'll pause here uh for a
minute.
Does everyone see how this is exactly
what's happening here? Except all we've
done is we've turned it from thinking of
it as a convolution acting on a array to
messages coming on a graph.
But it's the same story. Nothing has
changed. We've just translated to graph
language.
So any questions here.
Okay.
So now if there's no questions we can
say okay let's like make some
observations here.
In this view,
we have implicitly
same padding and zero padding. Whereas
for a con, we had this question of where
was the con fit?
Everyone see that? So, let me explain
what I mean by that.
In the picture of a con, we ask the
question, well, I don't know how to get
an output for this for a 3x3 con
necessarily because I can't fit a 3x3
filter. I'll have an out of memory
error. But in this picture, I will just
receive messages from some edges but not
from others. So if I follow this
procedure, I'll still just multiply
everything out, add them up, and I'll
have an answer.
But what that corresponds to is the
missing information that I don't have by
multiplying by zeros. So it's like a
zero pad.
And in this picture, no node says,
"Sorry, I have nothing. I'm out."
So it's always same padding.
As I apply this kind of processing, I
always get the same nodes back. No new
nodes are added, no nodes are deleted in
this picture.
Questions on that?
Yes,
>> an earlier question because in with
convolution we think of there just being
like one unified bias. In this case,
would we still like technically have
unified bias or do we just functionally
have one because all of the connections
have their own biases that just add up
together.
>> Okay, excellent point. So the way I
described it, so let me you're asking
about the biases. So let me explain the
biases as well as make note of another
point.
The way I described this is I said you
do all these multiplications add them up
and then finally you add a bias.
Okay. But implicit in this story is
weight sharing. So let me make a note of
that explicitly.
Make another note.
Weight sharing
across nodes.
So just as we said in the connet you
could imagine a connet where you do
different convolutions at different
places. In fact we had on the on the
discussion for you to see right you can
still do that but we said in practice we
share. Why? Because we want to say that
what we learned here is good over here
too. We do the same thing in a graph
except the weight sharing which was
weight sharing over pixels in a CNN
becomes weight sharing over nodes in a
graph neural net. But it's the same
story.
Okay. So everyone sees uh these two
points hopefully understands them.
Second is in our description of connets
we also had one by one coms and one by
one conss if you remember just acted on
the information in a particular pixel
and that just carries over here too.
Okay, we can still have operations. We
want to do this local to a particular
node. Just look at the information in
this node does some operation on it. A
one by one con, you can make it an MLP
like all that can still happen just as
we did in the blocks that we had. For
example, last time we talked about
resonant blocks, right? Remember in the
context we said there was some kind of
convolution and then there was a we'll
talk about other layers like
normalization and then there was a one
by one followed by nonlinearity followed
by one by one. So all that kind of story
just still works here. That's this
meaning of the one by ones.
So and just as in a connet
the matrices wi and biases B are
specific to a particular layer of
processing. So in a connet we do
different cons at different blocks. We
can do the same thing here
in a graph neural net.
So here the important thing is we
haven't changed anything. It's the same
as it was in a connet. We're just
interpreting it in graph language and
seeing that everything just carries
over.
>> Yes.
>> Um if we're using matrices for like the
gra does that imply that there's like
channels of the graph as well.
>> Excellent question. The question about
channels. So just as we had in a CNN in
a CNN we said what's an image? An image
is a rectangular array of pixels filled
with vectors. That's what we said was an
image. So here in a graph neural net,
we'll and those vectors are the same
size. In a graph neural net, we'll say
what's a graph problem? It's a graph
with in this particular case edges
labeled with one of some finite set
and inside every node of the graph is a
vector of the same dimension. That's how
the whatever your input is, you have to
turn it into this for me to start
working. The same thing for a CNN.
Okay. So
what I what I said here is that look
from this simple picture
doing no work at all.
We have an immediate recipe to
generalize CNN's to as long as we have
the following properties. We must have a
directed graph
and every edge has to be labeled from a
discrete finite set. Then with every
element of that finite set, we can
associate a weight matrix
and then we can follow this recipe.
Does everyone see that? So this is like
simply saying we look at a a CNN and we
say let's think about it as those on a
graph. What do we know how to do? We
know how to do this.
Nothing new is required to do this. So
now we ask ourselves
what kind of stuff do we get that
generalizes immediately like there's no
work required.
So weight sharing nodes do the same
things again no work 3x3 cons fine
matrices for edge labels we have
the idea of additional channels fine we
can do a con that creates more channels
at another layer no problem
residual connections no problem we can
still add things together
dropout for MLPS
No problem. Stocastic depth
regularization no problem. Nothing is
it just works.
Does it? Okay. This is is it good to
pause here? Any questions on this? When
I say just works, it means from the
graph story we've told
you do exactly the same thing and you
can do it on a graph. No thought is
required.
Any questions on these?
Yes.
>> I think I'm just a little confused.
Could you like for example like show how
you would like drop out on a graph?
>> Ah, excellent. So I didn't say drop out
on a graph. I said drop out for MLPS. So
remember we said when do you use dropout
in the CNN? You use them on the MLPS.
We said we don't use dropout on the
cons.
So dropout for the MLPS those are like
you still have MLPS here. and they they
don't they don't even care that there's
a graph. They just sit inside one node.
Okay. So from that point of view, it
doesn't even the dropout for MLPS
doesn't even see the graph.
>> Yeah.
>> Could you like illustrate real quick
what are the weights that are associated
with the graph again? Are they the edges
or what?
>> Okay. Excellent question. When I use the
word weight, I'm going to mean a
learnable parameter.
Okay, of our neural net. The neural net
is something that we design. We would
like to do the processing in a way that
respects the graph's topology. That's
why we're doing a graph neural net
because we saw this is useful for a CNN
to respect the images topology. So, we
want to kind of carry that same
principle over.
There are no weights associated with the
graph.
In this story, all we have is edges with
labels. There's no weights. there are
labels and those labels come from a
discrete finite set.
Okay, so there are no weights associated
with the graph. There are weights
associated with the graph neural net and
those weights associated with the graph
neural net for the thing that
corresponds to a 3x3 conf. Those weights
are associated with the edge labels.
Okay, that's what we have here.
>> Yes. Um, I think I get the difference
between like the CNN and the CNN, but
I'm not sure about the difference on the
coding part like should we just create
classes
>> for what? Sorry.
>> Like how how different is it when you
code it?
>> Ah, excellent question. So, okay, so
that's a really really good question.
So, the question was, okay, we
understand the story conceptually, but
what do you do when you're working with
code? Right? because you can't just say
well look I know that this particular
case is exactly like a CNN conceptually
you can't call the con class and have it
work because it expects arrays and here
we don't have arrays we have graphs this
is why on the first page I said use
these libraries
okay
so uh pytorch geometric for example will
give you classes that will deal with all
these these things for you. Okay? And
you can reuse those. So this is an
excellent point to make a note of
something that's is practically
significant. So in graphs
we have a graph and we can take a local
view. But in images you have a very
rigid and
rectangular structure and computers like
rectangular structures because they map
to memory arrays nicely and here it's
more free form. So there's a
computational hit you take by having to
have this flexibility and the libraries
work very hard into trying to get the
parallelisms to work when it can work
but you take a hit for doing it. Um but
the practical importance of graphs is so
high that it's worth people making those
libraries and making it efficient.
And that's why we're not going to ask
you to code it up um yourself because it
is a lot more um like detailed keeping
track of edges and graphs and not much
learning bang for the buck in doing that
um in this class at least. I'm sure a
graph neural nets class would make you
do it but this is not a graph neural
nets class.
So moving along. Okay. So now let's talk
about what stuff does not generalize.
So when you're can you just use this
exact kind of architecture as you did
before and the thing that doesn't
generalize that requires the most
thinking is
downsampling and pulling and relatedly
upsampling.
And the reason is if you think about a
graph right image it makes sense to say
give me that image at half the
resolution. That makes sense. We say
here is a graph of friends.
Give me this graph at half resolution.
Like what? Like what does that mean?
Right? It doesn't have an application
independent meaning you have to think
what am I trying to do? Why am I doing
this? What's going on? Right? What do I
want these new nodes to mean? Right? I
get a new graph. You can say give me a
graph with half as many nodes in it.
That makes sense as a question, but what
do you want from that half as many
nodes,
right? It's not as clear as throw away
every other pixel. Everyone see that? So
there's no clean way of generalizing
pooling and downsampling. And similarly
for upsampling for the same reason.
Any questions on that? So I just want to
flag that. So that's the part of the CNN
you can't just bring over.
You have to keep the same graph all the
time for your processing. No going down.
Any questions on that part?
Okay. Next thing what needs discussion
is normalization
because the pictures we had in
normalization before were kind of image
tied. So we need to kind of think about
them a little bit um for the question.
It won't take long but we do have to
think about it.
Okay. So the big insight that we're
using throughout is the graph in a graph
neural net is playing the role of the
empty grid of pixels in a CNN. Okay, the
graph corresponds to the empty grid of
pixels. The input to a CNN is not an
empty grid of pixels but a grid of
pixels with values filled in. And same
thing for a GNN. The input is a graph
with vectors in it. And then we do
processing.
Okay, so now let's just talk about the
normalization part.
So before we had this these kind of
pictures
where we said we have an axis for
channels. We still have an axis for
channels. You could have batches. So we
could have an axis for batch
um except it's no longer this nice
cubicle shape.
Why? Because in an image, we said we're
going to fix a resolution and all of our
images in the CNN are going to have the
same resolution. So our batch is going
to have the same size images. But for
graphs, if you're going to take many
graphs as your input to make a batch,
it might not be the case that your graph
has the same number of nodes. Many
natural settings, graphs have different
numbers of nodes. So think about, you
know, amino acids. The amino acids don't
have the same number of atoms in them.
They're different.
They might be related to each other. So
you want to train one network on all the
amino acids, but that doesn't work. So
there's a whole level of complexity in
thinking about batches in graph neural
nets that we're not going to talk about.
So batch normalization type ideas are
sort of don't quite work
naturally in units.
Okay, so
this one is kind of out uh for what to
do because it's hard to even deal with
the batch.
Next is sort of layerm. So layerm
doesn't look at the batches. It doesn't
care the fact that this picture doesn't
hold for the graph. You definitely have
a graph
and what lairs we have to do for layerm
is we have to say okay
in a CNN we have
you know pixels that we were averaging
over and we were averaging over them to
get
two things first is we wanted to say
look let's get more averaging
okay than just our channels
Second thing we said is that in many
practical settings, you know, there
might be a cat somewhere in the image.
So just for the fact there's not a cat
here or this is a boring part of the
image, I don't want to accidentally have
the normalization do something to it. If
there's an interesting thing, I want to
keep the interesting thing being louder
than the boring parts, for example.
So that's why we're doing this. But
here,
when we replace this, the natural
counterpart to pixels is nodes.
And so it is possible to implement layer
on a graph neural net where you do an
average both over channels and over all
the nodes.
This requires
one thing though. It requires your graph
to fit in memory.
Now we're going to take that for granted
in all of our discussion. But
practically speaking that is sometimes
not true.
Think about the graph of Facebook.
right? Has a massive social network. It
doesn't fit in memory.
So, but they want to train on this giant
graph. What do you do? So, there's all
this work in graph neural nets that is
also dealing with the case of when your
graph is too big to even fit in memory,
what do you do? Not a problem in CNN's.
We never work with images that are too
big to fit in memory.
>> Yes. I think like different graphs might
might have like different number of
nodes, right? Uh
>> yes.
>> So how are we supposed to
>> Okay, so I I said before this
not a good picture
because batches don't have the same
shape. So we really don't want to go
across batches.
There are techniques for doing batch
type stuff in graph neural nets, but I'm
not going to talk about them because
they're much more complicated.
So different different graphs might have
different number of nodes. So we just
never try to combine information across
different graphs in one training map.
>> Yes.
>> So in this case layer norm is sort of
just like I'm going to go through all my
nodes. I'm going to check all the
channels take the average of every
channel value of every node.
>> Yeah.
>> And that's like okay.
>> Yeah. This is like basically saying I
want the for example you think of the
RMS norm point of view. I want the
average RMS norm of my activations for
this particular output of this layer for
my entire graph to be one.
So that's what layerm would do. Layerm
style would do laror of course actual
lair norm also has this mean correction
but you know that's a that's a level of
detail that doesn't matter for the graph
to CNN distinction. Yes. If you think of
the channels as like the dimensions in
the vectors for each node, then is it
possible for different nodes to have
different dimensional vectors and
therefore the channels aren't the same?
>> Great question. The question was, is it
possible for different nodes of the
vector to have different dimension
inputs? The answer is maybe in your
original problem, but not when you start
feeding into the GNN.
You enforce that the same number of
channels exist everywhere.
So this leaves one more choice which we
didn't talk about before but it's a very
natural choice which just says yeah
don't don't try to do any averaging over
nodes just look at every node by itself
look at its channels
and just normalize that.
Okay, so in general the term that's used
for the channels, the vectors that are
sitting in a neural net at a particular
entity like a like a node in a graph or
pixel, it's called an embedding. That's
the word that's used for that. So this
is just looking at the embedding just
per embedding normalization.
You can do this for sure
and just apply the same embedding at
every node. the weights are shared if
you have learnable weights like for
example for scale or shift but if you're
doing like an RMS norm peg to one
there's no learnable weights at all
as always weights are shared across
nodes
but there's no you don't have to look at
what's going on in another node to
compute how to normalize this particular
value so this is the easy choice any
questions on this
so by default in a graph neural net
you'll just do this
Okay. So now we've talked about all the
stuff you know here this is easy this
we've now covered.
So let's keep going
and let's say okay are we done and the
answer is no. Okay we are not done. Um
why are we not done? Because there's
many kinds of graphs. I showed you
pictures and we've talked about this
case
where we have finite set of edge labels
in a directed graph.
We can do that.
But there's also directed graphs where
you have infinite edge labels. For
example, continuous things. For example,
what some people you might call weights
on graphs, weighted on weights on edges.
We don't know how to deal with that.
um you have undirected graphs which we
don't know how to deal with and you have
cases where you don't have labels.
We don't know how to deal with that. So
the most different than this is this
corner. Does everyone see that? So we're
going to talk about this corner next
because the ideas that we use to cover
this corner will then help us understand
everything in here.
>> Yes.
>> Yeah. I just don't get why we are so
attached to the fact that the graph is
directed or undirected because like if
I'm the pixel behind you, you are the
pixel on top of me. So,
>> but we have a different relationship.
The important thing is we have a
different relationship to each other.
So, when you have two pixels next to
each other, one is on the right and one
is on the left.
>> That matters for the conf.
is not just that they're next to each
other.
So
>> if I get the image that reversed
>> um so okay okay let me I'll try to make
this clear in a little bit but here's a
way of thinking about it suppose I
didn't I wanted to take the image
picture here
so let's look at this image picture and
suppose I just dropped all the labels
okay so I drop all the labels then this
pixel
knows it has nine neighbors,
but it doesn't know which ones are up
and which ones are down.
Does everyone see that? So, for example,
can I detect a vertical edge
versus a horizontal edge versus a random
scatter? I cannot because a vertical
edge is characterized by the idea that
there is some you know something
happening over here and then something
different happening over here but all I
have is a collection of edges so I can't
tell. So there's definitely a
restriction in what you can do if you
don't have labels on edges. Does that in
that intuition become clear?
So it's non-trivial what to do
in this setting.
Okay. So go back. Okay. So here's an
attempt that we can do that won't work
but it's I showed you in pictures but
it's good to sort of think about it in
math.
So the first attempt says let's try to
reduce to the understood case. So I
understand how to do directed with edge
finite edge labels. I don't have any
edge labels. So you could think not
having any is finite zero,
right? So I could just assign remember
we're processing it how we want to. So I
could just assign a label to everything.
Call everything edge.
I have a labeled edge labeled edge.
Okay?
And if I have an undirected edge, I just
say, yeah, I have edges in both
directions
and they're both labeled edge.
Okay,
so that now I've reduced it from here
syntactically into this case and I can
run all the machinery that I have. But
what does that machinery do?
That machinery would do this. A con
would look like this. But I wouldn't
have an index on the W.
I'm missing something, right? I'm
missing a subscript.
But then
unfortunately
the W can be brought outside the sum.
Does everyone see that?
So you might think, what's so
unfortunate about this? Okay.
Everyone see that? We do this. But now
all I can do is average my neighbors or
add them up. That's all I can do.
I can then do some scaling on it, but
not not really. If I take this picture.
So what ends up happening in these
situations is when you run a graph
neural net like this, you get a
phenomena that's sometimes called
dramatic over smoothing.
Okay. What happens when you average
together a bunch of things? At some
point you just average everything
together.
So lots of layers of processing. All you
end up doing is averaging everything.
So this is called over smoothing. Um
it's always a problem in graph neural
nets but this is like most dramatic case
of it. Um and so your expressive power
of the kinds of things you can compute
with this kind of network is too low.
You can't compute the interesting things
you want.
Questions on this?
Okay. So this approach doesn't work. So
we have to step back and ask what do we
actually know in this case?
What kind of what can we use?
So
we know that a node knows that it's
itself.
So it has a special piece of information
which is its own information H0 that
didn't come on any edge.
Okay. So you know that
and you can treat it specially
here. We didn't treat it specially
but we could.
Second you know how many neighbors you
actually have
because you're getting message on some
edges. So you know that you're getting n
such messages. That's another piece of
information you can actually try to use.
So I could do averaging for example.
But that doesn't help me by itself.
And all I have a kind of mathematical
way to think about it is I have a set of
information from my neighbors. I don't
have a list. I have a set.
All of the information I'm getting from
my different edges is equivalent to me.
there's no ordering information in
there.
So I have to respect this and look at
what design freedom I have given that I
have this limit these limitations.
So the architectural constraints that
this creates for our graph neural net
that I have to obey to be true to the
graph is I can use n and h0 in a special
way but I have to be permutation
invariant to the other things.
Okay.
So one such thing I could do is this.
But this is bad because of the fact this
is commuting.
I can pull the sorry I can pull the uh w
out of the sum the linearity.
So now the question is what can we do?
So here's an example of something we can
do
as a general form.
I want learnable weights. So I have some
function f with learnable weights.
It takes two distinct arguments
me because I can tell me and then it
just takes a sum
of
some other learnable function applied to
information I'm getting from my
neighbors. This is legal.
Okay, does everyone see why this is
legal? Because I'm using things that I'm
allowed to use. I'm allowed to use
myself specially and I have to be
permutation invariant and a sum is
permutation invariant
and I'm doing the same thing to all my
neighbors. My neighbors are being
treated symmetrically.
Okay. So now I want everyone to take one
minute talk to your neighbors and ask
yourself you can compute a list of other
permutation invariant sum like
operations operations that don't care
about the orderings of things. Sum is
one choice. What other choices do you
have? Okay, go.
[Music]
the dumbest idea.
>> Oh, wait. Yeah.
[Music]
That's
probably
[Music]
Okay.
>> So, time's up.
>> Uh, let's uh let's start taking. So,
maybe can people count your list? How
many things are on your list? So, how
many people have one thing they found?
Only one other thing.
Two other things. Couple of people.
Three other things.
Okay. Slightly more people. Four other
things. Okay. More. Five.
Six. Six.
Seven. Any other number higher?
Okay. So, let's just let's let's go
through and see what we can get. How
many different things we can get. Some
will be similar presumably to each
other. But someone want to start with a
list?
Someone said multiplication. Fine.
multiplication.
Okay, multiplication
true doesn't care about the order, but
you can just take logs and treat it as a
sum. So, it's kind of same thing kind
same kind of thing, but good to know.
Um, what else over there?
>> Um, inverse of the sum of inverses.
>> Inverse of sums of inverses. Yeah. Okay.
So, they're compositions. So what I you
can do in this picture here
if you think about something which is
basically an inverse
a sum of inverses and inverting that
that's all already contained in the
expressive power of what you're doing
here. So I'm not looking for things that
do operations and then take sums and
then do other things to that. Okay. So
I'm not going to count that as a a
choice.
>> Yeah.
>> Min or max?
>> Min or max. Yeah,
those don't care. Um, what else? Yeah.
>> Yeah.
>> Median.
>> Median. Yep.
Because you can just sort, right? And
then you could do something. Yeah. Min,
m, median,
>> others. Yeah.
>> Like order statistics maybe or something
like that.
>> General order statistics. Yeah.
These are things like median, right?
These are all in the f friends of
median.
Um, okay. Good.
Yeah.
>> Norms.
>> Norms. Yep.
As long as the norm doesn't care about
the ordering. So, uh, certain norms. So
all the LP type norms are all fine but
for example if you think about a norm
that involves a quadratic form inside
right that will not be legal because you
can't do a matrix multiply uh to compute
that norm but yes norms the right kind
um I'll write one down that's uh
basically the same as sum but we'll
treat it slightly differently because
we're allowed to is the n so we can do
an average. Um
but uh okay uh more anyone more choices.
>> Yeah.
>> Could you find the variance too?
>> Variance. Yeah. Because that's like
average and then other things that are
built off of average of another thing
that's uses the average. Good. Yeah.
>> Mode.
>> Um sure. Let's call mode in this mix in
the same family as this. Yeah. Mode type
stuff. Yeah.
>> Yeah.
>> Like the I don't have to call it like
the cardality but like the number of
unique items.
>> Sure. Good. Number of unique items.
Yeah. Count unique. Yeah.
These are all valid choices.
>> Yeah.
>> We have another another like learnable
function.
So we we want to have learnable
functions. Okay, remember the big
picture. The big picture is when we make
a neural net making a neural net is our
answer to I don't know what to do. I
want to make it learnable. However, to
make it learnable, I have to make an
architecture and I have to make certain
choices in my architecture and I in
neural net language we usually want to
make all the learnable parameter be
weights or biases of some kind or things
some a few other families of things that
we also consider learnable parameters.
So saying I want to make it learnable
doesn't answer the question that we're
trying to answer here which is what are
the kind of basic forms we can use out
of which we can make learnable things.
>> Yeah I have a question just so we're
doing this for each output channel but
then the inputs H's may have many
channels but they're all the same right
like H self and H all of your edges can
have multiple items per H right?
>> Yes. All of the hes are vectors of some
dimensionality, but the dimensionality
is the same. We're doing this for every
output channel.
>> Okay.
>> Yeah.
>> Could you look at things like
correlation with itself maybe or
something like that?
>> Yes, you can do correlations with self.
So, we'll come back to that. Uh yeah, so
we'll come back to that. Uh
I'll make that a special letter.
because that correlation with self
doesn't fall into this format here. I'm
really talking about replacing this guy.
Okay, but that we'll talk about that in
a moment. Um,
so uh
I want to point out uh something that
you might not have thought about as
being permutation invariant, but it is
permutation invariant. Uh we're going to
do le squares.
So
magic trick
every time you see average ask yourself
who's average is big brother right le
squares
right le squares is like an average in
spirit
so le squares thought of as a single
object that takes xy pairs and computes
a matrix to apply
Le squares doesn't care about the
ordering.
Everyone see this?
The order of the inputs doesn't matter
to le squares. So all of le squares is a
choice of something that's permutation
invariant.
as a block. But once le squares is in
all ML
is in,
right? Did you see that everyone le
squares is one example you know le
squares. So this is like you have to
have build these conceptual connections
in your mind. It helps you. Okay. You
know averaging is like le squares but le
squares is the root of like all ML. So
nearest neighbors
kernel methods everything that has the
flavor like you can think of as being I
treat things as a bunch of training
data. You don't care about the ordering
of the training data. All of that is in
this is a huge family.
Okay. Um, another thing that you should
be thinking about is if you have a bunch
of numbers,
you can do soft maxes.
A softmax operation takes a bunch of
numbers and turns them into things that
look like probabilities.
It doesn't care about the order,
but it kind of it gives you back the
same things counterparts for every
single thing. So you can also build
things out of using softmaxes in this
picture.
Okay. So you think okay wow
once you start asking yourself what kind
of things you can do you have a a pretty
rich vocabulary of stuff that's
permutation invariant. So now we're
going to keep going. Okay. Yes.
>> What exactly are the x y pairs for least
squares? Is is y h0 in every case? Like
what is
>> ah great question. So when you think of
an object like this you can think of it
as this. For example, for le squares,
you could say, fine, what I'm going to
do is I'm gonna have a function,
learnable function that takes the input
and extracts an x and a y. What x and y
should be, I don't know, make it
learnable.
Then I apply le squares to that.
>> I see.
>> And out pops a le squares matrix. Then
go ahead and apply that matrix however
you want on your data
as an example or nearest neighbors. Give
me some things for all that stuff.
Gotcha. So G is just like that.
>> So what's interesting here? So this is
actually um you might have heard this
general principle. Constraints inspire
creativity.
Okay, cons worked, right? Cons were
useful and they worked and so people
built connets and kept making them
better and working.
they didn't have to think about what
other general forms I might want
necessarily. But in the GNN community,
because you had this constraint of
undirected edges, you had to think of
what your actual design flexibility was
and that made people be creative.
So it turns out that even this format is
not the most general that you can get
because as was mentioned there is this
correlations with self idea
which said why in this picture why am I
not using myself in this function.
So let's we can do that.
So if everyone can see here, we can have
a function that acts on myself and then
some some like thing, which of course is
this entire family of stuff
that takes not just a learnable function
of the stuff that's coming from my
neighbor, but also myself.
Okay, so here's for example, so you
might think this is hard to think about.
This is very general. So how can I think
about this? How might I want to use
information about myself together with
the neighbor?
Does everyone see this as a like how do
you think about it? And the fact that
you've studied machine learning says
that well I actually do have one kind of
way that I'm used to thinking about
this. I'm used to thinking about this
for example when I take the kernel
perspective on regression problems or
classification problems.
So when you take the kernel this is not
the convolutional kernel kernel this is
kernels and kernel methods kernel. If I
take the kernel uh kernelized
perspective, the kernelized perspective
says
easiest to think about even from the
nearest neighbor point of view, how
should I predict what happens here? Let
me look at points that are like me. What
did they do? They did this. I should do
something similar. Right? That's the
nearest neighbor point of view. And
that's the kernelized perspective. More
generally, it says you compute some kind
of similarity between points and you use
that to interpret and weigh what that
particular point is predicting.
Everyone with me? So as in terms of math
format
inspired by kernel methods,
you can think about something that looks
like this.
So what's happening here is we're saying
look
we're going to take a sum of some
learned similarity measure between me
and a point and then some other learned
thing about that point.
I guess I could
be consistent.
So I'm pause here. Does everyone see the
kind of thought process journey that's
very natural from a machine learning
point of view that brings you to
something like this as a kind of generic
form that you might want to do
and we have also the understanding we
brought all these other things around.
Yeah. Question
>> what does S
function
what does it do? Ah, so this S I wrote
here I said was inspired by the idea of
some kind of similarity measure between
two things and I wanted to be learned.
So for a similarity measure,
okay, for a random variable, your go-to
distributions are Gaussian and uniform.
Okay, for a norm, your go-to norm is two
norm. And if that doesn't work, maybe
look at one norm or infinity norm. You
have like set of usual suspects, okay,
in your mind. Okay, for similarity
measure, what's your go-to similarity
measure?
>> Inner product.
Okay, and if you want to make it
learned, you're like, fine, I want to
learn similarity measure. I'll make
matrices
modulating the two things and then I'll
take their inner product. Does everyone
see that? Like this is just like like a
list in your mind of like complexity of
stuff and this is like go for the
easiest thing first. So that's always
the way we work in machine learning in
deep learning. Try something. What
should I try? Try the easiest thing
first. Does it work? If yes, great. If
not, try the next harder thing.
Everyone with me?
Okay.
So there's one more kind of thinking
that you have when you look at something
like this. So it's all about connecting
patterns in your mind. Yeah.
>> So essentially is introducing this
similarity like function just a more
strategic version of having just an
arbitrary function between um the self
node and the neighbor.
>> Um exactly. So here we have an arbitrary
function but I don't know how to think
about arbitrary functions. So we need to
think about families. There's too much
generality here. So because I want to
build a building block, I want to think
about something that I might want to
use. What might you want to use?
Something that might have already been
useful. So if something was useful
somewhere, odds are it might be useful
somewhere else.
And so we know from kernels kernel
methods that thinking about things in
terms of similarities and something is a
good way to think about coupled
functions. So let's just do that.
What I'm trying to show here is that
this kind of thinking isn't
hard.
It's just looking and saying, "What are
my list of choices?" It's kind of just
systematically going through stuff
you've seen.
The next thing when you observe
something like this, yeah,
>> should we have the H0 in the argument of
GW3?
>> Great question. The question was should
we put H0 inside this? And the answer is
no. Okay, why no? Because if we we
started with this and we said we don't
know how to think about this. So we want
to go to something simpler that we can
think about. So it's an odd kind of
simplicity that makes something longer
but it's still simpler. Okay. The reason
is this. I say general function. I don't
know how to think about general
functions.
Here I'm saying similarity like
functions
and general function of one thing. So
it's simpler because general function of
one thing I have a go-to thing MLP
something right
similarity functions I can start
thinking of how I might build a
similarity function. Namely I can use an
inner product. I have different
different things I would go to to do it.
That's why this we don't put
this here. It would be legal to we could
put H0 here. It's not that it's not an
illegal move, but it's not the first
move we make.
Okay. So, one more observation that I
want to say you might have just looking
at it.
So
when you look at something like this,
whenever you see some something times
something else,
okay, in your mind that should be like
I've seen this kind of stuff before,
right? And you have lots of different
places. But whenever you see a sum,
something and something else, you might
think maybe this should be an
expectation
because expectations look like that.
They look like sums of something times
something else.
Everyone with me? Okay. So this kind of
thinking should just prompt the thought
just a thought.
Should
this
be
an expectation?
Why might you want it to be an
expectation? You might want it to be an
expectation because you know many things
about expectations. You also know they
might be controlled. Whenever you see a
sum, you might be worried about dynamic
range. It's getting big, small,
something. So you might think if I make
it an expectation, I know at least it
won't the number of things in it won't
change it too much. Does everyone see
that? And in neural net land, you're
always worried about normalization.
Is something going to become too big,
too small? That's really bad.
That's another reason why you might say
it would be nice if it was an
expectation. Everyone with me? Okay.
Now,
how do you turn things like this into
expectations?
You turn one of them into probabilities.
That's how you do it. So, you ask
yourself, okay, which one should I turn
into a probability?
So you go back to thinking about
nearest neighbors or something. Okay. So
for nearest neighbors, what do you do?
You say nearest neighbor type thinking.
You say, "Okay, I'm here.
Who's nearby?
These are things that are nearby. I want
to take nearest neighbor regression. I
would like to take an average of these
nearby things.
Everyone with me?" So now you say ah how
similar am I to all of these? Turn that
into a probability and weight it by what
they are.
Everyone with me. So that's why you
should think ah the similarity is
probably the thing you might want to
turn into probabilities.
So
how do you turn a bunch of numbers? So
again maybe I should even mark mark the
vector status of these things.
This can be a vector.
This in general up here is a vector,
right? This up here is a vector.
But similarity I should think of as
being a scalar
like object.
So how do I turn a scalar type object a
bunch of them unsorted
into unordered into probabilities?
Softmax.
I have a I have a go-to thing for doing
this. I do it all the time. So, I can do
this. So, let's put all the pieces
together.
Okay.
Making them make take all these default
choices and just construct it.
Okay. So, design choices I'll use inner
product for similarity learned inner
product. To make a learned inner
product, I have to learn matrices
multiplying the two things.
I'll use expectation style for the sum,
some learned linear function. And I'll
use some MLP for the final combination
of stuff.
So I have to everyone with me like let's
just put this together like what kind of
thing do we get?
Here's what we get. Let's walk through
it.
So I take the stuff I get from the
previous layer, my H.
I know I'm going to have a residual
block. So residual.
I know I should pre-normalize.
That was a design thing we told you
before. So I put a norm.
Now I want the learned inner product
between me and the other guys, my
neighboring information.
How do I learn inner product? I make
learnable matrices that multiply this
stuff and I take the inner product.
Everyone with me? Just like literally
drawing out the idea design decisions
we've made in a graph.
>> Yeah.
>> Ah, so I want a bunch of inner products.
>> So I'm just doing this over and over
again.
Okay. So these this these are my S's my
scores right my scores are coming here
then I softmax them to get probabilities
I'll write the S for the scores from
before
so now I want to run into an expectation
that takes probabilities on one side and
have takes some kind of values on the
other side
up there. This is my
learned function
G
simplest learned function linear
function.
So I put a learnable linear function
here. I should use the same color I was
using before
for learnable things.
And now I get an expectation that
combines all these things. So now I've
got
this part of my general thing. Now I
want a general function. So what's my
general function? I stick something
everything into an MLP
with learnable weights.
So this reasoning comes from graph
neural net
just says I have to be permutation
invariant on neighbors. I can treat
myself se specially
and I choose to wrap everything in a
residual block because I learned that
lesson in resnets
and I'll put a normalization up out in
front somewhere because that's good
practice when I'm using ResNet.
Okay,
so this is the kind of thing that one
can do from the perspective of a
constraint.
I don't I can't do a con, but I want to
do something that lets me
take advantage of information on a
graph. And so the first place this kind
of stuff came up was in graph neural
nets because it's natural.
Okay. So, uh questions that people have
on what we're doing here. Yeah.
>> So, here we are updating like every node
based on the data, right?
>> Yes. And after we update your
boundaries, how are we going to um
define your positions with respect to
their new layers neighbors like?
>> Excellent question. The question was,
let me repeat it for the u recording.
The question was if we do this, we start
with a graph. The graph has a topology
of neighborhood. We then take
information inside the graph and we get
new information inside the graph at
every position.
Okay. Now the question is what do we do
about the graph topology?
And the answer is like a CNN we're going
to say the graph topology does not
change ever. It's always the same graph.
That's the style of operation we're
doing now. Okay? We're never changing
the graph topology.
Question.
>> Why don't we normalize our neighbors
when we pass?
>> Ah great question. Why don't we
normalize neighbors? We can. That's also
a choice.
I mean, the reason we're potentially not
normalizing the neighbors, we might want
to normalize the neighbors here or here
somewhere,
right? Is the inner products are not are
friendly
potentially to what's happening with uh
normalization. They don't care. Things
get bigger. That's okay. Potentially
softmax will scale everything back down.
It doesn't care if things are big. Cares
for other reasons, but not like very
much. Here we might want to normalize or
here. It doesn't matter where we do it
at some level. Um
because we do want to care we care if
the MLP gets gets hit in the right
place. So we might have to put a
normalization somewhere in front of it.
But that's like standard thinking.
There's nothing particularly graph
neural net or anything about. It's just
standard neural net thinking.
>> Yeah. My understanding is that the
output of this architecture is the
embedding for that node right
>> yes
>> how many times we are updating to get
the final embedding is
>> great question the question is if I'm
doing a graph neural net that I'm
talking basically about one block how
many blocks do we use in a residual
architecture and the answer is as many
as it takes to have things work without
making work working badly which is not
an answer okay just you try something
try small number of blocks, see if it
works. If it works, great. If it
doesn't, try adding more blocks. If it
works even worse, okay, probably need to
change something else. If it works
better, great. Is it still good enough?
No. Try adding more blocks. This is just
iterative refinement of neural
architecture. Um, same as a reset for a
con. There's nothing different about a
graph neural net and a connet in that
setup.
>> Yes, question.
>> You mentioned an inner product.
Practice. What inner product would we
use specifically?
>> Oh yeah. When I if I say inner product
and I don't tell you which one, it's
always uklidian inner product.
>> It's the easiest one. So you always do
that one.
>> Yeah.
>> I'm not sure if I miss like what
happened to like the spatial
information.
>> That's so we're undirected edges. So all
I know is that these are my neighbors.
I don't know where they are relative to
me. They're just my neighbors. That's
the whole problem.
So the fact that we don't know where
they are relative to me, the
undirectedness of the graph forces me to
be creative and to try to avoid this
over smoothing problem. So to avoid the
over smoothing problem, I need
nonlinearity
fundamentally because the whole problem
was the linearity of matrix
multiplication made just things become
averaging. So here I have to track
where's my nonlinearity.
Okay, so what's nonlinear here?
Uh because I'm almost out of time, I'll
just mark the nonlinear things for you.
Um
so here so there's nonlinearity inside
here
inside the MLP, but that's after the
combin combination of neighbor
information has already happened. So
that can't help me too much. Okay, with
this over smoothing problem by itself,
there's a nonlinearity inside the
softmax.
There's no nonlinearity here. There's
kind of a mild one of this
multiplication. So, it's mild nonlinear.
There's mild nonlinearity,
multiplication in the inner product.
And there's a normalization mildly
nonlinear.
So the important thing is there's
nonlinearity that's coming in this
process
which is I needed that to avoid the
problem. Yeah.
>> What do P and P signify again?
>> Sorry.
>> What do P and P? Oh, learnable matrix.
Learnable matrix. Learnable matrix
because I had to say I don't know what
to do. What do I do? Learnable matrix.
If this works, great. If not, I have to
make things more complicated. To make
them more complicated, I can make them
into, you know, MLPS or something.
Okay. So, uh I will continue talking. I
could stop here with graph neural nets
but um
I want to just tell you something this
approach here although it comes out
naturally in graph neural nets from
simply the constraint I don't there's
not much I can do because there's not
much I can do I have to be creative this
is a natural first thing this is called
this part here is called attention
mechanisms
Okay, this thing from here through here.
Okay, and they are very important in
transformers.
Here the motivation isn't a particular
desired functionality. It was oh my
goodness, I can't do anything,
right? What can I do? Right? It's just
it's a different way of looking at
attention coming from a different story.
When I we talk about attention um in the
transformer case, we'll talk about it
from a different angle of how you can
motivate it differently. But it's
important to understand that it also
comes out here. And so you'll see in the
literature many people will say a
transformer is just a graph neural net
except the graph is a complete graph.
That's all the undirected graph complete
graph gives rise to a transformer
from this picture. Okay. So that's a
historical uh kind of perspective.
But um next time I don't know I'll
decide the it turns out we can actually
solve this problem too. Okay. But maybe
I'll I'll do a little bit of that next
time. Um but that's cool for other
reasons. Okay. Office hours now.