We're going to continue. I have a couple
of announcements I want to make first.
So, uh, the main announcement I wrote up
there is we noticed that many students,
most students in the class have not
filled out the survey we, um, gave out.
It doesn't take that long, but we got
very useful responses from a small
number of students. We want to get from
everybody to see what people have to
say. So, we decided to do the thing that
many other classes do. We're kind of not
wanting to deal with this. Um, but we're
going to give everybody remember there's
the grading on this. There's no curve.
So, these 3% of points actually mean
something uh to everybody. Um, we'll
give it to everybody if 75% of the class
does the survey. Um, so please do the
survey. Encourage your friends to do the
survey. Uh, we just want to get
information uh from everybody to help
us. Uh, so the other announcement we
posted a couple of things on ED. I want
to make sure everyone's aware of them.
First, we uh said that we noticed that
the compute allocations, which we admit
our system is not the best because we
just have too little. But we noticed
that the little we did have wasn't
always being used. So lots of slots that
we' assigned to people weren't being
used. Um by so we decided to do is
remove the slot restriction. Um so you
go ahead and use it. Um if you find that
it's super busy or you can't get access
or it's not working then like post on
especially if you had that slot assigned
to you or something like you know post
on ed and say hey you know can you other
people get off I need to use it um kind
of thing but we we'd rather people use
the compute than not use the compute. So
we we've kind of removed that
restriction. Hopefully it'll work out
better for people who are using it. Um
the other announcement we made was we
know that we asked you for your draft
report to be submitted this Thursday.
The point of doing that is so that we
can quickly assign everyone to be a peer
reviewer and you can get your peer
review done over the weekend um before
Thanksgiving to give everyone else
feedback. So you can keep people can
keep working on their projects and get
get some useful feedback.
We've posted a description of what we're
expecting from the report and as well as
a link that can be used to submit the um
draft. We will we're adding everybody
there manually using the class upload.
So you should get an email. So if you're
if it's not working for you uh you know
tomorrow uh you know please you know
ping on it and we'll we'll we'll make
sure it's working.
So, um, hopefully everyone by now is
working very hard on their projects and
is seeing, oh no, the amount of stuff I
have to do is a lot more than what I
thought. And, uh, oh no, how am I going
to get this done? That was the intended
goal. So, it's fine. We expected this.
Uh, that's why we're asking for a draft
now and not the full final. So, tell
what you've done.
We expect to see a good good writing for
the parts which you we reasonably can
expect you to have done. stuff that
doesn't involve a training run and
descriptions of things. We expect you to
be able to do that. But we understand if
some training runs haven't finished,
you're waiting on some results.
Make a report that has what you can't
has what you have and then, you know,
hopefully you'll be able to get more of
it done ahead of the time of the final
um report submission.
So those are the announcements we wanted
to make. So our goal today is to
continue where we left off. And I would
like to because because I really want to
get to being able to teach you about
post- training of models. I want to try
to accelerate a little bit to get uh
into this uh the generative model stuff
today.
So um recall we were talking about uh
fine-tuning and adapting a model to a
new task. So we have these approaches.
So this is just recap. If your model is
promptable, one thing you can do is just
prompt it. Okay, this is the new thing
that was opened up by these large
language models and instruction tuning
and so on and in context learning. And I
want to reme remind you all practically
speaking, if you have information that
lets you use a prompt optimizer, you can
should use a prompt optimizer for your
task. No reason not to do that.
If you have a pre-trained model, you can
just use it as an embed or a feature
extractor. Remember this is how like
BERT was used uh and revolutionized NLP
and this strategy is called linear
probing if we haven't used this word
before because what you usually do is
you train uh you take them extract these
embeddings from the model and you train
a new task specific head for this task
and it's usually a linear thing you do
like a linear classifier or regression
things like this.
So
interestingly this works quite well in
many models uh even ones that are
promptable. Uh people have found that
doing a linear probe on the model can
perform better than a prompt uh for a
task and this is very interesting. Uh
larger models the disc discrepancy is
less but it it still exists. And there's
even more very interesting things that
people have found in this which is that
sometimes you can a model is doing quite
badly but a linear probe is doing very
well. Uh so the model in principle has
the information and the embeddings to be
able to disentangle things but it can't
do it uh in a prompted way.
Um advantage
it's pretty easy to do. You don't need
any data beyond the task you want to get
good at. Um and the disadvantage is this
sometimes doesn't work as well as a full
fine tune. So full fine tune I just
marked in green what you're tuning is
you take the model you have a task
specific uh head and you train
everything uh together on your data for
your new task.
Um so
again this tends to work better um on
new tasks. it can be a much much bigger
training job because your pre-trained
model might have lots and lots of
parameters in it and so this is a much
bigger thing to uh to fine-tune and as a
result it's harder to do the
hyperparameter search and everything
that you need to do to do a good job and
there's also a risk of overfitting.
We're going to talk more about this when
we talk about forgetting kind of a more
specific kind of overfitting that can
happen
but this is typically what people
compare to. We talked last time about
parameter efficient fine-tuning
approaches that can kind of are in
between uh these two by letting you use
Lauras and soft prompts and things like
this. If you want to you can think about
a soft prompt as being the flip version
of one.
Okay. So in one you treat the model as
an embed and you train a new thing at
the top. A soft prompt you can think of
as being flipped. you treat the top of
the model the same. You're going to use
the model's generative capacity to
generate answers, but you'll put
something at the bottom,
right, with the instructions, with the
soft instructions. Anyway, so this is
like recap. I wanted to hit some uh
practical tips here.
So, if you're going to do a full
fine-tune and your full fine-tune
requires you to have a new task specific
head, right, a classifier. there's new
categories for your classifier or you
know a regression that you want to do
that there's nothing you can start with.
Don't initialize for a full fine-tune
your head to some random parameters and
then do fine-tuning. This is not a good
way to do it. In general, you can do
better than this. So why is this not
good? The reason is that at the
beginning your head is initialized to
some random thing. It's not good at
doing its job at all. it doesn't know
what to look for. Uh when you do a full
fine-tune on that first few training
examples you give it, it's going to be
sending gradients through this head back
into the model. But these gradients
aren't very good because the head isn't
very good at doing what it's doing. And
so it's going to sort of throw random
noise into the pre-trained model and
move it around, shuffle it around. This
is generally not a good idea. Okay, this
is why this is not the practically best
way of doing this.
So a better choice is to initialize the
head to a linear thing after all to
zero. That way at the beginning it's not
throwing gradients back, right? Because
if this is zero, the gradients don't go
through. So at least the first few
examples have very little effect on the
model.
Everyone understand why this is a better
idea for how to initialize a head for a
full fine tune?
Okay, this of course is the context of
the head is for a new task. Like there's
nothing you can use for the head to
start it off. So even better than
initializing to zero is to do a
combination of this approach and this
approach. So what does that mean? Take
some of your data and just train ahead
first.
Okay, freeze the model. Now the head is
somewhat good at doing this task and now
do a full fine tune because now the
gradients are going to be better and
you'll get less damage to the u the
pre-trained model if you do it this way.
This is like a practical tip. There's
been theoretical work on this too, but
this is sort it it is practical. Any
questions on this basic stuff?
Okay, great.
So again you can do all this stuff and
take the spirit and combine it with uh
you know Laura as soft prompting that
should be clear to everybody. Yeah.
>> So the reason why initializing to zero
is a better idea is this is the head.
This is the final thing. So it's like a
linear classifier. So when you're doing
a linear classifier
typically you initialize it to zero like
you're doing if you're doing training an
SVM or anything you don't actually
initialize it to something random. So
for just from that point of view you
should think if you're just going to be
doing this you would have initialized
this probably to zero.
Okay does that is that that clear? The
reason people will sometimes just
initialize it to random is just used to
this deep learning kind of spirit.
They're like how do we initialize this
random but you have to remember right is
that really we justify random
initialization to you. The justification
we use said zero doesn't work but in
this case zero does work so you can do
it. Does that make it more clear? Okay.
Um yeah so this is like the universe of
things that one you know can tend to do
when one is fine-tuning a model for a
new task. So now last time we started
talking about metalarning which was to
say what if your goal was to make a
model better at being fine-tuned for
tasks.
So this is like categories two and three
up here. Okay
for for we're thinking of that about
that right now. We're going to switch to
thinking about category one in a little
bit, but I just in in for a short time
later, but I just want to think about
two and three right now. So last time we
said that well
one thing you can do for any you know
being fine tunable for a task you can do
nothing just have random initialization.
We're assuming that that uh you want to
beat that and it's possible to beat it.
You could have a general foundation
model that's just good at lots and lots
of tasks, not anything for the specific
task family that you're interested in.
And then the next thing that we're
talking about is this idea called MAML,
which is stands for model agnostic
metalarning, which is for the case where
you have a collection of tasks that you
think are related to each other and you
want to be good at fine-tuning within
this collection of task. Some of which
you don't actually have example
exemplars of. You have some examples and
you have some you don't have.
So to do this approach you need to
actually have training data. We talked
about this last time. So you have to
have some collection of tasks from this
family. And that means you need to have
you know training data and loss
functions that you could use.
You have to have some approach to doing
fine-tuning. For example three with a
Laura or just a full fine tune. We're
going to talk mostly from the
perspective of full fine tunes but you
should also think about Lauras as a a
choice.
and you have some approach to
evaluating. If you're gonna get if you
want to be able to get good at doing
something, you have to know if you've
gotten good at it. Okay, so that just
means some kind of hold out set, some
way of evaluating performance. So this
is all you need this to, you know, start
doing it. And so we closed last time
with these like two key insights that
I'm going to build out this time. And
one key insight behind MAML was to say
that in general for machine learning,
the default approach is if you're going
to be doing something at test time, you
should do something like it at train
time if you can.
Okay, you do what you're going to do at
testing, do it at training except make
sure you can take gradient steps, right?
That's kind of how we justified
everything. Then we said you could go
beyond, right, with certain
augmentations and things like this. But
the basic approach is do whatever you're
doing at test time, do that at training
time to get good at and you'll do it at
test time.
So that was one. And so
what the next thing is the other key
insight is to say that what you're going
to be doing at test time here, the goal
is to get good at learning a new task.
So at test time, you're going to be
learning a new task, which means you're
doing SGD steps and so on.
Everyone with me? So the insight was
that
doing SGD steps is like an RNN.
I'll make this much more clear in a bit.
And because we know we can train RNN's,
we can train this. Okay. So this is kind
of the
insight. So before I go into this, I
wanted to comment a little bit about
this that mammal was very important
intellectually for helping us understand
what was going on. And although in
practice today for many of these uh
approaches, one tends to be following
this general foundation model approach
as opposed to mammal, mammal had lots of
impact on the entire ecosystem. It could
be argued that the development of modern
libraries like Jax and then the updates
to PyTorch that came from competing with
Jax, a lot of this was prompted by the
need to be able to do things like mammal
which was very very clunky in old
PyTorch and old TensorFlow.
Okay, so had a huge effect on the
ecosystem.
Okay, so let me be precise about this.
So when I say we have a task,
I'm going to say that a task has some
training data. So task I has training
data associated with it. It has some
training loss associated with it and has
some test loss associated with it. Okay,
that's what it that's what we mean by a
task having an example of a task.
We have a whole bunch of these tasks,
whole family of these tasks and we have
a whole bunch of examples of this. We
want to train to do well on all tasks
from this family including held out
tasks. task that we will never see
during training is exactly modeling what
you do in machine learning generally.
So here there's a little note I want to
make. So let me just make this uh note
when I say collection of tasks there
they can be of different types just
related to the same domain. So you could
have a classification task. You could
have a regression task. You could have a
classification task that is classifying
into you know cats and dogs. You could
have a different classification task
that's classifying you know birds and
airplanes.
Okay. Somehow they're all related to
each other. So you can have different
such things. So
when you have tasks that don't share, if
all your tasks don't share what their
output looks like, then all of these
tasks you're going to tune by starting
with a head that's just zeros.
Okay? Because there's nothing there's
nothing you could already have to start
ahead with because every task is totally
different.
If however they do share some things
then you can have some kind of you could
hope for having a good initialization
for the head itself. So if many times
you're going to be looking for birds for
example there's like a bird score vector
that you probably want to initialize.
Everyone with me on what we're trying to
capture here. So this is very general
okay like there's many many different uh
tasks and so
yeah
>> so learnable is just the head.
>> So what we're going to be doing right
now is you think about we're doing a
full fine tune of a model for learning a
new task. So there's the shared part of
the model which we're always going to be
fine-tuning and there's also going to be
a head for the task. The task heads
across the different tasks may be
shared.
They have some shared commonalities to
them. Meaning that certain tasks might
be looking for the same kind of thing
like birds. In which case we want to
have a good initialization for the bird
score.
But other tasks we expect will be fresh
looking for a totally new thing that
you've never looked for before. And so
there's no way to have a good
initialization for that part of the head
which case we could initialize at zero.
Does that make sense? The goal is to
basically have a model that lets us
fine-tune it.
Well,
okay. So,
this is just an aside. From now on,
we're just going to you can think about
everything we do as if you want to, you
can either assume that we have all
shared heads, so there's only the model
with its weights, or every task is
totally different and we always start
with a zero head.
It's easier to think of it about it that
way, but nothing we're saying requires
that. You could have any kind of
complicated overlapping structure and
just learn the appropriate
initializations for those parts that are
overlapping.
Okay, so now we want to train like we
test. Okay, so suppose that we succeeded
in getting a good initialization. Let's
call it theta kn.
How do we use it for our new task? Okay,
let's be precise about this.
We'll start our model at theta 0.
We will then do gradient descent steps
using our task specific data and our
task specific training loss to get a new
set of parameters theta final. Everyone
with me? Then we will evaluate theta
final using some held out
d tilda and some test loss l tilda to
get a loss. That'll tell us how well we
do. Everyone good with this? I just want
to be very precise about what we're
doing at
uh when we when we when we finished
metalarning.
Any questions on this? This is standard.
This is like what you would do in your
in any ML class.
I'm giving you initialization. Train it
and see if you how well you did. That's
it.
Okay. So now,
>> yeah.
>> Ah, great. So, let me make me annotate
this for you.
This is
all
parameters
in the model. The entire par all the
parameters you're fine-tuning all the
learnable parameters. So all learnable
parameters.
Okay, that's what we're thinking about
here. Now for all these learnable
parameters of the model, if you include
a head, the head also has to be
initialized to something. So depending
on the setting, you can think of it as
always initialized to zero. Okay, every
task comes with its own task specific
head or all the tasks share the same
head structure. They're always going to
be classification among five classes.
Okay, then you could have a start with
something. Either way, it it just you
have we want is a way to start.
Okay, any questions on this? So when you
look at this as what you do, this looks
very different than we normally do in
machine learning. Okay, in machine
learning we have a standard form which
is we do this.
Okay, at test time this is what we do.
We have a model that has a parameter. We
feed an input into it.
We run to a loss layer with a y and it
gives us a real valued loss.
And then you train this using gradient
descent. Everyone with me? This is very
familiar. That does not look like this.
Does everyone see how one, two, and
three don't look like this?
We know how to do this.
So our strategy is we're going to force
one, two, and three to look like this.
And then we'll do this.
Everyone see the big picture of how you
think about things. It's like standard
way of thinking. I don't know how to do
something. I know how to do this.
I will try to fit this round peg into
this square hole.
Okay. And just see what I can do.
Okay. That's that's what we're trying to
do. That's why this is useful to teach.
It's a good way of thinking. Yeah.
>> So step two is doing
the final. Is that not
what we do?
We get a lot.
>> This is what we do machine learning all
the time.
>> Yeah. Yeah.
>> Okay. But um this is not test time.
>> Oh, I see.
>> Okay. This is what test time looks like
for us in machine learning all the time.
>> So I want to make this look like test
time. So just map it. Okay. Because this
is metalarning. What does that mean?
We're doing learning on our learning.
Okay. Okay. So, how do we do that is the
is what we're trying to do. Okay.
Everyone understand the kind of spirit
of what we're trying to do.
So, now I want you to take one minute,
talk to your neighbors and think
how do you how do you do this? So, you
know, like you have to figure out what
what's the X,
what's the Y, what's the loss layer, and
what's this box.
Okay, so take a minute, talk to your
neighbors, and see how would you force
it to be this.
Sorry.
I didn't realize
And then what is
the hopper in the bottle?
Wait,
that's the last layer.
That's true.
Okay. So, in the interest of time, I'm
going to stop everyone.
>> I'll come back together. Hopefully,
you've had a chance to think about it.
So, now let's like do it together. Um,
X has to be everything that runs through
your model. Okay, if it's going to run
through the operations of things you're
doing in one, two, and three, it's got
to be an X because that's the only thing
that runs through stuff is stuff in X.
Okay, so when you're running through the
model, what are you running? You're
running all of your training data D
through step two.
So X has to include D. You're also
running your held out data in step three
through your model. So you have to run
that too. So let's just like try to
write it out. Just just make make take
note of this. So it's all of D and it's
at least the X parts of three. X meaning
the inputs. We'll put the Y parts into
the loss.
Okay. So similarly
this is what your final evaluation looks
like. The only thing we use for the
final evaluation is the held out data.
So the only thing that's going into Y is
the label information in the held out
data
and it also of course includes the loss.
Okay, so that's the loss layer. So now
what do we know?
We know this stuff and we know this
stuff. However, this one still remains.
What does it mean to operate the model?
Everyone with me? So we want to match up
to 1 2 3. The output of 1 2 3 is the
output of the loss layer to get a final
loss. So now that let us get this.
Everything that's being fed into the
model has to be an X. So we've got that.
Now it's just the operation of the model
we have to deal with.
So for the operation of the model,
what we're going to do is we're just
going to look at what do we do step by
step. So
let's just what do you do? Okay,
we do training.
We start with theta kn.
We take theta kn and we do a forward and
backward pass on some permuted batch of
my training data.
The result of the forward and backward
pass is a gradient on the parameters
theta.
Everyone with me? We take the gradient,
we multiply it by a learning rate.
We then take the parameters and we add
the update.
This is an SGD step.
Okay. And then we do this again
to get theta 2.
And then we do it again
to get theta 3. And we keep going again
and again and again and again and again
through this until we've gone through
our training data.
Having gone through all these steps, we
have a final data. Does everyone see?
This is what we do to operate the model.
We do all this. Now, when you look at
this, you go, "Oh, this looks like an
RNN,
right? It's recurrent. You do the same
thing over and over again
except you have different inputs
uh also coming in to do it
and even has like a little residual
thing
on it.
Everyone sees this is what you're doing.
Great. So we do all this but this isn't
we're not done yet.
We then take the final thing
and we feed in
just do a forward pass up. There's all
forward and backward passes. This is
just a straightforward pass through our
network using the parameters theta final
and the held out data detailed x and
that gives us a final label or output
of our model which we then feed into the
loss layer.
So
that box of operating the model theta kn
means all of this.
>> Okay. So questions.
>> Yeah.
>> Are we just learning the initialization
in this setup?
>> Our only goal in metalarning is to learn
the initialization weights because our
goal is to have initialization weights
that will be good for fine-tuning.
We want a fine-tunable model. That's our
only objective, a fine-tunable model. We
don't care about what the fine-tunable
model by itself does. We just want to
know that it can be fine-tuned to do
what we want.
So
the insight was you look at this is a
deep model. You can backrop through it.
Now when you look at a model like this
and you look at the back prop through
it, you can be concerned
about this backdrop because you look at
this backdrop and you say, well, you
know, the the gradients are definitely
going to pass back through. Notice how
they're going to go through these skips.
They're going to go through all of the
layers nicely. They'll go back to the
beginning for sure.
Everyone will send a gradient back to
the beginning. Uh, so there's definitely
gradients flowing through here, but
there's nothing in this that's stopping
them from exploding.
Okay,
did you see that? Like there's nothing
there's no normalization type thing
sitting in here that's going to stop
these from exploding.
So there's a little bit of a risk of
what might happen.
Second thing you should notice is that
like for training an RNN
to do this you have to hold all of these
activations for doing back prop. So you
have to hold the activations that
correspond to the forward and backward
pass
here and the forward and backward pass
here. So your model you're building a
lot there's a lot of memory as you roll
out this learning process for a while.
Okay, so that's another thing. You could
run out of memory, but these are
details. You can deal with all of them
by taking fewer steps.
Okay.
>> Yeah.
>> What is the pi subscript?
>> Oh, the pi just mark it for you
by
permutation
of training data.
usual thing you run through your data
you permute it in some order randomly.
Okay,
so
all of this stuff when you take a
gradient through all of this what you
end up with is a gradient on this.
That's the gradient you care about. You
don't care about the gradients it's
generating along the way. There's no
learnable parameters along the way. The
only learnable parameters are theta kn.
So gradients go all the way back to
theta kn.
Everyone fine with this?
So
having a gradient on theta kn I can take
a step in that direction for a better
initial condition.
Right? Usual approach in machine
learning in deep learning. I want to get
better at something. I look at what the
gradient, which direction the gradient
points me. I take a step in that
direction and I hope this is better. And
I keep doing this.
So I did this for one task. I can repeat
it for a new task. So I have a
collection of tasks I'm learning from.
So I pick one task, I do this, I get a
gradient. I take a different task, I do
this, I get another gradient. If I want
to, I can take a step with batch size
one. Or I could average together a bunch
of batches to get a combined average
gradient. take a step on that. All the
usual things.
But this is the the point of mammo is to
say that this is your default approach
based on everything you've learned of
how you would get good at metalarning.
So just understanding this and unpacking
this insight was very useful for people.
Okay. So is this does this work? It
works in the same sense that you hope
everything works. You hope gradient
descent gets you to a better place. Same
thing applies here.
Okay. So to help you understand this,
I'm going to just do a schematic
picture. Same picture, but it's kind of
done in a more schematic style. So the
way to think about it is that for
mammal, there's an outer loop that's on
tasks
and that has associated with some
learning rate ADA out. That ADA out
outer is the learning rate that's
modulating how well how much you add of
this into your grade into your updates.
You have an inner loop on batches and
examples for a specific task. That inner
loop has its own learning rate, an inner
learning rate. So there's two learning
rates associated with this. An outer
learning rate, which is the one that
you're going to use to actually make
updates, and an inner learning rate just
to do tentative updates. So to draw this
out in a picture for you all,
I'll just made a little picture. Okay,
so this is a little picture.
So
in the outer iterations, we're going to
iterate over tasks.
We'll try task one, two, three. Now this
is the when I say the third task, it
doesn't mean the third task in my
collection. It means the third task I
chose to iterate on. So this is like
draw sampling with replacement
tasks, right? I just keep sampling them
with replacement
and I up I start at a initial condition
for my initial condition which could be
like Xavier initialized for my model or
it could be some pre-trained model based
on some other set of data that I'm
fine-tuning to be good at metalarning
for a family of tasks. Whatever it is, I
start with some initial condition. Then
I take gradient steps on the initial
condition down this way
until I get to my final initial
condition.
However, to get these gradient steps,
what I do is I do inner iterations where
I take for task one, I do I make an
initialization based on theta 0. So this
could be for example initializing the
head to zero. It could be initializing
the head for the overlapping segments
based on whatever the specific case is.
And then I take gradient steps based on
the training examples for that task.
I get a loss at the end on held out data
for that task
that gives me a real number. This allows
me to comput a gradient back onto this
initial condition. That gradient applies
then here. Okay, there's like a picture
of what's going on in mammal.
Any questions on this picture?
It's not a complicated idea
um by itself. It's just taking ideas
that you've seen before and connecting
them except one level lifted up.
And so, as I mentioned before, being
able to implement this uh really mucked
up uh old style PyTorch and TensorFlow
because old style PyTorch and TensorFlow
assumed that this thing would sort of be
frozen. But now we want to like take
gradients, hold those activations, take
the gradients through it, and then apply
another loop. And so that prompted the
development of lots of tools and and re
refactoring of how PyTorch and
TensorFlow worked caused the creation of
jacks uh to make this kind of stuff
easier to do. Then those ideas were
backported basically into PyTorch and
TensorFlow.
Okay.
So what I want to now you understand u
basic mammal I want to
talk about two variants of this idea and
I want to encourage yeah go ahead
>> question
like the loss you take on the parameters
it's only depend on the held out data
>> great question so
this loss that we take is on the heldout
data for this task. How do I get the
held out data for the task? As I
mentioned before, in many cases, there's
a limit to how far out we can roll this
thing out based on memory restrictions
on we can train.
And so we might have a lot of training
data for that task actually. And so
there's only a limited amount we can use
in this batch. And so we can choose to
generate our own heldout set from that
batch of training data. as an example.
And when that we revisit that same task
again, we might draw a new batch of
training data and a new batch of held
out data. When we revisit that same task
later on this these sets of iterations,
the memory is restricting us in this
direction, right? There's no memory
restriction on this direction because
that's just iterations.
So this should remind you of some
things. This should remind you of
this direction is like context length in
a language model where you have to train
on you have to hold the entire context
length and do all this stuff on the
context. Okay. So if you reflect on what
we're talking about in mamml, it
provides a very useful lens to help you
also think about
what is going on in the training of a
language model that you know is going to
do ICL. What's ICL? In context learning
is some kind of learning.
It's like gradient steps.
So the development of incontext learning
capabilities in language models has a
vague parallel to what's happening here.
Okay. But I want to make sure you
understand this. That way you can use it
to understand other things too.
So comments everything here has to be
differentiable. So if your task comes
with a held out loss that's not
differentiable, too bad. Switch to one
that is um for that job. It doesn't have
to be the same as your training loss,
but it has to be something
differentiable. So you can take a
gradient through it. If you can't take a
gradient, if you really want to say, I
want this loss and I can't differentiate
it, then you can do the RL type tricks
that we showed you in the homework,
right? If I have a non-ifferiable loss,
what do you do to make it still have a
gradient to train on? You can do those
tricks. In fact, the first development
of mammal was in the context of being
able to do those RL tricks. But later
people understood that those are not a
core part of what's required here.
>> Yeah.
>> Like the meta learning the main idea
here is that the visualization is a set
of parameters that can make us like
learn something really useful in the
end.
>> Yes. But um so what about like
computerization
is also like a set of parameters that
can make make things like learn learn
faster.
>> Great question. So the question was
repeating for the recording the question
was the goal of mammal we said was to
have a initialization that helps us
learn well. Um however
is this also initialization that helps
us learn fast right what does it mean to
learn well learning well could be I
converge to a good place at the end
could also mean I converge to a good
place faster so definitely in mammal
because you might have a limit on how
far out you can go based on your memory
uh in a sense you are encouraging it to
learn fast
um because the you're only taking steps
on fast learnings on basically few shot
learnings. So you're making it even
though you say you're making something
that's a good metalarner you're actually
training it to be a good fot learner
which means you're training it to
converge fast initialization that will
converge fast to a good place.
So I'll talk about I'll I'll discuss a
variant in a bit that will try to move
away from that. Yeah,
>> I'm like a bit confused. This like inner
iteration is this like fine tuning or in
context learning like how would you
descri
>> this is a fine tune that's running. Um
it's just we have to hold the whole
thing in memory.
Uh so we're doing a fine tune where
we're holding everything in memory and
we're passing a gradient then at the end
back to update the weights.
Okay. So I was making the connection for
you that this is
this is also few shot limited in how
much stuff you can put. So it feels at a
high level related to what you're doing
in a language model where you're
learning from using context.
>> So this is like context
in in many ways.
This helps you understand what might be
happening.
Okay. So a comment was just brought up
is this is actually because there might
be memory limitations or exploiting
gradient problems that makes you not be
able to take too many steps. Uh you're
actually implicitly saying hey learn
fast. So is there anything we can do
about that?
And so the first variant I want to talk
to is the humorously named reptile which
is literally named because it's more
primitive than mammal.
um which says can I avoid having to do
back prop through back prop because
remember each of these steps is back
prop and we're doing back prop through
backdrop so that's what had that's why
we had to hold all this activation all
this state around
and the answer is yes you can and the
approach in mammal in reptile is very
simple what reptile says is to
approximate the gradient So what it does
is it approximates the gradient.
Right? So the gradient is computed by
taking back prop through the whole
thing. But one approximation for the
gradient is to say look remember let me
go back the picture. I wish I could hold
everything on the this is where I'm
missing having a bigger board and using
it. So remember this is what we're
backing through is this thing. Notice
all the residual connections.
Okay.
So at some level if I want to
approximate the gradient
one approximation for the gradient is
just the gradient is saying what
direction do I wish theta knot moves.
Okay that's what a gradient is telling
me. Well, one approximation is where did
I actually move?
I moved to theta final. That was
presumably what I wanted to do.
And so one approximation is just theta
final minus theta kn.
Does everyone see that? Like what
direction do I want to move? Where did
you move?
Right? They're related, right?
And so I can approximate the gradient
with theta final minus theta.
This is within this is within one of
these horizontal segments.
So because with this approximation I
have the direction of the gradient.
Okay,
approximately
I'm not going to take a step in that
with that side. That would just be going
to theta final. I'm not going to do that
because I don't do that in gradient
descent. How big of a step do I take? I
take a step that's small in the
direction of the gradient. So I take a a
direction that's this thing small. I
have a learning rate. I don't go
straight. So this is different than
simply training the model on all the
tasks one after the other. If I train
the model on all the tasks one at the
other one after the other I would just
take this final thing
and move it to here.
Does everyone see that? That would be
training the model on all the tasks one
after the other. We don't do that.
Instead we just say from here I would go
to here in this direction. I'll take a
small step in that direction and that'll
be my update.
And what's the idea? The idea in a
reptile is to say that this approximates
the gradient but has a huge
computational savings because now I
don't have to save all the activations.
I can just run the RNN forward as many
steps as I want.
It also makes it easier to use other
optimizers
because I can, you know, it's easier to
take the gradients through anything now.
I can do whatever I want. roll out as
far as I want, do whatever I want, find
a final spot, and look at what direction
that was pointing me in and just move a
little bit in that direction. And the
idea is that every task,
the intuition is every task has two
things it might want. It might want to
move to a better thing for this task,
but also a better general position. So
by taking little steps, I'm going to
average out the things that are task
specific and just get a drift in the
direction of generally better.
and that'll move me to a better initial
condition. So, reptile
worked pretty well and in many cases it
would work as well as mammal um even
with limited rollouts but with extended
rollouts would work even better. So,
that's an approach that one can do.
Yeah,
>> I don't see how in reptile how the final
loss factors into that or does it at
all?
>> Ah, great question. Yes, in reptile you
ignore the final loss.
So then in that sense why not just like
why are you looking at the final why not
look at any of the intermediate like and
any of the intermediate steps also.
>> Uh great question. So the question was
why not look at any of the intermediate
steps and the idea is you look at the
final one because you expect there to be
some meandering from the randomness in
the batch and it's kind of all averaging
together. So you might as well look at
the final one as the net result of all
of that. And if you wanted to do
something different about that
averaging, the reptile approach would be
build it into your optimizer for inner
task.
See where you want to end up and just
use a small step in that direction to
approximate a better initial condition.
Okay. Yeah, great great points.
So this is very interesting. And now
another approach all everything I'm
doing with reptile and mammal was all
about uh the case where we're going to
do a full fine-tune.
So the natural question is if you wanted
to optimize a model using this kind of
thinking except not for a full fine tune
but just for being a good embedder.
How would you do it? Does everyone see
this? It's like just I want the same
approach of metalarning except not for
full fine tunes but for linear probe
and this is a a family of papers called
u anil meta optnet and r2d2 I don't I
forgot what these things stand for which
is basically optimizing for this thing
but here's the core idea and the papers
are more complicated but the core idea
is pretty simple
core idea says look
this is the thing that we're going to be
doing. Okay,
I'm putting both in green because we're
we want to learn new weights for this in
our metalarning. So metalarning, we want
to learn new weights for this is our
goal.
But how do we do it? So to understand
it, it's easiest to think about
regression problems. Okay, so let's
think about regression problems first.
So if we're doing a regression problem
with le squares or ridge regression, we
actually have a closed form formula for
the head.
Everyone remember we just like this is a
frozen feature extractor. It's just
vectors. We can then run those vectors
into a closed form formula to get the
head.
Any questions on that?
Great. that closed form formula is
differentiable,
right? There's nothing in that closed
form formula that's not differentiable.
So
you can just take a step, you take the
task, but instead of doing a whole bunch
of gradient steps, you just
do one formula. So everything up here,
you don't have to do gradient descent.
You just collect the data, do a formula.
That formula will then push gradients
back on its inputs.
Okay, having gradients on its inputs
means you get gradients on this
and you can take a step through that.
So
this works for regression problems
because you have a closed form formula.
Everyone good with that?
What about classification problems?
The key insight behind this approach is
to say that anytimes anytime your
problem is such that you can use a
convex optimizer,
you can do all kinds of tricks with that
convex optimizer to make it run pretty
fast. For example, you can do things
like Newton's method and so on on it. By
doing that, you can take a few steps in
your convex optimizer to get the
solution. That's why context problems
are so much faster to you do practically
than training a deep network, right? You
just have more stuff you can do and many
classification problems like SPMs,
right? In 127 you teach about SPMs,
right? So in 127 you saw how you can
cast an SPM as a a convex problem and
can solve it. So it turns out those
steps are also differentiable and you
can get for classification type problems
a counterpart to this differentiating
through this closed form formula that's
fast
and doesn't have this instability
problem. Yeah,
>> I think I'm a little confused because I
thought for linear probing like the the
parameters of the model constant.
>> Okay, excellent. So in linear probing
the parameters of this thing stay
constant. Our job is to make a good
model for linear probing. So now we want
to learn what to do here such that it is
good for linear probing on a variety of
tasks.
And because we're doing linear probing,
because we're doing linear probing,
those linear things can be optimized
taking advantage of their convexity of
the classical machine learning
algorithms.
Okay? And specifically doing things
like, oh, I'll take a few Newton steps
to solve it. Has have any of you played
with this where you try to do like
logistic regression, solving logistic
regression with a few Newton steps? Did
you guys have to do this in 189? I don't
know if you were made to do it. do a do
a few Newton steps for a logistic
regression. See how fast it converges
relative to gradient descent. Have you
done any of these comparisons of
something smarter relative to gradient
descent and it works much faster in a
convex problem? That okay that's what we
can exploit here. So this is another
approach uh to metalarning
that is for linear probes. So there's
lots of these things that people have
done
is the important thing about this is
more for your learning and
understanding. We'll give you a homework
problem on metalarning so you can watch
it work uh for a handcrafted example um
and you can see how it learns features
this way that are useful.
Okay. So yes.
So I guess so for the second item is
we're is that the idea that we're we're
just sort of
like are we just learning the head in
like a closed form fashion like more
efficiently
given that it's like a specific like
linear or like classifier or something
is what I what I'm missing is maybe like
the
where the the benefit is like coming
from over like is it just because the
gradients are kind of messy if you have
to pass through the whole model
Okay, so it's very important to
understand what we're trying to do.
Okay,
we want to make a model. Here's the
question. We're trying to make a model
that's good for linear probing.
So, we're going to have to adjust the
weights in here. That's a given. The
question is, how are we going to get
gradients to adjust this weight?
In the mammal approach, the way you got
those gradients was that you did full
fine-tunes on that, looked at that as an
RNN, and then passed gradients back
through that. In reptile, you did a full
fine-tune, you took gradient steps, and
you looked at the last point as the
default for where you would end up and
computed an approximate gradient and
then took a small step in that
direction. Here, we're not doing a full
fine tune. We're just the way we're
going to use it at test time is a linear
probe.
So because we're going to doing a doing
a linear probe at test time, we can just
solve the linear probe problem using
closed form at fake test time, which is
training time. So instead of doing
these steps here,
we just take the training data, run it
through our feature extractor in
parallel
and apply le squares.
So we don't have to do all of this.
There's no step by stepping. There's
just in parallel computation of features
and then the application of the le
squares formula.
>> So it's it's just a way to extract
gradients without having to actually
forward and backass the model itself.
>> We're going to have to forward and back
pass the model. We can get around that.
But what we're going to do is we're not
going to do a bunch of iterative updates
like this. We're going to get a gradient
for the entire task in one pump
because we'll we'll forward pass through
the model lots of forward passes through
the model in parallel. Now we have a
bunch of
numbers you know a bunch of vectors we
run them through le squares as a box. Le
squares is a box. Le squares will give a
prediction. That prediction we can you
run on held out data.
We can now run gradients back through
this model. So they go back through the
le squares flow to all of these parallel
instantiations of the model.
The key point is they can pass through
le squares
instead of having to go down an RNN. Le
squares is very stable with these
gradients. You can do it lot in
parallel. There's no recurrence.
So you can roll out as much as you want.
Run it through le squares pop out get
gradients to everything. compute now
gradients pass passing through these
weight the weight shared model and do an
update.
So it's just replacing
this step with something else. Instead
of doing this, you do le squares.
You still have to run gradients through
the model.
>> Yeah.
>> Yeah. So the main idea here is just to
make that inner learning loop more
compact and more efficient.
>> Yes. The inner learning loop is more
compact and efficient and stable.
It inherits all the nice very very nice
stability properties. So uh and again
you don't have a memory restriction. So
from a from a memory point of view uh
you have to be able to hold the features
but you can do remember we gave you this
problem on uh gradient checkpointing and
recomputation of gradients. Remember
that homework problem everyone?
So wait, do you remember this homework
problem? We gave you this homework
problem, right?
Where we said suppose you couldn't
actually store all the activations and
the gradients. What if you just
checkpointed the activations at every
fifth layer and then you had the
gradients at the end and then to backrop
it, you recomputee the activations that
you need and then you can backrop and
then you recomputee the activations.
Then you backrop then you recomputee the
activations and back prop. Remember that
homework problem that okay so here
you don't have to hold everything in
memory you can just
compute run forward one pass through
forward pass through your model
compute a bunch of features now run le
squares now back prop through that back
prop through le squares now you have
gradients on all of these
outputs of these models now rerun
forward passes back props individually
on the on that.
Okay, so it's very efficient and you
very nicely paralyzable. It just works.
You know, there's no exploding gradient
problems. It's just much nicer uh to
work with.
So for linear probes, you can do this
kind of stuff. And it's useful again to
keep these in your mind as you're
understanding things like in context
learning and stuff.
Okay, so that's all I wanted to say
about metalarning. I want to like move
on ahead to talk about a very important
concept. This is going to be talked
about more in discussion. So, but I want
to make sure you know about the concept
and then you'll see it more in
discussion. I think many of your
projects are engaging with this stuff
anyway. Lots of people's projects are
touching this problem. But so people
know observed the following phenomena.
This was first uh observed by people
when they were taking models and
continuously retraining them
uh for tasks as they saw them in the
field. What they experienced was that
when fine-tuning a model,
the model used to know how to do
something
after fine-tuning on other stuff, it
forgets how to do what it knew how to
do.
It got good at the new task but it
forgot how to do old tasks it knew how
to do. This is an empirical observation
that people had. This happens
and it was confusing to people because
they were like this other task there was
no interference. This this the task is
very different. Why is it not
remembering how to do this other task it
used to know how to do? And so people
ask the question of okay why is this
happening and what can we do about it?
Okay so everyone kind of understand the
idea of what this is. So one perspective
on this for finetuning is to say this is
not a problem. So let's we have to
acknowledge that this is not a problem
perspective before talking about the why
is it a problem. The not a problem
perspective says well I'm fine-tuning my
model for a new task. I only care about
the new task. If it can't do something
it used to be able to do, I don't care.
I'm not interested in that task. I'm
interested in this task. All I care is
how good is it at this task. If it gets
other things, fine, let it. Does
everyone see this?
Very reasonable point of view. Um,
and
there's a problem. Uh the problem is
that
sometimes the kind of thing you're
fine-tuning for is pretty broad
and
this is particularly the case with
modern language models. Um so you have a
language model that you've pre-trained
on lots of data so it can do all kinds
of things.
And then in real language models people
will run post-training. We'll talk about
post- training. I told you one example
of it which is I said hey we want to
make it follow instructions.
So we postrain it. We find fine-tune it
by saying
here are some examples of instruction
following. Okay. So what we wanted to
pick up from this is how to follow
instructions.
Everyone with me? So before it could for
example complete a poem about unicorns,
right? It could complete a poem about
nuclear fusion, also complete a poem
about making meth. Okay, then we
postrain it. Okay, and the examples we
give it aren't going to be examples of
making poems about everything. We just
want it to know that when I tell you to
make a poem, make a poem. Don't make me
give you the beginning of the poem and
complete it. Okay? So, I give it
instruction following examples. a
thousand or 10,000 examples is enough.
Empirically, people found
now I want it now to be able to
instruction follow all the things it
used to know how to do. Everyone with
me?
But this can happen
which means that now because I fine-tune
it to follow instructions, the simple
act of doing this fine-tuning made it
forget a bunch of other things it used
to know. That's not good.
Okay, so that's an example of it being
bad. The other example which is very
practical is you want the model to not
be offensive or dangerous. So you don't
want to give a formula for making meth
or a poem about making me math. Okay. So
you do alignment tuning and what people
observed is that when you did alignment
tuning on the models with kind of fine
tuning, the models became dumber
on things that had nothing to do with
unsafe behavior.
Okay, so it's not like it became dumber
because it couldn't do this unsafe
things are completely unrelated,
degraded.
So catastrophic forgetting is a real
problem. And uh when you have this idea
that the task you want to actually
fine-tune for should potentially be able
to access all kinds of other abilities
that might be required, but I don't want
to give all those as examples.
Everyone good with that? Okay, so I'm
watching the time.
So I will just jump and make sure you
understand the key practical solution.
What is the standard solution to this
problem? The default, if you can do it,
do this.
The default is that while you're
fine-tuning, don't just fine-tune.
Add a mix 10% some amount of
pre-training style data.
It could be actual data from the same
distribution that you did for
pre-training. Whatever it is that gave
the model the capabilities it had in the
first place.
Mix in some of that
while you're training. So as you adapt
the weights, make sure you don't lose
the capabilities it already had.
Everyone clear with this as an idea? So
this should be done if you can do it.
When can't you do it? You can't do it
when you don't have access to
pre-training style data.
So there are techniques and you'll see
one of them in the discussion
of how you could try to get around this
problem of not having pre-train
pre-training style data uh and you know
use that for uh doing the finetune to
try to avoid this catastrophic
forgetting problem. The discussion will
talk more about this including some nice
visualizations of why this can happen.
Um I wanted to sort of just give you
a potentially useful analogy.
So, Halloween just happened uh little
while ago and have any of you seen those
costumes that are like have powered like
air blowers? Have you seen those?
Anyone? Raise your hand if you've seen
these kind of costumes that have powered
air blowers. Okay, so many of you have
not. So think about a costume in which
you have air that's f like puffing it up
and filling out this air structure.
Okay,
you can think about machine learning as
being like blowing up a balloon, but
it's a leaky balloon. Okay, the data is
the air that's blowing in and the loss
and weight decay is like these leaks
that are making stuff go away. you train
your models with weight decay. And so
one intuition you could have is that if
you stop puffing air into this arm and
start puffing it into this arm only,
this arm is slowly going to go,
you know, like all the air will leave.
That is a kind of very coarse view of
what causes catastrophic forgetting.
Unless you have enough pressure from the
data, keeping the model kind of in
different directions, it'll degrade.
Now, that isn't exactly correct because
just turning off weight decay won't stop
the problem. So, if you want to
understand the next level of detail, you
can think of it this way. Your models
are never sparse,
right? They're never sparse in the
native weights. It's never that this
weight, this particular weight is
controlling this particular attribute.
It's always some vector,
right? And so the gradients are all in a
way on the task you want are throwing
random gradient noise in other
directions.
The pressure of data is keeping that
back pushing it back to converge to the
right thing. But without the
counterbalancing pressure of task data,
you'll just drift randomly in these
other directions and you'll lose
capabilities.
This is like pictures of how you think
why this happens. Yeah.
>> Does this also happen in the same way
with Laura when you're keeping all the
underlying but add?
>> Great question. So the question was what
about Lauras? And Lauras in fact suffer
less from catastrophic forgetting. They
still do, but it's less. And the reason
is that a lot of weights are effect a
lot of directions are effectively frozen
um by doing the how you're doing the
Laura. And so you have less ability to
sort of muck up uh certain uh certain
directions. Second is weight decay in
Laura is moving you towards the
pre-trained weights
and not to zero. So that's also helping
you not forget. So Lauras are are better
from the perspective of catastrophic
healing. They're not completely immune
from it though
um because they still have this gradient
in they still have this drift uh that
can happen within the dimensions that
are there if they can influence that
feature that that attribute. Okay. So
you can read more about this is very
important practically lots of little
tips and tricks that people have but um
I want to move on to the next thing.
So I want to talk about generative
models because I want to get to VAES a
little bit.
So
very briefly you've already seen a basic
kind of generative model which is these
auto reggressive generation models. We
talked about them a lot. I don't want to
um
belabor that. So when you think about
generative models as we talk about them
in the class we'll think about them in
two different categories.
one unconditional generation which is we
have a model we would like to draw a new
example that's it there's a model we
want a new example we feed randomness
into the model and we get a new example
this is interesting to study and useful
to understand less useful in practice
conditional generation is more useful in
practice conditional generation is I
want to sample from a conditional
distribution
so I have randomness and I have
conditioning and then I get a new
example that's distribution. So for
example, this would be give me a new
cat. Give me a natural image of a cat.
Everyone see this? That's like just
generative models generally. We'll talk
about this, but this is what's useful.
So
interestingly, it's useful to understand
approaches that don't work
first. So you should always try
something the most easy thing. If the
easy thing works, great. If the easy
thing doesn't work, you go to something
else. So it's good to understand the
easy things that don't work. I'm not
going to spend much time on it. I'll
come back to it next time because I want
to get a little bit into VAS. Um so one
approach is I use a classifier.
So classifier would go like this. I've
trained a classifier for cats
and now I would like to get a generation
of an image of a cat.
First way first try try of doing this is
I'll just draw a random image and I'll
ask is it a cat? If it's not a cat I'll
draw another random image. Does everyone
see why this is not going to work very
well?
Because most random images will be
random hiss. They will not be cats. They
will never be cats. Right? You will run
this till the end of the universe and
then you'll get one cat. Right? So that
won't work. So you say fine, but I this
thing is differentiable.
So I'll draw a random place and then
I'll do gradient ascent on the soft
prompt which is the image to make it be
a cat. Does everyone see that? like I'll
make it more cat-like because this is a
score, right? This also you' think it
worked. People really expected this to
work, but does not work. We'll talk more
about that later. So people say, okay,
you'll have to figure out in a way you
can think about diffusion models as
trying to solve that problem.
There's another approach which is I can
use an autoenccoder. So I just copy
stuff from how we talked about
autocoders before. So an autoenccoder I
want to draw samples from X. What can I
do? I can say fine X is too high
dimensional for me to sample. So I'll
make an autoenccoder. The autoenccoder
will take X drop it into a lower
dimensional space and then reconstruct
X.
So in a traditional perspective, I never
use the decoder. The decoder is just
there to train the encoder, which is a
good embeder. Everyone remember this?
But if this embedding is really
capturing the essence of what's
important in these images, I could just
try using the decoder to generate
samples.
So I train an autoenccoder.
I have a bottleneck and then I say
forget the encoder just feed in random
noise into the Z.
Can I get a sample of an image?
And the answer is this doesn't work
either.
Okay, I will talk more detail about why
this doesn't work um kind of in stages.
So practically speaking what happens if
you try doing this
is
if
Z too small
get
blurry
junk.
Okay. So
if you make Z too small D, too low
dimensional,
like one-dimensional, you'll get
something that looks like an image, but
it'll be like a grayscale gradient of
some kind. That's it. If you make it
like two-dimensional, you'll get like
some blob,
right? It won't be his,
but it will be like blob. It will not be
a cat, never a cat. And then you keep
increasing the dimension of Z and you'll
transition from blobby blobby blob blob
blob to hiss,
right? You'll never go you along the
path. You'll never be a cat. Okay.
Okay. Like randomly generating Z will
not give you something that looks like
an image. So
this brings in the idea of
why not like why isn't this working?
So the reason it's not working is that
all of the images that exist. So here
draw schematic picture
I'll draw it here.
This thing is all possible images
in here.
There's a very thin set
natural images
are tiny thin set in this vast space of
all images.
And this is called the manifold
hypothesis in machine learning. Lots of
natural data has this behavior that it
lives on a very thin set in a very large
embedding space. And the autoenccoder is
only fed things on this thin set.
But
if the dimensionality of the encoder, if
the Z the latent space is small relative
to the intrinsic dimensionality of
images, the m the manifold dimension,
then you'll get these things that are
blobby. They can't represent the
richness of an actual image. If the
dimensionality is bigger than dimension
of the manifold,
that's the thing, right?
In terms of volume, a piece of paper
occupies a tiny volume in
threedimensional space. That's the
problem with dimensions. That once you
go to a dimension that's higher,
the occupied
by this lower dimensional object is
zero.
And that's the problem. the instant you
get to Z to a larger dimension. Most of
the space in Z can't land on
this is a this is a onetoone mapping,
right? So this is not going to land on
something that makes sense here. And
there's nothing in training that's
forcing it to.
And so that's the problem. So you have
to deal with the problem that
this thing an autoenccoder during
training has nothing forcing it to try
to make be good at generation
generation.
And so it won't because the dimensions
won't match match up correctly.
So to do this one key idea to understand
is something called the variational
autoenccoder approach.
And
the first aspect of variational
autoenccoder approach is I want to use
this for generation.
Okay, which means I need to make at
generation time, I'm going to be have Z
be random.
And the general rule is if you're going
to be doing something at test time, you
should be doing it at training time.
General machine learning philosophy. So
if I want Z to be random at test time, Z
has to be random during training too.
Okay.
Now,
second thing, I'm going to be sampling Z
from some distribution.
I can't say I'm going to sample Z from
the distribution of images because I
don't have the distribution of images.
That's the whole problem. So, I have to
sample Z from some known distribution.
However, during autoenccoding training,
there's nothing that's controlling the
distribution of Z.
Z is just an intermediate to get to
Xhat. There's a loss on Xhat and X in
autoenccoding. So I need to add a loss
on the distribution of Z to make it
close to the distribution that I want to
sample from. Why? Because when I use the
decoder at generation time, I want to be
hitting it in a way that it was actually
trained and not with something that is
never seen during training at all,
completely alien.
Because if hit with something completely
alien, I'll get some random hiss out.
And then so those are my two main
ingredients but I have to also train it
which means it has to actually work with
SGD for training.
>> Yeah.
>> Yeah. So the main idea here is to let Z
land in that small manifold that we
specified.
>> So it's a good question. The question is
is the idea to make Z land in the
manifold? The answer is actually
different.
The answer is I want to make the decoder
D be robust to random noise in Z. So
that even if we don't land exactly where
we need to land, the decoder pulls us in
to where we need to be.
Whereas if we just have an autoenccoder,
there's nothing pressing the decoder to
do that. So I am out of time. Um, I'd
wanted to be able to talk more about
autoenccoders, but I will do that at
VAES next time. Um, we will
I will on Thursday I'll talk about it.
Discussion will not talk about uh VAEs.
Uh, but discussion will talk about
catastrophic forgetting.
>> You announced the survey.
>> Yeah, I announced the survey at the
beginning. Yeah. So, everyone please go
fill out the survey. Very important. So,
I have office hours now. I will uh take
questions on lecture and projects and
stuff.