Is this working? You can hear me? Yes.
Good. Okay, great. Okay, so today's
lecture is uh is pretty fun. I'm kind of
excited. We'll see how it goes. Um,
we're going to pick up where we left off
last time and we're going to continue
building out on trying to understand
optimizers and what optimizers are doing
and building to talking about this idea
of mu or uh maximum update
parameterization and what that what that
means. So the key problem that this MUP
idea is trying to solve is the idea that
look training models is really hard and
in particular training models can be
very expensive.
One key thing that is required to be
able to train models well is one needs
to be able to choose the appropriate
hyperparameters for the optimization
algorithm that is being used to train
the models. But searching for
hyperparameters and or searching over
hyperparameters to identify which is the
correct hyperparameter
is very very expensive like a training
run can be a million dollars right so
you can't really say like well let me
try with lambda equal to one and lambda
equal to two you know that's a big
that's a big deal so can we have
efficient ways by which we can select
the hyperparameters without having to do
a full training run on the full model
that we're going to be using and mu
brings a way of doing that of scaling
parameters from a smaller model to a uh
bigger model. So that's kind of what
we're going to be uh building towards
talking about. I was thinking maybe I
would get to muon uh the muon optimizer
today as well, but I'm probably only
going to be giving a sense of what it is
and then we will talk a little bit about
it in the in the following lecture.
Okay, any questions before I start?
Okay, good.
So last time we started with talking
about uh different matrix norms and we
were left with this question of what is
a good matrix norm to be thinking about
when we're doing deep learning. Right?
We observed that there is a natural
structure to deep learning problems in
that you have vectors that are your
inputs multiplied by matrices that are
your weight vectors. And when we think
about just all of our parameters put
into one big giant vector, for example,
as standard atom might do, we aren't
really taking into account the structure
of this problem, right? So we said well
there's maybe some advantage to thinking
about things in their true structure and
so we started looking at things we
started looking at matrices and then we
said okay can we formulate this
optimization problem in the context of
uh of matrices and we said what is the
right norm that we want to look at well
we remembered for example that Xavier
initialization brought in this one overd
kind of scaling right everyone remembers
that and that motivated last time for us
the idea of looking at the RMS or the
root mean square norm. Everyone remember
we talked about the RMS norm and you
should have seen it in discussion as
well. Okay, so this is familiar.
So we have this RMS to RMS norm for a
matrix and we're building off of the
induced matrix uh norm definition for
that and we did this last time. So just
writing it out here for your uh
to recap.
I don't know why this is showing up,
but basically when I'm looking at the
induced RMS to RMS norm, I'm saying if
my input vector has RMS norm at most
one, what is the maximum scaling that my
matrix can do in RMS norm to that
vector?
And the nice thing about this RMS norm
is that it's just essentially a scaled
version of our very, you know,
well-known two norm. So I can rewrite
this in terms of the two norms. These
are just constants and I can pull them
out and what I get here is the
optimization problem that is familiar to
me. And what is this quantity in the
pink box? This is just the spectral
norm, right? This is saying what is the
maximum scaling I can have for a vector
in the two norm sense. Everyone with me?
This is all recap revision. Everyone's
100% with me here. Right?
So what is important that I want you to
notice
is what has come into play here now by
naturally thinking about the RMS norm is
that the dimensions of the matrix have
kind of automatically shown up. Okay.
Everyone seeing this? So we wanted to be
able to take account of the structure of
the problem and the RMS norm you know we
it was motivated to us from Xavier
initialization but it's it's coming in
um naturally in a way that kind of we
would have expected from what we saw
with Xavier.
Okay, good.
The other thing we talked about last
time was the ha that we had this
optimizer recipe of sorts, right? where
we said okay let's look at this inner
product and we'll say
let's choose an appropriate norm and
let's choose how big we want to take a
step in that norm sense so we'll choose
this norm we'll choose this ADA and then
by solving this optimization problem
we're going to get an optimization
algorithm okay everyone remember that
this was kind of our recipe.
And when we think about choosing the
norm, well, the way to choose the norm
is to say, let's look at the problem.
Let's try to understand maybe something
about the geometry, something about the
structure. Maybe there's some properties
of the problem that can help us choose
that norm.
But what about ADA? Choice of ADA is
still a hyperparameter. We don't really
have necessarily a
way or a principled way that tells us
this is the ADA you should choose or
that is the ADA you should choose. the
way that we would choose ADA, I might
still be doing a hyperparameter sweep.
You know, how how how big are we willing
to make our normal?
Okay, but once we choose both of these
things, we basically are going to get an
optimizer. Everyone remember this
recipe? Okay, good.
So now, can we use this, you know,
induced RMS to RMS norm in our optimizer
recipe is a natural question that you
want to ask, right?
For example,
if we wanted to have some constraint
like the change in your RMS to RMS norm,
I'm just calling it RMS star over there,
is upper bounded by some gamma. And you
know last lecture we were calling these
gamas adas. Here I'm going to start uh
calling them gamma. You'll see why as I
proceed through the lecture because I
want to use ADA for something else.
Okay.
So here
we know that basically this is just a
scaling of this spectral norm and so I
can convert back and forth between these
two things.
But what I want to call out
is by thinking in terms of the RMS norm,
we've refocused our attention in a sense
on this singular hyperparameter gamma.
There's only one hyperparameter here
that we have to worry about. But if I
can focus on choosing this
hyperparameter gamma,
the nature of the RSMS norm
automatically is bringing in this D1
over D2, the dimensions of the matrix.
And so the specific geometry of the
specific layer comes into play just by
looking at this norm instead of looking
at say for example directly the spectral
norm. Okay. Okay, so it's a scaling, but
we're bringing in the dimensions of the
matrix. Okay, and the fan in and the fan
out. And how big is, you know, is is it
a big layer going to a small layer, a
small layer going to big layer, whatever
that is,
everyone see that?
Okay.
Okay. So this is good for us because if
you remember one of the things that we
were trying to do was we were trying to
say can we find a better optimizer. Our
idea for finding a better optimizer was
to say well maybe we should look at the
specifics of the geometry of each layer.
And just having one uniform step size
that operates across the entire
uh network might not be a good idea
because different step sizes might work
better for different layers. Right?
Now think about it. If you had if you
wanted to optimize a network and you
wanted to optimize your hyperparameters
to be good on a layerbylayer basis,
right? You have a different
hyperparameter for layer 1, different
one for layer two, a different one for
layer three. That hyperparameter search
has now suddenly got even more
complicated, right? It was already
complicated to begin with. Trying to do
it on a layerbylayer basis is even more
complicated.
So, we don't want to do that in general.
However,
if we can have some appropriate scaling
based on the geometry of the layer come
into play by the choice of norm that we
look at,
we can still maybe have a limited
you know limited search of
hyperparameter. We can only think about
searching over the hyperparameters gamma
but still get different effects in
different layers because of this d1 by
d2 scaling.
Does everyone see that?
questions.
Yeah. No. Okay. Good.
So, remember last time
we did one version of this problem
where we looked at specifically the
following, right? We looked at
Right? Right? We did this specifically
looking at the spectral norm
and what we got out was a simplified
version of the shampoo optimizer.
Everyone remember that where basically
we did this uh orthogonalization in some
sense we got out this UV transpose was
the optimal direction. Everyone remember
that?
Um,
so if I wanted to instead of the
spectral norm,
think about this RMS norm. Well, the RMS
norm is really just a scaled version
of the spectral norm, right? So when I'm
going to do my I'm going to solve this
optimization problem out, what I'm going
to get is going to be a very similar the
algebra is going to be very similar to
what I did for the calculation I did in
class last time. I'm not going to do it
out here right now. You can see
basically what's going to happen is that
all you're going to get is this scaling
factor kind of moving around in
different places. Okay.
what I'm not going to talk about in this
lecture but I will probably talk about
in the next lecture maybe if I have time
I can talk about it at the end of this
lecture I'm not I'm just not sure how
how much time we will end up having
this exact idea leads to what is now
called the muon optimizer okay
so let me tell you why the muon
optimizer is is important in a sense
This graph comes from uh Keller Jordan's
web page and Keller Jordan along with a
couple of other authors is uh the the
creator of of Muan. But what this shows
is on the x- axis basically uh time and
the y- axis is validation loss and
you're seeing how different optimizers
are behaving.
Adam is what you see in blue and what
you see in muon is it's massively
beating basically all of these other
optimizers um even these shampoo
variants. Okay, soap as I mentioned last
time is a variation of shampoo that is
specifically adapted for atom and uh as
is pointed out here soap can do better
but this is just a a kind of a rough
implementation of soap which is why it's
not performing as well as it uh as well
as it could but what I want to highlight
here is that the best one is muan
everyone see that okay
so muan uh has just had a tremend
tremendous tremendous impact in in the
industry.
This plot is a graph from what is called
the nano GPT
speedrun.
And this is basically a test bed that is
that has been developed for training a
uh specific model with a specific data
set. I think it's uh the fine web uh
fine web data set which is basically a
very clean version of the internet
and you're trying to figure out how to
minimize the training loss on a very
specific not that big model uh for for
this data set. And what started out in
the as the baseline this was uh
around 45 minutes. Okay. And then people
were optimizing, building on this,
building on this. And as you can see,
this is kind of the progression of how
uh
how long it took to get to a certain
validation loss level
for this particular nano GPT uh
benchmark. In a sense,
I want to call your attention to this
point. What happened here is the
introduction of the muon optimizer set
this new record
and boom suddenly there's like tweak
after tweak after tweak improvements on
this that have really uh changed how uh
people are thinking about optimization
and this got muon basically a lot of
attention from industry in terms of
changing how we're actually doing uh
optimization of these really large
models even at scale And so 2025
uh just February so this year actually
2025 is still here
um the Kimmy model was released and
Kimmy is now a trillion parameter model.
Okay, so it's one of the uh frontier
models developed out of I think the
moonshot AI lab in uh in China
and they published this paper saying
muon is scalable for LLM training. So
they took the core idea of muon and
identified that there are actually some
issues that come up when muon is uh used
in the context of uh attention blocks
and then there's some other issues that
come up with scaling with some of the
parameters becoming too small. They
introduced this idea called muon clip
which uh I'm not going to talk about. I
don't know maybe maybe we'll have time
to talk about maybe we won't have time
to talk time to talk about but the key
idea is that suddenly you can really
change the game in terms of you know how
much time and money is spent in terms of
scaling these models and so what the
work from Kim shows is that well you
know it's really nice to do this on some
nano GPT model which is tiny and you can
run on your in 45 minutes but to doing
this to doing this on a trillion
parameter model shows that these ideas
that we're talking about for the muon
optimizer, for the shampoo optimizer,
and for what I'm going to talk about in
terms of MUP are not just little like we
wanted to make a homework problem about
SVD because we love the SVD, but it
actually matters. Okay, you should also
love the SVD, but that's a separate
issue.
So I just want to make it clear that
there's a reason that we're spending so
much time on optimization and one of the
reasons we wanted to bring this is
because this is something that is
happening now. We wouldn't have been
able to maybe yeah this paper was not
out in the last year's last year's
version of this class. Right? So um it's
uh we're really trying to bring you to
this. Okay.
So these optimizers basically they're
they're great and there's a lot that we
can do with them. Muon is still
something that's being developed.
Shampoo is uh give me one second I'll
get to it. Shampoo
is also something that's really
interesting but as the point was brought
up someone last time really reminded us
that hey but you know shampoo
essentially requires you to compute the
SVD and that's really hard to do. So is
shampoo even efficient to to implement?
So turns out yeah shampoo can be
computationally expensive to implement.
So it's not something that's widely used
in practice. Muon solves that problem
and we will talk about how it's
implemented and how it's different uh
different next time.
But now let's say what we wanted to do
was we wanted to think about using the
ideas that we have developed so far but
focusing on something that we already
know how to do well which is sign SGD
and atom. Okay. So the next thing that I
want to talk about I'm going to pause
the discussion on muon. We're not going
to talk about it right now. But let's
say we want to bring those ideas to bear
in terms of thinking about Adam. Before
I go there I know there's a question at
the back.
>> So is the purpose of rescaling just to
distribute the computation power across
your entire network
layers equally? Is that what rescaling?
>> Okay good question. So um I think you're
talking about rescaling in terms of the
scaling the parameters right okay so I
will talk more about this but what I
when I talk about scaling of parameters
what I'm thinking of is I'm thinking of
I want to take a small let's say I want
to train some giant trillion parameter
model okay I don't want to do training
runs on this over and over again to
understand what the best hyperparameters
are so what I want to do is I want to
take a baby version of that model people
sometimes call this a proxy model and I
want to do a extensive hyperparameter
search on that baby proxy model
and then I want to oneshot transfer them
to the big model. I want to just say I
tune my hyperparameters here cheaply and
then I just use them there to get the
most performance. So I'm not trying to
do anything about computation in the in
terms of how the network is computing.
>> I see. So the in that you have the the
scale of the small proxy model and out.
>> No, no, D and D out has nothing to do
with the proxy model. Okay. Okay. Okay.
Okay. This is uh important
D in and D out here I'm are these are
just
the dimensions of this matrix A. The
reason I called them D in and D out is
that if I'm let's say I have um
you know ax
is equal to h and then x
belongs to rdn
and this belongs to r
right this is
your input is dimensional your output is
d outdimensional and so this aim here
I'm calling it a but I'm really think of
this as the w matrix my weight matrix in
my neural network. So this is what is
multiplying my uh input or my
activations.
This dout out has nothing to do with
proxy model, nothing to do with
parameter transfer.
Other questions?
Okay.
Yeah, I will talk about parameter
transfer uh soon, but we're just not
we're not there yet. I was just trying
to give you a I'll make it more clear
what we're talking about. I just want to
give you a big picture of why we're
doing what we're doing.
Okay. So, coming back,
let's take the following perspective. We
like Adam. Why? because well everyone
likes Adam or because uh there are nice
implementations in uh Python for this
already. We want to understand atom
and in fact we're going to think about
atom for the purposes of this lecture.
We're going to think about atom really
as just sin sd right because we want to
think about uh a simp simplified
perspective. A lot of these ideas will
extend uh directly to atom.
But I want to be intelligent about my
choice of step size when I'm doing sind.
Okay. I don't want to yeah I want to
just bring to bear everything I can in
and I want to do better at choosing this
ADA. Okay.
So can I do that by using somehow the
RMS norm or the fact that the RMS norm
brings in the natural geometry of the
problem into the calculations and the
optimization that you're doing. Okay, we
know that this RMS norm can do that. We
have this atom here and let's say we're
committed to using it. So can we just
improve the performance of atom is kind
of the perspective we want to take.
Everyone okay with the thing that we're
trying to do? Okay, we don't really know
what we're doing yet,
but we're just saying we like the RMS
norm, we like Adam. Let's try to bring
them together to understand if we can
better get a better step size for Adam.
Okay.
So let's say we want to do this for Adam
and we want to have an update for Adam
such that
we make sure that the RMS to RMS norm is
not too large. Okay.
So this is saying that the parameters
are changing the parameters on the of
the weights.
This is basically this is what this is
talking about. They're talking about
this delta w and this delta w remember
is just wt + 1 minus wt right it's the
change in w I haven't it's don't get
confused with the gradient and the delta
these are one is upside down of the
other
questions here on what we're trying to
do because if this setup is unclear then
like the rest is going to be more
confusing everyone good with this
okay Good.
So let's think about what's happening
with atom or sing really I should say
and let's consider a mini batch a tiny
batch just a batch one update. Okay.
So, first thing that I want to observe
is that
if I think about the gradient of the
loss with respect to my W,
if my batch size is one, then this
gradient is going to be low rank and
specifically it's going to be only rank
one.
Okay, why is this true?
This is true because for example you
know that for generalized linear models
in general you're you can only move you
can only take steps that are in the span
of the data right your gradient will
always take steps you're basically what
your the step that you're going to take
is going to be how how wrong are you
times your data
does everyone remember this
okay
so if If I only have one data point then
what I I have to move in the span of
that data point. So what is the
dimensionality of the step that I can
take? Well, I can only take a step in
that one direction in that one
dimension. Right? So the rank of this
gradient had better be one.
One thing that we can do if we have time
um I don't know that we will but if we
don't have time to do it in lecture you
definitely should is you should
calculate this out to make sure that you
can convince yourself that this is
actually rank one. Okay,
good.
So if this gradient is low rank and
let's say it's rank one, that means that
I can write it out in this outer product
form which is the singular value times a
U times a VRPOSE. Right? If it's a rank
one, this is what it spd looks like.
Everyone good? Okay, good.
So okay.
So what is the spectral norm of this?
What is the forbinous norm of this? Why
don't you take a minute and try to try
to do that and maybe just talk to each
other to make sure that you're like
everyone is okay with the setup that
we're doing because we're making some
jumps. So this is a good time to talk to
your neighbor and get some get your
questions resolved. If you can't resolve
them together, ask me. So on and so
forth. I'm gonna set a timer for you to
just talk about these norms and
um think
after
They just
appropriate.
[Music]
Okay, so that's my timer
first. Anyone have any questions? We're
good. Your neighbors understand what's
going what? Your neighbors understand
what's going on and you understand
what's going on.
>> Yeah. Okay. Good. So then what's the
spectral norm of this matrix?
>> Sigma, right?
>> Okay. Great. Easy. Excellent. So I can
just write that here. The spectral norm
of this
is just sigma. And what about the
frobinius norm?
>> Okay, the frobinous norm is also sigma.
Why is the probinius norm also sigma?
>> Yeah.
>> UV or orthonormal. So
>> okay, so there's many different ways to
see it. Um the way I like to see it is
that the provinius norm squared is just
the sum of the squares of the singular
values is one easy way. You can also
just take the trace. Um that's a third
option. But so the forbinous norm is
also sigma. Great. Okay.
So now we understand this matrix a
little bit. Now let's move to the next
thing. Right? Remember we're trying to
understand this equation.
and how our W's are evolving and we want
to understand well how are they how is
delta W how is the RMS to RMS induced
norm of delta W behaving so to
understand that first we have to
understand this matrix and then we have
to understand this matrix this sign
operation here remember I'm taking as
element wise so now that I understand
this uh gradient of the last matrix
let's try to understand this next matrix
which is consider Consider the sign of
this. Let's call it S. Element wise
sign.
What is the rank of S? How can we think
about that?
So again, I actually take a minute,
think about this. This is worth spending
some time on.
Are we still in
>> Are we still in
>> We're still in mini batch one.
Everything is the same. All we've done
so we have this matrix here. We know
it's spectral norm. We know it's
probinous norm.
What is the rank of S? We don't actually
need to use this to compute the
uh rank of S. But first think about what
are the entries of S going to be
>> just so that we're all on the same page.
They're going to be plus and minus one,
right? Okay, good. So,
>> okay, I'll give you one more minute. You
seem like you're just starting to think,
but okay.
>> One more minute.
>> Yeah. Question.
Okay, great.
So, um why don't I uh wait till
everyone's done or maybe okay, maybe I
can answer it. So, here the the question
that was asked is that wait this delta
WFL gradient is low rank specifically
rank one. Yes, this is true when you do
squared loss, but does it hold for other
losses too? Is there something special
about this loss? The answer is that it
it holds for uh other losses too. It
holds for any kind of generalized
uh linear loss. So for example, it would
hold for u cross entropy loss or
many losses that we commonly will will
be thinking about. Um and the the reason
this works is just basically
fundamentally the uh the chain rule,
right? So what you want to do to be able
to think about this just to give you a
hint of why this is true
is that let's say I have um
w * x is equal to h right so I have some
input this is my weight matrix w this is
my hidden layer h then I want to think
about now the um
derivative of the loss s with respect to
W.
And I'm going to think about this as
the derivative of L with respect to H
of H with respect to
W. Yeah, I think this is correct. Okay.
So, I'm going to think of this in terms
of the chain rule. And now what I want
you to you can look on your own time if
you have time later we can do it
together. But
this will just turn you can just show.
So how would how would I do this? I can
now I can I know I can look at this is a
linear equation. So I can look at how
every entry of H is influenced by every
entry of W. Right.
Right. How is H basically I can take
every row. So w so wigj * xj is equal to
hi right the sum over these things right
just the row times that column gives me
that entry in the just matrix
multiplication so what you'll see is
that this will just the x vector will
just pop up so a calculation worth doing
on your own time
but it's it's just just the chain rule
and linear algebra matrix vector
multiplications
>> yes
Excellent. Okay. So why are we talking
about the probinius norm suddenly? I
asked you to calculate the frobinous
norm here because we do not actually use
this but in two minutes I'm going to ask
you to make a similar calculation and
this will be helpful for you.
So this is just trying to get your cache
uh populated appropriately.
uh we are not really thinking about the
frobinous norm of this matrix right now
in any sense. There are other optimizers
that have been designed through thinking
about the frobinius norm. We're not
going there right now. Yes. Uh
other questions. Okay. So back to
thinking about the rank of X. Okay. So
how do we think about calculating this
rank of S? Well,
what do I know about S? I know s is
basically the sign
of sigma u vranspose right
okay well sigma is a singular value it's
always positive uh so I don't need to
worry about that guy so I have this is
basically the sign of
u vranspose
okay
so what is one nice thing about sign
if I have the sign of
let's say two numbers ui * vj
can I write this in terms of the
individual signs
is this sine of ui time s of vj right
positive time positive is positive
negative time positive is negative like
it all kind of works out Okay.
So can I write S in terms of
the signs of these individual vectors
themselves?
Right? Because this is just an outer
product, right? So every entry of S is
just a product of two scalers. It's
really convenient. There's no uh
so this is equal to the s of u
times the sign
of vranspose
but now what is this when I have a
matrix that can be written like this
what is the rank of s given this rank it
has to be a rank one matrix right
because I've written it as a diad
okay so this means that the rank of
must be one. Okay, everyone with me?
Good.
Okay,
so let's come back to this. So now I
have my WT + 1 is WT minus ADA * S. This
is my delta W. And we want this delta W
to have a small induced RMS to RMS norm.
So if we just work this out,
this means that I want ADA time the RMS
to RMS norm of S to be smaller than
gamma.
Which means that I have ADA time D in
over D out square root time the spectral
norm of S to be less than gamma. Right?
I'm just plugging in my definition of
the RMS to RMS norm.
Just algebra is has been done here using
the definition of RMS to RMS norm.
So if I want to make sure that this
thing is small,
the thing that I have to understand and
bound is now the spectral norm of this
matrix S.
Right? Okay.
So figure out the spectral norm of this
matrix S. What can we say about it?
Do it together. Do it together. Always
more fun.
And since there was this question about
the Frobinius norm,
And there was a reason that we pulled it
up. So maybe you want to think about the
provenius norm while you're figuring out
the spectral norm.
You're not
Yeah, I think
Okay. So,
how are we feeling about the spectral
norm of this?
So, what is the easier thing to
calculate for this? the spectral norm or
the frobinius norm.
>> The frobinous norm is much easier to
calculate for S, right? Because all the
entries are just plus and minus one. So
what is the Frobinius norm? Just the sum
of the squares of the entries, right? So
what is the FBI norm for this thing?
It's just the product of these guys.
But what do we know? It's just a rank
one matrix. So you actually have the
spectral norm is equal to the probinius
norm in this case.
Right?
So here I can easily write therefore
that the spectral norm is just the
square root of uh d in times dout.
>> Everyone with me?
Yes. Questions?
Okay. So, but we wanted this for a
reason.
I want to now plug this back in
to this here. And what do I get? I get
basically something that tells me how to
scale my step size for sin SGD. Right?
Ada was my step size for sin SGD that I
started out with. Everyone remember
that? And now what happens is that these
douts cancel
and I get square root dn time square
root dn. What I get is a 1 / dn times
this hyperparameter gamma. Okay.
Question
>> I just want to clarify. So what we did
earlier is just arguing that for any
matrix the norm and the spectral are the
same.
>> Yes.
>> Right. Why is that true? just
I mean just any
any rank one matrix can be written like
this that's just always true and though
the spectral norm is always this the
forbidden norm is always the sum of the
singular values squared or it is always
the trace of uh arpose a so whichever
way you do it you will still always get
the exact same
uh norm
everyone good here I'm not trying to
like do tricks I'm trying to make it
simple
okay okay okay stop I'll stop okay
questions
yes
>> elaborate
>> okay yes great great okay okay
so let's think of what s is okay. So S
is looking at this matrix. So let's just
do an example.
Okay. Consider the matrix A which is
equal to + 2 -1
-3 and + one. Okay. So the sign
sine of a is equal to
1 - one - one 1
okay so the probinius norm now of this
uh let me call this uh p
the probinius norm of p is equal to the
sum of the squares the probinous norm
there's many different ways to think
about it One way of thinking about the
Frobinius norm is just to say, well,
treat your matrix like a vector. Take
the sum of the squares of all of the
entries of the vector. So if I take the
sum of the squares of all of the entries
of this vector, I get 4 * or maybe the
better way to say is 2 * 2 * 1, right?
Because the sum the square of every
entry is 1, right? - 1^2 is equal to 1^2
is equal to 1.
This is two dimensions. This is two
dimensions and so I have four entries in
the matrix each of them give account for
one in my norm and so my frobinius norm
squared is equal to four here.
So now when I'm looking at my s I know
that the entries of s
plus or minus one. Okay, so I'm relying
on what are the properties that I'm
relying on? I'm relying on the following
properties of the forbidius norm and the
spectral norm. So the forbinous norm of
a matrix
is always equal to the sum over sigma i
squared singular values.
It is equal to the trace
of uh arpose a which is equal to the
trace of a a transpose
and is equal to the sum of a i j squared
over i and j.
Okay, these are all equivalent ways of
defining the frobinius norm.
Does this help?
>> Okay.
>> Yes.
>> Yes. You're showing that for each
gradient in the network the upper bound
on data like the learning rate is
different because it depends on the
dimensionality.
>> Yes. Yes. Yes. So I'm I'll come to that
but I want to just pause because I
I did not realize that this seemed like
I was making I was doing tricks. I was
really not trying to do tricks.
So are there do you want do you want me
to go through this again or
no? Okay.
Okay. Good. So then let's come to this.
I want to focus now on
uh this thing
and I want to uh interpret it a little
bit. Right?
So this is our our standard learning
rate for sinus GD. And as was pointed
out, what it's saying is that you want
to be scaling this as a function of your
DN. Okay.
And or another way of saying is that you
want to look at this through the lens of
DN. Like DN matters for how your weights
are going to change for the same step
size like for the same uh ADA.
D in is going to affect how the RMS to
RMS induced norm of your deltaW is going
to change. That is what this is saying.
Right? This DN is a natural this DN is a
natural parameterization.
It's a natural scaling that is
emergent in the problem. It's like it's
there. It's not like I forced it in
there. It came on its own when we
started looking at the RMS to RMS norm.
Okay. And so
what we want to say is that
looking at this learning rate scaling
with respect to for example the DN of
your uh of of uh the DN for your weight
matrix
might allow you to bound how your
updates are changing in an RMS sense.
Okay.
And so if I think about this, I can
think about
if I think of this gamma now as my
hyperparameter
and this d as the
natural scaling. This gives me a way in
which I can adjust how my
hyperparameters are different on the
layer bylayer basis based on the layer.
Okay,
does that make sense to everyone? And I
can do that without having to have a
explicit different ADA for layer 1,
layer two, layer three. I choose one
gamma for the entire network. But
because it's getting scaled by this DN,
I will effectively have different
learning rates at different layers.
Yes.
>> In practice, do we just set a dot to be
equal to or do we set this to be equal
to this? Yes. So here I'm looking at
this as a bound. So great question.
So here I I I I started out by saying I
want this to be small. But what we're
going to see is actually what we will
want is we want these delta W's to be
not too small and not too big. So we're
going to actually want these this to be
kind of approximately equal in some kind
of order sense. Um but none of our
calculations really depend on this what
this is. This could be an approximately
equal and everything will kind of still
uh follow through.
Okay.
Good questions. So
basically what this is saying is that if
you scale your learning rate inversely
with DN then you can always maintain
this uniform bound on your induced RMS
to RMS norm. Okay. And remember that the
induced RMS to RMS norm is helping us
maintain
that the features the different hidden
layers are all approximately the same
size. the entries are all approximately
one. Right? We arrived at that through
thinking about the Xavier initialization
perspective which says that we want
everything to be approximately of the
same order. Does does that is that
connection becoming clear? I'm going to
make it more clear. But do you remember
that?
I see I see question marks on people's
faces. But yes, question at the back.
ah okay great excellent
so here I did all of this and I'm like
oh you know great we found this new
parameterization we should think about
dn but I made an assumption here right I
made this assumption that uh we're
working with mini batch size one right
but in reality you will have bigger mini
batches so what happens when you have a
bigger mini batch or if you have a
bigger batch not just mini batch
the thing here that is kind of going to
break is this assumption
that your spectral norm and probinous
norm are the same. Now your forbinius
norm will be an upper bound for your uh
spectral norm and so what you will get
is you will just end up with uh a more
conservative scaling right because
you're replacing if you if you follow
through this calculation well I'm saying
that let me upper bound my spectral norm
by my probinius norm
and use that in my calculation and so I
will just get a more conservative
uh learning rate. Does that make sense?
That's a good question.
Okay.
Yeah. Actually, okay. This
said right here. Yes. Question.
>> I will be. Yes. I'll take smaller steps.
Yes.
>> Yes.
>> Practically does that run
if you're trying to optimize the
parameters if you're taking smaller
steps or is that just like a it's not
that bad? So um it it will it will add
runtime and so ideally you want these
bounds to be as tight as you possibly
can. Here we're trying to give an
intuitive scaling idea for what is going
on. Yes.
Question at the back. I saw someone.
Yes.
>> How does the mini batch size
>> I just didn't hear you. Sorry.
>> How does the mini batch size affect the
rank of the matrix? How does the mini
batch size affect the rank of the
matrix? So if I have more data points in
my mini batch, that means that my uh
rank can be can be larger, right?
Because I can I I have now more
directions that I can move in.
>> Yes.
>> So in this topd
the gamma
No, great question. So here I want to
maintain
this the learning rate in the
traditional way we are thinking you know
whenever we write our sin SGD
is still this ADA here my hyperparameter
that I'm choosing is gamma
which leads which then I scale by one
over dn to give me the ada which is the
learning rate if I think of learning
rate as
uh what what scales the sign matrix in
this particular equation.
>> Okay, so we're saying so that the
distribution for each layer will now be
>> the what we're saying is that
um oh I see okay this this was a this
was an ambiguous term. Okay. And I
understand where your confusion is
coming from. Um
what I'm saying is that the
um
the learn the learning rate that will be
applied on a layerbylayer basis will
scale as one overd
once I fix my gamma.
>> Yeah. Okay. Good. Sorry. This was this
was slight a slightly ambiguous
sentence. Thank you for pointing that
out. Okay. Good. So what this is
capturing this is the essence of what is
the MUP or maximal update
parameterization.
This is this extremely impactful work
from Yang and co-authors um I think it
was done uh it start it started as work
as as part of a Microsoft AI residency
um and then grew they have a series of
papers tensor programs one to tensor
programs 5 uh tensor programs 5 is the
most cited one and that's kind of the uh
where they develop a lot of this this
work and this paper is in some sense
famously
impenetrable.
Um it's it's it's using extremely
sophisticated mathematics
to be able to uh find out to be to to be
able to understand these scaling laws
that can uh that can help us uh
understand how to how to parameter
parameterize our layers. And after this
paper came out, there's been a series of
works. um one of the authors uh so for
example there's there's a paper that I'm
going to talk about by uh Greg Yang the
same Greg Yang uh Jeremy Bernstein and
uh Simon
James Simon James Simon Berkeley James
Simon from Berkeley
that um
takes basically a linear algebraic
perspective on the MUP paper and
presents it in a much more simplified
form. And then what what I've talked to
you is basically us going back and forth
and trying to further simplify that
paper to give a a streamlined uh
perspective. So this is a simplified
version of a simplified version uh that
we're that we're that we're that we're
but it captures the key the key idea.
Okay.
Anything you want to add or
conserviveness here shows up in part as
that's why
>> yeah okay yeah so we will talk about
this but yeah the the muon improves in
some sense on this because it can uh it
can close the gap uh on this
conservativeness. Exactly. Yeah. Thanks.
Okay.
Okay. So now what does this
parameterization what what do we mean by
parameterization? What what am I really
talking about?
So to introduce this problem of
hyperparameter search, I can move on,
right? We're good. Everyone's good with
me? Everyone's with me? Yeah. Okay,
good.
So this is a table from the Llama 3
paper sometime in 2020. And what I want
to call your attention to is this column
D model which is talking about the width
of the different models that are being
uh looked at. And
um
here are the different learning rates
okay
that are being used and all I want to
highlight here is that the learning
rates are different right the model size
changes and then the learning rate that
is required to train these model
changes. Okay. So finding the right
learning rate matters because if you use
the wrong learning rate you might not be
able to train you might not converge.
Okay, basically what I want to
communicate here
what Greg Yang and co-authors um I think
actually I should I feel there's a
second author who and therefor equal
contributors so I should make sure to I
shouldn't cite it as just Yang but
there's it's Yang and who and the first
two authors are equal contributors.
Um,
so this is figure one from the MUP paper
and what they're saying is
on the x- axis here is the the learning
rate. The y ais is the training loss.
Okay.
And they compare their maximal update
parameterization to what they call
standard parameterization which is kind
of a series of huristics that have come
together such as Xavier initialization
or her initialization or other rules of
thumb of how to uh scale your parameters
uh for uh for different models.
What the point the thing to point out
here is that as the width of my model
increases right each of these different
colors is a different width. Black is
the widest one. Uh pink is the least
wide one.
The optimal learning rate for training
these shifts and it shifts wildly. It's
not a little shift. This is a log scale,
right? This is changing by orders of
magnitude. Okay, so sometimes you want
to be taking really big steps, sometimes
you want to be taking much much smaller
steps. And as you can see, your training
loss will really change based on being
able to find that right hyperparameter.
Okay,
so this idea, this challenge of being
able to
find the right hyperparameter for a
large model without having to do many
many sweeps of that model to to identify
this is is a big deal.
versus when you look at the MUP
perspective. When you parameterize the
model in the right way,
what you have is, oh, look at all of
these different widths, look at their
training losses,
and look at where the optimum learning
rates are, right? They're all basically
in the same spot because you're
since you're looking at the model in the
in the right way, you're looking at the
parameterization in the right way. Okay?
And so that's what this MUP paper is is
trying to do. And this is incredible,
right? Because that means you can do a
hyperparameter search on a small model
that is cheap and then just say hey
trillion take this and go right here
trillion parameter model just just use
these zero shot transfer them.
Okay. So this is clearly important.
That's all I'm trying to say matters.
So what is parameterization really? And
it's in a sense it's about like it's
about choosing the right units when you
think about this from a maybe a physicsy
perspective. So I already talked about
the challenge of hyperparameter search
and it's bad if your network is large
experiment is expensive. Um and so yeah
can we optimize hyperparameters on
smaller networks and then transfer them
to larger ones? What is the right
scaling? Okay. And so I really like this
example from uh the MUP paper that I
want to kind of
illust use to illustrate the importance
of finding the right scaling. Okay. So
let's take an example that everyone
knows and is familiar with. Let's say I
have nothing to do with neural networks.
Let's say I have some iid samples from a
zero mean unit variance dist
distribution. Okay. Then I know from the
central limit theorem that basically x1
+ x2 + xn when divided by 1 / n
will converge in distribution to being a
normal with mean zero variance one.
Okay, we know this.
But if instead I was like I forgot my
cheat I wrote the right wrong thing down
on my cheat sheet and I forgot to write
the square root and I wrote it as 1 / n.
What happens?
Does this converge in distribution in an
any interesting way? No. This just
becomes zero, right? As n goes to
infinity
or if I chose a different scaling
instead of n I just chose a unit
scaling. Well, this just diverges
entirely, right? And so there is
something interesting about this
quantity. Okay? But for us to be able to
see it, we have to look at it at the
right scale.
Right? And when you choose this right
scaling,
you can see this kind of non-trivial uh
convergence that comes out that tells
you something about the uh behavior of
the quantities that you're interested
in. Okay. Yes. Question.
>> Are you saying that the sum of all the
variables?
>> No, I'm just saying that the the sum
will diverge. That's all I'm saying.
>> If I just
If I just add an infinite number of
numbers, they will just diverge.
>> But they can be positive.
>> They can be positive and negative. Sure,
you might have some. I'm just
>> Yes, there you you might cancel out, but
you will
>> I think it'll be a divergent series, so
you can get it to add up to whatever you
want. Actually, probably.
Um
I don't want to focus on the the limits,
but the the the idea is what I want to
uh I want to get at. But you're right
that it could cancel out and you could
get it to be whatever wherever you want.
But that's uh not what I want to focus
on. Okay.
Okay. So now let's let's think about
um this particular set uh this
particular function. So let's say I have
some function
um of x1 plus x2 plus xn and I have some
constant c here. Okay, so I define my
some fn of c as the expectation over all
of these data points x1 to xn of this
little f of c * this and c is some
constant belonging to r and let's say f
is some bounded continuous function um
okay
if I reparameterize this and I write
this c
as alpha over n Okay, so I
reparameterize it to take into account
the number of things in the sum. Okay,
and then instead of thinking about this
fn,
I want to think about this function g of
alpha. I want to think of this as a
function of of alpha.
Well, as n tends to infinity,
this thing is going to converge
to basically a normal with mean zero and
variance alpha square, right? And so as
n grows larger, I've kind of in some
lost this dependence on n through this
reparameterization, right?
And so
when I think about gn of alpha,
let's say now I want to optimize this
over alpha. I want to find the optimal
alpha star of n which is the argument of
gn of alpha
over alpha.
As n grows large,
gn is converging to being something that
doesn't depend on n at all. Right? And
so for n large enough,
one can believe that as
that that the specific n you choose
isn't going to really matter in terms of
finding this argument, this minimizer,
right? As you get larger and larger, I
can say well if you know this this if
alpha knot minimized at n then you know
maybe alpha knot will also minimize at
n1 if n and n1 are both large enough
right because I'm in this limit where
this model has in a way converged okay
and the reason I can say this right this
I can choose I can say oh I can use this
minimizer alpha not and use it for some
other value of
is because I have parameterized this
function to be in terms of alpha. If I
had not parameterized it to be in terms
of uh in terms of alpha and if I just
had this written as a function of C and
this square root and scaling had not
brought in I wouldn't be able to see
this particular convergence and I
wouldn't be able to make this claim that
oh I can choose the optimal value at a
certain scale and just use it at another
scale.
Okay,
does everyone see the point that is that
I'm trying to make with this example
that you know of averaging that
everyone's familiar with? Okay, so
that's the idea. Can we do something
similar for neural network
hyperparameters, right? It's not clear
that when you have um have a small
network and a big network, yes, I want
to train on the small network and I want
to be able to use it on the big network.
I want to do some scaling, but what
scaling?
Right? If the width doubles, do I
double? Do I have? Do I quadruple? Like
some scaling makes sense. That's
intuitive. But what scaling actually
matters? And it's not obvious to figure
that out, right? And what the MUP paper
is bringing forth is it's telling you
what that scaling is, right? How do I
look at the problem? And it's saying
that look you want to be looking at it
in terms of the dimensions of the weight
matrices that are in your that are in
between that are in your layers.
Okay, that's the perspective that it's
trying to bring out here like you know
in this case the right scaling was
square root n similarly what it's trying
to say is that right scaling is in terms
of those dimensions of the matrices.
Okay.
So in the last little bit of time that I
have, what I want to do
is I want to
give you a little bit more detail on
what this MUP parameterization is trying
to say.
And what I want to say to you is that
look, we've we have two things and I
will argue to you that both of these are
some things are things that are that are
desirable. Okay,
we want to look at these different uh
let me use a different color these
hidden layers of our network
and we want to have these hidden layers
do two things. One is that we want them
to be of a reasonable size. Okay, we
want to have all of these entries be of
order one. Right? That's how we got to
the RMS norm in the first place when we
started talking about Xavier
initialization. Okay, because these
things being too small or too big are
bad for us. Okay.
And the second thing that we want to
have is we want to have that these
layers are actually changing when we
update them, right? we don't want to
have uh them to be in some sense uh
not changing at all.
And so this leads to these two desired
properties for what uh this paper this
is the Yang and Bernstein and Simon
paper
call desired properties for feature
learning. they talk about these two uh
desiderata.
The first is that the RMS norm of your
layer should be approximately order one
should be order one and the second is
that
the change in your layer should also be
order one. Okay,
I want to point out that these thetas
are basically with respect to the
network width. So when I think about the
value of my HL and the value of my delta
HL,
my update is going to be much smaller
than my actual uh feature vector because
it's going to be scaled by some tiny
learning rate, right? But when I think
about it in terms of the network width
or the the fan in and fan out the D in
and D out um these are of the same size
is what this is saying. Question
HL here.
>> Yes, this delta HL is referring to the
change of HL at each gradient step.
Okay,
so just to recap, we know from Xavier
initialization that we want to have
something like this. We want we like the
RMS norms to be uh fixed.
So we want these to be all approximately
one. And this is adding a second desired
property which is saying that the
updates should also be approximately uh
order one
when you look at it as a function of the
width. Yes, question.
>> In this case, h is the actual values
stored in each entry, right?
>> H is yes. So, H um H are basically my uh
my my hidden layers. Yeah, the the
values. Um W's are what I'm going to use
to talk about my weights. And I'm going
to connect the two of them in just a
minute. So, basically, I have H L is
equal to W * HL minus one. Okay, if you
ignore the bias and you ignore the
nonlinearity
and the the weights are where the main
scaling relationships are coming from.
We're good. Okay. So, how can we achieve
this des uh these desired properties?
So, if we ignore the bias and the
nonlinearity, what I have is I can just
write HL as WL * HL minus one.
And now if HL minus one align for
example with the top singular vector
vector of WL I can just take the
spectral norm on both sides of this
equation and I can write this as an
inequality. Right? In general I have an
inequality here. But if I know that this
is aligned to the largest singular
direction or is approximately there then
I can just write this as an equality.
Everyone with me here?
I'm not going to show that this
alignment is the case. The paper argues
for that, but let's just take that for
granted um
for now. And then again, just
substituting the RMS norm for the uh
spectral norm. What we get is that well,
we want our W's to be approximately of
this order, D out by DN. But the easier
way to think about it in the way that
we're used to thinking about it is to
just it brings back this thing that
we've been thinking about uh or is that
you know we want to have the RMS to RMS
induced norm of our weight matrix to be
approximately uh theta 1. Okay.
So this gives us basically if I have
this
if this is of if this is approximately
RMS to RMS uh or what I want to say okay
let me come back
this has the right RMS induced norm this
has the right RMS induced norm gives me
that this has the right RMS induced norm
right if this is order one RMS to RMS
norm this is order one RMS to RMS norm I
can conclude that this will be order one
RMS to RMSS norm by just an induction
straight up argument. Okay, doing um
exactly this calculation here.
Okay,
a similar argument. I'm running short on
time to do this out. So maybe I'll do
this again next time. Um but I want to
just get the idea out to you.
I also want to make sure that my updates
have the same order.
It's the same idea and the same
calculation. All I'm going to do here is
now I'm going to take the same equation.
Oops.
I'm going to take the same equation
and now I can take the gradient and I
just do uh I even forget what this is
called. What is this called? The rule of
derivatives.
However you do you take the derivatives
and then um
you can see that I can write this as
delta w * hlus one plus uh wl times the
the gradient here. Um and now if I look
at uh
if I look at this what I get is that
basically this guy is going to be like
this from what we know. and or if I can
show that this is of this order, this is
always going to be like this. And so I
will get the desired properties again on
my update for my
uh hidden layers as well. Okay, so I'm
not going through this math particularly
carefully because we don't have enough
time, but I want you to just have one
takeaway, right? The takeaway that I
want you to see is that what the MUP
paper or that parameterization does is
it allows you to say let me take a small
model, let me let me train things on it
and then I will take their param the
parameters from that small model
transfer them to a bigger parameter with
the appropriate scaling to change the
weights given by the dimensions of these
uh input matrix weight of these of these
weight uh of these weight matrices,
right? And while the MUP paper looked at
this and came at this from a complicated
tensor math perspective,
a simpler linear algebraic perspective
can bring out in a sense the same
scaling laws making it much more
interpretable, understandable and
leading to therefore more progress
because you can understand it simply you
can actually work with it more easily.
Okay, we will pick up next time.
>> I just want to ask about the lecture
schedule.