So very few people because I guess a lot
of people are away for Thanksgiving
break. Oh well. Um
so I want to start with uh uh just a
couple of key announcements. Um first is
we announced the survey. We announced a
couple few lectures. I want to remind
everyone um please if you have not
already uh we have not reached this
number yet. So I want to encourage you
to encourage everyone in your groups and
everyone else to fill out the survey. Um
if the if you reach 75% of the class uh
doing the survey by Friday of this week
you know then we can award everyone 3%
uh extra credit just uh this actually
will make a difference to many people.
So uh this is useful for us to get
feedback. Basically we have one week
left but it's still good to have
feedback. So
the second thing I want to remind
everyone is that people have submitted
their draft um projects. We're working
very hard. Um we can tell by looking at
them people still have a lot more work
they want to do which is totally fine.
We accept this. Um but it's really
important to take this time. Everyone
was assigned one review to do. Please do
your review today. What does that mean?
Read the thing carefully and the we told
everyone it's supposed to be readable by
people in the class. So point out things
that are unclear, help them out, give
them uh guidance. What often happens to
people is that when they're doing their
own work, they take many things for
granted which are not obvious to someone
who has a little bit of distance from
the work. Um, we assign people
relatively randomly so that some people
some of the reviews that projects are
going to get are going to be from people
working in the same uh stream and some
are going to be from people working some
uh in a different one. So just to give
you know if you're if you're not
directly working on this you might think
wait a minute this isn't clear this
isn't uh understood like why aren't they
looking at this intermediate thing
that's the kind of feedback that's
extremely valuable give it um the point
of this is to help everyone's projects
be better so that by the end when the
final ones are due the next round of
peer review will be more minor in terms
of feedback and so that everyone's final
projects will be actually very very
good. Um
so this is you know really important for
people to do. We set today as the
deadline so that we could turn it around
and release it to everybody so you would
have them over break. Um not that we
necessarily are saying you have to work
on it during break. We just know that
historically lots of people have used
the project uh the Thanksgiving break to
work on their project. So we wanted to
make sure people got feedback ahead of
that time.
Okay. So this is uh the announcements I
wanted to make. Now uh continuing with
the material. So remember what we've
done. We've done we've introduced all
these different architectures. We talked
about you know general issues in deep
learning. We started talking about
generative models. um we went into VAES
and then we're taking this little break
for one and a half lectures basically or
less than one and a half lectures to
talk about something which is extremely
important currently and likely in the
future which is post-training of models
and test time compute. This is going to
also be useful when we talk about
diffusion models for generation uh next
week after Thanksgiving which is the
last topic we're going to talk about.
So uh the idea is you have pre-trained a
model and now we're going to use the
language model context uh to talk about
this but many of these ideas are far
more general but we're going to talk
about in the LLM context
and now it's trained on this
distribution which is coming from the
pre-training data and we mentioned
before you know like there's instruction
following isn't well represented and so
people need to do to make these models
try to follow instructions uh is to give
it some more data that's kind of aimed
at the distribution you actually want in
practice which is instruction following.
So we did talked about this you do uh
supervised fine-tuning which is like the
pre-training loss cross entropy loss
except you do it not on the questions
and only on the answers. We talked about
this last time. Okay. So then we talked
about last time the idea that
it was found to be useful to have models
think right to give longer answers
instead of just giving spitting out an
answer. And so the question became how
can we make models get better at solving
problems. We talked about this last time
just want to recap it.
And the chain of thought already
revealed one part of this which is that
we can trade off compute. we can spend
more computational resources to try to
get better answers. So this is part A of
our answer. This is generally called
test time compute. Spending compute at
actual test time when you're actually
doing it
as opposed to only training.
Now given that you're going to do this
the question became now how are we how
should we train it to be better at doing
this and what's the sort of balance
okay so last time we talked about this
as recapping it that you know for test
time compute the oldest approach we said
was hey
just prompt tell the model to give
longer responses is be careful, think
step by step. And that worked. But then
there's another approach
which is
instead of doing one try, generate n
responses.
Just sample it over and over. There's
randomness, right? Remember, because
you're sampling, so you're going to get
different things. And now, depending on
the problem setting, you can take a
majority or plurality vote. if the
answer is a clear answer that you can
have vote on. And we told you last time
about tricks that people can do to turn
problems that are not intrinsically
having majority plurality votes into
things that have majority plurality type
voting strategies like using another
language model to judge the response and
then take the majority of those
judgings. Um,
but you could also just say I'll take
the highest probability.
Okay. And that's what I want to spend
more time on uh today
because I went through it pretty fast
last time. Now, there's also another
choice you can do. Um, so remember I
talked about having an LLM read the
responses. You could also train. So, let
me write that down here explicitly.
train a reward model
to grade.
Okay, so this is like a you can think of
this as a variant.
So the idea here is you you could prompt
you could also fine-tune or otherwise
train some model that basically takes a
response and assigns a score and says
this is a good response and this is a
bad response. Then if you have such a
thing that actually scores something
then the natural thing is not to take
the majority or plurality to say well I
did a thousand responses and most of
them scored you know.5 I'll just return
you a representative.5 scoring one
you're like no what's the highest
scoring one right and you can return the
highest scoring one everyone with me so
you can think about these two choices is
as kind of interesting variations.
This is I train a reward model and then
I gives me a score and I return the
highest score. And the other is I just
think of the model itself as having a
probability and I think of the
probability as being a default reward
where I think that higher probability
things are probably better. Okay.
So these are uh approaches that uh one
can do. they are
incredibly important. And so before I
sort of continue, I want to mention that
uh
this kind of thing of generating end
responses is your you think of it as
your default way of spending test time
compute.
Okay? And everything you do should be,
you know, better than that.
Right? Kind of a way of thinking about
it because you you can do this. Okay. Um
okay. So now uh another approach that uh
you can take is to say let me find a
different way of sampling
that is going to give me just better
responses by the way I sample
themselves.
So there was a paper I mentioned before
that I want to talk about which is very
recent and it's useful from a teaching
point of view for multiple reasons. So
that's why I'm picking it not because of
its recency. Um that says uh titled
reasoning with sampling your base model
is smarter than you think. Okay. And so
this was motivated by the idea that
people observed which was they had other
ways which I'll talk about of
fine-tuning a model to be better at
reasoning. And people had observed that
when you take a model and you fine-tune
it to be better at reasoning and you ask
what are the probabilities
of the sequences that it generates under
the model before it was fine-tuned. Does
everyone understand what we're talking
about here? So the model before it's
fine-tuned generates response with some
probability. It can also be used to
score responses to say what's their
probability, right? You simply feed it
in, look at the probabilities that come
out and multiply them together. Okay?
And what they found was that
somehow the process of training a model
to be better at reasoning
was also curiously returning sequences
that were more likely under the original
model.
Okay, this is an empirical observation.
Uh
and so this paper basically takes the
perspective of saying okay can we just
turn that around and say that one of the
things that reasoning fine-tuning does
is it makes things more likely so let me
just be more likely.
Okay, that's the that's the idea here.
So this is an intuition I gave last
time. I don't know if everyone got it
because we're going really fast at the
end which was
what's the kind of heristic way of
thinking of why more likely might be
better is that if you're you've
experienced this as a human you're
talking or arguing with somebody and you
say some stuff and now you've talked
yourself into a corner
right and now you're like okay I can't
like there's no good way to proceed I've
kind of made some errors and Now I'm
just sort of stuck. And so you kind of
babble on, right? So what's the LM
counterpart of that? That babbling on is
a bunch of tokens that are all like low
probability and you have to pick one of
them.
What will that do? That'll make the
entire sequence lower probability. So
it's like an intuition as to why it
might be that probability is kind of a
way of telling that something's right or
wrong. It's not. So we only hear her
stick and intuition. Yeah.
>> Excellent. That's the next thing I want
to talk about. Okay. So
one thing I'll talk about this turning
down temperature in a in a exactly a
moment. It's related turning down the
temperature but it's not the same. Okay.
So the quick answer to that um since you
asked the question is that when I turn
down the temperature, I'm still moving
forward one token at a time.
Whereas fundamental to this intuition is
that you're moving along and then you
find yourself in a bad place
and that's what makes the entire
sequence have low probability. Um so
there's a intuitive difference. We'll
make that a little bit more. We'll see
it mathematically in a moment.
So we um what are the approaches that
people have to doing this? Uh one thing
of course is
this approach.
Generate n samples take the one that has
the highest probability. That's going to
give you higher probability samples. Did
everyone see that? Right. It's like if
you think of tossing a coin and you
would like to make the coin tosses, you
get to choose which coin you would
respond to and you'd like to make heads
more likely. You can just toss the coin
10 times and if you get a head, say
heads. If you don't say tails, what's
the probability of heads in this case?
It's much higher. Right? So this is like
the intuition. So this is one approach.
Another approach is
uh beam search where you generate things
one at a time. You keep a stack of sub
subsequences you're going to extend that
are the highest probability
subsequences. You try extending each of
them and you keep the highest to keep
whatever the highest scoring sequences
are. Okay, that's another approach of
sort of generating higher probability
sequences
um which is related to vurby decoding um
and uh in communications.
Now there's another approach and the
other approach is instead of sampling
from
the probability on sequences
I sample from the probability on
sequences raised to a power that's
greater than one. So remember we said
about probabilities. Probabilities are
numbers less than one. So if you raise
them to a power, smaller numbers will go
away faster than bigger numbers will.
And so if you just take the probability
and raise it to a power, it will not be
a probability anymore.
Okay? But you can normalize it. And if
you can sample from the normalized thing
that you get from raising it to a power,
that would give you something which puts
more probability mass onto higher
probability and less probability mass on
low probability.
Do you see that?
where I mean more probability under P
and less probability under P.
Okay. So now we can talk mathematically
about this uh issue which is is this
just low uh temperature sampling. Before
I do that, any questions that we're
trying to do here?
>> Yeah.
>> Why would you sample the different
sequences rather than just choosing the
highest probability?
>> You can do that too. Remember I said you
have to compare, right? Intuitively, you
want to compare to you choosing the
highest probability sequence. Now, the
answer could be that the highest
probability sequence isn't actually the
best one,
right? But among the high probability
sequences, there's a good answer.
So, you might want to sample from among
the higher probability sequences, not
necessarily the highest probability one.
That's kind of an intuition for it.
But you're absolutely right. That should
always be in your mind.
Okay. Okay.
Yeah. So, let me explain what that
means.
>> That's a sequence.
Okay.
Okay. So, that's like an entire
response.
It's not one token. It's the whole long
line of it.
Okay,
so now natural question is is this just
low temperature sampling? And the answer
is no. So why is it not? So let's just
think about what you want. Let's write
it out.
Let's consider some position t, right?
What do we want for some position t? I
want the probability
conditioned on the past. Okay, think
about this.
So what is that? This is the probability
of the entire sequence.
Okay.
And what I want to do is to raise it to
a power alpha is the thing I want to I
want to sample from.
Okay. So what I want to do here is I I
want to sample from this thing and I
have to normalize it right over
everything that could have gone in this
position. So notice what I'm doing here
is
let me make this notation very clear for
you. Okay, hold on.
What I mean here is
I'm doing the generation sequentially,
but I want to maximize the entire
sequence of length capital T. That's why
this is up to capital T. This is the
position we're talking about. But
there's also everything that's going to
come after.
And so when I think about the
probability
for this position, I have to integrate
out everything that's going to come
after.
Okay, so these guys are the ones that
we label this.
Okay, that's what that's doing.
Okay, I sort of put it I'm doing this on
purpose so you can see uh you know the
the comparison with what happens if you
do low temperature sampling. So I'm just
setting it up for you. Okay, everyone
clear? This is what you want.
Okay, so I want to generate tokens one
at a time with this probability
if I could, right? Is that what low
temperature sampling does?
Okay, so the corresponding low
temperature sampling, what does it do?
It doesn't do this integrating out,
right? What it's doing the low
temperatur
equal to one and raising it to a higher
power. Remember there's like a one over
temp one over temperature uh thing. So
that's what this is doing.
Everyone good with that? And then I
normalize that. There's no integrating
out the future.
Questions? That's like mathematically
what's different. Yeah. differentiation
step.
>> Yeah. The thing is so the it's like yes
it's one step versus the whole sequence.
So people get a little confused about
this because you think if I take the
probabilities and I'm going to be
multiplying them together. If I take
probabilities and multiply them together
raising that product to a power is
taking each individual term raising it
to a power and multiplying them
together.
That's why people get confused for so
for the individual terms raising to a
power that's true but the normalization
makes a difference and so that's how you
can think of it this way. Okay so this
is these two are different from each
other
so how do we see that they're different?
Let's bring in all the terms we were
integrating out. Okay. So I take this
probability and I write it with the same
integrating out business.
But now you see the difference is that
over there I have a sum of sum of things
raised to powers and here I have a sum
raised to a power and those two aren't
the same. Right? You can't you can't
take a power and bring it inside of a
sum. Right? That's not legal.
Okay?
So that's why they're not the same.
So this can't be accomplished by just
low temperature sampling. Low
temperature sampling is going to move
you towards higher probability things a
little bit, but you know, not
necessarily. In fact, that's why when
you're doing generations, you typically
don't all do generations always with
lowest temperature sampling because you
actually get bad responses if you go to
very low temperature sampling.
Okay.
So everyone's good with this
explanation.
Okay. So this is not the same thing.
So now the question is how can you do
this? Yeah.
>> I was just or actually I was just
wondering how do you actually you know
add up
like you don't know.
>> Oh exactly. Okay. So now that's the
point right. So now there's an obvious
easy way that you could try to sample
from the distribution which raises to a
power but that's low temperature
sampling but it doesn't work.
So now the question is how can you do
it?
Okay and that's the name of the game.
So what this paper does is it says that
we actually have in
a lot of science and engineering um
statistical physics and so on we have
techniques for doing this kind of a
thing. Okay, what's the kind of a thing
we want? We want to sample from a
desired distribution where we don't have
access to the distribution but instead
have access to something which is
proportional to the distribution.
Because what's different here is this
normalization.
Okay. And the normalization doesn't
care, right? The whole point of
normalization is just trying to make
everything become probability. And so
the technique that's used to do that
is called one standard technique is
called uh
markup chain Monte Carlo sampling. And
so the idea here something like refresh
your memory from your probability class.
So in your probability class you saw
that there's something called a markoff
chain right which is basically you set
up a situation in which there are
transitions that go from one state to
another state and you can evolve across
these states. And you remember from your
markoff chain thinking that there's the
idea of a stationary distribution of
your markoff chain which is what happens
intuitively if you let the markoff chain
run for a very long time without looking
at it. You just let it run and you
sample then you're going to sample from
the stationary distribution. Everyone
remember this? And so if you remember
I'll try I'm not going to teach you Mont
mark um mark up you know Monte Carlo um
but
the the
if you remember the conditions that for
computing the stationary distribution
there's two ways of thinking about it
right there's the igen value perspective
which is very important um there's also
the perspective that says you have to
have the distribution is invariant under
the matrix that represents the markoff
chain. Um, but you can also think of it
in terms of balance, right? That the
probability flowing into a node is equal
to the probability flowing out of the
node. When that is true, then you're in
a stationary distribution. And the key
thing is that for those for that kind of
thinking, you can if you if you know the
distribution you want and you have
something that's proportional, you can
rig it so that the transition
probabilities work out so that the
stationary distribution is the
distribution you want. That's the idea.
And then what you do is you initialize
somehow and you just take steps in this
markup chain. And the hope is that the
Markov chain will quickly converge to a
stationary distribution and you'll end
up sample from the stationary
distribution.
Now there's a enormous body of
literature in terms of how to make this
work what case when it works when it
doesn't work and lots of stuff but here
you have to remember there's a way of
doing this.
So the connection to test time compute
is the following.
Instead of doing one generation
and living with it or just taking a
bunch of fresh draws which is a just
spending compute I'm going to spend my
compute to walk along this markoff chain
and then see where I am end up. Okay,
that's what this paper is saying.
Okay, and thereby sampling from a higher
probability part for sequences.
So how do they do it? So the challenge
is the state space is enormous.
It's huge, right? It's all utterances of
length t. So how do you make this work?
So what they have is they have ideas
inspired by techniques in um MCMC.
So I'll write the algorithmic approach
from the paper. It's copied from the
paper and sort of try to walk you
through the key ideas.
So first key idea
is look this is the kind of thing you
want
probability raised to some power alpha
and so the what they're going to do is
instead of sampling from the entire
thing they're going to do it in stages
they're going to say first I'll take a
small block
and I'll take some steps along my markup
chain for this small block at the
beginning having found a suitable thing
here. I'll seed the next block with that
block. I'll fix that. That block is
fixed for a moment, right? I'll seed the
next block, but now I'll take steps in
this larger block, including changing
stuff in the earlier block.
Okay? Then I'll go again to another
larger block and I'll change the entire
block kind of step by step out. and with
the idea that over a small block it's a
smaller state space and I'll hopefully
get to a good distribution to start with
and then I can get to
having seated myself in a good
distribution I can evolve my markoff
chain better and therefore converge
better okay that's the idea everyone
here see the kind of core idea here I'm
trying to describe okay so I'm going to
be doing lots of generations
and so let me show how that works so K
here is how I'm iterating across these
blocks. Okay, so I'm going to start with
so B is the size of the block. KB is the
total length that I want to finally get
to.
And so
I have some prefix that I already have.
Uh then I sample from something bigger.
I initialize by just
sampling
from my proposing distribution which is
my LLM for the next part. Okay. So I
start with something I expand it. Okay.
That's this step.
Then I do n MCMC steps
which are going to pick a random
position
in this block the entire block.
and then say restart generation at that
point.
Okay, so now I have a new distribute a
new a new candidate. The key thing in
MCMC is to say you can think back to
markoff chains. If you have a markup
chain, you want to get the balance
conditions right, there's some
probability you stay in the state that
doesn't matter,
right? It's the probability flow out
versus flow in that matters.
And so for any pair, if the probability
of flowing out and in balance, you're in
a steady state. So that's the trick. So
what you do is you say, I need to
basically figure out what probability am
I going to reject this move, which means
stay where I am.
So I compute I can of course compute
what the probability would be under
proportional to my desired distribution
and I can look at the ratios. So this is
like comparing the stationary
distribution in the two states
okay by proportion and then I look at
the proportion of the probability of
making that transition. So it's written
it's written this way to connect to
markoff chain thinking. But what this
thing turns into
is just because because of how the auto
reggressive generation works is you just
look at
the ratio of the probability of these
two things because the conditioning just
cancels out in the probabilities because
remember the the LM is generating things
one at a time as conditional
probabilities producting each other. So
the common prefix just falls out just
going to cancel. So you just look at the
ratio of the of the two probabilities is
all this is.
And of course a probability can't be
bigger than one. So the best thing you
could the highest thing you can do is
just accept it right always you know
just take take the move with some
probability you'll take moves otherwise.
So what does this turn into? Right? The
interesting thing in the paper is it
doesn't go through the next steps of the
calculation. But we can. So
if this probability you're going for is
just the probability of your LM raised
to a power. This is the probability of X
prime raised to a power. This is the
probability of X raised to a power is
this ratio.
Okay? because ratio doesn't that's all
that you need for the ratio. This is
just the probability of X without being
raised to a power. This is just the
probability of X prime without being
raised to a power.
So you just get the probability
that this will cancel with some of this.
This will cancel with some of this and
you just get the ratio of the two
probabilities raised to a smaller power
by one. That's all it is. So what does
it mean? This particular algorithm
will always accept a move to a higher
probability sequence
because that ratio will be bigger than
one.
But it'll sometimes accept a move to a
lower probability one two.
Okay, that's what this thing is doing.
Any questions?
Yeah.
>> So like at a very high level it's just
kind of randomly sampling different
ways.
>> Yeah. So it's doing is it's saying I'm
going to generate. So here's a not quite
right response. Like this is not talking
about the seating part. So without the
seeding what it's doing is it's saying
let me generate a response. Let me pick
a random place in the response and just
like regenerate from that point forward.
Is this a higher probability or a lower
probability response? If it's a higher
probability response, good. If it's a
lower probability response, roll it.
Maybe take it and then do it again and
again and again. And this is like
climbing a hill stochastically in
probability is what this is doing. Of
course, it's also doing this like stage
wise seating to help get the
distribution to mix faster. Yeah.
>> What exactly does the block size do
here?
The block size makes it be that I don't
have to run
uh the
I can make this thing smaller like 10.
Okay. Instead of something enormous like
a billion.
So
>> So you're expanding your sequence by the
block size.
>> Yes. I'm I'm first doing this for a
short response. Then I do it for a
longer response seated with this climb
hill climb short response. Yeah.
>> Is the block approach kind of like
inspired by sampling?
>> Yes.
>> Okay.
>> Is all is all inspired by all of these
techniques uh for uh doing MCMC and
physics problems.
>> Yeah.
>> How does that last usually? How does
that is that what you're saying about
>> Oh, yeah. This So if I want to accept
something with some probability, how do
I do it? I draw a uniform and I compare
it against a probability threshold.
Right? So if the probability is one, I
always accept because uniform is always
between zero and one. But if the
probability says this thing says I
should accept it with probability 1/2,
then I'll draw a uniform. If the uniform
comes out less than a half, I'll take
it. If it comes out bigger than half, I
won't take it.
>> Yeah. So this are the actual sequence
generations like each of the final like
X12 X3
at their respective time.
>> No, no, this is this this is this is
generally the entire response. So this
will run and then I'll spit out a
Tlength response.
>> Yeah, I guess I was trying to clarify
that the each of the items in that
response are the result of each one of
the outer loop.
Okay, the outer loop is growing the
response.
Okay, so what this is doing,
what this outer loop, oops, what this
outer loop is doing.
So from here, this outer loop is it's
growing the response I'm working on. So
I start with working on a short
response. Then I work on a bigger
response. As I as I make the response
that my my my scratch paper is getting
bigger and bigger and then my what I'm
doing inside my inner loop is I'm making
modifications to the current response
randomly. Right?
>> So the output is actually the final
result of the inner sequence like one
specific.
>> Yes.
>> Yes. It's one final thing. the the
biggest one that I get to. I will then
do this and then I'm done. I return the
result.
>> Yeah,
>> I feel like I got the idea. But now I'm
confused. Where did the alpha come from?
How do we know it's proportional?
>> Oh, the alpha is a hyperparameter that I
choose for how much I want to skew the
distribution.
Okay, so by making alpha bigger, I'm
skewing more to
moving more mass to the highest
probability sequences.
So in the paper they say that they tried
on different problems and alpha of four
seemed to work pretty well.
Okay, for for their uh in the paper.
Yeah.
>> So I think I'm a little confused because
earlier we were saying that you want to
sample from like the probability the
entire sequence.
>> Yes,
>> this this is the thing I want to sample
from. So, let me just mark it
explicitly.
>> I want to sample proportional that.
Yeah. So, over here it says you want to
sample proportional from that. But like
previously you were saying it's like you
sample from like the sum of like x of
>> Oh yeah great great okay so good let me
let me make make sure it's clear okay so
when I was talking about this
explanation I was just trying to set up
the story so you could see that if I
were to try to do it one token at a time
I would need to sample one token at a
time from this distribution
I'm not going to do it one token at a
time. I'm going to do an entire sequence
at a time.
Okay. So, that's the this is thing. If I
try to do it one token at a time, I'm
not going to be able to do it with low
temperature sampling. So, I'm going to
do something different.
Okay. Yeah. Question. Uh so the tention
here is that we want to sample from
something unnormalized distribution
that normalization factor is inractable.
>> Yes, we want to sample from an
unnormalized distribution uh but to
normalize it is intractable. So we have
to do something MCMC is one thing one
can do. This is the idea.
So what's the payoff of this idea? I
showed this last time but it's good to
see it.
So what they did was they said
I will just like play with the
hyperparameters a bit and set alpha
equal to four and how many MCMC steps
I'll do like 10
and see okay what happens so I'm going
to spend a lot more compute by doing
this right
um
but what happens so they have a
different benchmarks
So they say I have this math 500
benchmark and the Quen 2.5 math 7
billion parameter model which is the one
they played with. They said I just ask
it to solve it.
It's one shot and it gets to 50%.
Okay. Now I do this where I take higher
probability sequences. What happens? No
training. I just sample it. the higher
probability sequences using this
approach I get 75%.
So I move up in this benchmark quite
substantially.
If I do this other benchmark called
human eval this quen thing hits 33%. If
I do this I get to 57.
GPQA another one of these benchmarks
20 28 to 39
no training just picking higher
probability sequences using this
technique
and they say this is pretty impressive
let's compare it to something else which
is an approach that I will mention var a
variation of in a moment so when in fall
2024 when deepseeek released their paper
um they had in it an approach for
fine-tuning for these kinds of problems.
So these kind of problems are special
because these kind of problems you have
a explicit right or wrong answer. You
know if it's right or wrong and you can
tell and so they say that if you have a
way of telling if the uh thing is right
or wrong you can fine-tune in a
particular way which I'll talk about and
I can target the math 500 data set. I
can say I want to target these kind of
problems and I'll do fine-tuning. If I
do that using GRPO, it gets to 78.5.
And if I do that targeting the human
devel.
So what it's saying is that
these curves are the first order of
looking at kind of capturing most of
that gain which is the surprising result
in the paper.
Okay, that mo mo mo much of this gain is
just can be obtained by just sampling
and never doing any training at all.
And what they say is that this this
curve here says okay the reason anyone
trains a model to be better at reasoning
on these kind of toy problems is because
you hope and expect that this reasoning
ability will transfer to other problems
too besides the particular kinds of
problems that you're training on. Okay.
And what they're saying is if you look
at
things that are RL trained for this
other benchmark on these kinds of
things,
but then apply it to this different
benchmark. Yes, it scores an
improvement, but this also scores an
improvement.
And they claim this is improvement is
bigger than this. It's not significantly
bigger than this, but it's hard to tell.
Okay, so this is the excitement behind
um this paper
uh and why it's kind of useful to think
about. I think it's useful from a
teaching point of view because it first
tells you about this this role of
sampling. Uh second is it talks about
why from a markup chain perspective
thinking about ratios of probabilities
might be very interesting and important.
we will have ratios of probability will
come up again in the next thing we talk
about.
But at this point I wanted to
um
pause and give everyone like a minute to
talk to these these are literally the
plots from the paper to talk to your
neighbors and ask this question.
Is this so you're doing peer reviews
now? If you saw something like this,
is this enough to tell the story
properly or should there be some other
bars on this plot?
Okay, do you see what I'm saying? So
here they say, I want here's a baseline
of doing nothing. Here's the other
approach that people talk a lot about um
GRPO a particular way of doing RL fine
tuning which we'll talk about in a
moment and here's us and they want to
show that they're as good as this. So
now talk to your neighbors for a minute
and ask the question is there other
things that should also have been in
this paper.
>> Okay.
We know that
so nice. Foreign
Okay. So, I'm gonna bring everyone
together just for the interest of being
able to talk more about more things
today. Um, okay. So, you've had a chance
to think about it. Uh, so who wants to
tell me uh some alternatives that should
have been in this paper?
>> Raise your hand. Yeah.
>> Try searching over responses.
>> Yeah. So the easiest one is
try
best of n
highest
prob oops
sequence chosen
right variant
Okay. So, yeah, very important because
this is selecting things that are higher
probability. It's a, you know,
sophisticated way of choosing things
that are higher probability. Um, best of
n is an easy way of uh of getting higher
probability. So we should see how we
should have been able to see for the
same amount of compute
right how much how does this do without
this it's kind of hard to tell from a
messaging point of view of the larger
picture for the community
if this was also very competitive that's
also very interesting it's good to know
right if MCMC is better than this it
means that maybe there's something about
going to these lower probability things
that is useful and we would understand
how much that is. As it stands, we
cannot tell.
Okay, so this is really a very mis
important missing thing that should have
been in this paper. Um, yeah.
>> Describe the relative comput.
>> Yes. Excellent. So the the paper
describes all of this and the paper says
that for their optimized choices they're
kind of burning uh something like factor
of nine cost uh of you know for
generating the response uh
and these but the thing is that when you
do this kind of uh RL training you do
find the responses do get longer
also. So that's also so they're getting
they're paying a factor of nine on the
longer responses to do this but there's
no training.
Okay. So from a what you should do in
practice situation of balancing compute
for practice is a separate question but
conceptual this paper is conceptual like
where are you getting the benefits
conceptually from
any more comments of what people want to
say here? Yeah.
>> Why are there no error bars?
>> Ah no error bars. That's a great
question. So often times when you see
the
uh performance on benchmarks they will
not respond with error bars because the
question about error bar is how do I
define what the randomness is uh for the
error bar. So when the thing you're
doing is gpo the error bars would come
there's two different sources of error
bars there's still some randomness in
the sampling of the of the trained
model. So I could try to see if I sample
from the train model again and again
what will I get? tends to happen there
is that the error bars are pretty tight.
They are there but those that's
certainly one. Everyone understand what
I'm saying? So the error bars you get
from just doing a generation because
you're doing some randomness. The other
error bar is for training a model is
what you would have done had you trained
it again.
That's very expensive. And so people
often do not report error bars on
something that's really expensive to do
multiple trials of.
um for their approach
uh the error bars would be multiple
generations error bars and the odds are
they'd be pretty tight. Um they would
not be that big but yeah they could have
reported that. So these error bars cost
compute to generate almost always. And
so
yeah
without any
original
response is more probable you can get
better
behaviors. Yes. Why is that?
>> Like I mean this paper only shows like
empirical evidence. Does it provide any
theory proof to that?
>> So the the observation that good
responses are higher probability at
under the base model was something that
people had observed from RL models
before. What they're saying is we should
look into this why it is the intuition
is what I described that if thinking
traces go the wrong way then they will
get stuck or will have branching points
that have very high probability on them.
So the paper describes this it called
there's a concept people talk about
pivotal tokens of tokens that you really
have to make the right choice on and if
you make the wrong choice you go bad. So
this is empirical observations people
have and so the idea is that the pivotal
choke token choice that you have to make
you have to get it right to have the
generation turnout correct. And so
that's one thing that it's explaining.
Now, in a way,
there's there's a subtlety here that I
want to talk about in a moment, but I
want to make sure people understand like
what the alternatives are. If anyone's
other alternatives that your group
discussed, I want to make sure this one
got talked about, but if there's others
that people have, then I want to include
them, too.
>> Yeah,
>> they could maybe optimization player.
>> Yeah. So, they could have tried prompt
optimization uh for the problem. Um I
believe for
these kinds of problems it doesn't help
much but I would like love to know
exactly how much it does help. So it's a
good good point
to prime two
because prompt optimization can also be
thought of as a way of eliciting the
capabilities that are actually in the
model. So that's a good point.
Um I suspect it won't have done much in
this case but I don't know I don't know
for sure. Yeah
>> one thing I just noticed is that their
base model seems to be like an already
kind of postrain model and they're doing
for further
reasoning capabil like this would hold
if you're trying to train it on a task
like you said to do or something like
that more like motor skills with the
Excellent point. So this comes back to
what I was talking about before. Maybe I
didn't make it clear. So I mentioned
this last time that the way that these
training things work is you pre-train
the model on a large set of things. And
then what you do is you mix in more of
the kinds of things you actually care
about into the pre-training mix itself.
Then what you do is you mix you do this
kind of thing where you say, "Okay, now
I'm also going to ask it questions. So
I'm going to have this separation where
I I supervise only on the responses and
not on the questions part. This is part
of the standard um training before you
do any RL training on a model. And so
it's true Quen math was trained with
this kind of mix that was math heavy and
aiming at math type of things and aiming
at reasoning about math sort of in the
mix to begin with and code. So it's code
and math. So the code and math these
things are trained on is much more than
the proportion of code and math on the
internet. Like most of the internet is
not coded math but a lot of their
training mix is coded math. So that's
already present. Um yes and that also
comes from that's why this this question
is in the field of how much of the
capability is actually already present
in the base model and what needs to be
unlocked sort of by RL training. But I
wanted to there's there's more here I
wanted to comment on before I move on.
Yeah.
>> Yeah.
>> So I was thinking like okay if you get
better
but like what happens if you use both
kind
of
>> Yeah. Excellent question. And so the
paper talks about this. So what the
paper talks about is that if you do
people have observed this empirically if
you do RL tuning on a model and then you
do on top of that best event generation.
Okay so I RL tune it first and then I
say now pick the best event. The gains
don't compound
the same way as they would for best of
end generally. And what they claim in
this paper is that this approach
actually does get further compounding
gains of best event in a way that RL
tuning doesn't.
But they don't have a comparison here
with straight best event on the base.
Yeah.
>> Does that mean that RL is performing one
collapse or causing collapse? So the
perspective is that uh the people worry
about in RL that whether or not by
making it favor certain kinds of things
you an experience as all fine-tuning
methods do uh forgetting which we talked
about in the class. So are we forgetting
important things by doing the RL
training as one would always fear in any
fine tune and so yes people worry about
that and they also worry that it's uh
yeah it's basically favoring more likely
things in such a way that might block
its ability to explore um when you do
many so these are all things that are
people care about which is why this is a
very very active field of current
inquiry
more comments on what other alternatives
before I want to move to one other
comment okay so not on simple
alternatives. Okay. So, other general
comments then I want to make one comment
then I want to move on.
>> Yep.
>> Is there any reason why you wouldn't
just fine tune on this sampling method?
Like could you just do a synthetic data
generation and then just
>> is that something that people are
interested in doing?
>> Yes, it seems like that's obvious next
step.
>> So, exactly. So, this is actually done
in practice and very important. So, um
that's one of the things I wanted to
mention. So, great. It's being
mentioned. Um so when you have best of
end for example or any method that can
give you samples that are more likely to
be correct you can then use these
samples that are more likely to be
correct in your process of fine-tuning a
model using another approach like RL. So
we'll talk about this in a bit when I
talk about like what you need to make to
make RL approaches work. So definitely
this compounds in fact versions of this
are being used even um I think in llama
2's training where they talked about how
so you go back a bit
remember this approach we mentioned
about training a reward model to grade
so if I train a reward model to grade. I
can generate better responses by simply
taking my model, doing a thousand
generations under my model, ranking them
under the reward model and giving the
best one.
So, uh you can then use these enhanced
mod enhanced uh responses to then do
training to make the model kind of get
better and better. So if you think about
it, what this kind of training that's
being described right now is is it says
I have some way of getting responses
that I think of as being better
responses. Um they're more likely to be
correct. Can I make the base model
itself generate those more likely?
Do you see that?
So that is a theme that people follow.
Now the interesting thing about it is
that
actually this sampling approach in a way
or like beam search for example beam
search makes it obvious that it's doing
computation but it's also doing
computation that's effectively doing
look ahead
right before it commits it looks ahead
now you could say that oh yeah you know
I have a so think about chess or some
other game I have a way of scoring
positions, right? And if I do the
scoring of positions together with look
ahead, right, then I can do very well.
But that does that mean the scoring of
positions by themselves are
so powerful? Not really. You need the
combination,
right? And so when one talks about what
RL training is doing or what other
trainings are doing, even SFTTS on these
kinds of things, you can think of it as
trying to get the model to actually
learn implicitly to look ahead
and see, okay, wait, I don't want to
choose this pivotal token the wrong way
because it's going to screw me up later.
So I'm going to make the correct choice
and not the incorrect choice. So it is
actually adding a capability just
because the model could generate with
best of end something doesn't mean that
when you run it once to do to do do as
well of best of n in one shot requires
more look ahead. Okay. So there is
something that's being u that can be
added. Yeah. Um there's another question
first. Yeah.
>> So this idea I think is very similar to
predictive control.
just use predictive control and PC
detect that
>> yeah so uh the connections between RL
and control is very very close they
actually all the RL techniques grow out
of control so in fact the class that
meets immediately before this one what
they're doing is actually MPC and RL uh
together at the end of it's a main
controls class so these are these are
one field they're not separate
Um, there's a reason why a lot of Ral
techniques come out of labs working in
robotics,
right? It's just historically the way it
is.
Okay. So,
um, yeah. So, I've talked about
everything I want to talk about here. I
want to move on and talk about RLVR.
Okay. So
RLDVR is in my opinion easier way to get
into understanding what's going on here
than what's called RHF. So as distinct
from mark this down. Oops.
So the very important critical paper I
mentioned before on instruct GPT was
about RLHF which is how can you use
human feedback to make models better. Um
it's actually I think harder to
understand if you start with RLHF. It's
easier to understand with RLVR as the
base. So, I'm I'm just going to use RLVR
as the base and then you can we'll think
about how RLHF fits in on top of as a
modification of RLVR.
So, what is RLVR? Um, verifiable rewards
just means that you have an automated
way of scoring and saying this is right
or this is wrong. You can verify.
So somehow you generate a response
something and there's a way of telling
if the answer is right.
Okay, that's the on your training data.
If you can do that, that's called
verifiable rewards. So one easy way is
math problem where you have a math
problem and there's a boxed answer and
you know the right answer for that box.
So you can say okay generate however you
want. Is the answer right or is it
wrong? You can just check the answer in
the box. So another way of thinking
about verifiable rewards is verifiable
rewards is something which can be
autograded using code.
So there was this very interesting paper
that I would recommend called the art of
scaling reinforcement learning compute
for LLMs. There's lots of stuff in this
paper that came out October 15th
curiously like like a day next to the
other paper I was talking about but just
coincidence.
And my treatment is going to be
influenced very strongly by this paper
because I think it's nice for how it uh
talks about things.
So
you did this homework problem where we
talked about you know thinking about
scaling rules right we gave you this
like how do you do estimation of how how
you set parameters for a model given
some kind of extrapol how could you do
extrapolative prediction so extrap we
talked you saw in the homework
extrapolative prediction is very
interesting and useful and it's used
practically because you're going to have
to make a potentially a large compute
decision and you want to know is this
worth doing or not and so you want to
extrapolate
to see how well would things go if you
did more compute
and we talked about you know MUP earlier
as a way of doing hyper parameter
transfer. So if you have some way of
extrapolating that well how would things
work potentially with something bigger
and that looks good you then want to say
okay how do I train it how to set the
parameters kicks in there right so this
is kind of saying okay if you're doing
reinforcement learning is there any way
to see the main theme of the paper is
there any way to see what is going to
work well without having to run it all
the way out everyone see this as the
interesting question. So I just want to
use this I think the paper is nice for
another reason but I want to use just
mention the main theme of the paper as
well. So then you can get to the other
thing I want to talk about.
So what they do is they say that look
actually you can think about this
Sshaped curve as telling you how RL
training will proceed. So what is it
saying? It's saying that when I do RL
training on a log scale
or that it seems to have a performance
that follows this kind of functional
form
where it starts off small
at some baseline level R0 and then as
you spend more compute it doesn't move
much and then it starts going into a
phase of getting gains and then it
starts saturating
and what you want to do is you want to
be able to know where is it going to
saturate to so you can see is this worth
doing or not and so what they're saying
is that actually these things can be fit
if I fit past this midpoint a little bit
I fit a curve I can actually predict
where the thing's going to asmtote and
that's useful okay because this is log
scale and so going from here to here is
actually a huge amount of compute it's
like most of the compute
>> yeah
is like comput
>> yes C compute it's just like counting
counting how much computational
resources you're spending like GPU hours
>> think of this as GPU hours
okay so again like these numbers are
like funny from a class point of view
you're like okay GPU hours in thousands
on a log scale right and like you guys
are like I have eight right so it's it's
a very um assist with the reality of the
field, right? So,
and what they're doing is they're saying
that if you're equipped with a way of
doing this prediction, then you can
actually try to think through which
approaches actually work well um in the
long run and which approaches only look
like they're working well but don't
actually work well. So what they do is
they say as after doing all this they
say look I will actually have I can
grade different recipes for doing RL for
verifiable rewards
and remember that GRPO that we mentioned
before the deepseek recipe which I mean
I'm not going to talk about in full
detail as well I'll point you to some of
the things that are about it that's this
curve and that's right here
okay this is the scale is not quite
honest right because it's point 4 to 6.
So you know it's but uh it's saying that
there are recipes that actually get to
better asmtoic places than gRPL and the
one that they're proposing is called
scale scale RL which is related to uh an
approach called miniax
uh which is basically so this is like a
more efficient version of miniax in
terms of compute is what the paper is
proposing.
So what I'm going to do is I'm going to
anchor my treatment of of uh RLVR on
this recipe to make sure you understand
the scale RL recipe and then I'll add
some terms to it that so you can
understand some of the others.
Okay, so everyone understands this kind
of idea of having a scaling law how it
might be useful. This is the first kind
of major scaling law for RL that could
predict where the asmtoic things were.
Empirically, of course, you don't have
theorems about this. just empirically it
seems to do this.
Okay, so
here so here's the problem. You start
off and you look in the paper and you
say, "Okay, what's the loss function?
You're gonna use blip
this." And the my goal is to make it
possible for you to understand what is
going on here and why is this happening
like why what are these choices mean
like what is even happening here. Okay,
so
let's look at what this is saying.
First thing this is saying is that
let's look at notation. Pyen
is the
probability you're going to be used to
generate examples. So how does RLHF
work? RLHF works like this. You take a
problem, a prompt and you say I'm now
going to generate
G capital G responses.
So, I'm going take 1,00 think of G as
1,00. I'll take 1,000 answers to this
question.
So, G is generations.
Then what's the intuition? The intuition
is like this. Very simple. It says for
all these generations I can score them.
You can think of the score as being one
correct answer, zero incorrect answer.
So intuitively there's three big cases.
You do a thousand generations and none
of them are right.
Okay, in that case you're like, I don't
know what to do here. I only know lots
of things that are wrong. There's some
interesting work on trying to learn from
even cases where everything is wrong,
but I'm not going to talk about that.
Other case, I do a thousand generations
and they're all right.
And it's like, okay, I'm getting these
right. Nothing much to do here.
Then there's some of them are right and
some of them are wrong. Okay.
Now, if you have some that are right and
some that are wrong, the idea of RL says
good doggy to the ones that are right,
bad doggy to the ones that are wrong.
Okay, what do I mean by that? It says
the ones that are right make the model
more likely to generate those and the
ones that are wrong make the model less
likely to generate those.
That's the high level picture. So RLVR
requires there to be some mixture of
these. Now it's about details. How do
you get this to work?
So that's what the generations are.
So now there's this twist. You have to
do these generations.
In an ideal theoretical world, you would
be doing these generations using the
model that you're training.
Okay?
In practice, you will not
you will do these generations using
something else. Why will I use something
else? Because one simple thing is code
that is optimized for doing generation
is different than code that is optimized
for doing training.
So at the very least you'll be using two
different sets of code. Do the
generations. the two different sets of
code will actually generate things
slightly differently for numerical
reasons alone because they're optimized,
right? You're using finite precision. So
you'll never be generating with exactly
the distribution you're training.
So you have to recognize there's two
different distributions. That's why
there is this thing that's being trained
distribution and the thing that's being
generated distribution. And you have to
account for the fact these two are
different.
A lack of accounting for the fact that
these two are different will cause
training RL training to fail.
Okay, so this is one thing that's been
around here. Okay, so now let's talk
about some more of the terms here.
Easy ones to explain.
This one
says
don't bother
if
we get
90% right.
We said we don't bother if you get them
all right. But it says if you get 90%
right, don't bother. Like don't don't
try to train on it. Just throw it away.
Okay, that's what this part means.
Now
comes the rest. Okay. So yeah,
>> where is the pass rate used in the
above?
>> Ah, it says that I only will execute any
of this if this pass rate is this way.
If I don't if my pass rate is above 90%,
I'm not even going to run a the loss is
zero. Just move on.
>> Yeah,
>> this is related to PO. Everything is
related, but this is not PO.
Okay. So now I want to remind we made
you do a homework. So now let's remember
this homework that we made you do. In
this homework we said how do you deal
with the fact of not having a gradient
because the function you want to
optimize doesn't let you take a
gradient.
And we said hey if the thing you're
optimizing is a probability distribution
what you need to be able to do is to
have a gradient on the parameters for
the probability distribution for this
expectation. And we made you do it first
in code. Then we had the code, have you
work through a version of it, then we
had you work through it a Gaussian toy
of it for the Gaussian case. And then we
had you think about it and say, "Hey,
actually in general, this kind of
expression
can be done as this other expectation."
So this is in the homework. We made you
do this. This is math. So instead of
doing a gradient of an expectation, I
can do an expectation of a different
thing.
And what I can do is I don't have to run
a derivative on the thing I can't
differentiate the f.
But I can take a gradient on the
probability except to take it on the log
probability.
Okay, this is this
you see that? So this you've already
seen in the homework. This is that
trick. That's what this is.
So this
is that. Now from the perspective of
homework three, if this is this, then
everything else
is this.
Okay, which is what? It's the thing that
you want to make better.
>> Yeah.
We don't do that.
>> Oh, we do definitely do. We definitely
do that.
>> So, it's like iteration like
>> Yes.
>> Just like
>> Yeah. Yeah. At every time that you're
doing this, you're always using a stale
thing or a different thing to do the
generations, but you don't want it to be
too far behind.
>> And then we just have things.
>> Yes. And so there's many tricks here. I
will see how fast how much I can do. I
want to make sure you get this
expression.
So everything here is spiritually F
which is the thing we want to make
better. So how let's like unpack it some
more. Okay. So the key thing is this
term here.
Okay.
This is called normalized advantage.
And what it means is it says of the
generations I did,
is this a good doggy or a bad doggy?
Okay, is it going to be raised up or
raised down?
So if it gets a reward, I want to move
it up. If it doesn't get a reward, I
want to move it down. Everyone clear? So
how do I do that? I do two things.
First thing I do is I remove the mean.
Why do I remove the mean? Because I want
some of them to be positive and some to
be negative.
Right? I want to go up, raise the
probability of things that are positive
and reduce the probability of things
that are negative. Everyone with me? How
do I do that? I simply take the average
reward and subtract it from the batch.
That's this.
Okay. Second is I normalize it by the
standard deviation. So it's on a
standard scale.
Okay. So this is just like input
standardization. It's like reward
standardization.
So this is the this is just the standard
deviation across the batch.
Batch by batch I mean this generation
batch. Okay. It's actually all the
rollouts.
Everyone good? Yeah.
>> How are you computing the advantage
estimates? Is there a separate reward
function for that?
>> Oh yeah. I verifiable reward. So every
time I can score I autograde everything.
So I get a generation, I autograde it.
You can think of it as binary. Good or
bad. Good ones get a reward of one. Bad
ones get a reward of zero. But you could
be more than more general than that.
Okay. So that's where verifiable rewards
come in because I can do this. So this
is remember this is from VR
>> question. Yeah.
>> Yeah. Sorry. Could you explain what pi
train and pull are exactly?
>> I'll come to those. Okay. So now we have
understood through here.
So now comes a bit of subtlety. Okay.
The subtlety goes that I have these
generations
and these generations are all responses
and they might be different things long.
How should I think about this?
I have two ways of thinking about it. I
can think of it as a collection of
responses individually or I can think of
it as a bag of tokens. Some responses
might be long, some might be short.
They're just bags of tokens.
Okay, this takes the bag of token point
of view. So when I look at the
probability, I look at the probability
of this specific token
being generated. Okay, that's what this
thing is is telling me.
And then I sum up over all of the
tokens. And I sum up this like this is
sum over the entire bag of tokens. And
this is normalized by the total number
of tokens.
Everyone see that? Okay. So this
just a perspective that one does. Okay.
Now here comes the issue. The issue is
homework three said I would like it's
very important in homework three that
this p theta is the same as this p theta
very important the expectation should be
of the thing that you're taking the
gradient of we have a problem here
problem is I'm generating under
something different
so when I do this the generations are
not under the thing I
Everyone see this issue? So I have to
fix this somehow. How do I fix it? I fix
this with an idea called important
sampling.
And what important sampling says is that
if something actually has a probability
that's higher under my distribution than
what this thing would generate it as,
count this more.
Okay? If it has a lower probability,
count it less. And that's what this is
doing. to think on this particular
token, how would the two different
distributions generate it? Compute the
ratio. This is to patch the fact that
I'm generating with the wrong
distribution.
Okay, that's this.
Okay,
finally now we have we understand all
the terms here. This just says as long
as the pass rate is less than 90% I
don't care where the mean is of the
reward. Let it be whatever it is. I'm
happy. It should it should not be zero.
It can't be that nothing nothing had any
reward. Something something worked.
Okay. But if you one thing worked I'm
going to use it
and this is this. Now final things to
worry about SG min epsilon.
Okay let's look at the sudian side
first. min part this says okay I'm going
to use this ratio
but
but but
if the probability under training is
really really low
from this than this guy
don't throw away this sample
okay if you let this probability if you
this ratio be very small this will give
this no weight in terms of computing a
gradient
hold on to them with some minimal weight
because there's some useful signal here
even though this is unlikely under my
training distribution.
Okay, so this is a lower clip. Don't let
it get too low. But if this probability
is very high in this particular variant,
let it be high. It's fine.
Go ahead, count it that way. count your
optimizer taking care of that.
Remember when you're training in your
optimizer, you also have gradient
clipping for your optimizer itself. It's
going to prevent very large gradients
from hitting. So you just let that be
dealt with separately.
Final word SG. What does SG mean?
>> No, stop gradients.
Okay.
So this is I'll make it a different
letter
stop
gradient. So this is like pytorch. What
does it mean? It means that remember
this is a loss function. You're going to
do auto differentiation on this. It says
I want the auto diff to go inside here.
This is where I want to go. Like that's
what this is. This is where the gradient
goes. This is me correcting
probabilities. Do not let the gradient
go into this.
This is not for the gradient to go into.
Okay,
this is basically to not do this would
be a bug
because this is you see what I'm saying?
This is this is not something that the
derative should be going into. This is
just to correct for the fact these two
distributions are different.
Okay, so this approach is what they say
works great. I'm out of time. So what I
might do next time is just tell you
about KL regularization. And you know
that's in their recipe. What they find
is that doing KL regularization doesn't
help. They do experiments and they say
it doesn't seem to help. But many times
you do do KL regularization which you've
already seen in VAE. So I'll just
mention it last next time before moving
on.
Okay. So if you want to think over
Thanksgiving you think about why
this thing might also look like
diffusion generation which we'll talk
about next week. I
>> I had a couple questions. First of all
for that last equation I was confused
about you said the min is used