[Music]
Okay, let's start. Uh so uh we're going
to continue our discussion of connets. I
want to make sure everyone knows there's
discussion tomorrow. So please if you go
to discussion uh we will the discussion
will have problems on some of the
material we talked about last time
resnets we'll continue discussion of
resnets and there'll also be a
discussion of some other things we'll
talk about as well as uh looking at the
dropout question that's on the homework
we have a piece of that on the on the
discussion uh for you uh to make sure
you understand it uh we are going to
announce soon
information about uh project
possibilities for you. Uh and also we
we'll have an announcement soon about
having
an another office hour on Friday.
>> Already
>> already Yeah, it's already assigned.
Yeah. So
>> office hour on Friday.
>> Two to three on Friday.
>> Last office hour on Tuesday.
>> Yeah. Let me make make a note of that.
>> 5:30.
>> So Friday TA office hour
5:31 Corey
2 to 3.
We added this as an alternate time that
you can also use and the last office
hours uh today are cancelled. These are
we moved it
again. We encourage people to come take
advantage of uh TA office hours. If
people don't come, we will cancel the
office hours.
>> There are some people who are scared to
come into office hours.
>> Yeah. Good. You should come. Should
come. Yeah. Um, you need to learn the
material. Uh, asking questions is a good
way. Coming to office hours prepared to
ask questions is a good way to get
yourself ready.
>> Office hours. Sit there and do your
homework.
>> Yeah.
Yeah. You have to do homework sometime.
Might as well do it then. Um, okay. So,
we're going to continue. So, uh,
everyone recalls the setting. Um, I'm
going to skip this thing that we did
last time about normalization layers and
continue talking about residual and skip
connections. We went a little fast. So,
I'll just quickly recap where we were.
So, people saw that networks were doing
neural network was doing quite well.
They saw that making them bigger made
them work better and they tried to make
them even bigger and then they observed
this odd phenomena. Although they were
adding parameters, they found that the
larger network was performing worse
uh and in training as well as in
testing. And this would
>> mic.
Let's see if this works better. Is that
okay? Uh so you normally
think of a phenomena like this as being
an underfitting phenomena because you're
doing bad and you're doing worse in
training but it was odd from the ML
community's point of view because you're
making the model bigger and it's
underfitting. So what was going on? They
said okay it's probably uh not training
very well. And so this the idea was
somehow the gradients as they're going
backwards are either diminishing or
becoming garbled and less informative.
And the idea was wouldn't it be great if
we could somehow create a gradient
superighway.
Some way of having the gradients come
from the later layers back to earlier
layers uh in a way that the earlier
layers could contribute without having
it get garbled by intermediate layers.
And so the first idea one might have of
basically adding links in the so
remember the gradients follow the path
of the forward network. So if you want
to add a path for gradients you have to
add paths in the forward network. So
from this point of view the idea was
well I could add lots of paths from
everybody to here
and then I could do the same thing to
every other position intermediate and
that doesn't work because the
activations get really big. So
the question was what's the minimal
thing you need to do to get gradients to
go everywhere and the idea was these
skip connections. So the skip
connections do is they add the input to
the output of a layer where now we're
going to think of a layer now in a more
flexible way as a block. The block is
now the thing that gets skipped.
Everyone with me? Before we thought
about a layer as being some weights,
some bias and then some nonlinearity
possibly, maybe not a nonlinearity.
Maybe a normalization comes in as a
layer. So now we're going to abstract up
to boxes and in the boxes are going to
be things like weights and biases and
nonlinearities.
So we have to decide what goes in the
boxes. But the idea behind the skip
connections is by adding these paths the
gradients will always remember a plus
splits the gradient in backrop the same
thing goes on both both sides of the
plus. So the gradient coming back
through the output layer will not only
go into this box and then continue on
here it will also just go over this plus
and then enter here. But by that token,
it'll also do this
back to everywhere any the gradient from
the last thing goes back to everybody
else. And by the same logic, the
gradient that's coming through this
penultimate layer is also going back to
everybody.
So every previous layer box sees
gradients coming from every future thing
in this picture. That's the idea.
Everyone cool with the idea?
Okay. So now what we're going to do is
we're going to talk about what goes
inside that box, that block that gets
skipped over.
So here it's interesting. So if you go
back and read the earlier papers and
then you look at what people are doing
today, you'll see a difference. So I
want to acknowledge that and I want to
give you the old perspective
and then the more current perspective on
this. Everything now follows generally
the more current perspective.
So the old perspective was that what you
do is
and they found it curious was that you
take
two layers
Okay, where a layer is the minimum kind
of component of a layer is there's some
weights, there's a bias and there's a
nonlinearity,
but you take two of the layers and you
put them inside of a box.
Okay, so there are even papers written
about this where the people are
wondering, wait, why doesn't it work
when I just put one, put the skip over
one? Why do I have to do two? Okay, so
people tried everything and they said
that, you know, two, I need at least
two. I could put three but two I need at
least two for it to work with just one
it didn't work right
so uh now again when I talk about this
layer when I when I write a weight
matrix W you should interpret it as
either this is like an MLP we just have
a weight matrix a dense weight matrix or
it's like a conflict both of these are
like weights so I'm going to treat these
interchangeably from the perspective
disc of discussions of uh resonance
Okay, so this is the again the uh the
old perspective when you just think
about uh the core building blocks, but
we said wait, we talked about
normalization layers. How do
normalization layers interact with these
residual connections and the blocks?
Everyone see this as the question? I
added a new idea adding these skips. So
we have to make sure we can make this
work with all of the ideas we had
before.
So the old way of thinking about this is
the is a picture uh that looks like this
which says
you have these normalization layers at
the end. So what's the logic? You do
some processing
then maybe things have gotten out of
hand and have gotten too big or not
behaving properly. So you stick in a
normalization layer to force it back to
where it needs to be and then you
continue. Everyone with me? So this is
the old perspective. Again, many papers
are written from this kind of
perspective. Uh there's one that's
particularly important that we'll talk
about later that you need to be aware of
uh which some students find quite
confusing which is the very famous
attention is all you need paper in 2017
is also written implicitly with this
style of thinking in it. However, that
style of thinking is now
more or less as a default obsolete. So I
want to talk about what how you think
about it in a more current perspective.
So what do you actually need to do? What
matters? Why did people observe that you
needed to have two?
So the core thing that it turns out you
need uh as a minimal object that sits
inside of the block that's going to get
skipped over is something that looks
like this.
So let's think about this. This is
something that should be very familiar
to you everyone.
This is the first neural net that you
saw in the class and discussion was this
right? Remember the thinking thinking
behind it was you have some inputs you
have some weights you have some biases
that made a bunch of elbow feature type
features then you had nine the
nonlinearity that made it happen but
then you need to combine them in
different ways and then you had another
set of weights and in particular there
was this problem that if you didn't have
this guy
the output of this is always going to be
positive
or zero and that's a bit weird. It It's
a very big limitation on what you can
express. But if you put these weights
afterwards, you can then go negative.
Everyone remember that? So it turns out
this is this is important.
Okay. So
why is this important? And here there's
uh you know early on there's papers
talking about exactly why working it out
uh mathematically, but it's useful to
think about this from an intuitive point
of view to grasp what's going on.
And the intuitive perspective is before
ResNets when you thought about a
multi-layer network what you had was a
bunch of nested functions. Does everyone
see that you take the output of one
layer as the input to the next. So this
is the first thing you see sees the
input and then the next layer sees that
as its input and so on and so on until
the end.
Okay.
And the ResNet perspective
instead looks like this. Because you
have these skips,
what you're doing is every layer's
output
is the output that was before it plus
some function, some new function acting
on the previous thing.
Did everyone see that?
So
if you squint at this a little bit, you
think, what does this remind you of,
right? Like anyone want to comment like
what kind of a thing does this look like
to you? Where have you seen this kind of
a thing before?
>> Yeah.
>> The way you might describe like a
system.
>> Yeah, it's like a recurrence relation
you might think of as like a system,
right? And if you think about those
recurrence relations that define
systems, you can think of them as
potentially coming from things like
discretizations of differential
equations,
right? So when you discretise a
differential equation, you get something
like this, except there's like a
multiplier here that says some something
small.
So if you think of it that way, this G
thing, this is like if you write, so it
feels like, let me just make a write
this out here.
feels like this.
I think there's a step size missing but
kind of has this kind of feel. So if you
take this perspective,
what you're trying to do is you're
trying to design a differential equation
that has a flow that takes you to the
place you want to go.
You start with an input and you want to
let it compute by like moving it around
and then getting you to where you want
to go. It's a nonlinear differential
equation.
So if you think of it that way now you
can appreciate more why the restriction
that G always be positive is bad is
really hurting you on what you can do
right you want to be able to sort of go
back and around
okay so that tells you why you know the
having a relu at the end all the time is
not a great idea
okay
so this hopefully helps now I wanted to
acknowge something right here. uh when
people first uh observed this and they
saw it, they were got quite excited and
uh another area uh sort of came into
being which was neural odes
where people think about differential
equations that are defined by neural
nets and resets felt like a neural OD
and people then it was really great
because suddenly
uh a lot of people became inspired from
the physics side and said we can think
about physics inspired neural networks
because now we can map them into resnets
and once you think of the OD perspective
you notice that when I wrote this thing
that should remind you of
you usually write it without a g
subscript t of course g can also def
depend on time that's also an od um time
varying but you used to write You you
think of writing it this way and a lot
of physical laws have this way. And so
people thought about hey if this is
interesting in physics maybe we can
bring this idea back to neural nets
and bringing the idea back to neural
nets of saying maybe there's useful
invariance of not having the G change or
not to change too much with time. Does
everyone see that as a way of thinking?
And so that translates into back into
the neural net perspective because
remember these G's here
are these boxes here. Does everyone see
that?
So what that suggests as an approach to
follow is to think about adding weight
sharing across depth.
Did everyone see that?
This is kind of how you go back and
forth across ideas. Neural net deep deep
deep neural nets are often about where
can you get an idea and how can you
figure out how to apply it and you see
does it work or not. So this turned out
to be quite helpful in many physics type
problems. Um but and people were really
hoping that the neural OD ideas when
applied to classical uh vision problems
would actually beat resonance. But it
turned out they didn't. Okay. And people
still don't completely understand why.
But something about the ResNet
architecture without having that much
weight sharing uh having basically no
weight sharing across depth does better.
Um
so this just a little story uh on the
side about how the evolution of these
ideas happened. Um weight sharing across
layers is something which continues to
be actively investigated uh today even
in transformers and the like. So I do
want to acknowledge that that idea
hasn't gone away but uh for the reset
case it turned out that resonance
without weight sharing across layers did
better for vision problems. Yeah.
Question.
>> Yeah. Isn't there something about like
in terms of like robotics when you're
learning system dynamics there's like
that kind of competition between the
output of a neural network and like the
true body physics. Is that is that kind
of similar to what you're talking about
here?
>> So right now I'm just talking about the
inspiration from physics. So of course
physics inspired neural nets and
thinking about this when you're actually
interacting with the physical world
where you believe the physical physical
world is actually defined and governed
by differential equations that's very
useful and so that's another side I'm
not talking about which is that if you
have uh an actual OD that you believe
governs the environment you can take
this perspective to fold a part of the
outside environment or simulated outside
environment into your neural net as a
frozen set of layers that's the world
and you can back prop through the world.
Okay, this is very useful in in idea. So
it is related but it's not what I was
particularly bringing up. Um other
questions on the I want to make sure
people understand the basics of this
resonate idea and potentially some of
the connections to neural. Yeah,
>> just going back a little bit. I'm a
little confused why
doesn't
Sorry.
>> Okay,
>> that's a great question. I'll come back
to this. Okay, so the question was wait
um we said here the problem was
everything was blowing up here still
everything is still adding up so why
isn't everything blowing up here? Is
that am I getting your question right?
Okay, that's a great question. Let me
give you the brief answer.
When you unroll this,
thinking about unrolling this, what do
you get when you unroll a differential
equation like this? You get an integral.
So when you unroll this, you'll get a
sum. How many terms in the sum? Roughly
the number of blocks.
So it is growing, but it's growing
arithmetically
with depth. So now this connects to the
issue of floatingoint precision, which I
want to talk about later, but I might as
well talk about it now since you asked
the question. Um, so if you have using
something like FB32, 32-bit floats, it
turns out you have plenty of dynamic
range and you can absorb this kind of
arithmetic growth easily.
If you start shifting to smaller and
smaller floatingoint representations,
this particular arithmetic growth can
start to become painful and then you
have to deal with it.
But uh at FP32, it's fine. FP16
also fine if you do mixed uh mixed
precision uh training FB8 and the like
it becomes quite tricky and you saw in
the homework we gave you homework think
about how MUP works with uh a floating
point and then you have to use tricks
like that to try to do rescalings that
are different on the forward path and on
the backward path to keep everything in
the right uh scale and if you've seen
recently uh Nvidia has released an FP4
format So fourbit numbers four bits
remember four bits is 16 numbers just 16
and talking about how you can get
training to work sometimes keeping you
know stuff at four bit precision. So
people are p pushing on this precision
issue which is an issue with with skip
connections. Okay. Does that answer your
question nicely?
>> Ah great question. So if you add
everything in uh here then it's not
because what's happening is that you
it's also happening at all previous
levels and so it's kind of blowing up um
as a result. Of course normalizations
would change that if you inserted
normalizations inside these boxes it
would potentially change it but I want
to acknowledge there is a difference
between this and this.
Um yes another question.
>> So when you're describing like weight
sharing across
is that not like the same ide.
>> Okay, great. So, let me distinguish
between weight sharing and uh not weight
sharing. So, when I do when I write it
this way, the picture here, this is this
has some weights associated with it. So,
this is the first set of weights. This
is a second set of weights. This is a
third set of weights. This is a i set of
weights. You know, this is the
nth set of weights and this is the n
minus one set of weights. You know,
think of it this way. They're all
different weights. When we think about a
neural net by default, there's no weight
sharing. The weight sharing that exists
in a conet is spatial. As you slide the
filters around there, the weights are
the same.
>> Is that good?
>> It's more like an RN, right? Where it's
like each layer has the same are just
being applied over and over and over
again.
>> So when I say when when you take the
neural OD perspective on this then you'd
say maybe I want to share weights
between these different things. Maybe I
should try doing that which you're right
when we talk about RNN's that we'll talk
about that kind of weight sharing. Um
but
people tried it and you know it helps
for many physics type problems is a very
useful thing but for straight image
processing and vision it turned out not
to beat uh not doing weight sharing.
Okay so coming back so now the question
is we've talked about the basic story
the core
you need to have something like this
that you skip over. Oh yeah question.
I'm just wondering like what would you
summarize in one sentence if the main
reason for the only like structure that
helps resets out
structures like
>> okay great question the question was so
what do we believe is the main reason
that resnets outperform the pre-resnet
architectures and that's the gradient
highway people believe the main thing is
it lets the gradients go back to
everybody
okay that's the clean answer that the
fact that it could also look like this
make inspired people to think about it
as the expressive powers of odes which
if you think about it what they're
thinking about is odes are natural and
define things in the world but they also
represent a kind of parsimony or compact
representation of physics with simple
equations and so people were attracted
by the idea that maybe if I could build
in the right kind of parsimony the right
kind of limited number of parameters by
doing parameter sharing I would get a
more faithful representation of reality
and it would be easier to train which is
a classical ML perspective but it turns
out that for lots of neural nets having
lots of parameters doesn't hurt you in
fact it can help you and that was
another theme of research that happened
we're not talking about it right now but
okay so I want to get back to the issue
of uh the normalizations
and here I want to recognize the modern
default which is different than this
approach So in the past people would do
things like this which is called
postnormalization
where you'd put the normalizations at
the end and the modern uh default is
normalizations go inside a block and
they go near the beginning of the block.
So if you have to make a design you you
do that.
Okay. So here's an example like this.
So remember here I'll use the blue
color. The skip is going like this
over everything.
So what this does is this makes it be
the case that there are no
normalizations along the skip paths. So
from the end to the beginning it never
the gradient never experiences a norm
a normalization layer just keeps hopping
back
and you put the norm uh near the
beginning as opposed to near the end. So
there's inside the block versus outside
the block.
The modern choice is inside the block
and then there's near the end or near
the beginning and the modern choice is
near the beginning.
and the near the beginning basically
says look a bunch of stuff might have
been added
up by the time I got here. So maybe the
activations are big or weird or
something. I'll normalize them first. So
now they're where I want them and now
I'll act on this.
Okay, any questions on this? And the the
practical importance is it's associated
with even more more stable training.
>> Yeah.
>> Is it not symmetric to just have the
normalization at the end because if you
go to the next layer
at the end
>> okay that's a great question. So the
question I'll repeat for everyone make
sure it's recorded properly is
why does beginning versus end matter
when everything is just repeated over
and over again. So the end of this is
the beginning of the next guy. So what
does it matter? Am I getting your
question correctly? Okay. So it matters.
It matters because the skips are
outside. Remember the first choice is
are this is the norms are do norms occur
inside the skips along the skip path or
not? And I'm saying not. Once you make
that choice, it's very different.
Okay? Because if I put a norm at the end
of this block hypothetically and then I
skip over it, the input to the next
block doesn't get the benefit of that
norm hypothetical norm that that you
were talking about drawing. So it makes
a difference. Um now people I say this
associated with more stable training. it
is the default if you have to do
something that said there are a few
recent papers that look at this question
of pre-orm versus postnorm in even
modern architectures and some
architectures claim that by doing a
little bit of postnorm you can ek out a
little bit extra performance
for reasons that are not quite clear. So
sometimes people will use a little bit
of postnorm in some places but again the
default now is to do it pre-orm.
Okay,
any questions on this?
So there's a really nice figure in
printince that helps you see uh sort of
what's happening.
So I thought I'd just replicate it
uh for everybody.
So what this does is it just
grinds through and says look if I take
this architecture as f1 f_sub_2 f3 f4
and just expand it out of what does that
actually mean you get
uh this thing if you want to make it
look like what's what's what's happening
in in potential parallel for the
gradient paths. So this shows you
directly that a gradient that comes back
here, remember a plus distributes the
gradient out, the gradient coming here,
it goes straight back to x, it goes to
f1.
It uh it goes see another path here. It
f there's f1. There's a path to f2 also.
Yeah, path to f2.
It goes to f3 and it goes to f4. So all
of the SS see directly that gradient.
You can see it from this perspective
more easily. Some people find this
useful. So I wanted to bring that up to
everyone.
So this is the gradient superighway
dimension of the uh residual
connections.
Okay.
So now uh with the residual connections
uh that are done, you might think, okay,
great. We know how to do this. We're
happy. Let's move on. There's one little
issue that we'll also talk about in
discussion but I wanted to make sure we
mention it here.
So here's a figure uh from Prince uh for
the you know very famous ResNet 200
architecture
of how does that look for doing image
classification. So this is for imageet.
So, imaget has a thousand uh classes
that uh people want to classify to. And
the way it works is it's using residual
blocks, but it's still following the
same pattern that we saw in older neural
nets, which is you still want to do this
image starts out big, then you make it
smaller, but add more channels, then you
make it smaller and add more channels
with distill information down. Remember
that principle from earlier? So you
still want to do that. So you know you
start with something big, you do make it
smaller, you have some uh these residual
blocks that all look like this. So this
is the old this is uh you know there's a
batchorm relu con batchorm relu con
batchorm relu like this
and but then you have to make it
smaller.
Okay. So some kind of subsampling uh
step happens. Then you have some more
blocks. You make it smaller. Some more
blocks. Smaller more blocks. And
interesting design choice that they
found in uh this in these resets was
that in the old days what you would do
was you would take at the end you would
take the entire image all the channels
flatten it into a giant thing and run it
through an MLP for classification.
What they decided was no, we're not
going to do that. Instead, they take the
entire image. So these are like seven by
seven images. The entire image has been
shrunk down to 7 by7. They take the 7
by7 image and they do what's called a
global average pool.
They take every channel and they just
average it across space. You can think
about this. Remember the intuition that
there's a catnness
channel. So now you say, I don't care
where the cat is in the picture. Just
tell me the average catness of this
entire image. So you do a global average
pool to compress it down. Now you just
have the channels and then you run the
channels through a fully connected layer
and then take a soft max.
Okay, so this is the kind of perspective
of getting rid of the large MLP at the
end. So all of the MLP like work is
being done by these one by one cons uh
throughout.
Okay. So this is like how people did it
for imageet. But there's a question if
you have a block that wants to include
something that's a downsampling like a
max pool or something with stride what
do you do? So I say what do you mean
what do you do? You do the same thing
you always do. So here I'll show you a
picture. Suppose you came in with a 100
by 100 image and it has 32 channels.
That's what this thing is. Then there's
a box, a block. This block includes
things like a max pool, stride,
something that makes a down sample. So
the output of this is a 50 by 50 image
with 50 channels. Let's say I just make
these numbers up.
So now I want to have a skip connection.
Does everyone see? This is what you want
to do. So, can I do this?
Maybe everyone take a minute, talk to
your neighbors and think about this.
This is important for you to It's like a
test of whether you understand what's
going on.
pretty good.
[Music]
Okay. So, interest of time, I want to
pull everyone back together. So,
first, can anyone tell me if I just add
this as a plus? What will happen?
>> Dimension error. Right? You can't add
something that's 100 by 32 to something
that's 50/50 by 50. It just doesn't
work. They're wrong shapes. They don't
add. In fact, there's different numbers
of things in there even. So, you can't
do that.
So,
first thought might be this is just
broken. Like you're dead, right? You
just can't do it. So, you have to
remember what are you trying to do?
Your goal, remember, is to make sure the
gradient here can pass back in some
meaningful way back.
That's the goal. So you want to create a
path for the gradient.
Now
the gradient at this point, right, is 50
by 50 by 50.
So it's not going to pass directly
through over here.
So what can we do?
What do we what's the minimal thing we
need to do?
>> So do some kind something that'll create
change the shape. Yes. So I need
something that'll change the shape.
Okay. So, I need something that changes
the shape. So,
what is an example of something that can
change the shape for me?
>> Yeah.
>> Down the image.
>> Down sampling the image. But it's
happening inside of here. There's some
downsampling happening inside of here.
So remember, when you downsample the
image, typically you're downsampling by
using a max pull or a stride, but you're
typically also increasing the channels.
So it need not be the case that there's
fewer things on the outside than there
are on the inside. Here there are, but
that doesn't have to be the case. It
could be there's more things here.
Just think from the perspective of the
mathematics of it. You need some object
that'll change the shape. What's the
simplest object you know that will
change the shape?
Someone say it out loud.
>> Matrix.
>> A matrix. Yes.
Example,
linear layer of some kind
matrix with right shape.
Okay, so it's called this linear like P.
Oops.
And it turns out one solution is simply
to add a learnable P matrix. So remember
what's the deep learning rule, right? I
need something.
I don't know what to do.
initialize somewhere, learn it is the
kind of default, right? So you could
that default actually turns out to work
in many cases. You can just slap in here
a matrix P initialize it so that it has
you know spectral norm that's like one
uh you know RMS type spectral norm one
going backwards. That's what you want to
do. It's a gradient path and
just let it learn. Okay, that's a valid
solution. Yeah.
>> Are we sharing across the connection?
>> Great question. Are you sharing the P
across the depth of uh skip connections?
And the answer is if you make them
learnable parameters, you do not have
to. People have done both things. In
fact, people found that and the res the
first ResNet paper didn't even make it
learnable. It just says I will pick a
matrix. So for example, if I'm
downsampling, one way of doing it is to
say if I'm downsampling uh in 4x4
blocks, which is what this is, like back
by a factor of two, I'll just put an
average
across the block for this matrix. If I
had 32 channels here, I will have that
average go over to the first 32 channels
here, and I'll just set the others to
zero.
So what that means is that the gradients
on those channels stop here. They won't
go back.
But the gradients on the first ones will
go back. That also works.
So people have experimented and for
different applications have different
choices of what they do. But the
important thing to understand here is
you have to do something.
You can't do nothing.
Okay? Because if you did nothing, you
didn't put the skip at all, you would
lose the gradients going backwards.
you'd lose the gradient super highway to
stop there.
Okay, so discussion will talk a little
bit more about this just to make sure
everyone gets it but it's an important
uh point for resonance.
Okay, so I want to move uh move on.
So this all this perspective was
uh you know if you look at the uh these
papers these are all like you know
resnet I believe came out in 2015 uh and
so this is you know all at that time
period
uh was the the next in the first in the
beginning of the modern age of neural
nets it was the first large
architectural advance that hadn't been
there before was was the residual
connections
Um and then people you know kept looking
at this and historical perspective is in
2017 uh transformers came out. uh people
started applying them to vision in 2018
2019 and by that time frame they were
really in many problems beating the uh
old connet architecture and so people
took a look again and said
is this because we are there's something
fundamentally better about what's inside
transformers which we'll talk about
later um or were we not doing connets
correctly and there's a really nice
paper which is a connet for the 2020s uh
by lead which came out in 2022. It's
actually a collaboration between
metaphair was called despair then um and
Berkeley and they proposed an
architecture they called con next
generation connet.
So this is useful to talk about like
what what things are happening here uh
introduce a couple more concepts.
So they went through and it's actually a
beautiful paper to read. I recommend you
look at it as a way to understand how to
think systematically about architectural
experimentation.
And so they really took everything and
they broke it out into pieces and says
what can I play with? What can I adjust?
How can I explore these different
things? What's really important? What's
not important? So it's a fun paper to
read and understand kind of from a
perspective point of view.
And so the original ResNet blocks look
like this that people after much
iteration, right? Uh, and what they did
was they said, "Well, I'm going to start
with 256 channels, for example,
and the first thing I'm going to do is a
one by one con that turns those 256
channels into 64 channels. Then there'll
be a batchorm and array luminal
linearity.
Then there will be a 3x3 con
with the same 64 channels. And then I'll
have another batch norm and
nonlinearity. And then I'll expand back
out using a one by one con 5 to 256. And
I'll put another batch norm. Then I'll
add the I'll actually add the skip and
then put the relu after.
Okay, this is the way that people used
to do things.
And
what they said was
you can do better than doing this. And
this has so remember we said at the very
beginning deep learning is there's lots
of freedom and so there is a bit of
pragmatic superstition that is useful
which is if you don't know why someone
did something just do the same thing
they're doing right you don't have to
understand everything you have to but
it's better to copy something else that
worked and change a little bit than to
try to do it from scratch because you
don't know why things work. Okay, this
is a kind of superstitious perspective
on deep learning, but people kept doing
it. And then they said maybe a lot of
these things are just happening because
people are doing them over and over
again and you don't need them and they
actually might be making things worse.
So the old style of thinking about
neural nets was very much fixated on
well you have some like you know they
use biological language you have some
synapse-like thing which is like some
weights multiplying stuff and then
there's an activation function and
there's a bias and then repeats so this
like ritualistic putting of the
nonlinearity everywhere
and they said maybe I don't need that
and what this one of the big shifts they
did was they said I'll have a linear
operation here. I'll have a linear
operations here and I'll put only one
nonlinearity inside this box.
Okay, actually there's two. There's the
nonlinearity from the normalization and
there's a nonlinearity in here. But
that's I'm not going to have
nonlinearities everywhere and I'm not
going to use batch norms and rails
everywhere. That's like one shift they
did and this improved performance. This
is a big a big source of performance
improvement. Not the choice of gay
versus relu. This is an excuse so I can
show you what this one is. But uh that's
not a big deal. But the having an linear
one place that was useful and having the
layer norm early was useful.
Okay. Next thing
uh they did was they said they looked at
the parameter counts involved and they
said it's actually better if I
instead of going from large number of
channels to a small number of channels
and then going back to a large number of
channels. This is this evolved but in
hindsight is a bit strange right because
remember when you were doing the example
with the elbows and the relus
having lots of things in the hidden
layer increases expressive power
right and folding it back so this is
saying look let's let's do the same
thing here let's have 96 channels and
then let's expand out and do to 384
think of this adding a lot more features
and then go through nine linearities and
then let's come back down.
Let's do it this way. And this saves uh
parameters also overall matches the
parameters basically.
Second thing they said is that look a 64
channel
uh traditional con has this 3x3 has lots
of parameters because you're actually
adding stuff together from all the
channels to get the output for a given
channel. A traditional con remember does
cons at every channel and then adds them
up to get you for a particular channel.
They switched to something called a
depthwise convolution which says treat
every channel as though it's its own
channel. Have a single con for that
channel. Make it a 7 by7 con. Do that
for the 96 different channels but have
no interactions among these cons.
This is called a depthwise convolution.
So I have a picture below of a depthwise
convolution.
So here's a 5x5 depthwise convolution.
You just have suppose there were three
input channels as an example. You just
have a separate filter for this orange
channel, a different filter for the red
channel and a different filter for the
yellow channel. And you take the outputs
and get a new output. Is everyone clear
on a depthwise? It's just
the channels don't interact with each
other. You treat every channel you treat
all the cons as though there are one
channel in and one channel out con.
channel by channel. No weight sharing
across channels. Channels can have all
do their own thing, but
uh as always, but you don't have any
interactions among channels. All the
interactions among channels happen from
the one by one.
And this helped because it saved a lot
of parameters here and they're able to
use them to get more expressive power
here.
and then a minor shift from batch norm
to layer norm
and instead of having it three times
having it only one place early.
Okay. So what this
there's a couple of lessons of this one
is that
convolutional architectures
uh sometimes architectures aren't
actually the problem. there
you have to get the details right.
Right. So what they proved pretty
convincingly was that the it wasn't any
advantages of attention in transformers
relative to connets that were giving the
advantages. It was that the connets
weren't quite doing the right thing and
a better co net could be competitive and
beat uh the transformers
at that point. Um later on there's like
another follow- on paper that we'll
maybe mention later in the class that's
the con next 2.0 which was talking about
the next difference between how people
were using transform architectures and
connets which has to do with
pre-training but we will come to that
later. So this is the constant dialogue
what is actually important what's
actually giving you useful gains.
So this is the culling away of
superstitious accretion
uh that has happens in uh design.
So there's always these different
nonlinearities. Uh so Wikipedia has a
really nice article on the gel. You
should you can look at it if you want.
As a pictorially it just has the instead
of the relu it's like a smoother curve
but a bit weird looking um as a curve.
The actual equation for this curve is
the CDF of a Gaussian times the input.
Okay, so this is just uh what it is. And
sometimes because it is a little bit
smoother around here in some cases works
a little bit better
again. But in the comics paper, it's not
that it was a major source of
improvement. It's just uh is an excuse
to for me to show you another
nonlinearity you should know about.
Okay. So now you know the kind of modern
uh connet uh picture. Um I want to sort
of talk a little bit about come back to
the issue of pooling because I want to
move on to how to think about problems
that are not uh is this image a dog?
Okay. Because if you saw again in the
ResNet picture I did here uh at the end
it did this global average pooling and
then it would give you an answer in
these thousand categories you know is it
a dog is it a cat is it an airplane or
so on but if you want to do more
interesting things like for example
label the pixels in an image this
doesn't work
and so one of the key things we're going
to need is we're going to need to be
able to
not just go down in resolution so that's
what I want to talk about
Okay,
so first any questions on basic connets
for classification?
Now you know the all the basic building
blocks, normalization layers, blocks
that have skip connections on them and
how you place the normalization layers
inside the blocks near the beginning.
So if you remember pooling uh for down
basically how to do downsampling how to
make the resolution get smaller you had
three basic choices again this is figure
and prince you can do stride or
subsampling which is that you
take a little block and just pick the
first entry in the block as the output
and throw away all of these guys.
And then we told you that you could do
this in a more efficient manner by never
calculating these guys in the first
place. And that was a strided
convolution. Everyone remember?
And then there's the idea of max pooling
which says in the block you actually
look at which one is the biggest and you
copy that over. So it could be different
entries. And we talked about how this
did gradient routing to the right spots
in the image.
And hopefully as you're doing the the
homework problem, you've done the
homework problem on uh what the
gradients look like, you see how what
this does is if you routed the
gradients, you're copying the right set
of things into the weights.
So if you were doing an edge detector
and there was actually an edge here,
you're going to copy like the edge like
behavior into the weights, which is what
you want. So this is the why back
pooling gives some advantages.
And then there's like average pooling,
mean pooling. It just takes the average.
Okay. So now the question is what if you
wanted to do the reverse? So each of
these takes you from high-res to low
res.
How do you go backwards?
If you wanted to go from low res to
high-res,
this is called upsampling.
So
let's think of two that are easy to
think about.
So you could imagine uh max unpool.
Okay. So max unpool would say
I have a two, a four, a four, and an
eight. And suppose this is a big
suppose. Suppose I also remembered
which spot these came from.
Okay. So I can for to do this I have to
remember something.
Okay. If you remember which position was
the max, you could undo it.
But you have no information about the
other spots. Does everyone see that?
Like you only have the max. You don't
know which was the what the other was.
So you have to put something there. You
could put zeros. For example,
so it's like a max unpool. The easiest
one to understand is just duplication.
The opposite of a mean.
If you knew the average here in this
block was a two, what do you fill
everything in with twos?
Does everyone see that? Again, natural.
So,
what's the counterpart upsampling for
just subsampling? So, remember this
picture here?
What if you wanted to reverse that
picture?
So, we're trying to reverse this one.
Okay,
what should we go to?
So,
this is where it came from. I just
copied from the above picture, but
there's no way we're going to get these
guys,
right? So, I just copied it over with
like blank spots there.
So, what should we put in the blank
spots? Anyone want to venture a guess?
>> Yeah.
>> What if you just randomly choose values?
>> Randomly choosing values. Okay, that's
an interesting choice. Okay, so if you
don't know what goes there to choose
randomly uh is a choice. However, that
is introducing a bunch of noise into my
processing. So it tends not to be a good
choice.
Okay. So you don't know what goes there.
You do something. Yeah.
interpolate.
>> Okay. So I'll write that as an idea.
Ideas.
>> Okay. What's another idea of what I
could do?
>> Okay. So the idea was so instead of
randomly generating it just for the
uniform distribution you could randomly
generate it using something else.
>> Okay.
So,
I'll write that one down.
Okay. So it turns out although you can
do this, it tends not to be a good idea
for the same reason that what you're
doing here is
you actually know almost nothing about
what goes on here. And this value might
not uh be telling you all the
information you need of what goes on
here. So if you randomly sample from
some distribution, you're just injecting
noise, which again, sometimes that's a
useful thing to do, but it's not a
generically useful thing to do. Um
interpolation in a smooth way says that
well you know something you don't know
what's here this three but you know
there was a five over there so maybe
something in between makes sense so use
something about the neighboring thing.
Does anyone want to give a different uh
idea?
>> Yeah. just like
ah so remember the question we're facing
just so make sure it's very clear all we
have is this
>> you
corner the top right corner Imagine
like rotating it. So,
>> so remember the idea here. So, this is a
proxy for an entire image.
Okay? So, you think about this is I I
drew four just because like it's small.
It's like an entire image. The entire
image started off 256 x 256 and now I
have 128 x 128. I want to get back to
256 x 256. So
I know what goes I know that this was
generated by downsampling. So I knew I
know exactly what goes into these spots.
I the problem is I don't know what goes
into these spots. So a rotation based
idea that's tied to a 2x2 block doesn't
generalize. Okay. So we have to think
about something that what's another
choice of what I can do. Yeah.
>> Initiate a function.
>> Um learn a function. Ah okay. Good. So
let's think about that way.
That's a good one. It's always a good
one, right? When you don't know what to
do, make it learnable. So,
make it learnable.
Okay.
So, if you want to make it learnable,
um we're going to go in that direction.
Uh so, one way to think about it is this
is a learnable version of a
I want to interpolate with neighboring
values in some way. I don't know how to
interpolate it. So I will make the
interpolation method learnable. Everyone
see that as a way to go. Okay, we're
going to follow that one. But there's
another one that I want to recognize as
a choice.
So I'll just write it down for interest
of time. for max unpool I said look I
don't know what goes there so I can just
fill it in with a default value and a
default value of zero is a useful
default value zero is a useful default
when you're thinking about linear things
because zero behaves nicely with linear
things nonlinear things you have to be
careful about using zero as a default
value but for linear is definitely a
useful thing
so this is just fill with zeros
Okay, so
it turns out that
there's a way of using things we already
know to achieve this make it learnable.
Okay. And the way you can make it um
learnable is to say the following. See
if I can write this idea.
Use approach D
followed by
uh
learnable
con.
So the discussion will have you engage
with this. But
what is this saying? This says how can I
do interpolation?
One way of doing interpolation is to
view interpolation as a kind of blurring
operation. So this comes from a signal
processing perspective. So if anyone has
seen how you think about changing uh
sampling rates in signal processing, you
follow this idea of you take something,
if you want to up sample it, you insert
zeros and then you smooth it.
So what that means is that you blur it.
A con is like a blur, a smoothing. So it
says I want to this has too much high
frequency stuff in it with zeros here.
So I put zeros in here. Just write
zeros.
So if I smooth this with some kind of
blur blurring filter then I'll get
something that's smooth everywhere. Does
everyone see that as the intuition?
Okay. So
so if I if I do D followed by a
learnable con this whole thing
behaves
like
learnable interpolation.
Okay, does everyone understand this?
This is the part that often even in the
I think the description in Prince's book
doesn't make this as clear. This is
intuitive. Nothing new is happening
here, right? It's just I would like to
do something I can fill with zeros and I
can do a con. Okay. So now comes the
idea of what's called a transpose
convolution.
So what is a transpose convolution?
Okay, it's a
think of it this way. In downsampling,
we had the idea that if I have a con
followed by subsampling,
I can avoid redundant computation
by just computing only the things I
need. And that was called a strided con.
Everyone remember this?
So now the question is in upsampling I
have this zero fill
upsampling this kind of thing followed
by a con
can I merge those two operations
together into a strided something
does everyone see this as the kind of
it's just by by analogy by parallel
so this thing is called a transpose con
and why it's cause called a transposed
con is a nice figure in printince that
shows you. So
over here you see a strided con.
It's taking x1 through x8 and
downsampling it by a factor of two with
a conve.
So, you know, this light edge is the
same edge that goes across.
The darker edge is the edge going to the
next thing. And the
lighter but not as light edge is going
up.
Okay?
And this is a strided con. Does everyone
see that?
Okay. strided con when you write it out
as a matrix
where the output is h and the input is
the x you get this diagonal structure
with weight which shared where here's
the con
everyone see it
okay now
let's do the opposite effect
where I go from low to I
I'm still doing a comp
still the same kind of con is happening.
Okay.
So what's happening is just to
understand this picture precisely
let me just uh put in some more things.
There's a hidden zero here,
but 0 multiplied by anything is zero. So
you don't have to worry about its edges,
outgoing edges. Does everyone see that?
They're there, but there's no point in
doing that multiplication. We can save
that work.
And then you get this matrix.
And now hopefully the name transposecon
is clear
right this matrix and this matrix you
know their shape is just like transposes
of each other
that's why it's called transpose con
okay so questions on this picture then
I'll I'll talk about it a little bit
more yeah
>> sorry is that hidden zero I know you
said that it's just zero so it
But like does it have like a connection
to H1 and H2?
>> Yes, you could you should think of it as
having
um now I can't do this but I would love
to do Okay, I'll just show you what I
want to do but it doesn't work. Okay, I
would take these
and I would copy them
up here
but it doesn't work. Okay, because I
can't copy like that for some reason.
Okay, but those edges are there. So if I
think about the idea of doing this step
here
followed by a learnable con,
right? These zeros are these zeros.
So you see that if I do a con with
zeros,
there's operations I'm doing whose
answer I know is going to be zero. So
let me just save those multiplies.
That's all that's this is a
computational savings. It's not a
conceptual step. There's nothing
conceptual here.
Transpose cons and strided cons exist
only for computational savings.
This is the part that students sometimes
get confused by seems like lots of
details but if you keep the big picture
straight it's it's easier to understand.
Yeah. I'm just wondering like what is
the obstacification
or are we moving to the
>> Yeah. So I mean uh I'm going to talk
about like semantic segmentation. So I
want to label everything in the image.
So how do I do this? I need to be able
to go back up to a higher resolution.
That's just the picture. But I want to
just talk about this operation first to
make sure the operation is clear.
Okay.
So if you remember the
um 3x3 perspective we had before
some people find this helpful some
people don't.
We said that look what's happening in a
in a con is that you have neighbors. So
this is different colored edges. You
have the mi edge that's like from the
same position to the same position. Then
you have the north and northeast and so
on. Different edges. And what you're
doing at the output is just taking all
the channel information
in different positions, multiplying them
by the appropriate weight learned weight
matrices, adding them up, and adding the
bias. That's a con. Now, I just finished
telling you that there's only regular
cons. That's it.
Conceptually, there's nothing different.
There's only regular cons. strided cons
transpose cons are just different
savings of computation by avoiding
multiplications by zero.
That's all you're doing. Okay. So in
this picture in a standard con you can
think about this sum always ranges over
the k by k positions in the con filter.
So for every output position, you're
going to look at all of the
uh neighboring positions.
The only difference is when you're doing
zero padding and you're at the edge, but
the edge in an image is small, right?
The edge, remember the edge grows. The
size of the edge is like the
circumference and the size of the image
is like the area. Circumference grows
linearly with the image. Area grows
quadratically. So most of the image is
inside.
So we don't we don't worry about saving
that. con on the zeros.
Not much not much to say there.
Um,
now in a transpose con, the issue is
that lots of the neighboring positions
are actually zeros.
The zeros are dense. They're every
filling your entire image is filled with
zeros. So, it's a lot of savings to not
do those multiplications.
Everyone see that? So you can think
about in this expression as this sum
only ranges over the relevant things the
ones that are not zero and that's
different for different positions in the
output.
Okay.
So um like here
you see the difference of different
positions here in this picture on one
dimensional picture. This one sees this
guy. This one sees this guy and this
guy. This one just sees this guy and so
on. Different positions see different
neighbors.
Okay, this hopefully helps uh some
people understand what's happening. Um
third approach to understand what's
happening is look at code. Okay, so this
is from uh D2L.ai. It's another
textbook. Um, it was nice because it had
like parallel sets of code that are
describing the same uh standard cons and
uh transpose cons.
And I've just marked for you what's uh
sort of different across the two things.
So this is a simplified case where we're
not talking about lots of channels, just
one channel in this in this picture.
uh and you start with an X. You have a
filter K you want to apply and what do
you do? Okay, so it has to fit in the
image. And this is where the fitting in
the image is different on the transpose
side than on the regular side. To fit
inside the image, you have to make the
image smaller,
right? By the height and width of the
filter. So everything fits.
But in the transpose you make it bigger
because everything will spill out
right to the outside because the
remember the outside in this picture the
outside of the image is thought of as
filled with zeros
uh for the transpose con. So that's this
plus h is here plus w.
Then you can think about the same exact
operation as two different ways of
looking at the sums.
One way is you range in the standard
conf you range over the output shape
and as you range over the output shape
you fill in that position with this sum
where you take the appropriate slice of
x around i and j the corresponding
position and you take the sum
and the transpose con perspective. on
the same basic operation is you range
over all the x positions
and you send those x positions
according to the filter out into y. Same
thing just two different ways of looking
at it.
This perspective plays nicely with
strides that down sample.
strides that upsample
and that's why you use one of the two
perspectives for the two cases to save
computation. Remember it's only to save
computation. There is nothing conceptual
in a transpose conf or a strided conf.
Any questions on this?
Okay. So now I want to put things
together and say now we have all the
building blocks we almost all the
building blocks we need. How do you do
image level tasks? By image level tasks
I mean a task in which the output is an
image. Machine learning thing will take
an image as an input and have an output
be an image.
The semantic segmentation is like the
easiest one where the image is the same
size as the beginning. Every pixel has
to be labeled.
So here's a figure um in prints for an
approach that people uh followed. So in
this approach what you do is you say
look I'm going to take the entire image
that I have and I'm going to build
something like a classifier pipeline.
Okay. So, I'm going to keep making it
smaller and smaller, and I'm trying to
figure out what is going on in this
image.
And in this spot in the middle, I've
basically distilled the entire image
down into these 4,96 numbers that are
representing what's happening. Then I do
the reverse.
I make it bigger and bigger and bigger.
So first I take these 4,96 numbers and I
make a little 7 by7 image and then
I remember I do I basically follow the
things going backwards. I do a max
unpool
and then I do these what are called
decons which are transpose conss.
So I do these transpose cons to make the
thighs bigger and bigger as I go
through.
Okay? And I make them all learnable.
So incrementally you make it bigger and
bigger.
>> Yeah.
>> Yeah. So the when you when you make it
get bigger it's transpose cons and then
they're just regular cons inside here.
Yeah. So the first side you have to go
transpose then the rest are regular. But
from a perspective they're just all
cons.
use a transpose con to save some of
those multiplications by zeros. That's
it.
Okay, so this is an approach and when
people did this approach, they found
that it kind of worked,
but it had a problem. And the problem it
had was that it forced all of the
information about the entire image
through this bottleneck
in the middle which was great from one
perspective because you wanted to
understand what is going on in the image
but it was bad from a different
perspective in that you wanted to have
fine grained information about every
pixel.
So the problem with this approach is
that it didn't separate out
um the big picture from details
and it's making the middle have to do
the job of both. Whereas semantic
segmentation involves not just saying
this is a cat but this is where the cat
ends.
So the idea
is this is solved by the idea of what's
called a unit.
And what a unit did was it said,
wouldn't it be great that
when I was looking at the image at a
higher resolution,
I could sneak back and look at the last
time in the processing I was at that
resolution.
Does everyone see the idea? So it says
like I've done a bunch of processing
that's giving me like information about
the bigger picture, but when I want to
tell the bigger picture at a higher
resolution, I should also look at the
last time I was at that resolution and
combine that with the big picture
information to get a new higher
resolution image.
So what it adds is a different kind of
skip connection.
Okay, where the idea is that you want
information at a certain resolution to
be carried through. So in this case,
this is this crop and concatenate. Crop
just means match this shape. Okay,
concatenate means literally copy
everything here over here.
Add extra channels. So some channels are
the transpose conf of this guy
and some channels are copies of the last
time I was at this resolution.
You follow that by doing regular cons
that combine the information together
between what was here last time I was at
this resolution and what I have new.
So you do that
and then you process for a while and
then you do it again when you move it to
the next higher resolution and you do it
again and again until you get back to
the beginning.
Okay. So if you think about a unit the
gradients in the unit flow again what
I'm not drawing here was not what I
didn't draw draw here is that they're
also the regular skips that are
happening
okay the regular skips are happening but
these extra skips that are also in these
crop and concatenates so the gradients
are flowing back that way too
yeah question
Oh,
>> the same size.
>> So, it's just it's to match the size. In
this particular example that they took
this figure from, the output was a 388
by 388. This is like some cell
segmentation paper and the input image
was was a different uh size 572 because
there's some boundaries that were being
ignored and so there's a cropping that's
just happening as a part of the way
these filters are built. The crop isn't
important. The idea is
match up pixel for pixel the information
that was present at the last time I was
at this scale.
That's the idea in a unit.
So what is it? Let me write that down.
bring information
for
this pixel
from earlier processing.
So this is critical um to getting high
quality image level things to work.
And so units aren't just used for things
like semantic segmentation, but any kind
of thing that has an image level target.
So for example, whenever you're using u
a generative model that says make me a
picture of a cat riding a dinosaur
playing polo, right? inside there to get
something to occur at a high resolution,
there's going to be a unit or unit type
structure that's going to help make this
thing be a nice big image.
So that's the last component that I
wanted to talk about in uh the
convolutional architectures. Um any
questions on this? I'm unfortunately did
not get to graph neural nets which is
the next topic I wanted to start. So I
will start that next lecture. Yeah,
>> I had a question about why we
channel input. Why don't we just add it
to the existing channel?
Anyway,
>> great question. The reason we do a
concatenate is that we immediately
follow it by a con and the con will have
a learnable way of doing the adding. So
the question becomes how do I add? Where
should I add? And the answer is I don't
know. Make it learnable. Con.
Yeah.
Usually it's even these cons in modern
architectures might even start with a
one by one conf.
Okay. So I'll have office hours now. Uh
we'll continue with graph neural nets
next lecture.
>> Hi professor.
>> Can I ask you a question?
>> Yeah.
Hi, my name is VJ.
>> Hey hi VJ.
>> Nice to meet you.
>> Um, so the question I had is like I was
reading the famous essay you and your
research recently by Richard H.
>> Yeah, it's a great research. Great,
great article. Yeah,
>> he says um you should know like the top
problems in your field attack. I was
wondering what you thought are the top
problems in machine learning right now
specifically in the area of deep
learning.